<text id="1884_d">
<chap title="Part I.">
<gap desc="Published in ALL THE YEAR ROUND. [November 1, 1884], edited by Charles Dickens"/>
<pb n="77"/>
<head level="2" align="center">THE CLIMBS OF THE ENGLISH LAKE DISTRICT</head>
<head level="3" align="center">IN TWO PARTS. PART I.</head>
<p>SOMEONE has said of England that it is a reproduction in miniature of the scenery of the Continent. It were difficult to justify the likeness instance for instance, but certain resemblances are obvious; and if the Dart be the English Rhine, the Ventnor Under-cliff the English Rivera, and so on, then with much more truth may the mountains of Cumberland and Westmoreland be said to stand for the Alps. And the climber who cannot reach the great European playground may well be content to practise upon the Cumberland peaks, which by-and-by, he will come to respect and love -- to respect for the difficult crag-work they offer, and to love for their beauty and grandeur; their gladdening views of dale, and lake, and tarn; their keen and healthful winds, like those Charles Lamb encountered atop of Skiddaw; their flying mists, and echoing storms. But he who would win their secrets from the mountains, and be filled with their inspiration, must court the mountain-spirits in their solitudes, and must shun the beaten tracks and "tourist centres." Round Ambleside you will indeed find hills and waterfalls, but the waterfalls are decked with greasy sandwich-papers and porter-bottles, and the hills echo the steam-whistles of the Windermere steamers, bringing crowds of thirsty "trippers" from the Staffordshire potteries. Brass bands play under your hotel windows; "char-a-bancs," waggonettes, and breaks of all colours rattle about with cargoes of tourists who have been "doing" some favourite "round;" tours pester you in the streets; and in the hotel coffee-room you overhear a gentleman ask angrily: "Why don't they build a 'ut on 'Elvellyn? They 'ave one on Snowdon."</p>
<p>Of course Ambleside has associations. Harriet Martineau and Dr. Arnold, Wordsworth and Hartley Coleridge are great names. To-day, Mr. W. E. Forster and Mr. Matthew Arnold love and visit it, and Birket Foster has made a pretty "bit" of the old mill. But the village is vulgarised almost beyond hope. Let the railway be brought there from Windermere, and its ruin will be complete. Though there is now no Wordsworth to pen noble sonnets of protest against further railway invasions of the district, there is happily an energetic Lake District Defence Association working strenuously to save from the destruction which threatens it the sweetest spot of English ground. Already it has defeated the Borrowdale and Ennerdale schemes, and long may it be successful in keeping the railway promoters at bay! Lovers of mountains will avoid Ambleside. Keswick is better as a mountaineering centre; for Skiddaw and Blencathara, the minor heights round Derwentwater, and the beautiful range stretching from Grisedale Pike to Grasmoor are all within easy reach. The farther you get from the stale air of towns the better. Grange and Rosthwaite, those beautiful Borrowdale hamlets, are tempting resting-places; but he who goes to Cumberland to walk and climb will not be satisfied till he finds himself face to face with the highest peaks at Wastdale Head.</p>
<p>Wastdale Head -- or, more properly, Wastdale, for that part of the valley below the lake is Nether Wastdale -- is the finest mountain-valley in England. Round its head are symmetrically groups the highest English mountains -- Scafell Pikes, and its companion, Scafell, Great End, and Great Gable. The lower heights of the Lingmell, Kirkfell, and Yewbarrow form stately buttresses for the loftier summits beyond. On all sides the mountains plunge straight down to the valley, and if you row over the glossy surface of Wast-water, close to the Screes, you can see the steep rocky slope continue straight down into the lake till it is lost in the black water. Approaching Wastdale Head by the carriage-road from the little coast-towns of Drigg or Seascale, where there are railway-stations, the valley appears a 
<pb n="78"/>
cul-de-sac, and people wonder how they can get away again without retracing their steps. There are but three exits, and these are mere "fell-tracks:" steep, stony zigzags, swept by mountain-torrents in winter, and in summer forming the most detestable paths. Seven scattered farms occupy the valley, and its church and schoolhouse are the smallest in England. Wastdale Head has sown its wild oats and become decorous. But get some old dalesman in a talkative mood, and he will tell you of other times, when old "Will" Ritson, sheep-farmer, innkeeper, and wit, was the genius of the place. What fun went on then under the shadow of Scafell; what feats of fish-spearing by torchlight; what wild fox-hunts over the fells; what fine wrestling-matches on the green on summer evenings; what card-parties, and dancing, and good-humoured riot! Once someone tied a donkey by its tail to the bell-rope of the little church, and the animal's struggles raised a clangour which brought the parson rushing to the spot. But times have changed. The frolic ways have been abandoned, and the dalespeople have settled down with gravity to their two staple industries of sheep-farming and entertaining tourists. Either at the inn, or at Mrs. Thomas Tyson's famous farmhouse, climbing-men linger through the summer. Some come in winter, and then the surrounding peaks offer excellent practice for Swiss mountaineering. They are enthusiastic fellows, these climbers. They ascend their favourite mountains times after time (one honoured pioneer of lake-climbing has made ninety-nine ascents to the summit of Great Gable); they are unwearied in finding new ways up everywhere, and their talk, when they get together, is of nicks and notches, ladders and ledges, gullies, ghylls, and chimneys, and even of cols, ar&#234;tes, and couloirs. All Cumberland and Westmoreland is familiar to them; they are at home on the Blencathara Edges, looking down to the waters of the dark tarn which is said to reflect the stars at noonday, on the precipices of Scafell, and Striding Edge on Helvellyn. They have clambered among the waterfalls of Piers Ghyll, climbed the precipice of Pavey Ark and the crags of Lingmell, crossed the sloping stones wedged in the cavern at Dungeon Ghyll, scaled the crags of Great Napes on Gable, and the great couloir in the front of Great End; yet ever do they return with greater fondness to the most enticing peak of all &#8212; the redoubtable Pillar Rock of Ennerdale.</p>
<p>The spell which this Rock throws over the minds of those who have once visited it is enthralling. It is of the nature of a psychological mystery not to be accounted for on ordinary grounds. It is strange. The Pillar Rock is merely a mass of crags, with no inherent different from other masses save that it juts up boldly some nine hundred feet from the precipitous breast of the Pillar Mountain. Yet, once seen, it is as the loadstone to the pieces of iron in the story of the Third Royal Calendar. Perhaps it is the fact of its unique position, standing alone overhanging the desolate valley of Ennerdale, its apparent inaccessibility, or the tragic interests which two deaths have given it. Whatever the secret of its attraction, that attraction is undoubted. One climber, a senior wrangler and member of the Alpine Club, has scaled the Rock more than forty times, and younger men are at this moment engaged in beating his record. It has been called, with exquisite inappropriateness, the English Matterhorn and the English Schreckhorn. But it has not the terrors implied in the latter name. It is, in fact, an interesting rock, accessible from several sides, the climbs being easy or difficult, according to the side from which they are made. Let us enter into details. Ennerdale is the longest and most desolate of the mountain valleys which radiate from Great Gable, the central knot of the Scafell system. Its upper end is closed by the magnificent dome of the Gable itself, and its sides are formed by the precipitous slopes of Kirkfell, the Pillar and the Steeple on the oen side, and High Crag, High Stile, and Red Pike on the other. An impetuous stream, the Liza, traverses the length of the valley, and flows into Ennerdale Lake. No habitation, no sign of human life breaks the solitude of the place. The murmuring of the stream, the cry of the raven of the hawk, are the only sounds. Upper Ennerdale is not, however, unfamiliar to the tourist; for the fell-track from Wastdale to Buttermere, after ascending by Black Sail Pass, descends into Ennerdale, and mounts on the other side to Scarf Gap, and so down to Buttermere. Those following this track may see the top of the famous Pillar Rock peering over a projecting ridge of the Pillar Mountain, and the most imposing view of the rock is to be gained by proceeding along the valley till opposite to it, and then climbing up to its <pb n="79"/>base. It is a fatiguing scramble, and it has been said that the cragsman taking this route, will find the way strewn with the graves of those who have preceded him. If there is exaggeration, there is also truth in the saying. Near the foot of the Black Sail Pass is a large cairn erected the memory of Mr. Edward Barnard, a London goldsmith, who, overcome by the fatigue and heat (it was August, 1876), there lay down and died. Not much farther, but high up on the mountain side, is an iron cross marking the spot where was found the body of the Rev. James Jackson, who, on May 1st, 1878, fell from the precipice of the Pillar Mountain. Just to the left of the Rock is the gully where the youth Walker slipped over the ice and snow, and was dashed to pieces, on Good Friday, 1883, and at any point of the walk a turn of the head will reveal the horrid gully in the precipice of Great Gable where the Rev. J. Pope was killed a year or two ago.</p>
<poem>
<line>You see yon precipice; it wears the shape</line>
<line>Of a vast building made of many crags;</line>
<line>And in the midst is one of particular rock</line>
<line>That rises like a column from the vale,</line>
<line>Whence by our shepherds it is called the Pillar.</line>
<line></line>
</poem>
<p>Thus did "the homely priest of Ennerdale" describe the Pillar Rock to Leonard in Wordsworth's poem, The Brothers, and the description is accurate. The whole Ennerdale front of the Pillar is broken up by projecting ridges which form a series of recesses or coves. In one of the largest of these coves stands the Pillar Rock, springing upward almost perpendicularly on the Ennerdale side to the height of eight hundred and seventy-five feet, but united on its other side to the Pillar Mountain by a neck, about one hundred feet below the summit of the rock. All climbs are best begun from this neck, and to reach it from Wastdale is best to ascend the Pillar Mountain from the Black Sail Pass, and walk on the level grassy summit till the small heath-covered top of the Rock is seen in air on the right-hand side, many feet below. An easy though steep scramble down the mountain-side then lands you on the neck. This route saves the long climb up to the base of the Rock from Ennerdale. Heated pedestrians approaching the Pillar from the valley have even been known to get bewildered by the many crags, to dispute among themselves as to which was the Pillar Rock, and to fall out by the way.</p>
<p>Standing on the narrow neck the Rock is immediately in front, and steep gullies sweep down to right and left. The left or western gully can be descended, and from a point about half-way down the "west climb" is commenced. The right or eastern gully, after descending steeply for several yards ends in a sudden pitch. Viewed from the neck the Rock does not justify its name. A scramble round its base will reveal it to be a cumbrous mass of crags, its greatest length extending north and south up the mountain-side. In three places it is cleft perpendicularly by deep gullies or chimneys, whose lines of clearage are parallel to Ennerdale, and therefore at right angles to the greatest length of the Rock. These gullies split the Rock into four separate summits; the highest called the "High Man," and the others "Low Men." (In the Lake District all lower summits are called "Low Men.") From the neck an easy way to the highest summit seems to present itself directly in front. The climber mountains gaily and with confidence, only to find himself cut off from the High Man by an impassable cleft, forty feet long on the level part at the bottom, thirteen feet wide at the bottom, and broadening towards the top. Opposite rises the main rock in a fine wall sixty feet high. This is the most southerly of the three gullies mentioned above. By an authority on the Pillar this false rock has been christened Pisgah, and the gap, Jordan.</p>
<p>Descending then from Pisgah to the neck, the attack must now be made from the right-hand or east side. Looking across to the Rock, a smooth sloping slab is conspicuous on its side. Make for this by scrambling a few yards down the east gully, and then ascending two natural steps (known as "the first ladder") about six feet high, which conduct to the upper edge of the "Broad Slab." The slab is covered with grass on its upper part; the lower part is smooth, and ends abruptly over the east gully. It is forty feet in length, twenty nine in width, and slopes at an angle of thirty-seven degrees. A crack about two inches wide runs horizontally across the slab, and without this aid crossing it would be a matter of some little difficulty, for there is a considerable drop on to the rough rocks of the east gully from the lower edge, and a slip here is not to be recommended. The crack affords good foot-hold, and a few steps carry you across the Broad Slab. A few yards of uneven but safe walking conduct to a sort of corner, where the climber is confronted <pb n="80"/> by a projecting curtain, with a deep notch between it and the main mass. To the left rises the erect wall of the Pillar; on the right is a precipice of about sixty feet. From this grassy corner there is a perplexing choice of inviting (or uninviting) routes, and strangers have been known to bother about for half an hour or more and then sometimes give up the ascent, unable to find a way. From the corner there are, however, at least three ways of ascent, known respectively as the routes by "the notch," "the ledge," and the "ar&#234;te." The notch way is far the easiest. Scramble up to the left-hand, aiming for the floor of the notch, between the curtain and the main mass. A moderate climb of twenty-four feet lands you on the floor of the notch, here twenty-one feet thick, and you find yourself on the south wall of the "Great Chimney," which is the name given to the middle one of the three gullies which have been mentioned as dividing the main mass of the Pillar Rock. The Great Chimney begins just at the top of the steep pitch in the east gully, and cleaves the rock almost to its highest summit. Seventy feet from its base, the chimney contains a sloping shelf, covered with rough grass. This shelf is sixty feet in length, slopes at an angle of forty-five degrees, and is known to the esoteric circle of "Pillarites" as the "Steep Grass." At the top of the Steep Grass the Great Chimeny suddenly narrows and dwindles to a small perpendicular chimney twenty-three feet high, about the width of an ordinary human body, and containing a large stone jammed half-way up. When on the floor of the notch the Steep Grass can be reached by a drop of eight feet. The easiest way, however, is to continue the ascent over comparatively easy rocks, keeping the Great Chimney on the right till you emerge on the grass at the top of the small chimney, whence a run carries you to the highest summit. Here you may add your visiting-card to the others in the tin-box hidden in the cairn, or you may sign your name in the visitors'-book obligingly left for this purpose by two London climbers in 1882.</p>
<p>This is probably the easiest way of ascending the Rock, though it is almost unknown. The only way which seems known to the local guides is that by the ledge. To ascend by way of the ledge from the corner below the notch, the climber must first get up the cleft or natural ladder in the curtain, which is directly in front after coming over the broad slab. The cleft &#8212; the "second ladder" &#8212; runs up the face of the curtain for ten feet, then broadens out into a scoop and ends but from the scoop a ledge is to be seen running to the right and winding round the curtain. The second ladder presents no difficulty to a moderate climber, as the hand-holds and foot-holds are plentiful. It is not, however, a place to run up, as the face of the curtain here turns outwards towards the precipice in an unpleasing manner, and a slip would precipitate the climber on to the rocks of the east gulley, some sixty feet below. Once up the ladder, the scoop offers a safe refuge, and the right foot must be placed on the ledge, which is here only about eighteen inches wide. There is, however, excellent hand-hold and foot-hold, and though there is a deep fall immediately behind, none but those with very unsteady heads need be afraid to trust themselves on the ledge. Almost immediately, it curves round the curtain, broadens out to ten or fifteen feet, and inclines downwards, when you step from it on to another corner of grassy ground. A swing round a little jutting rock with a seventy-foot drop just behind lands you on the lower edge of the Steep Grass. Scrambling up to the top, the small chimney is attacked by insinuating the body, and working upwards till just under the jammed stone. Throwing the arms round this, the climber gets his breast upon it, and then a brief struggle, while the feet are unoccupied in mid-air, enables him first to kneel and then to stand upon the stone. The upper part of the chimney is then attacked with ease, and the climber emerges at the point reached by the climb from the notch already described. This route by the ladder, ledge, and chimney was, it is said, first discovered by Mr. Leslie Stephen and a party of University men, about the year 1854. It is a pleasant and varied climb which does not overtax the powers of a moderate cragsman. Mr. H. I. Jenkinson, indeed, in his excellent Guide to the English Lakes (6th edition, 1879), says, "The rock has been scaled by very few, and it is exceedingly hazardous and foolhardy to attempt it;" but it must be presumed that this very exaggerated warning is intended for the waggonette-tourist, and not for the cragsman. The ascent from the notch by the "ar&#234;te" (or south wall of the Great Chimney) is a much harder climb than<pb n="81"/> either of these already described. It has been accomplished by only four or five men, and at one point near the top, where both hands have to be clasped round a pinnacle of rock while the weight is partly sustained by the knees, it verges on the dangerous.</p>
<p>The three climbs already described are all on the east side of the rock, and they lead direct to the High Man, the total height ascended being about one hundred feed. But there are other and longer climbs both on the east and west side of the rock which conduct to the summit of the Low Man, whence there is some good climbing to reach the highest point. Those climbs are very little known, and any detailed description of them is impossible, as they may be varied in several ways. As far as the summit of the Low Man, where the east and west routes unite, they are scrambles rather than climbs; but during the whole ascent great care is necessary, for on slipping on these sides of the rock the cragsman would bound from on rocky ledge to another, and finally pitch to the very base of the rock, if not beyond &#8212; a matter of some five hundred feet. More than one way may be taken from the Low Man to the High Man, but one is chiefly used. Care is necessary throughout; and the worst bit is the ascent of a wall of rock close to a poised block which is easily recognisable. The descent here is especially awkward. Indeed, in nine cases of ten the descent or rocks is more difficult than the ascent; had we eyes in our heels the difficulties would be equalised. Two ascents to High Man have been made from Jordan Gap by Mr. W. P. Haskett-Smitt, the first and only cragsman who has accomplished this feat. Much of our recent knowledge of the Pillar is due to Mr. Haskett-Smith, a most skilful and daring climber. This gentleman has ascended the rock by more than twelve distinct routes, and to his courtesy we are indebted for several of the measurements of parts of the Rock which are here made public for the first time.</p>
<p>Of early ascents of the Pillar Rock little is known. By the dalespeople it was long considered inaccessible, and Mr. G. Seatree, in his little pamphlet on the Lake District, says that it was first scaled by "a hardy young shepherd, named Atchinson," in the year 1826. Speaking of this, or some other early ascent, to a member of the Alpine Club, an old dalesman said, in that Cumberland dialect which is now becoming so rare: "Fwoks deah sai theer waz a chap at yance gat tul t' toop efter a fox, bit t' crahg waz seah brant an' slape in yah pleace at theer waz neah hod for owdther hand near fe&#249;t, an' he hed to ram his jackalegs inta a lahl crack to sarra for a step up." It may be noted that the shepherd James, in Wordsworth's poem The Brothers, is described as being killed through falling from the summit of the Pillar Rock, and the supposition that the poet was here confounding the top of the Rock ith the top of the mountain, is precluded by the accurate description he gives of the place in an earlier passage. The writer of Murray's Handbook to the Lakes was not, however, so well informed; for he makes the astounding assertion that the Pillar Rock is the top of the Pillar Mountain. Of ascents between that of the shepherd in 1826, and that of Mr. Leslie Stephen, about 1854, little or nothing can be discovered, though the name of Mr. Baumgraten is mentioned as among the first. It was not till 1874 that the Rock became known. About that time a bottle was deposited on the top, and visitors left their cards; but, on June 29th, 1876, two navvies who reached the top, carried away the bottle, cards, handkerchiefs, and other mementoes of the early climbers. As far as can be ascertained, a Miss A. Barker, who ascended July 9, 1870, was the first lady to reach the top; Miss Mary Westmoreland, of Penrith, was the second (1874); Mrs. Ann Crears (June, 1875) being the third; and Miss Edith Maitland and Miss Butler (August, 1875) the fourth and fifth. But of all the earlier climbers of the Pillar Rock, the Rev. James Jackson, the octogenarian clergyman of Sandwith, near Whitehaven, was the most remarkable. This enthusiastic old mountaineer was a man of character; energetic, quick-tempered, and eccentric. He was a bit of a versifier, had travelled on the Continent, and had brought home certain relics from Loretto, which he deposited on the top of the Pillar Rock, whence they were ruthlessly carried by the vandal navvies in 1876. He had an ethusiastic love for his native lake mountains, "from Black Combe to Skiddaw," and in his ramblings on the fells, he had often looked down longingly to the Pillar Rock from the mountain, but deemed it inaccessible. Having read, however, a rhyming account of their ascent, contributed to a local paper by the Messrs. Thomas and Edward Westmoreland, two noted Penrith climbers, the old clergymen resolved to try,<pb n="82"/> and aided by ropes and spiked nails he succeeded in reaching the top on May 31, 1875. Mr. Jackson was then in his seventy-ninth year, and he was immensely pleased with his achievement. He dubbed himself "Patriarch of the Pillarites," and at once took the Rock under his especial care. On May 1st, 1878, this fine old mountaineer, then in his eighty-second year, fell a victim to his passion for climbing. He started from Wastdale, provided with poles and ropes, intending to ascent the Rock; but as he did not return, search parties were organised, and on the second day his body was found in a large hollow called Great Doup, somewhat to the east of the Rock. The 1st of May had been misty, and it was evident that he had approached too near the edge of the precipice, had lost his balance, and fallen a distance of about three hundred feet. In a bottle in his pocket, which he had intended to leave on the Rock, were these lines:</p>
<poem>
<line>Two elephantine properties are mine,</line>
<line>For I can bend to pick up pin or plack;</line>
<line>And when this year the Pillar Rock I climb</line>
<line>Fourscore and two's the howdah on my back.</line>
</poem>
<p>Two years later two veteran lovers of the Lake Mountains (Mr. F. H. Bowring and the late Mr. J. Maitland, who had been playfully appointed "presumptive patriarch" by Mr. Jackson) placed a cairn and iron cross on the spot where the old man's body was found.</p>
<p>The sad death of the youth Walker, who was killed on Good Friday, 1883, by slipping on the snow and falling over the precipice of the east fully, has also led to the belief that the Rock is more dangerous than it really is. No accident has yet occurred on the Rock itself, nor need there be any if it be attempted in proper weather by active, steady-headed cragsmen. Between twenty and thirty persons reach the summit every year, and of these probably three or four are ladies. Almost all ordinary climbers go by the ladder, ledge, and chimney route, which is, indeed, the only one at all generally known. Ladies attempting the ascent will find an Alpine dress a great convenience. The actual top of the Rock is small, and to look over into Ennerdale gives something of the impression of being on a mast-head at sea. A unique ascent was made during the present summer, when a party of seven (including two ladies) climbed the Rock by the little-known east route, starting from the bottom of the Great Chimney, and took a guitar with them to the top. A pleasant hour of good music followed.</p>
<p>In another article we shall give an account of climbs in other parts of the Lake District.</p>
</chap>
<chap title="Part II.">
<gap desc="Published in ALL THE YEAR ROUND. [November 8, 1884], edited by Charles Dickens"/>
<pb n="110"/>
<head level="2" align="center">THE CLIMBS OF THE ENGLISH LAKE DISTRICT.</head>
<head level="3" align="center">IN TWO PARTS. PART II.</head>
<p>In a previous article we described the climbs of the most interesting English crag &#8212; the Pillar Rock in Ennerdale. In the present paper we deal with ascents in other parts of the English Lake District, and among these the precipices and crags of Scafell are second in interest only to the Pillar Rock itself. To describe with minuteness the many climbs on Scafell is impossible in the space at our disposal; the cragsman could well spend a fortnight in clambering about the mountain, and even then its climbs would not be exhausted. To climbers, Scafell is a more interesting mountain than its companion, Scafell Pikes. On the Upper Eskdale side the latter has indeed some fine precipices and crags, which are almost wholly unexplored; but nowhere does it offer such interesting ascents as those to be found such interesting ascents as those to be found on Scafell immediately around Mickledore. To be filled with the sense of the grandeur of the Scafell crags, it is best to approach them from below &#8212; that is, from Wastdale. On rounding the low shoulder of Lingmell above Wastwater, and following the course of the stream on the right hand, the stranger will find himself in a grand mountain cove. On either hand are Lingmell and the low shoulder of Scafell, while the rugged cliffs of Scafell and the Pikes are in front. Between the two mountains is the stranger, square, tooth-like gap called Mickledore, and from it the Scafell cliffs rise in a grand serrated curve, like the back of scaled monster rearing itself in air. From below Mickledore descends for more than half a mile a long, tapering, grassy mound, locally known as Brown Tongue. The resemblance is complete, and the wild mountain cove in which the tongue reposes may well be likened to the cavernous mouth of a giant. The place is solitary, remote, impressive. It becomes more imposing the nearer the cliffs are approached, and when close under the "battlemented front of Scafell," the wildness of the scene fills the mind. It is wholly grim and stern; no touch of beauty relieves the austerity. Whether sun-smitten in the summer noon, or enwreathed with flying mists, the cliffs of Scafell are always grand. They compose the finest rock scenery in England, and there is nothing grander in Scuir-na-Gillian or the Cuchullins.</p>
<p>Mickledore may be reached by scrambling up the steeply sloping "screes" which form its Wastdale slope; but the easier and more romantic approach is by the grassy ledge, which will be seen projecting from the face of the Scafell precipice. This ledge, or shelf, is in but few places less than four feet wide. In places it is composed of shattered heaps of rock, which seem barely to keep their equilibrium; but though there is a precipice of considerable height on the left hand, the passage along the ledge is free from risk, so long as the rock-wall on the right is closely hugged. By one who watched from below the passage along the ledge of some of the early pioneers of Lake climbing, it was christened the "Rake's Progress," and the name appears apt, when it is remembered that the ledge leads from the lower limb of the Lord's Rake to the Mickledore Ridge. Stepping from the Rake's Progress on to Mickledore, the stranger finds himself in what the guidebooks call "one of Nature's most savage retreats," and truly the scene is wild enough. The summits of Scafell and Scafell Pikes &#8212; the two highest mountains in England &#8212; are but one thousand two hundred yards apart in a straight line, but between them is the strange gap called Mickledore. From the summit of Scafell Pikes is rock-strewn sides slope gradually towards Scafell. Presently the slopes steepen on either hand,<pb n="111"/> leaving a saddle-shaped ravine. The saddle dwindles to a roof-like ridge, which stretches in a gentle curve from mountain to mountain, till it ends abruptly against the wedge-shaped cliffs of Scafell, which rise almost vertically for five hundred feet and more. Though the slopes of the ridge are steep, and the ridge itself is so narrow that it may easily be bestrided, there is no danger whatever in walking along it; yet appalling are the terrors of this gorge as told in the older guide-books. "It may indeed be crossed," says Murray, "but the passage is difficult, and at one point dangerous, and it should be attempted only by experienced cragsmen, or members of the Alpine Club." In another passage the same writer thus speaks of the southern slope from the ridge to the strange solitudes of Upper Eskdale &#8212; a slope which is indeed steep, stony, and tedious, but nothing more: "The descent into Eskdale is over terraces of slippery turf, and down slanting sheets of bare rock, which makes the enterprise, even with the assistance of a guide, one of peril. Some have attempted this descent, and turned back in terror at the difficulties before them; but there are places from which a tourist might find it even more difficult to retreat than to advance."</p>
<p>Looking up at the Scafell cliffs from Mickledore, the direct ascent appears impossible, as, in fact, it has hitherto proved. But there is more than one way of successfully turning the flank of these forbidding precipices. The routes by the "Broad Stand" and "Chimney," on the left or Eskdale side of Mickledore, are now tolerably well known to lake-climbers; they are even described with more or less accuracy in guide-books. The Broad Stand is reached by descending close under the cliffs for twenty-one yards till a cleft, eighteen inches wide, is seen between two small upright rocks. Any man of moderate size can worm his way through the cleft, and climb out at the end on to the grassy corner. From this point there is only one practicable way. It lies up walls and slopes of rocks, and "to any ordinary cragsman it presents," said Professor Tyndall, writing in the Saturday Review in 1859, "a pleasant bit of mountain practice, and nothing more." The Professor admits, however, that "to persons given to giddiness, or lacking sufficient sureness of foot or strength of grasp," the climb is not recommendable. The danger consists in slipping on any of the slopes or walls, when the climber would go bumping down many feet without any chance of stopping till, with considerable personal discomfort, he reached the base of the precipice. The entrance to the Scafell Chimney (a gulley two feet wide running into and up the face of the cliff) is a few yards lower down than the entrance to the Broad Stand. It is impossible to go straight up the Chimney, as the way is blocked by an overhanging slab, and escape must be effected either by the right-hand wall near the top, where the hand-hold is miserably inadequate, or by the "corner" forty feet up the Chimney. The passage of the corner is a matter of stride and balance, as there is no positive hold for the hands. There is a bad drop into the Chimney behind, and a slip in rounding the corner would end in broken limbs, if not a battered skull. A man essaying the corner must apply himself like a plaister to an unpleasant projecting rock, and then by shifting the weight from one foot to the other (for the legs are stretched widely apart) he can creep round. These climbs in the Chimney are very little known, and none of them should be attempted in wet weather, when the Chimney is indeed a mere spout. Even when the escape is made from the Chimney by the routes named, the remainder of the ascent requires care, as the rocks here are smooth, and they slope steeply towards Eskdale, some at as great an angle as fifty-four degrees. Last August a young and active climber, forgetting for a moment the caution that should always go hand-in-hand with daring, attempted to cross one of these smooth, sloping rocks. He slipped, and slid rapidly down for twenty-seven feet, vainly catching at the smooth surface and then bounded through the air in a leap of seventy feet, falling full on his face just as the edge of the dry watercourse below the Chimney. Happily the place on which he fell was loose and not rocky ground; and he escaped with a broken rib and some dangerous face and head wounds. The escape from death was almost miraculous; many men have been killed by falling a quarter of the distance. The adventure may serve to remind other climbers that the Scafell cliffs must be treated with due respect.</p>
<p>There is yet another and a more direct way of climbing the Scafell cliffs from Mickledore, which, for want of a better name, we may christen the "North Climb." This route is known to very few. It was discovered for himself in 1874, by Mr. George Seatree, the author of a pleasantly-written little pamphlet on the Lake District, now, <pb n="112"/>unfortunately, out of print. When Mr. Seatree ascended, he was with a friend, and the Wastdale people received his story with incredulity, "auld Will Ritson" declaring that "nowt but a fleein' thing could get up theear." Mr. Seatree, however, was preceded in this ascent by Major J.P. Cundill, R.A., who climbed this way both up and down alone as long ago as 1869. For the benefit of climbers we quote here Mr. Seatree's description: "From the ridge we traversed a ledge of grass-covered rock (the Rake's Progress) to the right, until we reached a detached boulder, stepping upon which we were enabled to get hand-hold of a crevice six or seven feet from where we stood. To draw ourselves up so as to get our feet upon this was the difficulty; there is only one small foothold in that distance, and to have slipped here would have precipitated the climber many feed below. Having succeeded in gaining this foothold, we found ourselves in a small rectangular recess, with barely room to turn round. From here it was necessary to draw ourselves carefully over two other ledges into a small rift in the rocks, and then traverse on our hands and knees another narrow ledge of about eight feet to the left, which brought us nearly in a line with Mickledore Ridge. From here all was comparatively smooth sailing." The "detached boulder" may be identified with certainty by noticing that it is embedded in the Rake's Progress close to the top of a funnel-shaped grassy gully, about ten or twelve yards from Mickledore. None but experienced climbers should attempt the "north climb" from Mickledore. It is unpleasant to stick on one of the higher ledges, for from these the climber looks almost vertically down to the valley many feet below. In these circumstances a sudden seizure akin to sea-sickness may assail the cragsman who has not his nerves under thorough control.</p>
<p>All who have been on the top of Scafell, near Mickledore, must have looked down with wonder and admiration into Deep Ghyll, that vast, almost vertical funnel, which descends from the top of the mountain to the Lord's Rake. It can be descended straight down its whole length, though in one palce there is a very steep pitch, and some little danger is incurred from falling stones. But the most upper part of Deep Ghyll is a pinnacle rock with some slight resemblance, from certain points of view, to the celebrated Pieter Botte in Mauritius, except that the stone on the top is much smaller than the knob which forms the summit of the Mauritius mountain. The Deep Ghyll pinnacle is perhaps best named the "Scafell Pillar," for on examination it will be found to have several features in common with the Ennerdale Pillar. Both have a Pisgah rock and a Jordan gap, both have a slating slab in similar positions. So inaccessible does the Scafell Pillar appear, that it is probable no one ever thought to making an attempt upon it till Mr. W. P. Haskett Smith, whose climbs on the Ennerdale Pillar were referred to in a previous article, looking at the Rock with the eye of a genius for climbing, thought he could see a way to the top. He made the attempt alone in September of this year, and successfully reached the top, being the first man to set foot on the summit of this forbidding peak. A week or two later, Mr. Haskett Smith, accompanied by Mr. J. W. Robinson, a local cragsman of much enthusiasm, judgment and skill, made another attack upon the rock. Starting from a point about sixty yards from the lower ned of the Rake's Progress, and climbing upwards, they soon entered a very long, narrow, almost vertical chimney, the ascent of which taxed their strength greatly. Emerging at last, they reached a steep ar&#234;te, which led direct to the ridge of the Scafell Pillar, and thus to the top, where they left their names in a glass bottle. Now that the way is known, the Deep Ghyll Pillar will doubtless be attempted by other climbers. On the whole Wastdale side of Scafell there is fine climbing, nor are the minor mountains which buttress the great heights by any means deficient in interest.</p>
<p>Of all the natural features of the Wastwater District, Piers Ghyll is perhaps the most noticeable. No one coming over the Sty Head Pass from Borrowdale can fail to see this remarkable fissure which, after making an almost right-angled bend in the low ground at the foot of Lingmell, suddenly narrows, and runs straight into the face of the Lingmell crags. So far as can be ascertained, Piers Ghyll has never been climbed. It is one of the few places which have resisted the assaults of the present generation of climbers. Of course when we speak of climbing Piers Ghyll we do no mean merely penetrating into the fissure till further progress is barred, and then climbing<pb n="113"/> out up one of the sides. The Ghyll cannot properly be said to have been climbed until all the obstacles in the ravine are overcome, and the climber emerges at the top, under Lingmell crags. In all probability this feat will be soon achieved; but so far, notwithstanding the elaborate attempts which have been made with ropes, ice-axes, and steel wedges, everyone has failed. Anyone may scamble a good way along the torrent-bed in Piers Ghyll. Soon the ravine narrows, the stream is pent in narrow bounds, the walls on either hand rise higher and are almost perpendicular. Daylight is obscured, and after heavy rain the noise of the falling water is deafening. The first difficult place is a smooth slab of rock on the left hand. This can be passed; but the difficulties begin at the third waterfall, where there is a vast curving rock shelving towards the stream. Much, of course, depends on the state of the stream. Long ago, when Mr. James Payn, then a young man at college, visited the Lake District, it was his ardent delight to roll huge stones down the mountain-side and hark as they thundered into the Pease Ghyll (for so the novelist spells the name). Mr. Payn tells how a shepherd of Wastdale, collecting his sheep on Lingmell in the snow, slipped and fell into Piers Ghyll. His iron heel caught in some crevice and wrenched off the boot-sole, thus breaking the fall, the man survived his perilous adventure. There is a rumour too that a hardy climber, resolved on conquering the passage of the Ghyll, passed difficulty after difficulty till he reached the spot from which advance and retreat seemed equally impossible. He lost nerve, and dared not make an attempt. There he remained for twenty-four hours, his shouts rendered impotent by the roaring waters. At last, when starvation stared him in the face, he gathered courage, and flung himself from his resting-place into the deep pool formed by one of the falls. The water broke his fall, and he scrambled back a sound man. But his adventure is not forgotten; and the local guides tell you flatly that Piers Ghyll cannot be climbed, and that its summit was the haunt of evil spirits. But the Matterhorn succumbed nevertheless, and so, we doubt not, will Piers Ghyll when the right man appears. To climb the whole length of Piers Ghyll, and then scale the Lingmell crags above, and so reach the summit of the mountain, is pronounced by a competent judge the hardest and finest climb in the English Lake District, and one which would keep the climber as severely on the stretch as any piece of rock-climbing in Switzerland.</p>
<p>The exhaustible richness of the Wastwater district, from the climber's point of view, tempts us to linger too long in it, to the exclusion of other districts. We will not speak, therefore, of the chimneys in the north side of Great End, of the "Horn," the "Screen," and "Westmoreland's Chimney" on Great Gable, or the Stirrup crags on Yewbarrow, or of the rotten gulleys in the Screes, but will pass to the consideration of climbs in other parts of the district.</p>
<p>Of these, Striding Edge, on Helvellyn, is by far the best known. Scott's grandiose poem and Wordsworth's exquisite verses have given immortality to Striding Edge. Save for the ugly dam which banks up the shore of the Red Tarn for the convenience of the Glenriddging lead-mines, which have almost destroyed the beauty of the upper reach of Ullswater, all is now as it was when young Gough &#8212; Scott's Pilgrim of Nature &#8212; slipped over, and was killed, in the spring of 1805. The setting of the two poems is there, all except the eagle. If you chance to be on Striding Edge on a stormy day, when the mists are boiling up from the coves of Grisedale, you will say it is a place an English Manfred might choose for his soliloquies. But as for danger, there is hardly any. To the cragsman it is a promenade; for ladies, merely a pleasant piece of exertion. If any persons are rendered giddy by the steepness of the slopes, and on the Grisedale side they are certainly steep, they can be perfectly secure by taking the lower path. Not far from the Patterdale end of the ridge is a small iron cross, set up to the memory of one Robert Dixon, who was killed on Striding Edge while following the Patterdale fox-hounds in November, 1858. The cross is small, and may easily be missed among the rocks.</p>
<p>Far more imposing than the Striding Edge on Helvellyn is the little-known Sharp Edge on Blencathara. Blencathara is one of the very few lake mountains about which legends are told. On the neighbouring Sowter Fall, marching regiments, troops of phantom horsemen, and all sorts of strange apparations have been seen; and in Scales Tarn, lying at the foot of the precipitous Tarn Crag, the stars<pb n="114"/> are to be seen at noonday. The Broad, Narrow, and Sharp Edges on Blencathara are among the most interesting things to be seen among the lake mountains, and the Sharp Edge is certainly the sharpest in the district. It is much narrower than Striding Edge, but nowhere does it offer any difficulty to the ordinary climber. The ascent of Tarn Crag, after leaving the ridge, is indeed much more unpleasant. In ice and snow these ridges present real difficulties. In the winter of 1880-01, an overhanging snow-cornice extended for a mile from the first to the second cairn on Blencathara, and so solid was it that it was possible to stand on the cornice well out beyond the edge of the mountain.</p>
<p>In these two papers it has been our aim to furnish the cragsman with a rough guide to the best rock climbing in the Lake District. Space compels us to omit several interesting places, such as Pavey Ark, the climbs from Grisedale Pass up to St. Sunday Crag, and others. A stranger may waste valuable time in finding the climbs best worth doing; for, except in Mr. Prior's convenient little work, he will not find any printed account of them. Mr. Prior is aware of the existence of the Chimney and Broad Stand routes up Scafell; he even gives a vague little diagram of the "easy way" up the Pillar Rock. But with this noteworthy exception, the stranger is unaided by the guide-books. Wherever there are mountains, the climber can always find ascents for himself, but nowhere are the climbs so interesting and so numerous as in the neighbourhood of Wastdale. To see the Lake District properly, it is best to take a certain number of centres, and explore thoroughly the country round each. Let no one be persuaded to strap a knapsack on his shoulders and roam the country. Beautiful scenery is not to be enjoyed by rushing through it with a heavy weight on your back; you must live in it to love it. Bowness, Keswick, Langdale Valley, Wastdale, Patterdale, and Mardale Green will be found excellent centres. Round each of these places there is scenery of differing character. Few things are more remarkable in the Lake District than the variety of its scenery. The elements are of the simplest; the effects produced are most varied. The district is seamed with mountain valleys, yet no two are alike. Nature seems to have lavished all her beauties on this unique spot of English earth. It is exquisitely compact. The most varied beauties lie side by side, but they never jostle or compete with each other. There is space enough for each to have its appropriate setting. It is this compactness of the English Lake District which constitutes at once its charm and its danger. A very little work in the way of "railway enterprise" would ruin the district for ever. Already the railways approach perilously near the most sacred solitudes. Between Penrith and Keswick, the railway actually comes within the mountain rampart, and cuts off Blencathara from its fellow peaks. At Lakeside, at the foot of Windermere, there is a station almost on the lake; at Coniston is another; at Keswick the station is only a few minutes' walk from Derwentwater; at Boot, in Eskdale, the terminus is within ten miles of the remotest mountain fastnesses.</p>
<p>In England, with its vested interests and antique rights, we cannot unfortunately adopt the example so worthily set by the United States, in the case of the Yellowstone Park, and keep for the enjoyment of the public for ever the most beautiful spots of our overcrowded island. But with regard to the English Lake District, it should be well understood that any further railways will ruin it beyond hope. In Switzerland, where the distances are much greater, and the heights much vaster, a few mountains railways are almost unnoticed; in Cumberland and Westmoreland they would dominate the landscape. The specious plea of the public good cannot be urged in favour of schemes of railway extension in the lakes. Trains carry tourists to the very confines of the district on all sides. Private gain is the only motive which can prompt to further "railway enterprise." The Lake District Defence Association is doing excellent work. Already it has defeated the Borrowdale and Ennerdale schemes &#8212; schemes for mineral railways, which would have absolutely ruined the beauty of the two valleys. But railway interests are very powerful, and fresh schemes are floated every year. Manchester, having fouled with sewage and manufactures all the streams in its neighbourhood, has laid violent hands on Thirlmere, and is only waiting the necessary capital to convert that lake into a reservoir. The example cannot but be encouraging to the promoters of railway schemes. That they will triumph before long seems more than probable, and when that day comes the Lake District will be irreparably ruined.
</p>
</chap>
</text>
