<text id="1776_a">
<pb n="title"/>
<head level="2" align="center">AN</head>
<head level="1" align="center">EXCURSION</head>
<head level="2" align="center">TO THE</head>
<head level="1" align="center">LAKES</head>
<head level="2" align="center">IN</head>
<head level="2" align="center">WESTMORELAND and CUMBERLAND;</head>
<head level="2" align="center">WITH</head>
<head level="1" align="center">A TOUR</head>
<head level="3" align="center">Through PART of the</head>
<head level="1" align="center">NORTHERN COUNTIES,</head>
<head level="3" align="center">In the Years 1773 and 1774.</head>
<gap desc="underlined"/>
<head level="2" align="center">By W. HUTCHINSON.</head>
<gap desc="double underline"/>
<head level="3" align="center">LONDON:</head>
<p>Printed for J. WILKIE, No. 71, St Paul's Church-yard, and W. CHARNLEY, in Newca&#8747;tle.</p>
<gap desc="short underline"/>
<p>MDCCLXXVI.</p>
<gap desc="blank pages"/>
<pb n="1"/>
<head level="2" align="center">AN</head>
<head level="1" align="center">EXCURSION, &#38;c.</head>
<gap desc="image of Bowes Castle, Yorkshire surrounded by a wreath"/>
<p>WHENEVER I have read the de&#8747;criptions given by travellers of foreign countries, in which their beauties and antiquities were lavi&#8747;hly prai&#8747;ed, I have always regretted a negleƈt which has attended the delightful &#8747;cenes in this i&#8747;land. The monuments of antiquity, di&#8747;per&#8747;ed <pb n="2"/> over this country, are many and curious, &#8747;ome of them aro&#8747;e in the remote&#8747;t ages, and point out to us the revolutions and hi&#8747;tory of our own kingdom: a degree of knowledge of the fir&#8747;t importance to Engli&#8747;hmen.</p>
<p>The rapid progre&#8747;s of cultivation in the northern counties, within this century, threatens the de&#8747;truƈtion of many of their antique remains; -- the plough &#8747;hare has already in many places gone over them, and perhaps in another age not even their names will remain to denote their &#8747;ite. -- To pre&#8747;erve their memory to after times, to point out therefore, and de&#8747;cribe their &#8747;trength, form, and magnitude, I humbly pre&#8747;ume, are no in&#8747;ignificant pur&#8747;uits in the traveller, who thereby con&#8747;igns to po&#8747;terity the evidence of tho&#8747;e circum&#8747;tances in hi&#8747;tory, which will be momentous to all ages.</p>
<p>Such &#8747;entiments gave ri&#8747;e to a &#8747;ummer's excur&#8747;ion, the plea&#8747;ures of which I have endeavoured to communicate to the reader in the following pages.</p>
<pb n="3"/>
<p>We were conduƈted to Bowes in Yorkshire.</p>
<head level="2" align="center">BOWES</head>
<p>Is of great antiquity, in which is its chief con&#8747;equence. -- The country around is meanly cultivated, its habitations in general melancholy; and what alone claims the attention of a traveller, is the ruin of a ca&#8747;tle, &#8747;uppo&#8747;ed by &#8747;ome of Roman con&#8747;truƈtion; but with greater propriety by others, to be the <i>Turris de Arcubus</i>, built by Alan, fir&#8747;t Earl of Richmond, in the time of the Conqueror: It is &#8747;ituate near the old high &#8747;treet, which led from the Cataraƈtonium of the Romans.</p>
<p>This ca&#8747;tle is fifty three feet in height, built of hewn &#8747;tone, of excellent workman&#8747;hip, forming a &#8747;quare of equal &#8747;ides, eighty one feet each; the windows are irregular; and the walls, which are cemented with lime mixed with &#8747;mall flints, are near five feet in thickne&#8747;s -- it is now much defaced, the outward ca&#8747;ing being &#8747;tript off in many places. -- This edifice <pb n="4"/>appears to have been divided into &#8747;everal apartments, the principal of which was vaulted, and &#8747;upported by a central pillar.</p> 
<p>Bowes Ca&#8747;tle is &#8747;ituated on the brink of a hill, declining &#8747;wiftly to the &#8747;outhward, at who&#8747;e foot runs the river Greta; -- it is &#8747;urrounded with a deep ditch, beyond which, on the &#8747;outhern &#8747;ide, is an open area or platform, extending from the ca&#8747;tle-moat ninety paces: and from ea&#8747;t to we&#8747;t one hundred paces: the angles are obtu&#8747;e, and a wide acce&#8747;s appears in the centre. -- On examination, this is indi&#8747;putably proved to be the remains of the Roman &#8747;tation, the Vallum having formed a &#8747;trong outwork to the ca&#8747;tle, of great height towards the &#8747;outh. -- This kind of &#8747;ituation was in many places cho&#8747;en for ereƈting fortre&#8747;&#8747;es, after the departure of the Romans; &#8747;everal ca&#8747;tles which we viewed on our tour, are &#8747;o placed. -- On the ea&#8747;tern point of the &#8747;tation, we were &#8747;hewn the &#8747;ite and remains of a Bath, with its aqueduƈt, which are now totally in ruins, and overgrown with weeds and brambles -- the foundations &#8747;hew the building to have been thirty feet<pb n="5"/> long within, and twenty broad, with a &#8747;mall apartment to the ea&#8747;t fifteen feet &#8747;quare; the acce&#8747;s from the &#8747;outh.</p>
<p>On a late inclo&#8747;ure of &#8747;ome common lands belonging Bowes, an ancient aqueduƈt was di&#8747;covered, which conveyed the water the di&#8747;tance of two miles from a place called Levar, or Levy-pool, to the ca&#8747;tle, &#8747;ufficient to &#8747;upply the garri&#8747;on and al&#8747;o the baths. This di&#8747;covery led me, in the &#8747;ucceeding year, to Levar-pool, in hopes I &#8747;hould find, in that &#8747;eque&#8747;tered and little-vi&#8747;ited place, &#8747;ome remains of Roman-work not known to antiquaries, and fix the &#8747;ite of the baths of Lavatrae, e&#8747;pecially as &#8747;ome adjoining lands bear the name of Lavartree, or Laretree; but my expeƈtations were di&#8747;appointed, nothing but va&#8747;t works of ancient &#8747;tone quarries were to be &#8747;een; from whence, in all probability, the materials for building the Roman Vallum and the pre&#8747;ent ca&#8747;tle were won.</p>
<p>Antiquaries have hithero fixed the ancient Lavatrae at Bowes, that place corre&#8747;ponding with the di&#8747;tances &#8747;et out in <pb n="6"/>the Itinerarie. -- The antiquity of Bowes is confirmed by the great number of Roman coins found there, Plate I. and II. for &#8747;everal of which I am indebted to the Gentlemen of that place; particularly the late Charles Lowe Whytell, E&#8747;q; who &#8747;ince the fir&#8747;t publication di&#8747;covered them, in laying the foundations of a &#8747;ummer &#8747;eat; and forming his garden ground near the old ca&#8747;tle.</p>
<p>The uppermo&#8747;t coin repre&#8747;ented in Plate I. is a con&#8747;ular medallion of HADRIAN, of the old mixed bra&#8747;s, &#8747;uppo&#8747;ed to be &#8747;truck on the fir&#8747;t day of January, a day &#8747;acred to Janus, and ob&#8747;erved by the Romans with great &#8747;olemnity, as portentive of the felicity or adver&#8747;ity of the new year. It would be tedious to de&#8747;cribe the whole, as they are accurately &#8747;hewn in the Plate. The letters placed above each denote the metal.</p>
<p>Several parts of earthen ve&#8747;&#8747;els have al&#8747;o been dug up here, of the red kind; by placing many of the fragments together, I have been able to form &#8747;uch parts of two of them as are repre&#8747;ented in Plate II. One
<pb n="7"/>
of the ve&#8747;&#8747;els, when entire, has been about twelve inches over the brim, the other about ten: the figures are finely relieved, and the red glazing pretty well pre&#8747;erved -- I am inclined to think the&#8747;e have been &#8747;acred ve&#8747;&#8747;els, the one dedicated to the &#8747;ervice of VENUS, the other to DIANA; they were u&#8747;ed as the Urceus, and held the water with which the people were &#8747;prinkled. -- Mr Addi&#8747;on in his travels, &#8747;ays, that on many altars he perceived the Patera was formed without any handle: the form of the&#8747;e ve&#8747;&#8747;els, and the figures with which they are ornamented, will not allow a conjeƈture that they were &#8747;epulchral: -- the fe&#8747;tival of the Roman Hunters, &#8747;acred to Diana, and for which &#8747;ervice one of the ve&#8747;&#8747;els appears to be adapted, was celebrated on the thirteenth day of Augu&#8747;t.</p>
<p>Camden &#8747;ays, he &#8747;aw an altar to the honour of HADRIAN in the church at Bowes, with this in&#8747;cription:</p>
<poem>
<line>IMP CÆSARI DIVI TRAIANI PARTHICI maxfilio</line>
<line>DIVI NERVÆ NEPOTI TRAIANO Hadria</line>
<line>NO AUG. PONT. MAXIM --</line>
<line>Cos I--PP--COH. IIII F--</line>
<line>IO. SEV.</line>
</poem>
<pb n="8"/>
<p>From the mo&#8747;t diligent &#8747;earch, I could find no &#8747;uch in&#8747;cription; -- he &#8747;ays the following fragment was al&#8747;o found there:</p>
<poem><line>-- -- --</line>
<line>-- -- --</line>
<line>NOL . CAE -- --</line> 
<line>FRONTINVS --</line>
<line>COH.I.THRAC.</line>
</poem>
<p>Sir Robert Cotton obtained from thence an altar thus in&#8747;cribed:</p>
<poem><line>DAE FORTVNAE -- pro Deæ.</line>
<line> -- --</line> 
<line>-- --</line>
<line>VIRIVS LVPVS -- Proprætor under</line>
<line>LEG. AUG. PR. PR.	Severus.</line>
<line>BALINEVM VI -- pro Balneum.</line>
<line>IGNIS EXVST</line>
<line>VM. COH. ITHR</line>
<line>ACVM REST</line>
<line>ITVIT CVRAN</line>
<line>TEVAL. FRON</line>
<line>TONE PRAEF</line>
<line>EQ.ALAE VETTO -- the Vettones were a people of Spain.</line>
</poem>
<p> -- He thought this &#8747;o curious, that he removed it to Connington. From this in&#8747;cription we may determine, that whil&#8747;t Virius Lupus ruled as Lieutenant General and Proprætor of Britain, under Severus the Emperor, the fir&#8747;t cohort of the Thracians <pb n="9"/>lay here in garri&#8747;on, for who&#8747;e u&#8747;e he re&#8747;tored the hot baths. This place was al&#8747;o garri&#8747;oned by a <i>Numerus Exploratorum</i> in the time of the Notitia<ptr target="n1"/>.</p>
<note id="n1">Camden's Britannia.</note>
<p>The modern name of Bowes we may with &#8747;ome degree of propriety derive from the authority of an ancient manu&#8747;cript belonging the di&#8747;&#8747;olved mona&#8747;try of St Mary's in York:</p>
<p>" Alanus niger Comes Richmondiæ, " unus fundatorum hujus mona&#8747;terii, frater " fuit Ducis Britanniæ, intravitq; Angliam " in Exercieu Willielmi Conque&#8747;toris; " cui diƈtus Willielmus contulit, " pro &#8747;ervicio &#8747;uo, Dominium &#38; Comitatum " Richmondiæ: et po&#8747;tea idem Alanus “ primus Comes Richmondiæ, in defen&#8747;ionem " Tenentium &#8747;uorum Comitatus " prædiƈti, contra expugnationes hominum " de We&#8747;tmoreland et Cumberland " rebellantium, contra diƈtuna Conque&#8747;torem, " ac cum Go&#8747;patricio Duce Northumbriæ " adherentium Regi Scotorum, " ædificavit &#8747;ibi Turrim de Arcubus, in<pb n="10"/> "quo con&#8747;tituit Guillermum con&#8747;anguineum " &#8747;uum præfeƈtum &#8747;uper 500 &#8747;agittarios; " et dedit ei, &#8747;eutum proprium " cum armis Britanniæ, et tres arcus de&#8747;uper, " ac unum bundellum &#8747;agittarum, " pro capitali in&#8747;igni &#8747;uo: ip&#8747;e Guillermus " exindè nuncupatus fuit, Guillermus de " Arcubus<ptr target="n2"/>."</p>
<note id="n2">He was Ance&#8747;tor to the famous and knightly family of Bowes in the Bi&#8747;hoprie of Durham.</note>
<p>The antient cu&#8747;tom of Thorotoll is &#8747;till pre&#8747;erved here, though the fortre&#8747;s is no longer maintained, or of u&#8747;e to the country; which was the original con&#8747;ideration for a tax, now become grievous to the public: -- the right of execution and the ancient power of the Furca were happily extingui&#8747;hed with the Feudal tenures.</p>
<p>From Bowes advancing towards We&#8747;tmoreland, we were re&#8747;pited from the &#8747;ad &#8747;cene of barrenne&#8747;s which we were obliged to pa&#8747;s, by &#8747;ome infant inclo&#8747;ures and attempts towards cultivation; -- the climate, dreary vicinage of mountains, and <pb n="11"/>inclement &#8747;kies, &#8747;eemed to deny indu&#8747;try her natural rewards.</p>
<p>About two miles from Bowes is a &#8747;ingular curio&#8747;ity, called <i>Gods-bridge</i>, being a natural bridge of lime&#8747;tone rock, where, through a rude arch, &#8747;ixteen feet in &#8747;pan, the river Greta precipitates its waters; -- the way formed on the crown of this rock is about twenty feet wide, and the common carriage road over the river. -- After the Greta has pa&#8747;&#8747;ed this bridge, at a little di&#8747;tance it gains a &#8747;ubterraneous pa&#8747;&#8747;age for near half a mile; and in a lineal direƈtion breaks out again, through the cavities of the rocks. A few &#8747;canty meadows border the river, and cultivation &#8747;eems to awake from ignorance over the adjoining lands; where the plough &#8747;hare begins to make the traces of indu&#8747;try on the &#8747;kirts of the de&#8747;ert.</p>
<p>As we proceeded, <i>Spittle</i><ptr target="n3"/> pre&#8747;ented its <pb n="12"/>&#8747;olitary edifice to view; behind which, <i>Stainmore</i> ari&#8747;es; who&#8747;e heights feel the fury of both ea&#8747;tern and we&#8747;tern &#8747;torms; -- a dreary pro&#8747;peƈt extended to the eye, the hills were cloathed in heath, and all around a &#8747;cene of barrenne&#8747;s and deformity; -- the lower grounds were rent with torrents, which impetuou&#8747;ly poured from the &#8747;teeps in winter; and cha&#8747;ms harrowed on the &#8747;ides of hills, yawned with ragged rocks, or black and rotten earth. -- Here and there &#8747;cattered plots of gra&#8747;s variegated the pro&#8747;peƈt, where a few &#8747;heep found pa&#8747;turage; and now and then a little rill was &#8747;een in the deep dell, which as it flowed in di&#8747;con&#8747;olate meanders, was tinged with the &#8747;able &#8747;oil through which it pa&#8747;&#8747;ed. -- No habitation for mankind appeared on either &#8747;ide, but all was wilderne&#8747;s and horrid wa&#8747;te, over which the wearied eye travelled with anxiety.</p>
<note id="n3">At this place was an ancient Ho&#8747;pital, called Rerecro&#8747;s Ho&#8747;pital, or the Spittel upon Stainmore, which was given to the Nunnery of Maryke before 1171, by Ralph, &#8747;on of Ralph de Multon, or by Conan Earl of Richmond, and continued parcel of their po&#8747;&#8747;e&#8747;&#8747;ions till di&#8747;&#8747;olution. It was granted 7 Ed VI. to William Buckton and Roger Mar&#8747;hall. -- Vide Mona&#8747;t. Vol. I. p. 485. -- Dugdale's Baron, Vol. I. p. 270. -- Gale's Appendix to Richmond, p. 86.</note>
<pb n="13"/>
<p>At the turnpike-hou&#8747;e on Stainmore &#8747;tands a cylindrical &#8747;tone, which appears to have been a Roman guide po&#8747;t; the in&#8747;cription has had relation to a Coh. V. but is in every other part &#8747;o obliterated that it cannot now be made out. We approached ROY CROSS<ptr target="n4"/>, which is &#8747;aid to be the boundary &#8747;tone dividing York&#8747;hire from We&#8747;tmoreland. -- Heƈtor Boetius has de&#8747;cribed this to be the meer-&#8747;tone, ereƈted at the time that William the Conqueror granted Cumberland to the Scots, on condition they &#8747;hould hold it of him by homage, and a compaƈt not to engage in any mea&#8747;ures prejudicial to the crown of England. -- This cro&#8747;s &#8747;tands within the remains of a large entrenchment, defended by banks of earth ten paces wide, through which the pre&#8747;ent turnpike road now pa&#8747;&#8747;es. Plate III. fig. I.</p>
<note id="n4">Camden's Britannia.</note>
<p>Its form is an oblong &#8747;quare, extending from north to &#8747;outh, with two openings on every &#8747;ide of the &#8747;quare, exaƈtly oppo&#8747;ite each other, defended by a mound
<pb n="14"/>
of earth, placed in the front of each pa&#8747;s, ri&#8747;ing from the plane about five perpendicular feet, which is near the height of the entrenchment in its highe&#8747;t part.</p>
<p> -- The ea&#8747;tern &#8747;ide is two hundred and &#8747;eventy paces in length, the openings on the &#8747;ides are ten paces wide, the moles which defend the &#8747;ame thirty-&#8747;ix paces in circumference, and &#8747;tand ten paces from the outward edge of the entrenchment: the a&#8747;cent of the adjoining ground on this &#8747;ide is gradual for near half a mile.</p>
<p> -- The northern end is two hundred and forty-nine paces in length, with two openings therein, defended by moles of earth, &#8747;imilar to tho&#8747;e on the ea&#8747;tern quarter; and as the ground here is flat for a con&#8747;iderable di&#8747;tance, &#8747;o this part of the entrenchment was by nature rendered inacce&#8747;&#8747;able from the North by a deep mora&#8747;s.</p>
<p> -- The we&#8747;tern &#8747;ide is &#8747;imilar to tho&#8747;e before de&#8747;cribed, being two hundred and &#8747;eventy-eight paces in length, &#8747;tanding
<pb n="15"/>
on a &#8747;wift de&#8747;cent, which falls without intermi&#8747;&#8747;ion for half a mile or upwards.</p>
<p> -- The &#8747;outhern end is in length one hundred and eighty-one paces, has its openings and moles as before de&#8747;cribed, but &#8747;tands on the brink of a precipice of con&#8747;iderable height: -- on the highe&#8747;t ground within the entrenchment is a large mound of earth, of a &#8747;quare figure, ari&#8747;ing from the plane near three perpendicular feet, and in circumference fifty-three paces.</p> 
<p>We have little or no account of this entrenchment in hi&#8747;tory, and are left to conjeƈture to what people it might belong. -- As it lies on the Roman road, it &#8747;trikes one with an apprehen&#8747;ion, that it was of Roman original; but the &#8747;ingularity of the pa&#8747;&#8747;es and mounds which guard them, do not corre&#8747;pond with their u&#8747;ual mode of fortifying a camp, though the interior mound may not improperly be regarded as the Prætorium. From the confliƈts between the northern Engli&#8747;h and the Normans after the conque&#8747;t, and prior to William's ceding Cumberland to the Scots, 
<pb n="16"/>
it may be conceived this was a camp of one of tho&#8747;e powers. I remember to have read in &#8747;ome author who&#8747;e name I cannot at this in&#8747;tant recolleƈt, that on this ground Egbert fought a battle with the Piƈts, and in memory of his viƈtory the <i>Roy Cro&#8747;s</i> was ereƈted<ptr target="n5"/>.</p>
<note id="n5"><p>About the year one thou&#8747;and and &#8747;ixty-&#8747;even William the Conqueror and Malcolm King of Scotland concluded a peace at Newca&#8747;tle under the&#8747;e conditions, that King Malcolm &#8747;hould enjoy that part of Northumberland which lieth between Tweede, Cumberland, and Stainmoor, and to do homage to the King of England for the &#8747;ame. In the mid&#8747;t of Stanemore there &#8747;hall be a cro&#8747;s &#8747;et up, with the King of England's image on the one &#8747;ide, and the King of Scotland's on the other, to &#8747;ignify that one is marche to England, and the other to Scotland. -- This cro&#8747;s was called the Recro&#8747;&#8747;e, that is to &#8747;ay, the Cro&#8747;&#8747;é of the Kings.</p>
<p>Vide Hollin&#8747;hed's Chronicle of Scotland, p. 255.</p></note>
<p>As we travelled from thence for &#8747;everal miles, all around was one continued melancholy &#8747;cene; -- the hills encrea&#8747;ing in height, the vallies in depth and de&#8747;olation; -- the wind &#8747;ounded among&#8747;t the rocks, whil&#8747;t a heavy vapour in &#8747;ome parts clouded their &#8747;ummits; in others driving rain was &#8747;een &#8747;treaming along the dales, and &#8747;hrowding their gloomy rece&#8747;&#8747;es: <pb n="17"/>-- the wearied mind of the traveller endeavours to evade &#8747;uch objeƈts, and plea&#8747;e it&#8747;elf with the fancied images of verdant plains, purling &#8747;treams, and happy groves to which we were approaching: -- whil&#8747;t we were thus engaged, unexpeƈtedly the &#8747;cene opened, and from &#8747;uch a horrid wild, gave us a pro&#8747;peƈt as delightful as the other was di&#8747;gu&#8747;ting.</p>
<p>Over a rugged and rocky foreground, we looked upon STAINMORE-DALE in front; her verdant meadows cheared the eye; her &#8747;weet &#8747;eque&#8747;tered cottages, her gra&#8747;&#8747;y plains, and little &#8747;hades of &#8747;ycamores, &#8747;eemed enchanting, as their beauties were enhanced by the deformity from which they had e&#8747;caped. On the right hand a mountain ari&#8747;es, hiding its grey head and naked brow in clouds; the &#8747;ides are barren rocks, in who&#8747;e chinks a few &#8747;hrubs are &#8747;een clinging, and ca&#8747;t a teint of green to variegate the grey precipice. -- On a wild and forlorn &#8747;ituation, in an opening on the &#8747;ide of this mountain, HELLBECK HALL is de&#8747;cried, covered with trees: the place &#8747;eems calculated for di&#8747;content, and hid from all that's<pb n="18"/> chearful, befitted to a mind full of di&#8747;appointment and de&#8747;pair; all its pro&#8747;peƈt, is barrenne&#8747;s; the voice of water-falls, breezes mourning in the branches of the cop&#8747;e, or hi&#8747;&#8747;ing in the fi&#8747;&#8747;ures of the rock, its mu&#8747;ic; the deep &#8747;hadows render it gloomy; and overhanging vapours, damp and dreary.</p>
<p> -- Yet HELBECK has its beauties; -- it contra&#8747;ts with the vale beneath, where the exten&#8747;ive plain reaches the very bounds of CUMBERLAND, whose lofty mountains we perceived, tinged with blue vapours, and mixing their &#8747;ummits with the &#8747;ky. -- In the foreground lay</p>
<head level="2" align="center">BROUGH,</head>
<p>who&#8747;e ancient ca&#8747;tle, formerly the &#8747;eat of the Pembroke family, afforded a noble objeƈt; around which, rich meadows dre&#8747;t in fre&#8747;h verdure after mowing, plots of ripening corn, &#8747;parkling &#8747;heets of water, &#8747;een through the trees which decked their margins, the windings of each brook, little groves of a&#8747;h and &#8747;ycamore, fanta&#8747;tically di&#8747;per&#8747;ed and intermixed with villages and cots, formed the beauties of the <pb n="19"/> vale; on this hand extending towards <i>Kirby Stephen</i>, on that to <i>Dufton</i>, and in front as far as PENRITH BEACON.</p>
<p>As we began to de&#8747;cend the hill towards BROUGH, and leave the de&#8747;erts of Stainmore, we pa&#8747;&#8747;ed an antient Roman Fortification, called MAIDEN CASTLE -- the Roman road led immediately through it -- its form is &#8747;quare, built of &#8747;tone, each &#8747;ide forty paces in length; -- it is defended by outworks, the neare&#8747;t being a &#8747;mall ditch with a brea&#8747;twork of large &#8747;tones &#8747;et ereƈt, and the outward one a ditch and rampart of earth. This place has been of great &#8747;trength in former times, from its natural &#8747;ituation, commanding the pa&#8747;s from Brough. -- The a&#8747;cent on the &#8747;ide oppo&#8747;ite to Brough, is very &#8747;teep for more than a mile; to the South it is inacce&#8747;&#8747;able, by rea&#8747;on of the precipice on who&#8747;e brink it &#8747;tands; and towards the North, the ground is every where rugged and mountainous. -- Camden &#8747;ays, the Roman road led from hence to <i>Cave-Vorran</i>, in Northumberland<ptr target="n6"/>. Plate III. fig. 2.</p>
<note id="n6">Camden's Britannia.</note>
<pb n="20"/>
<head level="2" align="center">BROUGH</head>
<p>Is now divided into two &#8747;mall mean towns, the one called Church Brough, the other Market Brough, &#8747;eparated by a little brook which falls into the river Eden. -- Hu&#8747;bandry is little advanced here; the management of gra&#8747;s land is the farmer's whole excellence, the meadows being kept in good order, and very rich: -- the inhabitants are ignorant of men and manners, but &#8747;ubtle and crafty<ptr target="n7"/>.</p>
<note id="n7"><p>"Roger Lord Clifford, in 4 Edward III. 1330, "procured the King's charter for a Market upon Thur&#8747;day " every week at his manor of Burgh upon Staynemoor " in We&#8747;tmerland; and a Fair yearly, to begin " two days before the Fea&#8747;t of St Matthew the Apo&#8747;tle, and to continue for the day and morrow after."</p>
<p>Dugdale's Baronage, Vol. I. p. 339.</p></note>
<p>On parties of plea&#8747;ure, time &#8747;hould never be limited; -- to ride po&#8747;t through a country, is too much the cu&#8747;tom of travellers, by which they can reap no more than a &#8747;uperficial idea of it: -- the &#8747;peculative traveller is never confined to roads, times, or &#8747;ea&#8747;ons; but as the circum&#8747;tances exciting his curio&#8747;ity lie either to <pb n="21"/> the right or left, the pur&#8747;ues the objeƈts of his attention, regardle&#8747;s of every other motive.</p>
<p>The plea&#8747;antne&#8747;s of the morning called us very early from Brough; -- the dawn advanced with a deep calm -- the clouds broke from the hills, and drew their grey veil from the face of the morning, revealing her in blu&#8747;hes -- the valley lay wrapped in &#8747;tillne&#8747;s -- Care and Indu&#8747;try had not departed from their night's rece&#8747;&#8747;es -- the ear was hu&#8747;hed, and all around &#8747;eemed to be the region of tranquility; -- ere long, various &#8747;ounds grew on the &#8747;en&#8747;e, and the living land&#8747;cape gave us new plea&#8747;ures; the cottagers being now abroad, bu&#8747;ied in the &#8747;everal occupations of the field.</p>
<p>As we pur&#8747;ued our journey, at an opening of the road to the left, we viewed the ruins of</p>
<head level="2" align="center">BROUGH CASTLE.</head>
<p>In former times this was a formidable fortre&#8747;s, and of Roman original; its &#8747;ituation on the Roman road leading to BROVONAICUM<ptr target="n8"/><pb n="22"/> by ABALLABA, and its di&#8747;tance from LAVATRAE prove, that this was the antient VERTERIÆ mentioned by Antonine and the Book of Notices, where, in the decline of the Roman empire, a band of the <i>Direƈtores</i> were &#8747;tationed. -- The name of Burgh or Brough is of Saxon extraƈtion; -- &#8747;uch &#8747;ituations were cho&#8747;en by that people, for ereƈting ca&#8747;tles, as being already places of &#8747;trength. Camden &#8747;ays, but from what authority I know not, that in the time of the later empire, little ca&#8747;tles, calculated for defence, and as &#8747;torehou&#8747;es for corn, began to be called Burgs. -- The building to the ea&#8747;tern &#8747;ide is circular, and &#8747;eems to be of modern architeƈture, but to the we&#8747;t there remains a noble tower, apparently of great antiquity. The whole ca&#8747;tle &#8747;tands on a con&#8747;iderable eminence to the north and we&#8747;t, ari&#8747;ing &#8747;wiftly from the plain; to the &#8747;outh and ea&#8747;t the acce&#8747;s is not &#8747;o &#8747;teep, but is guarded by a deep ditch and rampart, which appear to be the remains of the old Roman &#8747;tation, forming an area to the ca&#8747;tle. -- In the beginning<pb n="23"/> of the Norman government, the northern Engli&#8747;h con&#8747;pired here again&#8747;t William the Conqueror<ptr target="n9"/>.</p>
<note id="n8">Camden's Britannia.</note>
<note id="n9">Camden's Britannia.</note>
<p>In the la&#8747;t century this place was repaired by the Counte&#8747;s of Pembroke, who made it her re&#8747;idence. -- This appeared by the following in&#8747;cription<ptr target="n10"/> which lately &#8747;tood over the South entrance: " This " ca&#8747;tle of Brough under Stainmore, and " the great tower of it, were repaired by " the Lady Ann Clifford, Counte&#8747;s Dowager " of Pembroke, Dor&#8747;e, and Montgomery, " Baron Clifford, We&#8747;tmoreland,<pb n="24"/> " and Ve&#8747;ey, High Sheriff by inheritance " of the county of We&#8747;tmoreland, and " Lady of the Honor of Skipton in Craven, " in the year of our Lord God 1659, " &#8747;o as &#8747;he came to lie in it her&#8747;elf for a " little while in September 1661, after it " had laine ruinous without timber or " any covering ever &#8747;ince the year 1521, " when it was burnt by a ca&#8747;ual fire. " I&#8747;a. cha. lviii. ver. 12. -- God's name be " prai&#8747;ed." -- The &#8747;tone which contained this in&#8747;cription, &#8747;ome few years ago fell down and was de&#8747;troyed.</p>
<note id="n10">This in&#8747;cription reminds me of one put up on a like occa&#8747;ion by the Counte&#8747;s of Pembroke, on Skipton Ca&#8747;tle, which runs as follows: " This Skipton Ca&#8747;tle " was repaired by the Lady Ann Clifford, Counte&#8747;s " Dowager of Pembroke, Dor&#8747;e, and Montgomery, " Barone&#8747;s Clifford, We&#8747;tmoreland, and Ve&#8747;ey, Lady " of the Honor of Skipton in Craven, and High Sheriffe&#8747;s "by inheritance of the County of We&#8747;tmoreland, "in the years 1657 and 1658, after the main part of " it had lain ruinous ever &#8747;ince December 1648 and the " January following, when it was then pulled down " and demoli&#8747;hed almo&#8747;t to the ground, by the comand " of the Parliament then &#8747;itting at We&#8747;tmin&#8747;ter, becau&#8747;e " it had been a garri&#8747;on in the then civil wars in " England. I&#8747;aiah, cha. lviii. ver. 12. -- God's name be "prai&#8747;ed."</note>
<p>As the &#8747;un advanced, he gave various beauties to the &#8747;cene, the beams &#8747;treaming through the divi&#8747;ions in the mountains, &#8747;hewed us their due per&#8747;peƈtive, and &#8747;triped the plain with gold -- the light falling behind the ca&#8747;tle, pre&#8747;ented all its parts perfeƈtly to us -- through the broken windows di&#8747;tant objeƈts were di&#8747;covered; -- the front ground lay in &#8747;hadows; -- on the left the pro&#8747;peƈt was &#8747;hut in by a range of craggy mountains, over who&#8747;e &#8747;teeps &#8747;hrubs and trees were &#8747;cattered; -- to the right a fertile plain was extended, &#8747;urmounted by di&#8747;tant hills; over their<pb n="25"/> &#8747;ummits the retiring vapours, as they fled the valley, dragged their watry &#8747;kirts, and gave a &#8747;olemn gloom to that part of the &#8747;cene. Behind the building, the lofty promontary of Wilbore Fell lifted its peaked brow, tinged with an azure hue, and terminated the pro&#8747;peƈt.</p>
<p>In order to examine this fortre&#8747;s with greater attention, I revi&#8747;ited it the &#8747;ucceeding year. -- When I attempt to give a rea&#8747;on for my &#8747;econd vi&#8747;it to the LAKES, and beating the &#8747;ame road again, my eyes &#8747;wim with tears, and my heart-rending &#8747;orrow is renewed to me in all its energy, for the ine&#8747;timable lo&#8747;s I have &#8747;u&#8747;tained &#8747;ince my fir&#8747;t excur&#8747;ion, in my fellow-traveller, my draught&#8747;man, my friend, my &#8747;econd &#8747;elf, my <i>Brother</i>; -- his virtues were too excellent to be detained from Heaven; -- he departed in the flower of youth, amid&#8747;t all the fire of genius, in the twenty-third year of his age. -- Plate IV.</p>
<p> -- With him the unfini&#8747;hed draughts of tho&#8747;e admirable views were lo&#8747;t; -- to recover them, though imperfeƈtly, from my great inferiority in that art, I again vi&#8747;ited<pb n="26"/> the objeƈts of his admiration, I repa&#8747;&#8747;ed his lines, trod his &#8747;teps, and with a melancholy degree of &#8747;atisfaƈtion viewed the &#8747;cenes, which were then become to me &#8747;olemn memorials of him who was not.</p>
<p> -- But to return -- half mankind know nothing of the beauties of nature, and wa&#8747;te in indolence and &#8747;leep the glorious &#8747;cene which the morning pre&#8747;ents; -- as we pa&#8747;&#8747;ed on, the varied pro&#8747;peƈt kept attention awake.</p>
<p>At the di&#8747;tance of a mile from Brough, WARKUP, to the left, affords an agreeable view; -- Warkup Hall, &#8747;hrouded with a rich grove of &#8747;ycamores, overtops the village; the verdure of the meadows, with &#8747;ome exten&#8747;ive fields of yellow corn, contra&#8747;ted by the hills of pa&#8747;ture ground which lie on the &#8747;outhern &#8747;ide, brown with the &#8747;ummer heat, and tufted with bru&#8747;h-wood, gave a plea&#8747;ing variety: whil&#8747;t the morning beam breaking a&#8747;lant upon the valley, and gli&#8747;tering on the brook, with the blue teints of &#8747;moke that aro&#8747;e from the hamlets, painted the rural &#8747;cene. -- We were furni&#8747;hed with ideas
<pb n="27"/>
which &#8747;till rendered this pro&#8747;peƈt more plea&#8747;ing, as they reminded us of the &#8747;ocial &#8747;pirit of the owner of Warkup, in who&#8747;e life, ho&#8747;pitality and benevolence are truly charaƈterized.</p>
<p>We pa&#8747;&#8747;ed over the ground where BROUGH HILL FAIR is annually held on the la&#8747;t day of September; -- a toll is due on this occa&#8747;ion to Lord Thanet, for every head of black cattle, &#38;c. pre&#8747;ented there; -- for &#8747;everal years pa&#8747;t the number of cattle expo&#8747;ed to &#8747;ale, on an average, amounted to eight thou&#8747;and and upwards, one thou&#8747;and horses, together with a prodigious quantity of &#8747;heep. -- All kinds of merchandize are brought to this fair.</p>
<p>The valley now growing more extensive, encrea&#8747;ed in varieties, and plea&#8747;ed us with a new &#8747;cene of cultivation and hu&#8747;bandry; the large traƈts of ground which we pa&#8747;&#8747;ed along, were lately common, but are now dividing and forming into inclo&#8747;ures. -- Three tumuli of different magnitudes lay on our left, one of which was lately opened at the in&#8747;tance of the Bi&#8747;hop of Carli&#8747;le, and &#8747;ome remains of
<pb n="28"/>
arms, with the a&#8747;hes of the interred, were di&#8747;covered. -- By what was found there, it was apprehended the tumulus was Briti&#8747;h.</p>
<p>At the &#8747;ixth mile &#8747;tone we &#8747;topped to admire the &#8747;ingularity of the view to the right, where a range of mountains, ari&#8747;ing from the exten&#8747;ive plain over which we were travelling, &#8747;tretched to the we&#8747;tward, and afforded a romantic and noble &#8747;cene; the neare&#8747;t hills, with rocky brows and barren cliffs, rai&#8747;ed their grey fronts above the humble bru&#8747;h wood, which girt them in the mid&#8747;t, whil&#8747;t their feet in ha&#8747;ty &#8747;lopes de&#8747;cended the vale in pa&#8747;turage: further retiring from theeye, the mountain called <i>Cro&#8747;s-Fell</i>, with a front of naked rock, overtops the adjoining hills; being &#8747;aid to exceed the mountain <i>Skiddaw</i>, in Cumberland, one hundred and ten perpendicular feet in height: -- further extending we&#8747;tward, the chain of mountains lay in per&#8747;peƈtive, till they died away upon the &#8747;ight, and in azure hue &#8747;eemed to mix with the &#8747;ky; whil&#8747;t at the foot of this va&#8747;t range of hills, three &#8747;maller mounts, of an exaƈt conic form, running parallel, beautified the &#8747;cene, being covered with<pb n="29"/> verdure to their crowns; -- the neare&#8747;t, called Dufton-Pike, was &#8747;hadowed by a pa&#8747;&#8747;ing cloud, &#8747;ave only the &#8747;ummit of its cone, which was touched by a beam that pointed it with gold; -- the &#8747;econd pike was all enlightened, and gave its verdure to the pro&#8747;peƈt as if mantled with velvet; -- the third &#8747;tood &#8747;hadowed, whil&#8747;t all the range of hills behind were &#8747;truck with &#8747;un&#8747;hine, &#8747;hewing their cliffs, caverns, and dells in grote&#8747;que variety, and giving the three pikes a piƈture&#8747;que projeƈtion on the land&#8747;cape: -- nature, as if delighted to charm the eye of man, at this time ca&#8747;t an accidental beauty over the &#8747;cene; -- the &#8747;mall clouds which chequered the &#8747;ky, as they pa&#8747;&#8747;ed along, &#8747;pread their flitting &#8747;hadows on the di&#8747;tant mountains, and &#8747;eemed to marble them; a beauty which I do not recolleƈt has &#8747;truck any painter, and which has not been de&#8747;cribed even by the bold hand of the immortal Pou&#8747;in. The mo&#8747;t exqui&#8747;ite fancy of a painter could not have devi&#8747;ed more plea&#8747;ing variety of light and &#8747;hadow, than what was ca&#8747;t upon this pro&#8747;peƈt.</p>
<pb n="30"/>
<head level="2" align="center">APPLEBY,</head>
<p>
To which we now approached, though placed on an elevated &#8747;ituation, was concealed from our view till we arrived within half a mile; when from the hill which we had a&#8747;cended, it gave an agreeable &#8747;urprize. On the brink of a lofty eminence, fronting towards the Ea&#8747;t, beneath which runs the river Eden, the ca&#8747;tle pre&#8747;ented it&#8747;elf. The &#8747;teep, on who&#8747;e brow this noble edifice is ereƈted, is richly cloathed with wood; &#8747;ave only where a rugged cliff of red hue breaks through the trees, and gives an agreeable variety to the land&#8747;cape. -- The front of the ca&#8747;tle is irregular and antique, but lo&#8747;es great &#8747;hare of its beauty, by the joints of the building being whitened and bedaubed with lime. Over this front, the top of a fine &#8747;quare tower is di&#8747;covered, who&#8747;e corners ari&#8747;e in turrets; -- the land&#8747;cape to the left is richly wooded; -- to the right it is divided by hanging gardens, which adjoin the town, overtopped with dwellings: -- the pavillions belonging the hou&#8747;e of John Robin&#8747;on, E&#8747;q; with the parterres and &#8747;loping plots of gra&#8747;s ground, modernize
<pb n="31"/>
a &#8747;cene, which condemns all faƈtitiou&#8747;ne&#8747;s of ta&#8747;te; and by the &#8747;implicity and elegance nature pre&#8747;ents to us on the adjoining lands, reproves the di&#8747;tortions which &#8747;he receives from dull right lines and angles: -- but whil&#8747;t I cen&#8747;ure fa&#8747;hion, I revere the owner of this man&#8747;ion, who&#8747;e excellencies are too eminent to want the traveller’s applau&#8747;e.</p>
<p>As we approached the bridge, and ca&#8747;t our eyes upon the valley, we were delighted with the happy a&#8747;&#8747;emblage of woods and meadows, which form the little vale, where Eden flows; through the thronging branches the water was &#8747;een, in many places, refleƈting a tremulous beam, and &#8747;parkling in the &#8747;un’s rays; -- over the valley, rude cliffs and hanging rocks, on this hand, appeared projeƈting through the trees; on that, was &#8747;een the lofty front of the ca&#8747;tle.</p>
<p>The pro&#8747;peƈt from the terrace, which is under the ea&#8747;tern front of the ca&#8747;tle, is very beautiful; -- to the right, the river Eden forms a winding lake the di&#8747;tance of half a mile, who&#8747;e banks are cloathe
<pb n="32"/>
with lofty hanging woods, de&#8747;cending in a &#8747;wift but regular &#8747;weep to the brink of of the &#8747;tream. Below us, the water murmured over a wear, where a mill added to the plea&#8747;ing &#8747;ounds. On the left, lofty cliffs and precipices ari&#8747;e perpendicular from the water, over who&#8747;e brows, oaks and a&#8747;hes hanging, render their a&#8747;peƈt more romantic by the &#8747;olemn &#8747;hade. -- On the ground above, the public road leading to Appleby, winds up the hill, on who&#8747;e &#8747;ide &#8747;ome cottages are &#8747;cattered; whil&#8747;t all behind the di&#8747;tant ground is formed by mountains, &#8747;hadowed with clouds.</p>
<p>Whil&#8747;t here we &#8747;tayed, enjoying this &#8747;weet &#8747;cene, I could not forbear pointing out to my companion a little tenement which had been remarked to me, &#8747;tanding oppo&#8747;ite to us, on the brink of the river, where the faire&#8747;t maid re&#8747;ides that graces Eden’s banks; -- &#8747;tately and tall, &#8747;he &#8747;eems the lily of Eden’s garden, whil&#8747;t &#8747;he is fair and meek as lilies; in her countenance beauty is graced with intelligence, and in her behaviour innocence is mixed with politene&#8747;s.</p>
<pb n="33"/>
<p>The garden grounds around Appleby Castle are without ornament, and calculated for u&#8747;e only.</p>
<p> -- On the we&#8747;tern &#8747;ide of this ca&#8747;tle, detached from the re&#8747;t of the edifice, is a lofty &#8747;quare, called by the people CÆSAR’S TOWER, but whether of Roman con&#8747;truƈtion, is impo&#8747;&#8747;ible to a&#8747;certain: -- I am induced to believe it, from the mode of architeƈture, to be of Norman original: -- the corners of the tower form a projection of near a foot from the plane of each front, and ri&#8747;e above the re&#8747;t of the building in &#8747;quare turrets, now covered with lead, the remaining part of the top being embra&#8747;ured: -- there are two &#8747;mall windows in each front, near the middle of the building, parallel to each other. -- This tower is defended by an outward wall, forming a cre&#8747;cent at the di&#8747;tance of about twelve paces, now remaining near twenty feet high, &#8747;trongly &#8747;u&#8747;tained on the out&#8747;ide by buttre&#8747;&#8747;es, ereƈted on an eminence thirty paces in a&#8747;cent, and defended by a deep ditch without. -- The quarter fronting to the ca&#8747;tle lies open to
<pb n="34"/>
the area, which is enclo&#8747;ed by a wall, continued from the points of the cre&#8747;cent.</p>
<p>This was the antient ABALLABA, where the <i>Aurelian Maures</i> kept a &#8747;tation: -- it is almo&#8747;t encompa&#8747;&#8747;ed by the river Eden. -- William King of Scotland, in his incur&#8747;ions, &#8747;urprized this fortre&#8747;s &#8747;ome little time before he was taken pri&#8747;oner at Alnwick, which happened in the year 1174, where, with an army of eighty thou&#8747;and men, he was overcome by a handful of opponents, under the command of Barnard Baliol. King John in his northern tour recovered the ca&#8747;tle, and gave it to Robert Vipont for his &#8747;ingular &#8747;ervices. -- Camden &#8747;ays the a&#8747;&#8747;izes were entirely held there; and it was the common gaol for malefaƈtors<ptr target="n11"/>. -- It is probable the Roman &#8747;tation was &#8747;ituate on this eminence, and that the pre&#8747;ent ca&#8747;tle &#8747;tands on the &#8747;ame ground; but the Vallum is totally effaced.</p>
<note id="n11">Camden’s Britannia.</note>
<p>The great Hall is worthy the ob&#8747;ervation of travellers, there being enclo&#8747;ed in
<pb n="35"/>
a ca&#8747;e in the wain&#8747;cot, a fine piece of portrait painting, of George Clifford, Earl of Cumberland, his lady, and daughter, afterwards Counte&#8747;s of Dor&#8747;et, Pembroke, and Montgomery, ornamented with their pedigree, and hi&#8747;torical notes of their lives and atchievements. -- A &#8747;tranger is from thence conduƈted through an adjoining room, where the ragged remains of embroider’d furniture, give you a deplorable idea of decaying magnificence, and the vanity of pride; -- the door of a clo&#8747;et being &#8747;uddenly thrown open, you are &#8747;tartled from your reverie by the &#8747;haking of armour, and the &#8747;ight of a compleat &#8747;uit, trembling in every joint. -- This is pre&#8747;erved with great attention, as having been worn by the &#8747;ame George Earl of Cumberland, the la&#8747;t Earl of that name, and father of the Counte&#8747;s of Pembroke, by whom great po&#8747;&#8747;e&#8747;&#8747;ions came to the Thanet family. -- The arms are richly embo&#8747;&#8747;ed and inlaid with gold, and &#8747;hew the Earl to have been a man of low &#8747;tature.</p>
<p>In its ichnography, this ca&#8747;tle is not much unlike to the ruins of Brough; the
<pb n="36"/>
towers of each being detached from the main edifice, and placed to the we&#8747;t.</p>
<p>Appleby ca&#8747;tle is one of the &#8747;eats of the Earl of Thanet, but of late years much negleƈted by the family. -- Lord Thanet is hereditary Sheriff of the county of We&#8747;tmoreland, and as &#8747;uch intitled to many privileges; &#8747;ome of which, in this age of liberty and cultivation, are rather oppre&#8747;&#8747;ive; his free-chace in particular.</p>
<p>The great po&#8747;&#8747;e&#8747;&#8747;ions of the Counte&#8747;s of Pembroke, in this country, came into the Thanet family in the following manner: -- John Earl of Thanet &#8747;ucceeded his mother, Margaret Counte&#8747;s of Thanet, as Baron of Clifford, We&#8747;tmoreland, and Ve&#8747;ey, in the year 1676; and in the year 1678 he al&#8747;o &#8747;ucceeded his cou&#8747;in, the Lady Alathea, &#8747;ole daughter and heire&#8747;s of James Earl of Northampton, by his fir&#8747;t wife, the Lady I&#8747;abella, his mother’s &#8747;i&#8747;ter: whereby he became po&#8747;&#8747;e&#8747;&#8747;ed of the whole inheritance of his grandmother, the Counte&#8747;s of Pembroke<ptr target="n12"/>.</p>
<note id="n12">Colling’s Peerage.</note>
<pb n="37"/>
<p>The <i>town</i> of <i>Appleby</i> chiefly con&#8747;i&#8747;ts of one wide continued &#8747;treet, hanging upon the &#8747;wift decline of a hill, in a direction north and &#8747;outh; the ca&#8747;tle terminating it on the &#8747;ummit, the church at the foot. -- The &#8747;ituation is agreeable in the &#8747;ummer &#8747;ea&#8747;on; but in the winter, cold. -- The meadow and pa&#8747;ture grounds are beautiful; but there is little tillage; it having been a received opinion for ages pa&#8747;t, that grain would not ripen or come to perfeƈtion &#8747;o near the moors and mountains, from whence a continued moi&#8747;t vapour is &#8747;uppo&#8747;ed to be borne into the valley, which blights the corn in its blo&#8747;&#8747;om, and prevents its filling or coming to maturity: but this ab&#8747;urdity is declining thro’ experience, which hath taught the inhabitants, that the want of knowledge in agriculture was the chief defeƈt, and the impetuous rains to which a mountainous country is &#8747;ubjeƈt, their greate&#8747;t detriment.</p>
<p>This is a very ancient Borough, and by pre&#8747;cription &#8747;ends two members to parliament. -- It is the county town, but not ble&#8747;t with a &#8747;ituation for trade. -- The markets
<pb n="38"/>
are not populous, the country adjoining, by rea&#8747;on of its exten&#8747;ive wa&#8747;tes and uncultivated lands, being thinly inhabited<ptr target="n13"/>. -- This is a corporation town, and governed by a mayor, alderman, and common council. -- The late confliƈts in political matters have enriched the inhabitants; the conte&#8747;ted eleƈtions for this borough having be&#8747;towed on the burgage owners many thou&#8747;ands of pounds.</p>
<note id="n13"><p>Appleby, antiently Aballaba, was a city in the time of the Romans: had a charter from Henry I. and confirmed by King John. It continued a place of great account till 1176, when it was utterly de&#8747;troyed by the Scots, as appears from a &#8747;tone in the &#8747;chool garden-hou&#8747;e. -- It enjoys the &#8747;ame privileges as York, by grant from Henry III.</p>
<p>Appleby ca&#8747;tle was granted the 4th of King John, to Robert Vipont, which includes the barony, but not the burrough of Appleby, that having been granted to the burge&#8747;&#8747;es there by King Henry II. and confirmed by King John, in the &#8747;econd year of his reign; &#8747;o likewi&#8747;e by Henry III. in the 16th of his reign.</p>
<p>Dug. Baron. Vol. I. p. 347.</p>
<p>Edward II. in the 5th year of his reign, 1312, took the town of Appleby into his hands, for the arrearage of their yearly farm. The town remained in the King’s hands a con&#8747;iderable time: the town&#8747;men came and made fine to Edward III. and he re&#8747;tored it to them, to be holden by them in the &#8747;ame plight as they held it before the caption.</p>
<p>See Record at full length in Madox Firma Burgi, p. 162, pro Burgen&#8747;ibus de Appleby.</p></note>
<pb n="39"/>
<p>The place where the judges of a&#8747;&#8747;ize &#8747;it in judgment on criminals, is very antique and remarkable: -- by the arms placed on one of the corner pillars, it appears to have been ereƈted by the Pembroke family: -- it is &#8747;ituated in the market place, fronting the north; the &#8747;ides are opened by a rude balu&#8747;trade, and in the front &#8747;upported by pillars; &#8747;o that it may properly be &#8747;aid, the judge &#8747;its di&#8747;pen&#8747;ing ju&#8747;tice in the forum.</p>
<p>The Buildings in this place are chiefly antient; &#8747;ome few modern hou&#8747;es of red free-&#8747;tone, which have a remarkable fine effeƈt, are inter&#8747;per&#8747;ed. -- Near the &#8747;ummit of the hill, &#8747;tands an obeli&#8747;k, a pillar of the Ionic order, ari&#8747;ing on &#8747;ome few &#8747;teps; on the ba&#8747;e of which is cut this remarkable in&#8747;cription: -- “<i>Pre&#8747;erve your liberties, “ maintain your rights</i>." -- It &#8747;eems to be placed there as a public &#8747;atire on the conduƈt of the burgage owners, and to imply, hither and no further the conflagration of public virtue advanced. -- As it had its origin in the conte&#8747;ted elections, it excites a &#8747;mile of deri&#8747;ion on the countenance of the traveller, to who&#8747;e
<pb n="40"/>
mind it renews the odious ideas of the corruptions of the age. -- In the mid&#8747;t of the town, to the annoyance of every pa&#8747;&#8747;enger, &#8747;tand a filthy &#8747;laughter-hou&#8747;e and &#8747;hambles.</p>
<p>Here is a School, amply endowed, founded by <i>Robert Langton</i> and <i>Miles Spence</i>, Doƈtors of Laws. -- It was under the conduƈt of one Reginald Bainbrig, in Camden’s time; who &#8747;peaks of him with great re&#8747;peƈt. Before the door of the &#8747;chool-hou&#8747;e, &#8747;ome Roman altars are placed, fully treated of by other travellers: among&#8747;t which antiquities, Reginald Bainbrig has given a memorial of his folly to po&#8747;terity, by &#8747;ome in&#8747;criptions in antique charaƈters, to celebrate his own memory, in which at lea&#8747;t his latin inelegance “QUI DOCUIT HIC" might have been &#8747;pared. Here is al&#8747;o an ho&#8747;pital founded by the Pembrokes, with a &#8747;tipend for a chaplain: -- the ho&#8747;pital is built on a &#8747;quare, forming an area in the center<ptr target="n14"/>.</p>
<note id="n14"><p>In this town was a hou&#8747;e of white friars, &#8747;aid to have been founded by the Lord Ve&#8747;ey, Lord Percy, and Lord Clifford, in 1281. After the di&#8747;&#8747;olution it was granted to Chri&#8747;topher Crakenthorpe, 35 Henry VIII.</p>
<p>See Tanner, p. 588.</p></note>
<pb n="41"/>
<p>The road we pur&#8747;ued from Appleby, for &#8747;everal miles, gave us great plea&#8747;ure: the vallies through which the river Eden flows, are &#8747;ingularly beautiful; their woody banks and level meads afford variety of land&#8747;capes, particularly below <i>Crackenthorp</i>. On the oppo&#8747;ite &#8747;hore of the river, &#8747;urrounded with a thick wood, the ruins of <i>Buley Ca&#8747;tle</i> are &#8747;een, now con&#8747;i&#8747;ting only of one &#8747;hattered tower. -- This was an antient retreat of the Bi&#8747;hops of Carli&#8747;le.</p>
<p>We pa&#8747;&#8747;ed KIRBY THORE, where no remains of antient Roman grandeur, &#8747;poken of by Camden, are now to be found, except the ve&#8747;tigia of part of the Vallum. He pre&#8747;umes this was the Gallagum of Ptolomy. -- The maiden way, a Roman pavement, leads from hence to Caer-Vorran, on the Piƈts wall; along which, it is probable, &#8747;tood tho&#8747;e &#8747;tations &#8747;poken of by Antonine, tho’ now totally effaced. -- In this neighbourhood were tho&#8747;e <pb n="42"/> written rocks, who&#8747;e in&#8747;criptions are pre&#8747;erved by Camden, though obliterated by time, or ignorant workmen<ptr target="n15"/></p>
<poem>
<line>VARRONIVS</line>
<line> -- EFECTVS LEG. XX. W<ptr target="n16"/>.</line> 
<line> -- AEL LVCANVS</line>
<line> -- P. LIC. II AVG. C.</line>
</poem>
<p>which may be read thus: Varronius præfeƈtus Legionis Vice&#8747;ime valentis Viƈtricis Aelius Lucanus præfeƈtus Legionis Secundæ Augu&#8747;tæ ca&#8747;trametati &#8747;unt. -- In another place --  </p>
<poem>
<line>CM. OCT. COT. COSS.</line>
</poem>
<p>-- The twentieth Legion, called Valens Viƈtrix, kept their re&#8747;idence at Deva or We&#8747;t Che&#8747;ter, and the &#8747;econd Legion, Augu&#8747;ta, at I&#8747;ca, that is, Caer-Leon, in Wales. -- They probably were employed again&#8747;t the northern powers, and encamped here.</p>
<note id="n15">Camden’s Britannia.</note>
<note id="n16">VV.</note>
<p><i>Acorn-Bank</i>, late the &#8747;eat of the Dal&#8747;tons, but now of William Norton, E&#8747;q; an elegant modern building, covered with fine plantations, lay in our way; commanding an agreeable, though narrow pro&#8747;peƈt, over rich meadows to the &#8747;outh,
<pb n="43"/>
de&#8747;cending to the town of <i>Temple-Sowerby</i>; of which place we were told nothing memorable, but that there remained to this day a pecuniary compo&#8747;ition, paid to the Lord of the Manor, in lieu of his cu&#8747;tom with each bride within his juri&#8747;diƈtion. -- It is an extra-parochial place, and from its antient owners, the Knights Templars, enjoyed many privileges which are now ob&#8747;olete.</p>
<p>We then pa&#8747;&#8747;ed WHINFIELD PARK, an exten&#8747;ive fore&#8747;t, the property of the Earl of Thanet, where we had the plea&#8747;ure of viewing a large traƈt of ground, lately enclo&#8747;ed from the park, and growing corn. -- There is not any thing can give greater &#8747;atisfaƈtion to the eye of the traveller, than to behold cultivation and indu&#8747;try &#8747;tretching their paces over the heath and wa&#8747;te, the fore&#8747;t and the chace: -- population mu&#8747;t follow, and riches en&#8747;ue. -- In Whinfield, the remains of an antient oak, of prodigious &#8747;ize, is &#8747;hewn to &#8747;trangers, called <i>Three-brother Tree</i>, a name ari&#8747;ing from the concealment of three brethren within its cavity. -- On the way &#8747;ide, the &#8747;hattered trunk of an oak, called <i>White
<pb n="44"/>
Hart Tree</i>, is &#8747;een, a contemporary perhaps of the other, though inferior in &#8747;ize -- the monument of elap&#8747;ed centuries, and the effigy of old age; &#8747;tretching forth its withered limbs on one &#8747;ide, and on the other, a &#8747;canty foliage and poor remnant of life. -- This tree is nine yards and two feet in circumference.</p>
<p><i>A &#8747;tone pillar</i>, ereƈted by the &#8747;ide of the road, next attraƈted our attention; near to which &#8747;tands a &#8747;tone table. -- The &#8747;talk of the pillar is hexagon, the top of it &#8747;quare; on the &#8747;ides of which are repre&#8747;ented, in &#8747;everal quarterings, the arms of the Pembrokes, a &#8747;outh dial, and the following in&#8747;cription: --</p>
<p>“This pillar was ereƈted anno Domini “ 1656, by the Right Honourable Ann “ Counte&#8747;s Dowager of Pembroke, &#38;c. “ daughter and &#8747;ole heire&#8747;s of the Right “ Honourable George Earl of Cumberland, “ for a memorial of her la&#8747;t parting in “ this place, with her good and pious “ mother, the Right Honourable Margaret “ Counte&#8747;s Dowager of Cumberland, the “ 2d of April 1616; in memory whereof
<pb n="45"/>
“&#8747;he al&#8747;o left an annuity of four pounds “ to be di&#8747;tributed to the poor of the pari&#8747;h “ of Brougham, every &#8747;econd day of “ April for ever, upon the &#8747;tone table here “ hard by. Laus Deo<ptr target="n17"/>.</p>
<note id="n17"><p>Margaret Counte&#8747;s of Cumberland was the third daughter of Francis Earl of Bedford, and married George the third and la&#8747;t Earl of Cumberland.</p>
<p>Dugdale’s Bar. Vol. I. p. 345.</p>
<p>She ereƈted a monument in her life time, in Appleby church, for her burial. -- She parted with her daughter, Ann Counte&#8747;s Dowager of Pembroke, at the pillar, 2d of April 1616, and died the 24th of May 1616, and was buried at Appleby.</p>
<p>See her Epitaph in Le Neve Monumenta Anglicana, Vol. III. p. 52, No. 96.</p>
<p>Ann Counte&#8747;s Dowager of Pembroke died the 22d of March 1675, and was buried at Appleby.</p>
<p>See her Epitaph in Le Neve, Vol. IV. p. 168, No. 425.</p></note>
<p>We quitted the high road in order to pa&#8747;s by BROUGHAM CASTLE, a &#8747;pacious ruin, &#8747;ituate on the banks of the river Emont; that we might enjoy the pro&#8747;peƈt to advantage, we cro&#8747;&#8747;ed the river, and made a &#8747;weep round the mill, which &#8747;tands almo&#8747;t oppo&#8747;ite to Brougham; from thence the view opened upon us with an happy effeƈt. --</p>
<pb n="46"/>
<p> -- The mill with its &#8747;treams lay on the left -- a &#8747;hining canal, formed by the river Emont, margined with &#8747;hrubs, &#8747;pread a con&#8747;iderable di&#8747;tance to the right -- whil&#8747;t the &#8747;treams which fell over a wear made a foaming ca&#8747;cade in front. On the oppo&#8747;ite brink of the channel &#8747;tands the ca&#8747;tle; -- the &#8747;ide next the river is divided by three &#8747;quare towers; -- from thence on either hand a little wing falls back, the one leading to the gate-way, the other conneƈted with the outworks, which extend to a con&#8747;iderable di&#8747;tance along a gra&#8747;&#8747;y plane of pa&#8747;ture ground, terminated by a turret, one of the outpo&#8747;ts of the ca&#8747;tle: -- the centre of the building is a lofty &#8747;quare tower; -- the &#8747;hattered turrets which form the angles, and the hanging galleries, are grown over with &#8747;hrubs: -- the &#8747;un beams, which &#8747;truck each ga&#8747;ping loup and bending window, di&#8747;covered the inward deva&#8747;tation and ruin, and touched the whole with admirable colouring and beauty. -- To grace the land&#8747;cape, groups of cattle were di&#8747;per&#8747;ed on the pa&#8747;ture, and through the tufts of a&#8747;h trees, which were irregularly &#8747;cattered on
<pb n="47"/>
the back ground, di&#8747;tant mountains were &#8747;een, &#8747;kirting the horizon.</p>
<p>The lower apartment in the principal tower &#8747;till remains intire; being a &#8747;quare of twenty feet, covered with a vaulted roof of &#8747;tone, con&#8747;i&#8747;ting of eight arches of light and excellent workman&#8747;hip. The groins are ornamented with various grote&#8747;que heads, and &#8747;upported in the centre by an oƈtagon pillar about four feet in circumference, with a capital and ba&#8747;e of Norman architeƈture. In the centre of each arch rings are fixed, as if de&#8747;igned for lamps to illuminate the vault.</p>
<p>From the con&#8747;truƈtion of this cell, and its &#8747;ituation in the chief tower of the fortre&#8747;s, it is not probable it was formed for a pri&#8747;on, but rather was u&#8747;ed at the time of &#8747;iege and a&#8747;&#8747;ault, as the retreat of the chief per&#8747;ons of the hou&#8747;ehold.</p>
<p>In Mr Gro&#8747;e’s ingenious preface to the Antiquities of England and Wales, we have the following ob&#8747;ervations: “ On an “ eminence in the centre, commonly, tho’ “ not always, &#8747;tood the keep or dungeon:
<pb n="48"/>
“&#8747;ometimes, as in the relation of the &#8747;iege “ of Bedford ca&#8747;tle, emphatically called “ the tower; it was the citadel or la&#8747;t retreat “ of the garri&#8747;on, often &#8747;urrounded “ by a ditch, with a draw bridge and “ machicolated gate, and occa&#8747;ionally “ with an outer wall, garni&#8747;hed with &#8747;mall “ towers. In large ca&#8747;tles it was generally “ a high &#8747;quare tower, of four or five &#8747;tories, “ having turrets at each angle: in “ the&#8747;e turrets were the &#8747;tairca&#8747;es, and “ frequently, as in Dover and Roche&#8747;ter “ ca&#8747;tles, a well. If in&#8747;tead of a &#8747;quare, “ the keep or dungeon happened to be “ round, it was called a julliet, from a “ vulgar opinion that large round towers “ were built by Julius Cæ&#8747;ar.</p>
<p>“The walls of this edifice were always “ of an extraordinary thickne&#8747;s; which “ has enabled them to outlive the other “ buildings, and to with&#8747;tand the united “ injuries of time and weather; the keeps “ or dungeons being almo&#8747;t the only part “ now remaining of our ancient ca&#8747;tles. “ Here were the &#8747;tate rooms for the governor, “ &#38;c."</p>
<pb n="49"/>
<p>The approach to this ca&#8747;tle is guarded by an outward-vaulted gateway and tower, with a port cullis; and at the di&#8747;tance of about twenty paces, an inward-vaulted gateway of ribbed arches with a port cullis; through which you enter a &#8747;pacious area, defended by a lofty wall.</p>
<p>This ca&#8747;tle is &#8747;ituated on the north &#8747;ide of the Roman &#8747;tation RRONOVAICUM, which has formed an area and outwork one hundred and twenty paces &#8747;quare, defended by the Vallum and an outward ditch; both at this time very di&#8747;cernable. -- The angles of this camp are obtu&#8747;e, like mo&#8747;t others of that people. -- This was the &#8747;tation of a band of Defen&#8747;ores<ptr target="n18"/>, and in the Book of Notices is laid down as being &#8747;eventeen Engli&#8747;h miles from VERTERAE. -- Brougham was the Lord&#8747;hip and Ca&#8747;tle of the Viponts, included in the Barony of Appleby and Brough, given to Robert de Vipont by King John, from who&#8747;e family it de&#8747;cended to the Cliffords; but who was the founder is not known.
<pb n="50"/>
-- On the outward gate, the remains of the arms of the Vallibus or Vaulx family are to be ob&#8747;erved, being chequy Or, and gules; from whence I am led to conjeƈture they were builders, or great contributors to the works. -- This ca&#8747;tle is now the property of Lord Thanet.</p>
<note id="n18">Camden’s Britannia.</note>
<p>Having now entered the county of Cumberland, and pa&#8747;&#8747;ing on behind CARLTON, the &#8747;eat of James Wallace, E&#8747;q; the eye wandered over a fine cultivated country, from whence we had a di&#8747;tant view of the rich valley of Lowther, graced with noble and exten&#8747;ive woods. -- As we approached PENRITH, the mountains and piles of rocks, which &#8747;tand on ULS-WATER, afforded an augu&#8747;t &#8747;cene -- and at the termination of the road the ruins of Penrith Ca&#8747;tle pre&#8747;ented them&#8747;elves. -- The genius, virtue, and indu&#8747;try of the owner of the rich lands which we were then pa&#8747;&#8747;ing, aro&#8747;e to our thoughts; -- the benevolent mind mu&#8747;t ever be touched with plea&#8747;ure, to di&#8747;cern the rewards of pro&#8747;perity ble&#8747;&#8747;ing the man of merit.</p>
<pb n="51"/>
<head level="2" align="center">PENRITH</head>
<p>Is an agreeable town, &#8747;ituate on the ea&#8747;y decline of a hill to the &#8747;outhward; it is unchartered, being governed by the Steward of the Honor, and a Jury. -- A con&#8747;iderable manufaƈtory of cotton and linen checks is carried on here, and al&#8747;o a great trade in tanned leather; -- the town hou&#8747;e is in ruins, having been de&#8747;troyed by a fire &#8747;ome few years ago; -- the ornaments mentioned by Camden are in &#8747;ome parts remaining, which prove the ancient patronage of the Warwicks; -- the hou&#8747;es in general are well built, the inhabitants facetious and polite. -- The name of this place is derived from the colour of the hills near it, PENROETH being in the ancient Briti&#8747;h language a red hill.</p>
<p>There was formerly in this place a hou&#8747;e of Grey Friars<ptr target="n19"/>, founded before the reign of Edward the Second, but its revenue, to my knowledge, is not mentioned by any author; -- in the 34th of Henry VIII. it was granted to Robert Tyrwhit, E&#8747;q. -- There are two charity
<pb n="52"/>
&#8747;chools here, one for boys, and another for girls, well endowed.</p>
<note id="n19">Tanner, p. 77.</note>
<p>In the year 1385 Penrith &#8747;uffered &#8747;everely by the Scots, who taking advantage of the retreat of Richard II after he had carried fire and &#8747;word into their country, ravaged all the di&#8747;triƈts on the borders, and laid this town in a&#8747;hes. That Monarch’s conduƈt on this occa&#8747;ion was highly reprehen&#8747;ible, and it became one of the principal charges brought again&#8747;t him.</p>
<p>Our fir&#8747;t excur&#8747;ion from Penrith was to mount the &#8747;teep hill on which the Beacon is placed, upwards of a mile to the northward of the town; -- the labour was great by which we a&#8747;cended, but the view amply rewarded out fatigue. -- The beacon hou&#8747;e is a &#8747;quare building of &#8747;tone, and happily &#8747;ituated for the purpo&#8747;e of alarming the country in times of public danger, as it commands an exten&#8747;ive vale.</p>
<p> -- The northern window of the beacon hou&#8747;e affords a pro&#8747;peƈt of Cro&#8747;s Fell, with the Pikes of Dufton, together with a chain of mountains extending from ea&#8747;t to we&#8747;t near thirty miles; the we&#8747;tern
<pb n="53"/>
point &#8747;inking in the &#8747;pacious plain where the city of Carli&#8747;le lies. The utmo&#8747;t bounds of this view are formed by a ridge of Scotch mountains. -- Some faint appearance of St. Mary’s church, marks to the eye the &#8747;ite of Carli&#8747;le.</p>
<p> -- The ea&#8747;tern window pre&#8747;ented a view of the country we had pa&#8747;&#8747;ed, bounded by the hills of Stainmore, and that lofty promontary Wilbore-fell, with its neighbouring mountains above Kirby Stephen.</p>
<p> -- The &#8747;outh window pre&#8747;ented to us a view of Brougham Ca&#8747;tle, with its plains of pa&#8747;ture ground. -- The &#8747;preading woods of Lowther, intermixed with rich cultivated lands, formed the ri&#8747;ing grounds. -- Some parts of the lake of Uls-water were &#8747;een, whil&#8747;t the mighty rocks and mountains which hemmed in the lake, lifted up their heads in rude confu&#8747;ion, and crowned the &#8747;cene.</p>
<p> -- The we&#8747;tern window afforded a new, and not le&#8747;s plea&#8747;ing pro&#8747;peƈt; -- the town of Penrith lay before us, and here and there the river Emont &#8747;hewed its windings through the woods. -- The hill which
<pb n="54"/>
ri&#8747;es above the town is crowned with the awful remains of a royal fortre&#8747;s; -- time has de&#8747;poiled its grandeur, but its Honors &#8747;till &#8747;urvive to its noble owner, the Duke of Portland, who therewith holds the Honor of Penrith, formerly a royal franchi&#8747;e. -- Beyond the&#8747;e objeƈts, amid&#8747;t a range of mountains, at the di&#8747;tance of eighteen miles, Skiddow is &#8747;een, who&#8747;e maje&#8747;tic front &#8747;urmounts all the high lands that terminate the view.</p>
<p> -- The whole pro&#8747;peƈt from the beacon hill, as you turn every way, pre&#8747;ents you with a va&#8747;t theatre, upwards of one hundred miles in circumference, circled with &#8747;tupendous mountains.</p>
<p>Common ju&#8747;tice requires, that in whatever &#8747;tation of life merit is di&#8747;covered, it &#8747;hould receive a degree of prai&#8747;e proportioned to its excellence. -- From this univer&#8747;al principle, which benevolence delights to cheri&#8747;h, I mu&#8747;t not pa&#8747;s in &#8747;ilence the de&#8747;erts of our Penrith ho&#8747;t: -- The common conduƈt of publicans prepo&#8747;&#8747;e&#8747;&#8747;es the mind of the traveller, when he enters an inn, with the unfavourable idea, that your ho&#8747;t is an unfeeling extortioner, impertinent,
<pb n="55"/>
curious, and impo&#8747;ing; -- whoever vi&#8747;its Penrith, either on bu&#8747;ine&#8747;s or plea&#8747;ure, will find the keeper of the White Swan the very rever&#8747;e; -- a man above his rank in &#8747;entiments, above his fellows in propriety of manners; his hou&#8747;e commodious and clean, his provi&#8747;ions excellent, and his attendance prompt and not impertinent.</p>
<p>Our &#8747;econd excur&#8747;ion from Penrith was by LOWTHER to the LAKE OF ULS-WATER; -- we pa&#8747;&#8747;ed the village of <i>Clifton</i>, memorable for the &#8747;kirmi&#8747;h on the 18th day of December, 1745, between the Duke of Cumberland’s forces and the rebels. -- On the approach to Clifton from Lowther, the way which the Duke’s forces advanced, lies Clifton moor, a &#8747;pacious Common, de&#8747;cending with an ea&#8747;y &#8747;lope towards the village; -- on the we&#8747;tern &#8747;ide the road is &#8747;ituate, within twenty yards of the inclo&#8747;ures, which are fenced by hedges and &#8747;tone walls, from whence the rebels begun firing on the Duke’s hor&#8747;e, and made &#8747;ome &#8747;laughter; -- to the ea&#8747;t, the land de&#8747;cends to &#8747;ome &#8747;wamps, with &#8747;mall inclo&#8747;ures, at the foot of which is a
<pb n="56"/>
narrow dark lane, pa&#8747;&#8747;able for no more than one hor&#8747;eman at a time. Near this place General Honeywood received tho&#8747;e marks of &#8747;avage barbarity which had almo&#8747;t co&#8747;t him his life. -- A little detached from the village &#8747;tands a cottage, where the rebel Captain, Hamilton, with &#8747;ome others, had concealed them&#8747;elves. This being di&#8747;covered, one of the Duke’s Hu&#8747;&#8747;ars, with great dexterity, attacked the hou&#8747;e, and riding round it, fired &#8747;everal &#8747;hot in at the window, which did &#8747;ome execution, and obliged Hamilton to &#8747;hew him&#8747;elf; when there began a &#8747;ingle combat, between two equally expert in hor&#8747;eman&#8747;hip and the u&#8747;e of arms; in which Hamilton was taken pri&#8747;oner, after giving and receiving many wounds.</p>
<p> -- A train of melancholy &#8747;entiments flowed in upon the mind, on pa&#8747;&#8747;ing the ground rendered famous to po&#8747;terity by battles and &#8747;laughter; -- when rebellion adds its horrid dye to darken the retro&#8747;peƈtion, the &#8747;oul recoils at the &#8747;ad unnatural &#8747;cene; and tears &#8747;tart from the eye, to weep the &#8747;ins of fell ambition, and the pride of man.</p>
<pb n="57"/>
<p>We vi&#8747;ited the pre&#8747;ent works of Sir James Lowther, to which he is plea&#8747;ed to give the name of <i>The Village</i>; the buildings are of &#8747;tone, hand&#8747;omely &#8747;a&#8747;hed, and covered with blue &#8747;late. -- Our approach was at the ea&#8747;tern end, where the work there proceeding formed a cre&#8747;cent, behind which, the other buildings are thrown in &#8747;quares. -- The de&#8747;ign for which the proprietor is building this beautiful place, is, to entertain a number of linen manufacturers, the ereƈtions being calculated for that purpo&#8747;e, with proper apartments for the direƈtors and governors of &#8747;uch a work. -- By appearance, it &#8747;eems as if it would be capable of receiving a thou&#8747;and arti&#8747;ts. The utility and greatne&#8747;s of this projeƈt are too manife&#8747;t to require the traveller’s animadver&#8747;ions; enough it is to &#8747;ay, that &#8747;uch works, under the au&#8747;pices of &#8747;uch men, give the ob&#8747;erver infinite plea&#8747;ure. The di&#8747;tances between the rich and poor, in this luxurious and proud age, have been too di&#8747;tinƈtly maintained. -- The wealth and felicity of this nation depends upon the intimate conneƈtion between property and trade. -- Where opulence is diffu&#8747;ed in
<pb n="58"/>
works to ble&#8747;s the indu&#8747;trious poor, in projeƈts to promote manufaƈtory and arts, panegyric is &#8747;ilenced by that inward approbation and e&#8747;teem, which leads the mind to regard &#8747;uch virtue, in the charaƈter of the rich man, with reverence.</p>
<p> -- We pa&#8747;s’d along from this agreeable &#8747;cene to a place called the College, from its having been formerly the re&#8747;idence of the preceptors of the Lowther Family: where our admiration was enlarged by the princely works there carried on, at the &#8747;ole expense of Sir James. We obtained admi&#8747;&#8747;ion to in&#8747;peƈt the carpet manufactory, which is conduƈted in the manner of the Goblines. -- It is not po&#8747;&#8747;ible to convey any competent idea of the beauty of this work by de&#8747;cription; -- the &#8747;hag thrown up on the face of the carpeting is about half an inch in thickne&#8747;s, which renders it &#8747;o durable, that a new ereƈted man&#8747;ion would not out&#8747;tand &#8747;uch furniture. The colours are di&#8747;po&#8747;ed with the utmo&#8747;t ta&#8747;te and judgment, in repre&#8747;entation of natural flowers; as delicate, ea&#8747;y, and ju&#8747;t, as the works of the pencil. -- We were &#8747;o fortunate as to &#8747;ee in the looms
<pb n="59"/>
&#8747;ome carpets of peculiar beauty; the one wrought on a copper-coloured ground, &#8747;cattered with &#8747;prigs of flowers; the other on a violet ground; - the ro&#8747;es and convolvulus, the je&#8747;mines and carnations, were exqui&#8747;ite; -- they looked like fre&#8747;h pulled flowers thrown upon velvet; their di&#8747;po&#8747;ition was in the happie&#8747;t ta&#8747;te, and the colours given to form the mo&#8747;t agreeable changes and variety. -- The ma&#8747;ter of this work, in an open and polite manner, conduƈted us; not omitting one circum&#8747;tance which he apprehended could add to our plea&#8747;ure in the in&#8747;peƈtion. -- The &#8747;pinning for this work is done by children from the foundling ho&#8747;pital. -- Tears of plea&#8747;ure gushed from the eye, to behold the&#8747;e poor orphans, who would otherwi&#8747;e perhaps have been totally lo&#8747;t to the world and them&#8747;elves; thus, by &#8747;o excellent a charity, &#8747;aved from the hands of de&#8747;truction and vice, rendered u&#8747;eful members of &#8747;ociety, and happy in their indu&#8747;try and innocence.</p>
<p> -- The carpet manufaƈtury is carried on &#8747;olely for Sir James’s plea&#8747;ure, and not for &#8747;ale; we were informed that &#8747;ome
<pb n="60"/>
little time ago a piece of this work was pre&#8747;ented to her Maje&#8747;ty.</p>
<p>Pa&#8747;&#8747;ing from the college we de&#8747;cended the banks of the river Lowther, who&#8747;e woody &#8747;cenes are every where piƈture&#8747;que and plea&#8747;ing: --</p>
<poem>
<line> -- “In this path</line>
<line>“How long &#8747;oe’er the wanderer roves, each &#8747;tep</line>
<line>“Shall wake fre&#8747;h beauties, each &#8747;hort point pre&#8747;ent</line>
<line>“A different piƈture; new, and yet the &#8747;ame<ptr target="n20"/>.</line>
</poem>
<note id="n20">Ma&#8747;on’s Garden.</note>
<p> -- The beauties of the pro&#8747;peƈt at A&#8747;kam Bridge engaged our attention -- the water de&#8747;cending over a rocky channel, fell in irregular and foaming &#8747;treams; -- the little plain above was dre&#8747;&#8747;ed in brighte&#8747;t green; the lofty banks on every hand, were cloathed with &#8747;tately oaks, &#8747;ave only where a bold promontary, which overhung the road we had pa&#8747;&#8747;ed, &#8747;hewed its rocky brow from out the &#8747;hade which crowned its threat’ning front.</p>
<p>A gentleman who was &#8747;o obliging as accompany us in this day’s excur&#8747;ion, conduƈted our rout with great judgment; --
<pb n="61"/>
from Lowther, he cau&#8747;ed us to a&#8747;cend the hills, which bordered upon Uls-water, &#8747;o that the Lake was totally concealed from us in our approach, till we were ju&#8747;t upon it.</p>
<p> -- Having attained the &#8747;ummit, with no &#8747;mall degree of patience and fatigue, it opened &#8747;uddenly upon our view, pre&#8747;enting a &#8747;heet of water in the form of an S, nine miles in extent, and above a mile in width; -- as we looked thereon from an eminence, we could di&#8747;cern all its bays, &#8747;hores and promontaries, and in the exten&#8747;ive land&#8747;cape take in a variety of objeƈts, thrown together with all that beauty, which wood and water, lawns, ri&#8747;ing &#8747;weeps of corn, villas, villages, and cots, &#8747;urmounted by immen&#8747;e mountains and rude cliffs, can form to the eye; -- the country to the right, for many miles, was variegated in the fine&#8747;t manner, by enclosures, woods, and villas; among&#8747;t which Gray&#8747;tock, Dacre, and Delmain were &#8747;een, whil&#8747;t to the left, nothing but &#8747;tupendous mountains, and rude projeƈting rocks, pre&#8747;ented them&#8747;elves, vying with each other, for grandeur and eminence.</p>
<pb n="62"/>
<p>We de&#8747;cended to the village of POOLEY, and from thence, by a winding road on the margin of the Lake, pa&#8747;&#8747;ed on near a mile, to a &#8747;mall inn, where we left out hor&#8747;es.</p>
<p>On the water we were accommodated with one of the Duke of Portland’s barges, which have been &#8747;ent there by his Grace for plea&#8747;uring; -- a &#8747;trong &#8747;outh breeze rendered the Lake &#8747;o rough, that the &#8747;urf broke over the bow, whil&#8747;t the &#8747;well gave us motion, almo&#8747;t equal to that felt at &#8747;ea; my companion &#8747;uffered no &#8747;mall mortification by this accident, as it incommoded him in drawing views of this admirable &#8747;cene. -- We were obliged to coa&#8747;t it up the lake, and keep as much under the wind as po&#8747;&#8747;ible, the labour being great to make any way, with four boat-men at the oars.</p>
<p> -- As we took the boat, there &#8747;tood to our right, a mountain almo&#8747;t circular, covered with verdure to the crown, ari&#8747;ing &#8747;wiftly from the edge of the water many hundred feet in height,
<pb n="63"/>
and &#8747;hadowing us from the &#8747;un; -- to the left, the lake &#8747;pread out its agitated bo&#8747;om, whitened with innumerable breakers, above a mile in breadth; who&#8747;e oppo&#8747;ite &#8747;hore in one part a&#8747;cended gradually with cultivated lands from the village of Pooley, &#8747;kirting the hills; over which, &#8747;ome &#8747;cattered wood was happily di&#8747;po&#8747;ed in irregular groves and winding lines; whil&#8747;t all above, the brown heath reached the &#8747;ummits. -- This land adjoined a mountain much &#8747;uperior in height to that on our right, ri&#8747;ing almo&#8747;t perpendicular from the lake, with naked cliffs: on its rugged &#8747;ide, through the grey rocks, was torn a pa&#8747;&#8747;age for a rivulet, who&#8747;e waters fell precipitate with a mighty noi&#8747;e into the deep below; -- the ground more di&#8747;tant, which was &#8747;een &#8747;till upwards, over an expan&#8747;e of water not le&#8747;s than four miles, con&#8747;i&#8747;ted of lofty rocks and bold promontories, here and there &#8747;hewing naked and &#8747;torm-bleached cliffs; and in other places, &#8747;cattered over with the &#8747;pring of young oaks, ari&#8747;ing from the &#8747;tocks of trees which the ax had lately &#8747;lain. -- We could not forbear lamenting the lo&#8747;s of &#8747;o great an ornament to this romantic &#8747;cene, as a fore&#8747;t of timber
<pb n="64"/>
trees hanging on the&#8747;e declivities mu&#8747;t have been, from this and every other point of view on the lake.</p>
<p>As we pa&#8747;&#8747;ed along, having doubled two &#8747;mall capes, we fell into a bay, under the &#8747;eat of John Robin&#8747;on, E&#8747;q; of WATER MELLOCK. -- From the very margin of the lake, in this part, the gra&#8747;s ground a&#8747;cended gradually in an ea&#8747;y &#8747;lope, where were di&#8747;per&#8747;ed, in agreeable irregularity, pretty groves of a&#8747;h: there</p>
<poem>
<line> -- “ Many a glade is found,</line>
<line>“ The haunt of wood gods only, where if art</line>
<line>“ E’er dar’d to tread, ‘twas with un&#8747;andal’d feet,</line>
<line>“ Printle&#8747;s, as if teh place was holy ground.<ptr target="n21"/>"</line>
</poem>
<note id="n21">Ma&#8747;on’s Garden.</note>
<p> -- Above which, the ea&#8747;y inclining hills &#8747;hewed us yellow fields of corn, overtopped by the white front of a venerable man&#8747;ion, more noted for ho&#8747;pitality, than the elegance of its &#8747;truƈture.</p>
<p> -- The plea&#8747;antne&#8747;s of this bay, the verdure of the new-mown meads, with the &#8747;hade of the grove, induced us there to take our noon-tide repa&#8747;t.</p>
<pb n="65"/>	
<p> -- Whil&#8747;t we &#8747;ale to regale, the barge put off from &#8747;hore, to a &#8747;tation where the fine&#8747;t echoes were to be obtained from the &#8747;urrounding mountains. -- -- The ve&#8747;&#8747;el was provided with &#8747;ix bra&#8747;s cannon, mounted on &#8747;wivels; -- on di&#8747;charging one of the&#8747;e pieces, the report was echoed from the oppo&#8747;ite rocks, where by reverberation it &#8747;eemed to roll from cliff to cliff, and return through every cave and valley; till the decrea&#8747;ing tumult gradually died away upon the ear.</p>
<p> -- The in&#8747;tant it had cea&#8747;ed, the &#8747;ound of every di&#8747;tant water-fall was heard, but for an in&#8747;tant only; for the momentary &#8747;tillne&#8747;s was interrupted by the returning echo on the hills behind; where the report was repeated like a peal of thunder bur&#8747;ting over our heads, continuing for &#8747;everal &#8747;econds, flying from haunt to haunt, till once more the &#8747;ound gradually declined; -- again the voice of water-falls po&#8747;&#8747;e&#8747;&#8747;ed the interval, -- till to the right, the more di&#8747;tant thunder aro&#8747;e upon &#8747;ome other mountain, and &#8747;eemed to take its way up
<pb n="66"/>
every winding dell and creek, &#8747;ometimes behind, on this &#8747;ide, or on that, in wonderous &#8747;peed, running its dreadful cour&#8747;e; -- when the echo reached the mountains within the line and channel of the breeze, it was heard at once on the right and left, at the extremities of the lake. -- In this manner was the report of every di&#8747;charge re-echoed &#8747;even times di&#8747;tinƈtly.</p>
<p> -- At intervals we were relieved from this entertainment, which con&#8747;i&#8747;ted of a kind of wond’rous tumult and grandeur of confu&#8747;ion, by the mu&#8747;ic of two French horns, who&#8747;e harmony was repeated from every rece&#8747;s which echo haunted on the borders of the lake; -- here the breathings of the organ were imitated, there the ba&#8747;&#8747;oon with clarinets; -- in this place from the har&#8747;her &#8747;ounding cliffs, the cornet; -- in that from the wooded creek, among&#8747;t the caverns and the trilling water-falls, we heard the &#8747;oft-toned lute accompanied with the langui&#8747;hing &#8747;trains of enamoured nymphs; whil&#8747;t in the cop&#8747;e and grove was &#8747;till retained the mu&#8747;ic of the horns. All this va&#8747;t theatre was po&#8747;&#8747;e&#8747;&#8747;ed by inumerable
<pb n="67"/>
ærial beings, who breathed cele&#8747;tial harmony.</p>
<p> -- As we fini&#8747;hed our repa&#8747;t, a general di&#8747;charge of the guns, rou&#8747;ed us to new a&#8747;toni&#8747;hment; although we had heard with great &#8747;urprize the former echoes, this exceeded them &#8747;o much that it &#8747;eemed incredible: for on every hand, the &#8747;ounds were reverberated and returned from &#8747;ide to &#8747;ide, &#8747;o as to give the &#8747;emblance of that confu&#8747;ion and horrid uproar, which the falling of the&#8747;e &#8747;tupendous rocks would occa&#8747;ion, if by &#8747;ome internal combu&#8747;tion they were rent to pieces, and hurled into the lake.</p>
<p>During the time of our repa&#8747;t, the wind was hu&#8747;hed and the lake, which on our fir&#8747;t entrance was troubled and foaming, now became a &#8747;hining mirror, refleƈting rever&#8747;ed mountains, rocks, groves, meads, and vales; -- the water was &#8747;o tran&#8747;parent, that we could perceive the fi&#8747;h and pebbles at the depth of &#8747;ix or eight fathom; -- -- we now doubled a woody promontary, and pa&#8747;&#8747;ing by the foot of Gobery Park, a&#8747;cended into the narrow
<pb n="68"/>
part of the lake, leaving the gra&#8747;&#8747;y margins and &#8747;cattered cop&#8747;e, which had bordered the water as we pa&#8747;&#8747;ed by Water Mellock; now all around us being one &#8747;cene of mountains, which hemmed us in, ari&#8747;ing with awful and precipitate fronts; -- here the white cliffs rai&#8747;ed their pointed heads, there the &#8747;haken and rifted rocks were &#8747;plit and cavated into va&#8747;t &#8747;helves, cha&#8747;ms, and dreary cells, which yawned upon the &#8747;hadowed lake; whil&#8747;t other &#8747;teeps le&#8747;s rugged were decked with &#8747;hrubs, which grew on every plain and chink, their &#8747;ummits being embrowned with &#8747;un-parched mo&#8747;s and &#8747;canty herbage.</p>
<p> -- The &#8747;cene was nobly awful as we approached STARBURY CRAG; -- at every winding of our pa&#8747;&#8747;age, new hills and rocks were &#8747;een to overlook tho&#8747;e which had but the minute before been new upon our pro&#8747;peƈt; the clouds hung heavily upon the mountains, rolling in gloomy volumes over their heads, in &#8747;ome places dragging their ragged &#8747;kirts along the &#8747;ides of &#8747;teeps, giving them a deep and melancholy &#8747;hade; in others, admitting
<pb n="69"/>
the &#8747;un-beams, which illumined the winding dells with a greyi&#8747;h light.</p>
<p>Within a little di&#8747;tance of the &#8747;hore, we were &#8747;hewn a &#8747;pring, de&#8747;cribed to be of &#8747;ulphurine quality, but negleƈted by the neighbouring gentlemen, and remaining unanalized: its &#8747;ituation was &#8747;uch, that it was inconvenient to go to view it, &#8747;o that we only depended on the relation of our attendants for its de&#8747;cription. -- On my &#8747;econd vi&#8747;it to this lake, I enquired indu&#8747;triously after this valuable curio&#8747;ity, with intention to a&#8747;certain its qualities, but could not return to it; and from the a&#8747;&#8747;urances given me by Mr Robin&#8747;on, that he had never heard of &#8747;uch a &#8747;pring, I am inclined to believe the account given us was erroneous; -- &#8747;o liable are &#8747;trangers to be deceived and impo&#8747;ed on by their guides, on who&#8747;e veracity they are &#8747;ometimes obliged to rely for the information they obtain. -- This leads me nece&#8747;&#8747;arily to ob&#8747;erve, that this kind of writing is &#8747;ubjeƈt to the illiberal critici&#8747;ms and condemnations of every local pedagogue, who&#8747;e peculiar ta&#8747;te or &#8747;uperficial knowledge, may be piqued by the traveller’s inattention to his particular
<pb n="70"/>
vein, or the objeƈts of his prejudice, which, together with the impo&#8747;itions the traveller is liable to, by the lying talents of tho&#8747;e to who&#8747;e conduƈt he is obliged to tru&#8747;t, and from whom alone he mu&#8747;t receive intelligence, renders the ta&#8747;k of de&#8747;cribing irk&#8747;ome, and the attempt to communicate the plea&#8747;ures of a journey di&#8747;agreeable.</p>
<p> -- The fi&#8747;hermen belonging Mr Robin&#8747;on were &#8747;o obliging as to make us two draughts; but were not fortunate enough to take any very large fi&#8747;h; -- they drew trout, perch, and &#8747;kelley, (which la&#8747;t is a &#8747;pecies of trout not uncommon in alpine lakes<ptr target="n22"/>) all which were of excellent flavour. -- They &#8747;ometimes take a trout peculiar to this water, of thirty pounds weight and upwards, and eels of eight or nine pounds.</p>
<note id="n22">Vide Pennant’s Brit. Zool. Vol. III. p. 267, where it is de&#8747;cribed under the name of Griniad.</note>
<p> -- After a voyage upwards of nine miles, we returned down the centre of the lake, and again arrived oppo&#8747;ite the woody<pb n="71"/>promontary, which joins the extreme of the cultivated lands of Water Mellock, when the view down the lake opened upon us.</p>
<p> -- The meadows, groves, mountains, and rocks, which environed the lake, were di&#8747;po&#8747;ed in the mo&#8747;t piƈture&#8747;que order, bending around the margin of an expan&#8747;e of water five miles over; -- the lands of Water Mellock now lay at a di&#8747;tance to the left, &#8747;urmounted by &#8747;ome &#8747;mall conic hills, the heights of Gobery Park, that ranged we&#8747;tward, and terminated by the gra&#8747;&#8747;y mountain, at who&#8747;e foot we pa&#8747;&#8747;ed upon our entrance. -- The&#8747;e &#8747;weetly intermingled groves, corn fields and meads, gently inclining to the lake, where they &#8747;unk on the gra&#8747;&#8747;y margin, or &#8747;tretched into ea&#8747;y promontaries, now lay in the happie&#8747;t arrangement; -- to the right were rocky &#8747;teeps, down which the foaming cataraƈt was hurried; from whence the up&#8747;tretching inclo&#8747;ures, on gradual declinations, formed the more di&#8747;tant hills; above, from hanging groves that overlooked each other, blue rocks, crowned with brown heath, appeared; --<pb n="72"/>at the extreme of this fine cre&#8747;cent, &#8747;tood mount DUNMORLET, of a beautiful conic form, from its &#8747;kirts to the crown covered with oaks, a&#8747;hes, and firs, fortunately mingled; at who&#8747;e foot, the &#8747;ingle arch of Pooley bridge, the outlet of this mighty lake appeared, bending over a little valley, where a few cottages were &#8747;cattered; over which, at the extremity of the dale, Penrith beacon formed a plea&#8747;ing obeli&#8747;k. -- The beauties of this &#8747;cene were encrea&#8747;ed by the refleƈtion in the water, where the deep green hue was &#8747;een to mix with the olive and the grey of the adjoining objeƈts; whil&#8747;t the back ground &#8747;eemed to decline in fainte&#8747;t purple, variegated with the deep crim&#8747;on &#8747;treaks of an evening &#8747;ky.</p>
<p> -- We lay upon our oars &#8747;ome time, reluƈtant to quit this pro&#8747;peƈt, and enjoyed the mu&#8747;ic of the horns; -- the exqui&#8747;ite &#8747;oftne&#8747;s and harmony which the echoes here produced, were not to be de&#8747;cribed; the mu&#8747;ic &#8747;eemed to i&#8747;&#8747;ue from &#8747;ome re&#8747;ounding temple, which &#8747;tood concealed behind the mountains, where the mo&#8747;t &#8747;olemn and delicate &#8747;ymphony was heard,<pb n="73"/> as if reverberated from the brazen dome, or marble colonades; and as the breeze at intervals grew &#8747;ofter, one might imagine the voices of a thou&#8747;and chori&#8747;ters had filled the lenghtened chorus.</p>
<p> -- It happened fortunately for us, that the &#8747;un &#8747;ome &#8747;hort time before &#8747;etting, &#8747;hone out &#8747;erene; -- we made a little turn to look back upon the dark and rocky &#8747;cene we had pa&#8747;&#8747;ed, when the vapour which had for &#8747;ome time almo&#8747;t covered the mountains with a gloomy veil, appeared to roll upon the breeze like a mighty curtain, and withdrew, opening gradually to the eye the pompous theatre. -- No &#8747;ooner were the&#8747;e cumbrous volumes lifted above the &#8747;ummits of the we&#8747;tern hills, than the horizontal rays broke in upon the mountains; the gra&#8747;s on the heights which was parched and turned of ru&#8747;&#8747;et hue, received the light in a delicate manner, becoming a rich &#8747;hade to the bright gold teints with which the &#8747;un beams, pa&#8747;&#8747;ing through the evening vapour, &#8747;truck the cliffs, as the &#8747;lantway rays pierced each valley and inter&#8747;tice of the mountains; here beaming
<pb n="74"/>
over a whole hill, there tinging the tops of rocks, and catching the edges of the precipice, with the lu&#8747;tre of burni&#8747;hed gold; whil&#8747;t the deep &#8747;hades of every vale, each dell, cha&#8747;m, and cave, heightened the colouring above. -- In the water we traced all this piƈture&#8747;que &#8747;cene inverted, the long and deep &#8747;hadows thrown from the mountains over the lake, made the objeƈts, which were thus illumined, beautifully refleƈted on this &#8747;able mirror.</p>
<p> -- Here the mind was touched with pious and reverential thoughts, which alone delight in &#8747;ilence, whil&#8747;t contemplation dwells on the mighty author of &#8747;uch wonderous works; to whom it is acceptable, that the heart of man, &#8747;eeking him in &#8747;uch &#8747;cenes as the&#8747;e, &#8747;hould pay that adoration which no language can expre&#8747;s.</p> 
<p> -- Approaching night rouzed us from our rhap&#8747;odies; the clouds were deeply tinged with crim&#8747;on, and the whole lake &#8747;eemed to glow with a fine carnation; -- as the &#8747;un de&#8747;cended, the vapours which hung with a grey hue over the hills now
<pb n="75"/>
a&#8747;&#8747;umed a flame colour, and &#8747;eemed to wind up a multitude of glowing &#8747;treams in the mo&#8747;t grote&#8747;que figures; whil&#8747;t all below was &#8747;inking from the eye in &#8747;olemn confu&#8747;ion; -- the whole range of mountains appearing as on fire, the images of Ovid immediately occurred to my memory:</p>
<poem>
<line>-- “ Cauca&#8747;us ardet</line>
<line>“ O&#8747;&#8747;aque cum Pindo, marjorq; ambobus Olympus</line>
<line>“ Aeriæq; Alpes, &#38; nubifer Apenninus."</line>
</poem>
<p>We regained the little inn at the foot of Dunmorlet, where our hor&#8747;es waited, and returned towards Penrith, delighted with our voyage, in conver&#8747;ation enumerating the wond’rous and enchanting &#8747;cenes to which we had been pre&#8747;ent; till we reached DELMAIN, the &#8747;eat of J. Hazell, E&#8747;q; -- the rich woods which are &#8747;pread around this man&#8747;ion, together with its hand&#8747;ome &#8747;tone-built front, gave us expeƈtation, whil&#8747;t we &#8747;aw it in the morning at a di&#8747;tance, that it would be &#8747;till more plea&#8747;ing on a nearer view; but we could not forbear turning our eyes away in di&#8747;appointment, when we perceived the approach kept with a degree of negligence, which di&#8747;graced the elegant &#8747;truƈture.</p>
<pb n="76"/>
<p>In my &#8747;econd vi&#8747;it to Uls-Water, I pa&#8747;t by the remains of the ca&#8747;tle of DACRE, which gave the baronial title to the family of Dacres.</p>
<p>Bede and William of Malme&#8747;bury &#8747;ay that a mona&#8747;try &#8747;tood here, but no remains of it appear at this time.</p>
<p>This place is famous for the following congre&#8747;s: -- upon the defeƈtion of Guthred, Anlaf his brother, and Inguld king of York, Athel&#8747;tan levied a great force, and entered Northumberland &#8747;o unexpeƈtedly, that the malecontents had &#8747;carce time to &#8747;ecure them&#8747;elves by flight. -- Guthred gained proteƈtion from Con&#8747;tantine king of Scotland, to whom Athel&#8747;tan &#8747;ent deputies, demanding his per&#8747;on, or upon refu&#8747;al, he threatened to come in que&#8747;t of him at the head of his army. Con&#8747;tantine, although greatly piqued at this in&#8747;olent me&#8747;&#8747;age, yet afraid of the formidable arms of Athel&#8747;tan, con&#8747;ented to meet him at Dacre; to which place he came attended by the then king of Cumberland, where they did homage to Athel&#8747;tan.</p>
<pb n="77"/>
<p>In the church-yard of Dacre are four remarkable monuments, being the effigies of bears in &#8747;tone, about five feet high, &#8747;itting on their haunches, and cla&#8747;ping a rude pillar, or ragged &#8747;taff, on which two of the figures have their heads re&#8747;ted; the other two carry on their backs the figures of a lynx, the one of which is in an attitude as if endeavouring to rid him&#8747;elf of the animal on his &#8747;houlders, with head twi&#8747;ted, and paws ca&#8747;t behind him. Their po&#8747;ition is &#8747;uch, as to form a &#8747;quare, two to the ea&#8747;t of the church, and two to the we&#8747;t. -- There is no traditional account of the occa&#8747;ion on which they were placed there; and it &#8747;eems probable they are the remains of the decorations of the mona&#8747;try, to which the Warwick family were benefaƈtors. -- Plate, Fig. I.</p>
<p> -- In the church, within the altar-rails, lies the figure of a Knight Templar, much mutilated, and without any in&#8747;cription.</p>
<p>The Ca&#8747;tle of Dacre is now di&#8747;mantled, and has little remains of its former &#8747;trength or grandeur; the moat being <pb n="78"/>filled up, the outworks de&#8747;troyed, and only three towers &#8747;tanding, one of which is inhabited by pea&#8747;ants -- This was the original &#8747;eat of the Barons de Dacre, and from thence &#8747;prung that illu&#8747;trious family: -- it continued in the po&#8747;&#8747;e&#8747;&#8747;ion of the Dacres till the reign of Queen Elizabeth, when it came by marriage to the Earl of Su&#8747;&#8747;ex; the la&#8747;t Earl of which name dying in the reign of Queen Ann without i&#8747;&#8747;ue male, it was &#8747;old to Sir Chri&#8747;topher Mu&#8747;grave, and from him was transferred to Edward Hazell, E&#8747;q.</p>
<p>After our arrival at Ul&#8747;-Water, we rode along the &#8747;hore by Water Mellock, to the head of Gobery Park, there to enjoy the pro&#8747;peƈt of the Lake, with its oppo&#8747;ite mountains. -- In this park, a quarter of a mile from the &#8747;hore, is a fine water-fall; -- the &#8747;tream breaks from the &#8747;ummit of of a cliff cloathed with wood, and falls precipitate through a black rocky &#8747;cene near eighty perpendicular feet in height, and &#8747;ixteen feet in breadth; -- after it has pa&#8747;t about two thirds of its fall, the whole torrent is received into a cleft of the rock, where its pa&#8747;&#8747;age is impeded by fragments <pb n="79"/>
of &#8747;tone and fallen timber; beneath which the water, through a multitude of &#8747;mall apertures, breaks forth and forms a foaming &#8747;heet, which is received into a large ba&#8747;on, worn by the floods, from whence it flows through a thick woody glen, till it &#8747;inks into the lake.</p>
<p>At the foot of this rivulet we took to the boat, which waited for us; -- a gentle breeze curled upon the water, and afforded the u&#8747;e of our &#8747;ail; -- this, though it accommodated us with one plea&#8747;ure, deprived us of another, for the echoes from the di&#8747;charge of the canon, were not equal to tho&#8747;e heard on our former voyage: though the report was returned in &#8747;ix or &#8747;even echoes, yet the &#8747;ound was hurried forward from one end of the lake to the other, without any return from the oppo&#8747;ite &#8747;hore; -- the mu&#8747;ic of the horns was lo&#8747;t in the va&#8747;t &#8747;pace, and two German flutes, which were played on by part of our company, were only to be heard under the &#8747;helves, and in rece&#8747;&#8747;es of the rocks.</p>
<p>We a&#8747;cended the lake, &#8747;o as to have a view of its upper extremity; -- on the <pb n="80"/>right, the &#8747;hores are rocky, and cloathed with wood; -- the oak hoes, being fine conic eminences, crowned with timber trees, ari&#8747;e above the cliffs, over which &#8747;tupendous mountains elevate their fronts, varied with the beautiful colourings of verdant herbage, mingling with grey rocks, and topped with brown heath: whil&#8747;t, at the feet of the&#8747;e heights, the cultivated vales of Glen-riddin and Glen-coyn, with their &#8747;cattered cots, mo&#8747;t agreeably form the lower land&#8747;cape; -- the water in this part is ornamented with two beautiful i&#8747;lands. -- At the head of the lake, the margin is compo&#8747;ed of meads, over which the hills called Glencoyn Pikes, and a va&#8747;t amphitheatre of rocky mountains, bound the view; -- to the left, the &#8747;hore a&#8747;cends gradually, and is formed of &#8747;everal fine wooded promontaries, ea&#8747;y inclining meadows, and little coppices inter&#8747;per&#8747;ed among&#8747;t the rocks.</p>
<p>The &#8747;late quarries of Sir James Lowther are &#8747;een on the brow of the mountains at the head of the lake; -- the&#8747;e &#8747;lates are of a fine blue colour, and when won are brought down the &#8747;teeps of the&#8747;e va&#8747;t hills<pb n="81"/> on hor&#8747;eback, by winding pa&#8747;&#8747;es, to the lake, where they are received into flat-bottomed boats, and navigated to proper &#8747;tations for country &#8747;ale.</p>
<p>Travellers &#8747;hould land at <i>Blarvike</i>, from whence, by walking over two rocky eminences, in a truly alpine &#8747;cene, where nothing but a chaos of rocks is &#8747;een impending over the lake, almo&#8747;t without a mark of vegetation, an agreeable view of the upper limb of the lake is gained, with all its beauties, enhanced to the eye by the frightful deformities through which the &#8747;peƈtator hath pa&#8747;&#8747;ed to attain the pro&#8747;peƈt.</p>
<p>At the foot of the lake, on the Cumberland &#8747;ide, near the &#8747;ummit of one of the mountains, on its &#8747;outhern declination, we viewed an antient fortre&#8747;s called CAERTHANOCK. -- The country people give it the name of <i>Maiden’s Ca&#8747;tle</i>. -- It &#8747;eems to have been calculated more for a place of concealment, than defence, as it is overlooked by two adjoining hills, and lies under a gradual de&#8747;cent from the crown of the eminence on which it is placed. --<pb n="82"/> An oblong &#8747;quare is formed on loo&#8747;e &#8747;tones, twenty paces in length and fifteen in breadth; -- this is &#8747;urounded with a circular mound of earth eighty paces in diameter, defended on the out&#8747;ide by a ditch, which remains &#8747;ix paces wide. -- This place is not noticed by Camden, or any other author I have met with. -- The name expre&#8747;&#8747;es it to be a Briti&#8747;h fortification, though the circular entrenchment is not agreeable to that mode of defence.</p>
<p>Mr Hazel, of Delmain, is po&#8747;&#8747;e&#8747;&#8747;ed of the <i>Chace of Markendale</i>, which borders on the lake, and includes mo&#8747;t of the heights which lie upon the ea&#8747;tern &#8747;ide. -- The lands of his manor being cu&#8747;tomary tenure, are attended with this badge of &#8747;ervility, the tenants are bound to attend their Lord’s hunt within this chace once a year, which is called in their court roll a <i>Boon Hunt</i>. -- On this occa&#8747;ion they have each their di&#8747;triƈt allotted on the boundaries of the chace, where they are &#8747;tationed, to prevent the &#8747;tag flying beyond the liberty.</p>
<pb n="83"/>
<p> -- A &#8747;tag chace was promi&#8747;ed the gentlemen of the country, on the marriage of William Hazel, E&#8747;q; heir apparent of the Hou&#8747;e of Delmain, who&#8747;e excellent charaƈter and merit had rendered the occa&#8747;ion a cau&#8747;e of great fe&#8747;tivity in the neighbourhood; but as I was not fortunate enough to be pre&#8747;ent at this diver&#8747;ion, &#8747;hall beg the reader’s attention to a de&#8747;cription given me by one who had enjoyed a &#8747;imilar &#8747;cene. --</p> 
<p> -- “ A &#8747;tag having been &#8747;eleƈted from “ his herd, the hounds were conduƈted “ to the cop&#8747;e, where he lay inattentive “ to the dangers which &#8747;urrounded him. “ -- On being rou&#8747;ed, he &#8747;tretched his “ limbs, advanced his antlers with &#8747;olemn “ dignity, and looked di&#8747;dainfully upon “ the approaching hunters; he quitted the “ cover, and in contempt of the threatenings “ of his foes, &#8747;eemed &#8747;carce to touch “ the ground, as he bounded upon his “&#8747;pringing pa&#8747;terns, and made his flight “ in vaultings and &#8747;portive leaps. -- -- The cry “ of the hounds was &#8747;ingularly melodious, “ being re-echoed from &#8747;hore to &#8747;hore, and <pb n="84"/> “ added to the mu&#8747;ic of the horns. -- The “ hills were cloathed with &#8747;peƈtators; -- on “ the lake were &#8747;everal barges with colours “ di&#8747;played, and other boats, crowded “ with people. -- The &#8747;tag at fir&#8747;t took the “ heights, where &#8747;ometimes he was &#8747;een “ climbing the mountains with incredible “&#8747;wiftne&#8747;s, whil&#8747;t the hounds appeared “ in a &#8747;lower train, pur&#8747;uing, yet lo&#8747;ing “ ground, &#8747;o much did he &#8747;eem to out&#8747;trip “ them. -- At other times, the interpo&#8747;ing “ mountains robbed us of the &#8747;ight, “ but indulged us with the mu&#8747;ic of the “ cry; from the melody of which, attention “ was not diverted by having the “ pack in view. -- Again they came in “ &#8747;ight; -- the &#8747;tag flew over every fence “ as an arrow from the bow; -- the hounds “ appeared to gain ground; -- the various “ windings of the fugitive along the &#8747;teeps “ were all in view; -- at length he found “ his flight and &#8747;peed did not avail him; “ he meditated to &#8747;ave him&#8747;elf by artifice, “ &#8747;ubmitting to de&#8747;cend into the lower “ grounds, and quit the hills. -- The people “ who attended, perceiving the well-known “ &#8747;ignal of his declining &#8747;peed, “ with their &#8747;houts from every quarter <pb n="85"/> “made each cliff and vale re&#8747;ound. -- “ Echo deceived our ears in a &#8747;urprizing “ manner; for the &#8747;houts were &#8747;o repeated, “ as if the whole exten&#8747;ive circus was “ crowded with people, and the huzza “ given by tens of thou&#8747;ands. -- In&#8747;tantly “ all the ve&#8747;&#8747;els on the lake were put in motion, “ and the oars were bu&#8747;ied in plying “ to that quarter to which the &#8747;tag advanced; “ it is their u&#8747;ual cu&#8747;tom, when “ pre&#8747;&#8747;ed by the hounds to take the water, “ to plunge into the lake, and tru&#8747;t to their “&#8747;wimming. -- Many of the pack jumped “ into the water -- and the chace was continued “ even in the lake. -- The unhappy “&#8747;tag found, though he e&#8747;caped his common “ enemy, yet other foes, which rendered “ all his efforts for &#8747;afety vain; -- the “ boats enclo&#8747;ed him, and brought him again “ to &#8747;hore. -- To prolong the diver&#8747;ion, “ his di&#8747;tre&#8747;s was doubled; -- a re&#8747;pite was “ given for &#8747;ome moments; -- hope aro&#8747;e “ upon his heart, but of &#8747;hort exi&#8747;tence! “ with looks of terror he &#8747;oon beheld his “ pur&#8747;uers upon him: -- after many flights “ and once more watering, the noble fugitive “ was driven to his forlorn hope; “ -- his timid nature was changed by nece&#8747;&#8747;ity,<pb n="86"/> “ and courage aro&#8747;e from de&#8747;pair; “ -- he &#8747;tood, and with his horns bayed “ the approaching hounds -- his la&#8747;t and “ &#8747;ad ineffeƈtual effort; -- he was &#8747;eized, “ and by the hunters &#8747;aved from being “ torn piece meal by the dogs." --</p> 
<p> -- Compa&#8747;&#8747;ion and the finer feelings have nothing to do with the chace: -- were men to give way to &#8747;ympathetic &#8747;entiments, the di&#8747;tre&#8747;s and mi&#8747;ery of the innocent animal which is pur&#8747;ued and hunted down, would overcome the melody of the cry, and the beauty of tho&#8747;e artifices which the pur&#8747;ued employs in vain to &#8747;ave his life. -- Let &#8747;uch men avoid the chace. -- Men of robu&#8747;t and hardy con&#8747;titutions, feel the lea&#8747;t compa&#8747;&#8747;ion or &#8747;entiment, and tru&#8747;t the lea&#8747;t to thought. -- Such are the heroes of the hunt. -- I have been told, that after the captive has received his death’s wound from the keeper, it is u&#8747;ual for the hunters to compleat their joy, by &#8747;taining each other’s faces with the gore.</p>
<p>A little ramble took place on the en&#8747;uing morning; -- in our way, we were <pb n="87"/>&#8747;hewn the tenement, where, in the great tempe&#8747;t &#8747;ome few years ago, Mi&#8747;s Bolton and her female friend were overwhelmed in the ruins of their hou&#8747;e: -- Over who&#8747;e untimely monument even piety lets fall a tear, and re&#8747;ignation bows to heaven with &#8747;ighs, whil&#8747;t hope in holy whi&#8747;pers tells, that innocence and virtue called from hence become angelic.</p>
<p>We viewed the ruins of Penrith Ca&#8747;tle; -- it is &#8747;aid to have aro&#8747;e on the foundations of a Roman fortre&#8747;s. -- Camden &#8747;ays, in the reign of Henry VI. it was repaired out of the ruins of a Roman fort near to it, called Maybourgh<ptr target="n23"/>: but this opinion is very erroneous, and entirely exploded by the author of Magna Britannia. -- The buildings form a &#8747;quare, and are &#8747;ituate on a ri&#8747;ing ground, &#8747;urrounded with a ditch; -- the &#8747;ite towards the town is much more elevated than any of the other quarters. -- If any remains of Roman work is to be found there, it is on this quarter, <pb n="88"/>where the area bears the appearance of the old vallum. -- This front con&#8747;i&#8747;ts of the remains of an angular tower to the ea&#8747;t, which now &#8747;tands &#8747;eparated from other parts by the falling of the walls; -- the centre, which projeƈts a little from the place of the front, is ha&#8747;tening to decay, pre&#8747;enting to the eye broken chambers, pa&#8747;&#8747;ages, and &#8747;tairs; -- this part of the building is &#8747;till conneƈted with the we&#8747;tern angular tower, an open gallery forming the communication; -- below this gallery, a large opening is made by the falling of the building, forming a rude arch; through which, and the broken walls to the Ea&#8747;t, the interior parts of the ruin are perceived in a piƈture&#8747;que manner: -- nothing remains within to attraƈt notice.</p>
<note id="n23">If Bi&#8747;hop Nichol&#8747;on had not correƈted Camden in his account, that Penrith Ca&#8747;tle was repaired out of the ruins of Mayburg, a bare view of the Ca&#8747;tle would do it, being intirely built of red hewn &#8747;tone.</note>
<head level="2" align="center">PENRITH</head>
<p>Was formerly a part of the See of Durham, but in the time of the ambitious Anthony Beck, King Edward I. di&#8747;membered it. -- It is &#8747;aid in a compromi&#8747;e of differences between Henry III. and Alexander the Scotti&#8747;h King, that Henry &#8747;tipulated to grant to Alexander two hundred <pb n="89"/>librates of land (each librate being four oxgangs, or, as &#8747;ome compute, of twenty pounds yearly value) in Northumberland or Cumberland, if &#8747;o much of Henry’s land could be found therein, where no ca&#8747;tle &#8747;tood; and that Penrith was part of this grant. -- It is not doubted that Henry VI. po&#8747;&#8747;e&#8747;&#8747;ed this ca&#8747;tle, and re&#8747;tored it. -- Richard Duke of Glouce&#8747;ter, afterwards Richard III. about the year 1472 married Ann the widow of Edward Prince of Wales, &#8747;on to Henry VI. and daughter and co-heire&#8747;s of Richard Nevil, Earl of Warwick and Sali&#8747;bury, by whom (as part of her dowry) he had the Honor of Penrith; -- he repaired and beautified this ca&#8747;tle, and made it the chief place of his re&#8747;idence; where, from his munificence and noble manner of living, he acquired great popularity and e&#8747;teem; in &#8747;o much, that he drew from thence five thou&#8747;and men to honour or &#8747;upport his coronation. -- This ca&#8747;tle was afterwards di&#8747;mantled in the time of the Proteƈtor Cromwell, and has lain in ruins ever &#8747;ince. -- In the time of William III. it was granted to William Bentick, Earl of Portland.</p>
<pb n="90"/>
<p>From thence we went to view a place by the inhabitants called <i>Arthur’s round Table</i>, near to Emont Bridge, and about half a mile from Penrith. -- This is &#8747;aid to be of great antiquity, but there is no tradition, when, by whom, or for what purpo&#8747;e it was made. -- It is cut in a little plain near the river, of an exaƈt circular figure, &#8747;ave to the ea&#8747;tern and we&#8747;tern &#8747;ides an approach is left to the common level of the plain: -- the trench by which it is formed, is near ten paces wide; the &#8747;oil which has been thrown up on the outward &#8747;ide making a kind of theatre: -- the approaches are ten paces wide, and the whole circle within the ditch is one hundred and &#8747;ixty paces in circumference. -- We were induced to believe this was an antient tilting ground, where ju&#8747;tings had been held: the approaches &#8747;eemed to an&#8747;wer for the career, and the circle appears &#8747;ufficient for the champions to &#8747;hew their dexterity in the u&#8747;e of the lance and hor&#8747;eman&#8747;hip; the whole circus being capable of receiving a thou&#8747;and &#8747;peƈtators on the outer &#8747;ide of the ditch. -- It is not probable that this was an intrenchment or fortified<pb n="91"/> camp, it being too &#8747;mall for &#8747;uch purpo&#8747;es; and more particularly it is overlooked by an adjoining ri&#8747;ing ground, from whence it might be annoyed by mi&#8747;&#8747;ile weapons. Another rea&#8747;on for the &#8747;ame opinion, given by a learned author, is, that the ditch is on the inner &#8747;ide<ptr target="n24"/>.</p>
<note id="n24">Magna Britannia.</note>
<p>It is &#8747;aid of the order of Knights of the Round Table, that it was in&#8747;tituted by King Arthur, to the end there might be no que&#8747;tion about precedency, and to teach heroic minds not to be ambitious of place, but merit.</p>
<p>At a little di&#8747;tance from the round table, and nearer to Emont Bridge, is another circular ditch, with a very low rampart, but of much greater &#8747;ize, being &#8747;eventy paces diameter, without any apertures or advances. -- If we pre&#8747;ume the other was intended for feats of chivalry, this may be &#8747;uppo&#8747;ed calculated for pede&#8747;trian exerci&#8747;es.</p>
<pb n="92"/>
<p>At about half a mile’s di&#8747;tance we viewed a place called MAYBROUGH. -- A hill, which ari&#8747;es gradually on every &#8747;ide about one hundred and forty paces from the level of the lands below, forming the lower &#8747;eƈtion of a regular cone; -- the a&#8747;cent is on every &#8747;ide grown with oaks and a&#8747;hes, and &#8747;eems, from the reliques of the ax, to have been covered in former ages with wood, though no very antient trees now remain &#8747;tanding. -- The plate fig. I repre&#8747;ents an interior view of the place.</p>
<p> -- The &#8747;ummit of the hill is fenced round, &#8747;ave only an opening left to the ea&#8747;t, twelve paces wide; -- the fence is very &#8747;ingular, being compo&#8747;ed of an immen&#8747;e quantity of loo&#8747;e pebble &#8747;tones, which &#8747;eem to have been gathered from the river, by their quality, and the &#8747;imilarity there is between them and the gravel of the bed of the Emont. -- No kind of mortar appears to have been u&#8747;ed here, the &#8747;tones lie uncemented, and in a heap, the foot is near twenty paces wide, ri&#8747;ing to an edge, in height about eight feet from the level of the interior plain. -- Here and <pb n="93"/>there, time has &#8747;cattered a few trees and bru&#8747;h-wood over the pebbles; but in other places, there are loo&#8747;e and naked, both on the out and in&#8747;ide of the fence. -- The &#8747;pace within, con&#8747;i&#8747;ts of a fine plain of meadow ground, exaƈtly circular, one hundred paces diameter; -- inclining a little to the we&#8747;tward from the centre, a large ma&#8747;s of unhewn &#8747;tone is &#8747;tanding ereƈt, placed with the &#8747;maller end in the earth, on which &#8747;ome little a&#8747;h trees have taken their growth, by &#8747;triking their roots into the natural fi&#8747;&#8747;ures of the &#8747;tone; -- this &#8747;tone is in circumference near its middle twenty-two feet and &#8747;ome inches, and in height eleven feet and upwards; it is a &#8747;pecies of the free &#8747;tone, and appears to have been gathered from the &#8747;urface, and not won in any quarry or bed of &#8747;tone. -- The inhabitants in the neighbourhood &#8747;ay, that within the memory of man, two other &#8747;tones of &#8747;imilar nature, and placed in a kind of angular figure with the &#8747;tone now remaining, were to be &#8747;een there, but as they were hurtful to the ground, were de&#8747;troyed and removed.</p>
</text>




<!--This is a comment
As discussed, I have kept the old writing style as well as the quotation marks for external accounts, which in the original text signal a new line.
I have ignored the title at the top of each page.
Long lines(/hyphens) in poems, have again been digitised as double hyphens.
On pp.7/8 the Latin poem/words are enclosed in big brackets, which I have ignored. 
As before, I have digitised the ‘†" reference exactly like the ‘*’, following on from each other, eg. pp 19/20.  
On p. 42, a poem reference is made at the side, I have nevertheless put that at the end as well.
On pp. 60/64, the author and title of the poem are given as a reference at the bottom, in this case I have therefore merely digitised them as a note. -->
  
 

