<text id="1830_a">
<gap desc="front matter, not digitized"/>
<gap desc="Map of Windermere"/>
<chap title="Cover">
<pb n="cover"/>
<head level="2" align="center">LEIGH'S GUIDE</head>
<head level="3" align="center">TO THE</head>
<head level="1" align="center">LAKES AND MOUNTAINS</head>
<head level="3" align="center">OF</head>
<head level="2" align="center">CUMBERLAND, WESTMORELAND,</head>
<head level="3" align="center">AND</head>
<head level="2" align="center">LANCASHIRE</head>
<p align="center">ILLUSTRATED WITH</p>
<p align="center">A MAP OF THE COUNTRY, AND MAPS OF WINDERMERE, DERWENT WATER, BORROWDALE, ULLSWATER, GRASMERE, RYDAL WATER, AND LANGDALE</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center"><i>SECOND EDITION</i></head>
<head level="3" align="center">ENLARGED AND IMPROVED</head>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">LONDON:</head>
<head level="3" align="center">PRINTED FOR M.A. LEIGH, 421, STRAND.</head>
<head level="3" align="center">(REMOVED FROM 18, STRAND.)</head>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">1832.</head>
<gap desc="front matter"/>
<p>"In truth, a more pleasing Tour than these Lakes hold out to men of leisure and curiosity, cannot be devised. We penetrate the Glaciers, traverse the Rhone and the Rhine, whilst our domestic lakes of Ullswater, Keswick, and Windermere, exhibit scenes in so sublime a style, -- with such beautiful colourings of rock, wood, and water, -- backed with so tremendous a disposition of mountains, that if they do not fairly take the lead of all the views of Europe, yet they are indisputably such as no English traveller should leave behind him."</p>
<p align="right">CUMBERLAND'S DEDICATION TO ROMNEY.</p>
<p>"As my object is to reconcile a Briton to the scenery of his own country, though not at the expense of truth, I am not afraid of asserting that, in many points of view, our <i>Lakes,</i> also, are much more interesting than those of the Alps."</p>
<p align="right">WORDSWORTH.</p>
<gap desc="Contents"/>
</chap>
<chap title="Preliminary Observations">
<pb n="1"/>
<head level="3" align="center">A</head>
<head level="2" align="center">GUIDE TO THE LAKES</head>
<head level="3" align="center">OF</head>
<head level="2" align="center">CUMBERLAND, LANCASHIRE,</head>
<head level="3" align="center">AND</head>
<head level="2" align="center">WESTMORELAND.</head>
<gap desc="line"/>
<p>THE Lakes are usually visited between May and October; but more particularly from the end of June to the end of August. The length of the days during this period is favourable for excursions, and the mountains are adorned with all the beauty of summer foliage. Those persons, however, who prefer the green hues of spring and the olive tints of autumn, will visit the Lakes either in May or September. The pedestrian will select these months on account of the coolness of the weather, and the artist will choose the latter, as the landscape is then more rich and diversified than at any other part of the year.</p>
<p>The accommodations for tourists are excellent. The Innas are clean and comfortable, the charges reasonable, and the Guides generally very civil and attentive. Boats, cars, horses, and other means of conveyance are to be found at all the principal places. The price usually charged for a post-chaise and pair of horses is 1<i>s.</i> 3<i>d.</i> a mile, and for a car and single <pb n="2"/> horse 1<i>s.</i> per mile. The post-boy or driver expects about 3<i>d.</i> a mile. The roads have been very much improved within a few years, and are now in an excellent state.</p>
<p>There are two principal Routes for persons visiting the Lakes, either to commence at Penrith and terminate at Lancaster, or <i>vice vers&#227;.</i> Tourists from the North will prefer the former, and those from the South the latter route, which is also the best for viewing the scenery. The lakes will the be seen in the following order: --</p>
<table width="90%">
<tr>
<td>CONISTON WATER,</td>
<td>BASSENTHWAITE WATER,</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ESTHWAITE OR EASTHWAITE</td>
<td>BUTTERMERE WATER,</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>	WATER,</td>
<td>CRUMMOCK WATER,</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WINDERMERE WATER,</td>
<td>WAST WATER,</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RYDAL WATER,</td>
<td>ENNERDALE WATER,</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GRASMERE WATER,</td>
<td>LOWES WATER,</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LEATHES OR THIRLMERE WATER,</td>
<td>ULLS WATER,</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DERWENT WATER,</td>
<td>HAWES WATER.</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>We shall, therefore, suppose the Tourist to be setting out from London for Lancaster, and afterwards visiting the ruins of Furness Abbey, as the first object of interest.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="I. From LONDON to LANCASTER.">
<head level="3" align="center">I. From LONDON to LANCASTER.</head>
<table width="90%">
<tr>
<td width="20%"></td>
<td width="10%">Miles.</td>
<td width="70%">Inns.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Barnet</td>
<td width="10%">11</td>
<td width="70%">Commercial, Green Man, Red Lion.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">St. Alban's</td>
<td width="10%">21</td>
<td width="70%">Angel, Woolpack, White Hart.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Dunstable</td>
<td width="10%">33 &#189;</td>
<td width="70%">Crown, Sugar Loaf.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Woburn</td>
<td width="10%">42 &#190;</td>
<td width="70%">George, Bedford Arms, Magpie.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Newport Pagnelll</td>
<td width="10%">51 &#189;</td>
<td width="70%">Saracen's Head, Swan.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Northampton</td>
<td width="10%">66 &#189;</td>
<td width="70%">Angel, George, Peacock.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Market Harborough</td>
<td width="10%">83 &#189;</td>
<td width="70%">Three Swans, Angel.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Leicester</td>
<td width="10%">98 %</td>
<td width="70%">Blue Bell, Three Crowns, Crane, White Hart.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Loughborough</td>
<td width="10%">109 &#190;</td>
<td width="70%">Anchor, Bull's Head.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Derby</td>
<td width="10%">126 &#189;</td>
<td width="70%">Bell, George, New Inn, King's Head.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Ashbourn</td>
<td width="10%">140</td>
<td width="70%">Blackmoor's Head, Green Man.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Leek</td>
<td width="10%">155</td>
<td width="70%">George, Buck.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Macclesfield</td>
<td width="10%">167 &#190;</td>
<td width="70%">Macclesfield Arms, Old Angel.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Stockport</td>
<td width="10%">179 &#190;</td>
<td width="70%">Bulkeley Arms, Horse Shoe, White Lion.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Manchester</td>
<td width="10%">186</td>
<td width="70%">Bridgewater Arms, Bull's Head, Spread Eagle, Commercial, Star, Swan.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Bolton</td>
<td width="10%">197 &#189;</td>
<td width="70%">Bridge, Boar's Head, Commercial, Swan.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Chorley</td>
<td width="10%">209</td>
<td width="70%">Oak, Bull, Bull's Head.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Preston</td>
<td width="10%">218 &#188;</td>
<td width="70%">Black Bull, Three Legs of Mutton, Red Lion.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Garstang</td>
<td width="10%">229 &#188;</td>
<td width="70%">Eagle and Child, Royal Oak.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="20%">Lancaster</td>
<td width="10%">240 &#189;</td>
<td width="70%">Commercial and Royal Oak, King's Arms, White Hart, New Inn.</td>
</tr>
</table>
<gap desc="line"/>
<pb n="4"/>
<head level="3" align="center">LANCASTER.</head>
<p>The capital of Lancashire is seated on the Lune, at some distance from its entrance into the sea, vessels of large burthen not being able to come within six miles of the town. The streets are well paved, and the houses generally well built. Over the river is a handsome Bridge, and along the quay is a fine range of warehouses. The population amounts to 12,613.</p>
<p>The Castle occupies a commanding situation, and is in itself an imposing structure. The greater part of it is modern, but portions of the edifice erected in the reign of Edward III. still exist. At the top is a large square keep, called John of Gaunt's Chair, from which there is a most extensive and beautiful prospect.</p>
<p>Contiguous to the Castle are the County Courts and Shire Hall, which are remarkably handsome, built from designs by Mr. Harrison, and near them stands the Church, a Gothic structure, containing several monuments.</p>
<p>The Town Hall or Sessions is a handsome stone building of the Doric order, erected from designs by Major Jarrat. It contains portraits of Lord Nelson and Mr. Pitt, by Lonsdale.</p>
<p>The New Bridge, by which Lancaster is approached from the North, is an elegant structure of five arches, designed by Mr. Harrison. It is 549 feet in length.</p>
<p>From the Work House Hill there is a fine view of the town and the castle, as well as of the surrounding country.</p>
<pb n="5"/>
<p>There are several other public buildings in Lancaster, but none of them particularly remarkable. It carries on a considerable trade in coal and limestone by means of its canal, which is conveyed over the Lune, about a mile from this place, by an aqueduct bridge. Many small ships are built here.</p>
<pb n="6"/>
</chap>
<chap title="From LANCASTER to ULVERSTONE, OVER THE SANDS.">
<head level="3" align="center">II. From LANCASTER to ULVERSTONE,</head>
<head level="3" align="center">OVER THE SANDS</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lancaster to Hest Bank</td>
<td width="20%">3 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Hest Bank to Lancaster Sands</td>
<td width="20%">&#190;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lancaster Sands to Kent's Bank</td>
<td width="20%">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Kent's Bank to Allithwaite</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Allithwaite to Flookboro'</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Flookboro' to Leven Sands</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Level Sands to Ulverstone</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">21</td>
</tr>
</table>
<!-- I *can* figure out how to add the separating line above the sum miles, but I feel I'm already pushing it a bit with the table structures; I'm not sure if nested tables would be appreciated with what you'll eventually be doing with the text. If it's acceptable to employ some further html, I don't mind amending it to do so -->
<p>In order to reach the Sands when the tide is out, the Tourist should set out from Lancaster at the same time as the Ulverstone "Over Sands" Coach, which goes every day. Crossing the sands in the summer season, in company with the regular guides, is seldom attended with any danger; but those who want courage to venture upon them, may take the route to Ulverstone, described in the SUPPLEMENT, No. 13.</p>
<p><i>Hest Bank</i> is a small bathing-place, pleasantly situated on Morecambe Bay. The Tourist then arrives at the</p>
<head level="3" align="center">LANCASTER SANDS.</head>
<p>The tract across these sands varies from 7 to 11 miles in length, according as the sea approaches to, or recedes from, the shore. The average distance may be considered 9 miles. Guides are appointed by government to conduct travellers through the rivers Keer and Kent, which pass over the sands to the <pb n="7"/>sea. They receive but a small salary, and it is usual for each passenger to give them a few halfpence. The guide at the Keer is on foot, and at the Kent on horseback. The latter is called <i>The Carter,</i> the family of that name having fulfilled the office for a long period.</p>
<p>On a fine day nothing can be more delightful than a ride over the Lancaster Sands, which command views of the whole coast of Morecambe Bay from Peel Castle to the shore beyond Lancaster. On the right, is a bold and deeply indented shore, with richly wooded valleys stretching far into the country; and, on the left, Heysham Point, with the village hanging on its side, rises abruptly. To the right also appear Warton Craig and Arnside Fells, and far beyond them the broad head of the lofty Ingleborough. Castle Heads, a pyramidal hill rising above the station at Kendal, is also visible, as well as Arnside Tower, formerly a mansion of the Stanley family. Near the latter, is a grey rock, called Silverdale Nab, between which and the Cartmel coast the Kent rolls towards the sea. At the mouth of the estuary are two wooded islands, and at the head, beneath a hill, are seen the village and church of Heversham. The Cartmel shore presents hills covered with woods, and backed by the lofty chain of the Westmoreland and Cumberland mountains.</p>
<p><i>Kent's Bank.</i> At the foot of a hill 3 miles from this spot, and on the west shore of the Kent, is the mansion <i>Castlehead.</i></p>
<p><i>Allithwaite.</i> About 2 miles distant is the pleasant town of CARTMEL, containing 400 inhabitants. It <pb n="8"/> is principally supported by persons visiting the mineral springs in its vicinity. The church, formerly attached to a Priory, is adorned with carved wood and monuments. There is also a Free Grammer School, and in the vicinity are several villas. The Prior of Cartmel was formerly charged with the office of Guide across the Sands, but since the Dissolution it has been held by patent of the Duchy of Lancaster.</p>
<p><i>Flookboro'</i> was once a market town. On the right beyond it, is <i>Holker Hall,</i> the seat of Lord George Cavendish. It contains a good collection of pictures, and is surrounded by a fine park. --We then reach the</p>
<head level="3" align="center">LEVEN SANDS.</head>
<p>The track across is about 3 miles in length. The passage of the Leven is rather more dangerous than that of the Kent, as the sands are frequently shifting. The Guide here is on horseback. The views obtained in crossing are very picturesque: the coast is deeply indented, and the peninsulas beautifully fringed with wood. On one side of the river appear the Cartmel Fells and the woods of Holker Hall; and, on the other, the Ulverstone Fells, clothed with verdure. The view up the river is terminated by the mountains which surround Coniston Water and Windermere. Towards the south is <i>Chapel Island,</i> at the mouth of the Leven, and on the Ulverstone coast appear the grounds of Conishead Priory and Bardsea, with its rocks and woods.</p>
<pb n="9"/>
<head level="3" align="center">ULVERSTONE</head>
<p>Is a neatly built town, situated on the declivity of a small range of hills, sloping towards the south-east. It is rather more than a mile from the river Leven, with which it communicates by a broad canal. Ulverstone may be considered as the capital of the district of Furness, the weekly market on Thursday having been long removed from Dalton to this place. The neighbouring fells abound with slate, limestone, and iron ore. The inhabitants are engaged in the export of these articles and in the manufacture of cotton-twist, hats, canvas, and checks. The town has a Church, a Theatre, Assembly Rooms, and a Library. From the hill beyond the church there is a fine view of the town and the adjacent sands. The population amounts to 4876.</p>
<p>There are two good Inns, the Sun and the Braddyb Arms.</p>
<p>A coach goes every day to Lancaster, over the Sands, and there is another round my Millthorpe several times a week.</p>
<p>In the vicinity are several gentlemen's seats: the most remarkable is that of CONISHEAD PRIORY, 2 miles distant; of whih Mr. West says, "it is a great omission in the curious travller to be in Furness and not to see so wonderfully pretty a place, to which nature has been so profuse in noble gifts, and where art has lent its best assistance, under the regulation of an elegant fancy and a refined taste." The house is now being rebuilt of stone in the Gothic style, from designs by Mr. Wyatt, and when completed, will form a very <pb n="10"/> handsome residence. It has an elegant conservatory, and in the park is a pretty hermitage.</p>
<p>About half way between Ulverstone and Conishead Priory is SWARTHMOOR HALL, a farm-house, which was occupied for some years by George Fox, the founder of the Society of Friends, who married the widow of Judge Fell, to whom the estate belonged. The bedstead on which he was accustomed to sleep is preserved here. A quarter of a mile distant is the Meeting House which he built, and which is still used by the Friends of the neighbourhood.</p>
<p>At WHITRIGS, 3 miles west of ULVERSTONE, on the Dalton road, are some of the largest iron mines in England. The ore is obtained by driving levels into the mountain. It is found in a limestone stratum mixed with a variety of spars.</p>
<p>WALNEY ISLAND, situated about 9 miles south-west of ULVERSTONE, is remarkable for its immense numbers of wild-fowl, sea-gulls, &#38;c. In some parts they are so numerous, that the visitor cannot move a yard without treading on their eggs.</p>
<pb n="11"/>
</chap>
<chap title="III. From ULVERSTONE to FURNESS ABBEY.">
<head level="3" align="center">III. From ULVERSTONE to FURNESS ABBEY.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%">Miles.</td>
<td width="20%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ulverstone to Dalton</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Dalton to Furness</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Return to Ulverstone</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">12</td>
</tr>
</table>
<head level="3" align="center">DALTON</head>
<p>Is an ancient little town, which was once the capital of Furness, and a place of considerable importance. It has now little more than 700 inhabitants. The Church and the remains of the Castle are situated on a bold ascent. All that now exists of the latter is a tower, in a chamber of which the Abbot of Furness held his secular court. It was afterwards used as a gaol for debtors. The present churchyard and the site of the castle are supposed to have formed part of a castellum, constructed by Agricola. Romney the portrait-painter, was born at a place called Beck-side, in Dalton.</p>
<p>Beneath the brow of the hill on which the church and tower of Dalton stand, a brook flos through a narrow valley that winds about the distance of a mile to</p>
<head level="3" align="center">FURNESS ABBEY.</head>
<p>These magnificent remains are situated in a close glen called the Vale of Nightshade, or, more literally, from its ancient title Bekansgill, the Glen of Deadly Nightshade, <pb n="12"/> that plant formerly abounding in it the neighbourhood. Its romantic gloom and sequestered privacy particularly adapted it to the austerities of monastic life; and in the most retired part of it, King Stephen, while Earl of Mortaign and Bulloign, founded, in 1127, the Monastery of Furness, and endowed it so richly, that is was second only to Fountains Abbey in Yorkshire. It was dedicated to St. Mary, and received a colony of monks from the monastery of Savigny, in Normandy, who were called Grey Monks, from their dress of that colour, till they became Cistercians, and, with the severe rules of St. Bernard, adopted a white habit, which they retained till the Dissolution in 1537.</p>
<p>The ruins are approached by a small wooden gate, forming the entrance to the immediate precincts of the Abbey, an area said to contain sixty-five acres. On the left, just within this gate, is a small modern-built manor-house, beyond which a full view is obtained of the Abbey, having a lawn in front, and inclosed on each side by noble trees. Within a few years, the appearance of the ruins has been very much improved, by removing the rubbish with which they were encumbered.</p>
<p>The principal parts of the Abbey remaining are the school-house, the arched roof of which is still perfect; the refectory, formerly a noble hall, along the centre of which was a row of columns, supporting the roof; the chapter-house, still bearing traces of its rich sculpture; and the church, the great window of which forms a conspicuous object. In the church are four ancient recumbent statues, and four stalls, in which the priests <pb n="13"/> occasionally sat during the service; there are also numerous fragments of sculpture.</p>
<p>The Abbey is built of a pale red stone, dug from the neighbourhood rocks, now changed by time and weather to a tint of dusky brown, which accords well with the hue of plants and shrubs that every where emboss the mouldering arches.</p>
<p>The finest view of the ruin is from the hill opposite the East window, through which are seen, in perspective, the choir, distant arches, and remains of the nave of the Abbey, backed by the woods. This perspective of the ruin is said to be 287 feet in length; the choir part of it is in width only 28 feet inside, but the nave is 70; the walls are 54 feet high and 5 in thickness. Southward from the choir extend the pillars and arcades of some chapels, now laid open to the day, as well as the chapter-house and the cloisters. Beyond these, and quite detached, is the school-house, the only part of the monastery that still has a roof.</p>
<p>From the rising ground of <i>Hawcoat,</i> one mile W. of Furness Abbey, there is a very fine prospect. On a clear day, it embraces the whole length of the Isle of Man, with part of Anglesey, and the mountains of Caernarvon, Merionethshire, Derbyshire and Flintshire, shadowing the opposite horizon of the channel.</p>
<p>Returning from Dalton, the tourist may pass through Urswick and over Birkrigg Common, by Bardsea and Conishead Priory to Ulverstone. The view from the summit of Birkrigg is extremely grand, particularly at high water. Hence, on a clear day, may be seen the whole extent of Morecambe Bay and the coast of <pb n="14"/> Wales, above which Snowdon forms a conspicuous object. To the N.E. appear Ulverstone and the Furness Hills, and in the distance are seen the mountains of Cumberland and the lofty Ingleborough.</p>
</chap>
<chap title="IV. From ULVERSTONE to BOWNESS">
<pb n="15"/>
<head level="3" align="center">IV. From ULVERSTONE TO BOWNESS,</head>
<head level="3" align="center">by CONISTON WATER, ESTHWAITE WATER, and</head>
<head level="3" align="center">WINDERMERE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ulverstone to Lowick Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">5 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lowick Bridge to Nibthwaite</td>
<td width="20%">1 <unclear>&#189;</unclear></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Nibthwaite to Coniston Waterhead</td>
<td width="20%">7 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Waterhead to Hawkshead</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Hawkshead to Sawrey</td>
<td width="20%">2 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Sawrey to Ferry House</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ferry House to Bowness</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">23 &#188;</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>From Ulverstone to Coniston Water, the road passes along a narrow vale, over which are scattered several farms. Four miles from Ulverstone, the lake and vale of Coniston form a splendid landscape. At the head of the lake is seen the Old Man, having Wetherlam on its right, and Walney Scar on its left, whilst in the distance, to the left, appear the Scawfell Pikes, and to the right, Helvellyn and Fairfield. In the foreground, dark rocks frown over the surface of the lake.</p>
<p>Half a mile further is LOWICK HALL, once the seat of a family of that name, but now occupied as a farm-house. Behind it are rocky mountains, with a few stripes of heath. Just beyond, on the left of the road is LOWICK CHAPEL.</p>
<p>At LOWICK BRIDGE, the tourist crosses the Crake, which is the outlet for the waters of Coniston. Half a mile beyond it are iron works.</p>
<p>Near NIBTHWAITE, Coniston Water opens in full <pb n="16"/> view. The best prospect of it is to be obtained from a very small hill on the left of the road, about a quarter of a mile beyond this village.</p>
<p>The scenery improves as the road passes along the Eastern bank of the lake, and approaches its Northern extremity. One pretty bay is succeeded by another: the road is sometimes on the margin of the lake, but generally a little distance from it; it is frequently lost in wood, out of which there are, however, occasional glimpses and more extended views through groups and fringings of single trees. The morning is the best time for this ride. In the afternoon, if the sun shines, much of the effect is lost by the change of light.</p>
<p>CONISTON WATERHEAD INN is beautifully situated on the shore at the head of the lake, of which it commands a fine view. Here boats may be hired, as well as a chaise and horses. In a stream, at a short distance, the proprietor of the inn usually keeps some char, for the gratification of visiters. This fish is only in high season, however, during the winter months.</p>
<p>Above the inn is the villa of WATERHEAD, situated upon a fine elevation, and commanding a charming view of the lake with its pretty shores. From the house and grounds the Man Mountain forms an interesting object.</p>
<p>From this place, excursions may be made, not only on Coniston Water, but also to the Vales of Yewdale and Tilberthwaite, which afford fine views. These, however, can only be visited on horseback or on foot.</p>
<p>From Waterhead Inn, a complete tour of the lake may be made in a carriage, by the following route. Pass Coniston and Torver churches, and a little beyond <pb n="17"/> the latter, turn to the left, and proceed by Oxen Houses to Water Yeat, near which, cross the Crake at Bowdray Bridge, to Nibthwaite; or go from Water Yeat to Lowick Bridge, and thence to Nibthwaite, from which place to Waterhead the route by the east side of the lake has been already pointed out. By Bowdray Bridge, the tour will be about 14 miles, and by Lowick Bridge, nearly 17 miles.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">CONISTON WATER</head>
<p>Is sometimes called THURSTON WATER. It is six miles long, and three-quarters of a mile at its greatest breadth. Its greatest depth is 27 fathoms, and it abounds with trout and char: the latter are larger than those of the other lakes.</p>
<p>The shores are beautifully indented, and present, in succession, several small bays. Both banks are adorned with woods, interspersed with meadows and patches of rocky common. Near the foot or southern extremity are several finely wooded and rocky promontories of great beauty. Close to the Eastern shore are two islands, one of which, covered with firs, is called <i>Peel Island.</i></p>
<p>Mrs. Radcliffe thus accurately and elegantly describes Coniston Water. "This lake appeared to us one of the most charming we had seen. From the sublime mountains, which bend round its head, the heights on either side decline towards the south into waving hills, that form its shore, and often stretch, in long sweeping points, into the water, generally covered with tufted woods, but sometimes with the tender verdure <pb n="18"/> of pasturage. The tops of these woods were just embrowned with autumn, and contrasted well with other slopes, rough and healthy, that rose above, or fell beside them to the water's brink and added force to the colouring, which reddish tints of decaying fern, the purple bloom of heath, and the bright golden gleams of broom, spread over these banks. Their hues, the graceful undulations of the marginal hills and bays, the richness of the woods, the solemnity of the northern fells, and the deep repose that pervades the scene, where only now and then a white cottage or a farm lurks among the trees, are circumstances which render Coniston lake one of the most interesting, and perhaps the most beautiful, of any in the country."</p>
<p>The chief feeders of Coniston Water are Black Beck and Coniston Beck, both entering on its Western Side.</p>
<p>The principal mountains rise towards the head and on the Western side of the lake. The highest point is called the</p>
<head level="3" align="center">OLD MAN, OR MAN MOUNTAIN.</head>
<p>This is said to be 2580 feet above the level of the sea. Upon the summit, where there was formerly a beacon, are three heaps of stones, called the Old Man, his Wife, and Son. The top is covered with moss, and extends about half a mile in length and a quarter in breadth. Hence the prospect is very extensive, particularly towards the South. In this direction are seen Coniston Water, the shores of Lancashire, part of the coast of Cumberland, the Isles of Walney and <pb n="19"/> Man, and, on a fine day, Snowdon, with the mountains in its vicinity. To the North, appear Scawfell and Bowfell, and in the distance, the loftiest part of Skiddaw. From ths spot, also, may be seen a portion of Windermere, and two tarns, called Low Water and Levers Water.</p>
<p>The shortest mode of reaching the summit of the Old Man is to commence at the Black Bull, near Coniston Church. The road is very steep and angular. The copper-mines, near LEVERS WATER, and the slate-quarries, above LOW WATER, may then be seen in the ascent. Levers Water is about a mile in circumference, and is surrounded, except on the South side, by steep and craggy heights. Low Water is rather smaller.</p>
<p>Leaving Coniston Waterhead, the tourist ascends a steep hill, from which there are good views of Coniston Water, the valley, and the surrounding heights. The scene is rich in wood and water, and in diversity of mountain line it is rarely exceeded. The deep and solitary windings of Yewdale appear particularly interesting. The road divides about a mile from Waterhead, the left leading to Ambleside, and the right to Hawkshead. A good view of Esthwaite Water is obtained on descending the hill towards Hawkshead. The fells of Ambleside and Rydal are here in full view, with a portion of the head of Windermere.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">HAWKSHEAD</head>
<p>Is a small and ancient town, with about 797 inhabitants. It is situated at the foot of a mountain near the end of <pb n="20"/> the beautiful narrow vale in which lies Esthwaite Water. The Church is seated on the front of an eminence commanding a prospect of the lake and the whole valley. Many of the houses are old and of singular construction, and would form good subjects for the artist. The views in the vicinity are very fine.</p>
<p>Hawkshead has a good school, founded by Archbishop Sandys, who was born at this place. The Town House was erected chiefly by the subscriptions of gentlemen who had been educated here.</p>
<p><i>Inn.</i>-- The Red Lion, where a post-chaise is kept. One mile distant, on the direct road towards Ambleside, are the remains of HAWKSHEAD HALL, which the Abbot of Furness kept possession of by stationing monks, who performed duty in the vicinity. Over the entrance is the room where the bailiff of Hawkshead administered justice in the name of the abbot. It is now occupied by a farmer.</p>
<p>Two miles North-east from Hawkshead, on the right of the road to Ambleside, is BLELHAM TARN, a small lake, from which a stream passes into Windermere by Low Wray. It has some good hedge-row trees on its South-west side; there are no striking features near its margin, but the grand mountains of Rydal and Ambleside swell finely over it.</p>
<p>From Hawkshead the road proceeds along the side of</p>
<head level="3" align="center">ESTHWAITE or EASTWHWAITE WATER.</head>
<p>This placid lake is two miles in length and half a mile in breadth. It is surrounded by a good carriage-road, and over the outlet by which it discharges itself is a <pb n="21"/>narrow stone bridge. Two peninsulas, fringed with trees and coppice wood, and cultivated to their summits, contribute much to its beauty. The principal is that which projects from the Western shore. The mountains of Langdale, Grasmere, and Rydal, are seen to great advantage from the shores of this lake; and the town of Hawkshead, with its elevated church, is a pleasant feature.</p>
<p>BELMONT, about a mile North of Esthwaite Water, is a handsome mansion, commanding a fine view of the lake, having Gummers How for its remote distance. It was built about 1780, by the Rev. Reginald Braithwaite. ESTHWAITE LODGE, on the West side, and LAKE BANK, on the East, are also pleasing villas.</p>
<p>Near the upper end of the Esthwaite Water, or rather in an ajoining pool, is an island containing two perches of land, which is said to be floated about by the wind.</p>
<p>The fish found here are perch, pike, eels, and trout. There are no char, though this lake is connected with Windermere, in which that fish abounds.</p>
<p>The scenery between Hawkshead and Sawrey is good: the irregular figure of the lake, its pretty enclosures, woods, and buildings, with the Langdale Pikes in the distance, make many charming sylvan pictures.</p>
<p>The road then passes through the village of SAWREY, and ascending the hill which separates Esthwaite Water from Windermere, affords the tourist a fine view of the Coniston and Langdale mountains. The descent of this eminence commands a prospect of a considerable portion of Windermere.</p>
<pb n="22"/>
<p>The FERRY HOUSE is a good inn, delightfully situated on the shore near the centre of Windermere, and almost surrounded by a grove of aged sycamores. From this situation there are three distinct views. The first, looking down the lake by Berkshire Island and Storrs, to Rawlinson's Nab; the second, towards the North-east, looks over Belle Isle upon Hill Bell; and beyond the two points projecting from the island and from the parsonage lands, appears water; and between these points, a fir island: Rayrigg is seen over it, and in that reach of the lake beyond the points, the mansion in Belle Isle towers above the trees. The third view, looking Northward, is from the spot where one of the carriage ferry-boats is usually moored; the trees on the right rise from Crow-Holme, with a little peep of Belle Isle beyond it; opposite to which, Furness Fell swells boldly from the water, the banks of which are adorned with trees. One of the Lily of the Valley islands forms a pretty object, and far beyond it is seen a part of Wansfell, with the woods about Dove Nest. In the remote distance are the Rydal mountains and Scandale Fell.</p>
<p>Here post-horses, a car, and boats are kept. Carriages and horses can cross by the ferry-boat. The charges made for conveyance are, Passengers 2<i>d.</i> each; Post-chaise, 3<i>s.</i>; Gentleman's Chariot, 3<i>s.</i> 6<i>d.</i>; Carriage, 4<i>s.</i>, besides a gratuity to the ferryman. No charge, however, is made for the return of the vehicles on the same day.</p>
<pb n="23"/>
<head level="3" align="center">THE STATION HOUSE</head>
<p>Stands upon a hill above the Ferry House. It was erected by Mr. Braithwaite, from whom t was purchased by the late J.C. Curwen, Esq. It is surrounded by an enclosure, at the entrance of which is a cottage, occupied by the keeper, who will show the visiter to the building, by an excellent path. This path is bordered by oak, ash, and birch trees, springing from the sides and out of the fissures of picturesque rocks, to which have been added, hollies, laurels, and other evergreens, as well as an abundance of flowers.</p>
<p>On this ascent the eye is not allowed to roam beyond the enclosing wall, for this is a local sort of beauty, and cannot come in competition with any of its neighbouring scenes, or with the distant mountains.</p>
<p>The Station House consists of two stories; the lower occupied by dining and other rooms, and the upper by a drawing room, from which there are splendid views, embracing nearly the whole extent of the lake, from Newby Bridge almost up to Ambleside. The windows contain stained glass of various colours, through which the scenery has a pleasing effect. This is one of the most delightful spots near Windermere, but to be enjoyed in perfection, it should be visited in the afternoon or evening, when the sun shines.</p>
<p>In front, Berkshire, formerly called Rampsholme Island, clothed with wood, presents its entire length. To the left, the Ferry Point, closing with the wooded isle of Crow-holme, forms a fine promontory, behind which is a semicircular bay, bordered by sloping hills, <pb n="24"/> covered with verdure. An extent of water, 12 miles in circumference, spreads towards the North, intersected by promontories or studded with islands. The Eastern view presents all that is beautiful, grand, and sublime. In front are seen the tops of the houses and the church of Bowness, above which rise Banerigg and Orrest Head. Troutbeck Park comes next to view, and above that are seen Hill Bell, Fairfield, and Rydal. Towards the south, and from the western shore, a promontory, called Rawlinson's Nab, juts out into the lake; and opposite to it is the Storrs, another wooded promontory. Over the former, the lake spreads out into a magnificent sheet of water, and following the winding shore, to the south, seems lost behind a jutting rock on the east side. Above Park and Landen Nab, the summits of other distant mountains close the scene.</p>
<p>Returning from the Station, the tourist should visit HARROW FARM HOUSE, from which there is also a delightful view of the lake. It is situated on the side of the lake opposite Belle Isle.</p>
<p>Leaving the Ferry House, the tourist may either hire a boat to visit Belle Isle and Rawlinson's Nab, and afterwards proceed to Bowness; or he may go by the ferry-boat direct to Bowness, and there hire a boat to survey the lake. The prices charged for the passage at the ferry have already been mentioned.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">WINDERMERE, or WINANDERMERE,</head>
<p>Is the largest of the English lakes. Measured down the middle, from north to south, it is 10 &#189; miles in <pb n="25"/> length, but by the road, along its east bank, it is 2 or 3 miles more. Its breadth varies considerably, and at the broadest part is nearly 2 miles. The depth also varies from 5 to 37 fathoms. The circumference of the lake is about 26 miles, and the area comprises between 4000 and 5000 acres.</p>
<p>Windermere is usually said to belong the Westmoreland, although the whole of the western, and a considerable portion of the eastern shore, are in Lancashire.</p>
<p>The principal feeders of the lake are the Rothay and the Brathay.</p>
<p>The Rothay rises in the mountains near Wythburn; on the descent from which it is joined by several mountain-torrents; the principal is that from Easedale Tarn: it then passes through the lakes of Grasmere and Rydal, and in its mazy course through the continuous vales of Rydal and Ambleside, receives tributary streams of Rydal, Scandale Beck, and Stock Gill. At a place called the Landing, its waters join the Brathay, and in little more than half a mile, the united streams enter Windermere at its head.</p>
<p>The Brathay has two sources: one rises in that part of Great Langdale called Langdale-head, from which it runs in a course of about seven miles to Elter Water; the other rises at the three county stones on Wrynose, whence it descends to Fellfoot; and, after having passes through Little Langdale Tarn, unites with the branch from Great Langdale in Elter Water. The stream then passes Skelwith Bridge and Brathay Bridge, beyond which it joins the Rothay, about half a mile from its entrance into Windermere. From the <pb n="26"/>County Stones on Wrynose, it forms the boundary between Lancashire and Westmoreland.</p>
<p>The Troutbeck also contributes to the supply of Windermere, and enters it on the eastern shore near Calgarth Park.</p>
<p>The lake discharges its superfluous waters at Newby Bridge, at the southern extremity. There they assume the name of the river Leven; and, after a course of a few miles, fall into Morecambe Bay.</p>
<p>Windermere is plentifully stocked with trout, perch, pike, eels, and char; and its banks are much frequented by various kinds of wild-fowl, such as swans, geese, ducks, teal, widgeons, gravigers, didappers, &#38;c. The char are much esteemed; they are caught during the winter months, potted, and sent to London and other places. The char is a fish about twice the size of a herring. Its back is of an olive-green; its belly of a bright vermillion, softened in some parts into white, and changing into a deep red at the insertion of the fins.</p>
<p>The shores of Windermere are beautifully diversified by sloping hills, hanging woods, cultivated grounds, and numerous charming villas, which add much interest to the natural beauties of the scene. Diffusiveness, stately beauty, and -- towards the northern end -- magnificence, have been justly pronounced the characteristics of this lake. It experiences scarecely any alteration in appearance from the prevalence either of wet or dry weather, and always maintains nearly the same level. It is, however, often agitated violently and suddenly by the wind; and is, on this account, dangerous for sailing vessels. Almost every resident, <pb n="27"/>however, in the vicinity has a boat, and some persons keep two or more. During summer, when they are seen tacking from side to side, the lake has a gay and animated appearance, particularly when enlightened by the sun, and set off by the deep-toned backgrounds of shadowed mountains.</p>
<p>The clearness of the water is remarkable. As Mr. Gilpin justly expresses it, 'the eye cn see distinctly, in smooth water, through a medium of at least a dozen yards; and view the inhabitants of its deep recesses, as they play in shoals, and --</p>
<poem>
<line>-- sporting, with quick glance,</line>
<line>Show to the sun their waved coats, dropped with gold.'</line>
</poem>
<p>Windermere is adorned with fourteen islands, called <i>holmes;</i> but their effect is much diminished by being group in a narrow part of the lake. The principal is</p>
<head level="3" align="center">BELLE ISLE, or CURWEN'S ISLAND.</head>
<p>This beautiful island derives its second title from the late J. C. Curwen, Esq., to whom it is indebted for many of its decorations. It is also sometimes called WINDERMERE ISLAND, and sometimes the GREAT ISLAND, being the largest on the lake. It contains about thirty-six acres, and is surrounded by a gravel walk nearly 2 miles in circumference, on which strangers are allowed to walk. Its form is oblong; its shores irregular, retiring into bays, and broken into creeks. The surface, too, is uneven; and a small ridge runs through the middle, falling down in all shapes into the water. The mansion is a handsome <pb n="28"/>building, begun by Mr. English, a former proprietor of the island, and completed by Mr. Curwen. It commands a view of the whole lake, and is surrounded by noble trees and shrubberies. At the landing-place is a neat boat-house. Nothing can exceed the variety of scenery presented to the eye in a walk round this delightful island, and no tourist who is in search of the picturesque should omit to visit it. Mr. Housman thus describes the views obtained from the North and South sides of the island. "The Northern shores afford a mixed prospect of the beautiful and sublime; a number of scattered islands interrupt the line of uniformity, which would otherwise bound a reach of the lake four miles and a half in length, and in some parts above one in breadth. These islands, in shape and clothing, display a pleasing variety in the foreground of the picture. The side screens are different; that on the left consists of a rocky ridge, descending to the water, partly covered with verdure, on which flocks of mountain sheep are seen feeding, and partly clothed with thick woods, or scattered with straggling trees and evergreen shrubs, over which the heights of Furness Fells are peeping into the lake. On the right, neat villages and farms, half buried in wood, form a delightful mixture of woodland and cultivated fields, stretching, in a gradual ascent, from the water's edge to the tops of some of the hills. In front, we have a large collection of high mountains, with pointed summits, rearing up in different attitudes, and one overlooking the top of another, as if anxious to gaze on the beauties of the lake. Turning to the south, we observe the lake extending many miles in that direction, <pb n="29"/> with variety of shore, and patched with islands. In every point of view, mountains, at different distances, raise their bulky crests, and form a noble ampitheatre round the lake.</p>
<p>"From the Southern side, also, a good prospect opens before us, particularly to the foot of the lake. The two ferry points creeping towards each other, with the island of Crow-holme on the right, form a picturesque strait, through which Berkshire Island, towards the centre of the lake, is seen raising its head above the water. Beyond this, Rawlinson's Nab on the West, and Storr's Point on the East, are two bold promontories, which push abruptly into the lake. The line of shore on each side is much indented, and sweetly fringed with trees; while the waving hills, which guard the lake, are clothed either with a combination of verdant fields and sweeping woods, or a mixture of grey rock twisting through a grassy turf, and scattered evergreen trees and shrubs."</p>
<p>The other principal islands of Windermere are <i>Rough-holme,</i> of a circular form, covered with trees; <i>Lady-holme,</i> on which formerly stood an oratory; <i>Hen-holme,</i> a rock clothed with shrubs; <i>Grass-holme,</i> shaded with a grove of oaks; <i>Crow-holme,</i> and <i>Berkshire Island,</i> or <i>Ramps-holme.</i></p>
<p>On leaving Belle Isle, the tourist should go down the lake to RAWLINSON'S NAB, by which mode he will obtain the best views of the scenery. Rawlinson's Nab is a lofty peninsular rock, of circular form, projecting into the lake from the Western shore. From this spot the lake is seen spreading in different directions, in two fine sheets of water. Towards the south, <pb n="30"/> the view is bounded by bold and well-wooded hills, interspersed with rocks and patches of inclosed ground. The view northwards is broken by small islands and promontories, amongst which Storr's Point appears conspicuous; and beyond it, Bannerigg and Orrest Head are seen to great advantage.</p>
<p>From the CAT-RAG, a little to the south of Rawlinson's Nab, a good view of the south end of the lake is obtained.</p>
<p>STORR'S HALL stands upon a promontory on the east side of the lake, about 2 miles south from Bowness. It was erected by Sir John Legard, but has been rebuilt by John Bolton, Esq., from designs by Mr. Gandy.</p>
<p>The best situation on the water for viewing the scenery round the head of Windermere, is about half a mile from the entrance from the entrance of the Brathay into the lake. Here the high lands at Rydal, Ambleside, Troutbeck, and Applethwaite, with Hill Bell and the neighbouring summits, are seen to the greatest advantage.</p>
<p>The slate trade of Langdale is aided by the lake of Windermere. The slate is brought in carts from the quarries to the landing at the mouth of the Brathay, and thence conveyed in boats to Newby Bridge, where it is again put into carts, and sent by the side of the Leven to the sea, below the Low Wood powder-mills.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">BOWNESS</head>
<p>Is a village delightfully situated at the bottom of a small bay on the eastern shore of Windermere. It is well described by Mr. Gilpin as "the capital port-town of the lakes, if we may adopt a dignified style which <pb n="31"/> the grandeur of the scene suggests. It is the great mart for fish and charcoal, both which commodities are largely imported here, and carried by land into the country. Its harbour is crowded with vessels of various kinds, some of which are used merely as pleasure-boats in navigating the lake."</p>
<p>Bowness has two good Inns, the White Lion and the Crown; the latter is smaller, but better situated than the other. Visiters may also readily obtain lodgings in private houses.</p>
<p>Boats for Windermere may be hired at the Inns. The charge for a boat to visit the Island and the Station House, and return to Bowness, is 2<i>s.</i>; to go to the head or to the foot of the lake and return, 5<i>s.</i>; of if the boat is hired by time, 1<i>s.</i> per hour. The boatman will also expect something for himself, as he depends entirely on such donations, the boats belonging to the proprietors of the Inns.</p>
<p>The Church is a neat, but small edifice, containing several sepulchral memorials of families resident in the vicinity. There are also remains of a painting window which formerly belonged to Furness Abbey, and is supposed to have been executed in the reign of Edward III. The most perfect part resembles the Crucifixion. Near the altar is a marble monument by Flaxman, erected in memory of Dr. Richard Watson, Bishop of Llandaff, who formerly resided at Calgarth Park, in the vicinity. He was buried in the church-yard, where there is a tomb with a simple Latin inscription. The Church also contains a singular epitaph on one Philipson, written by himself.</p>
<p>The rectory-house is pleasantly situated, fronting <pb n="32"/> the lake, along the shore of which the glebe-land extends for about half a mile.</p>
<p>Near Bowness are eminences of various degrees of elevation, affording excellent views of Windermere. On a hill above the village, is the station pointed out by Mr. Young for taking a general view of the whole lake. This station should be visited in the morning. It has been thus well described by Mr. Young; though, it must be acknowledged, in rather glowing terms:--</p>
<p>"Having viewed the most pleasing objects from these points, let me next conduct you to a spot where, at once glance, you command them all in fresh situations, and all assuming a new appearance. For this purpose, you return to the village, and taking the by-road to the turnpike, mount the hill without turning your head (if I was your guide, I would conduct you behind a small hill, that you might come at once upon the view), till you almost gain the top, when you will be struck with astonishment at the prospect spread at your feet; which, if not the most superlative view which Nature can exhibit, she is more fertile in beauties than the reach of my imagination will allow me to conceive. It would be mere vanity to attempt to describe a scene which beggars all description; but that you may have some faint idea of the outlines of this wonderful picture, I will just give the particulars of which it consists:--</p>
<p>"The point on which you stand is the side of a large ridge of hills that form the eastern boundary of the lake, and the situation high enough to look <i>down</i> upon all the objects; a circumstance of great importance, <pb n="33"/> which painting cannot imitate. In landscapes, you are either on a level with the objects, or look up to them; the painter cannot give the declivity at your feet, which lessens the object as much in the perpendicular line as in the horizontal one. You look down upon a noble winding valley, of about 12 miles long, every where inclosed with grounds, which rise in a very bold and various manner; in some places bulging into mountains, abrupt, wild, and cultivated; in others, breaking into rocks, craggy, pointed, and irregular; here rising into hills covered with the noblest woods, presenting a gloomy brownness of shade, almost from the clouds to the reflection of the trees in the limpid water of the lake they so beautifully skirt; there waving in glorious shapes of cultivated enclosures, adorned in the sweetest manner with every object that can give variety to art, or elegance to nature; trees, woods, villages, houses, farms, scattered with picturesque confusion, and waving to the eye in the most romantic landscapes that nature can exhibit.</p>
<p>"This valley, so beautifully enclosed, is floated by the lake, which spreads forth to the right and left in one vast but irregular expanse of transparent water; a more noble object can hardly be imagined. Its immediate shore is traced in every variety of line that fancy can imagine; sometimes contracting the lake into the appearance of a noble winding river -- at others, retiring from it, and opening into large bays, as if for navies to anchor in; promontories, spread with woods, or scattered with trees and enclosures, projecting into the water in the most picturesque style imaginable; rocky points breaking the shore, and <pb n="34"/> rearing their bold heads above the water; in a word, a variety that amazes the beholder. But what finishes the scene, with an elegance too delicious to be imagined, is, this beautiful sheet of water being dotted with no less than ten islands, distinctly comprehended by the eye; all of the most bewitching beauty. The large one presents a waving various line, which rises from the water in the most picturesque inequalities of surface; high land in one place, low in another, -- clumps of trees in this spot, scattered ones in that, adorned by a farm-house on the water's edge, and backed with a little wood, vying in elegance with Borromean palaces; some of the smaller islets rising from the lake like little hills of wood; some only scattered with trees, and others of grass of the finest verdure; a more beautiful variety is nowhere to be seen."</p>
<p>About a mile north of Bowness, is the little village of RAYRIGG, at which is a small verdant hill, commanding a fine prospect of the northern portion of Windermere. To the left, are seen Bowness and Belle Isle; and in front, over the hills which slope towards the lake, appears the Old Man. Further to the right is the valley of Langdale, extending many miles back to the mountains called Langdale Pikes. At the head of the lake are the woods and mansion of Brathay, and above them rises Loughrigg Fell. Immediately to the right of the spectator are seen Troutbeck Valley, and Calgarth Park at its mouth.</p>
<p>On the margin of the lake, between the village and Bowness, is RAYRIGG HALL, standing on a gentle eminence.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="From BOWNESS to AMBLESIDE.">
<pb n="35"/>
<head level="3" align="center">V. BOWNESS to AMBLESIDE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Bowness to Troutbeck Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">2 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Troutbeck Bridge to Low Wood Inn</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Low Wood Inn to Ambleside</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>Quitting Bowness, the tourist proceeds towards TROUTBECK BRIDGE by a picturesque road, the higher parts of which command fine views of the mountains round the head of Windermere. Amongst those which come successively in view are, the Old Man, Wrynose, Scawfell Pikes in the distance, Bow Fell, Great Gavel in the distance, Langdale Pikes, Loughrigg Fell, and Fairfield. The grounds at Brathay and Clappersgate enrich the borders of the lake with a tasteful variety of buildings and trees.</p>
<p>At the mouth of the valley of Troutbeck, which abounds with the picturesque, is CALGARTH PARK, which was the seat of Dr. Richard Watson, the learned Bishop of Llandaff. This elegant mansion was built by the Bishop in 1789; and here he expired in 1816, in his 79th year.</p>
<p>LOW WOOD INN is a handsome hotel, occupying an enchanting situation upon the margin of a small bay of Windermere. It commands a most beautiful prospect, embracing the whole of the upper part of the lake, and extending southward as far as Belle Isle. Boats may be obtained here for excursions on the water; and a cannon is kept for the purpose of gratifying visiters with those extraordinary reverberations which follow its discharge in these romantic districts.</p>
<pb n="36"/>
<p>The high ground above Low Wood Inn commands views of peculiar beauty. These may be enjoyed by making the following excursions. The first must be made on foot. The second and third may be made either in a carriage or a cart.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">1. --TO SKELGILL.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Low Wood to Low Fold</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Low Fold to Skelgill</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Skelgill to Low Skelgill</td>
<td width="20%">&#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Low Skelgill to Troutbeck Road</td>
<td width="20%">&#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Troutbeck Road to Low Wood</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">4 &#189;</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>A little to the North of Low Skelgill a fine view is presented of the islands on Windermere, with Bowness and the neighbouring seats on the left, and on the right, the Ferry and Station Houses. The foot of Furness Fell, on the same side, beautifully embays the lake. The house in Curwen's Island forms a good object, rising above the neighbouring trees. This island and the Ferry House point appear as one promontory, the intervening water not being visible; but the Bowness Ferry point is distinctly seem, together with the seat of Storrs and the summer house at the end of a strip of land jutting into the lake. Gummer's How closes the scene.</p>
<pb n="37"/>
<head level="3" align="center">2. --TO TROUTBECK.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Low Wood to Troutbeck Guide-post</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Troutbeck Guide-post to Troutbeck Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Troutbeck Bridge to Low Wood</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>The view from the top of the hill, about half-way between Low Wood and the Guide-post, is one of the most enchanting amongst the lakes. It embraces all the islands of Windermere, which are seen here to the best advantage, the most desirable spaces being left between each island and the shores of the lake, which spread out into beautiful bays. The two ferry points are not so distinctly seen from any other place.</p>
<p>The village of Troutbeck commences rather more than half a mile from this point of view, --at an ancient farm-house. Here a guide-post directs to Kendal over Troutbeck Bridge. The view between the Bridge and Low Wood is frequently interrupted by woods.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">3. TO KIRKSTONE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Low Wood to Ambleside</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ambleside to Kirkstone Guide-post</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Kirkstone Guide-post to Troutbeck</td>
<td width="20%">4 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Troutbeck to Low Wood</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">11 &#190;</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>These excursions may, of course, be made with equal facility from Ambleside.</p>
<p>Beyond Low Wood the road passes by <i>Water Head,</i> <pb n="38"/> which is so called from its situation at the head of Windermere.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">AMBLESIDE</head>
<p>Is a small market town, with about 1095 inhabitants, picturesquely situated on the steep declivity of a hill in the valley of the Rothay, which extends from the head of Windermere towards the north. It is about 1 mile from the lake, and the valley is 3 miles in length. The town is irregularly built, and very much resembles a large village. It is defended on the north side by a semicircular range of fells, of which Rydal Head is the most remarkable. From these fells there are delightful views of Windermere. The rivulet called Stock Gill passes through the town, and here forms the line of separation between the parishes of Bowness and Grasmere.</p>
<p>Ambleside is a place of great antiquity. Roman coins and ancient arms have frequently been found in its vicinity; and in a field near the head of Windermere are slight traces of the Roman station which is said to have been the <i>Dictis,</i> where a part of the cohort <i>Nerviorum Dictentium</i> was stationed. This fortress has been described by Camden. It was situated at the junction of the roads from Penrith, Keswick, Ravenglass, Furness, and Kendal, all of which it commanded, and was accessible only on one side.</p>
<p>The Chapel of Ambleside is a neat Gothic structure, erected, in 1812, on the side of the original building: it forms a pretty summit to the village when viewed from many parts of the valley. There is also a good Grammar School, founded by John Keswick in 1723, <pb n="39"/> and an Exhibition of Views of the Lakes, which was established by the late Mr. Green, and is continued by his family. Here the tourist may obtain a collection of views at a moderate expense.</p>
<p>During the summer, this town is very much frequented; its centrical situation and romantic scenery inducing many tourists to make it their head-quarters. Lodgings may be obtained here. The Salutation is the principal inn. The Commercial is a tolerable inn, and there is another called the White Lion.</p>
<p>Here boats may be hired for viewing the beauties of Windermere. The landing-place is about three-quarters of a mile distant.</p>
<p>A stage coach from Kendal to Whitehaven passes through Ambleside every morning, and another in its way from Whitehaven to Kendal passes every evening, except on Sunday.</p>
<p>About three-quarters of a mile from Ambleside, at a place called the <i>Groves,</i> is</p>
<head level="3" align="center">STOCKGILL FORCE.</head>
<p>This is one of the most beautiful cascades amongst the lakes. Like other water-falls, it is seen to most advantage after wet weather; but, even if the season be dry, it merits a visit for its singular beauty. The torrent which forms the fall rises in the mountains behind Ambleside, and flows, in a narrow channel, through an opening in the rock, which is partially concealed by overhanging foliage. At the summit of the fall, which is altogether about 150 feet, the torrent is divided into two streams by a huge crag, covered with moss, trees, and shrubs. After falling about half the <pb n="40"/> depth, they dash against a rock, from which they rebound in foam and spray, and unite at the bottom in a dark gulph. Thence the water rushes down a steep and craggy channel, through a narrow <i>gill</i> or valley, and joins the Rothay below Ambleside.</p>
<p>The space between the Force and the Woolen Mill will delight the artist, as at every step in this distance, the river exhibits either excellent compositions or rich detached pieces for the embellishment of landscape. The transparent stream runs over a bed of the finest formed rocks and stones, which by their inequalities produce, in every variety, the prettiest water-falls; sometimes, confined to a narrow-channel, the water, impatient of resistance, dashes impetuously down the steep crag to a momentary rest; but oftener spanning the little channel, in gentle motion, slips over the smooth rocks, softening into beauty their original tints. The margin of this gill is sometimes low, sometimes swelling, but oftener in steep and grassy banks, or bold projecting rocks; the native woods, in wild intricacy, impend from the rocks, which are additionally clothed with fern, moss, and other vegetation. Wansfell Pike is occasionally seen through the vista on looking up the river, and the Langdale Pikes on looking down it. Near the Woolen Mill is an old summer-house once belonging to Ambleside Hall, the ancient family seat of the Braithwaites, which stood in Ambleside at the junction of the Keswick and Penrith roads. It stands upon a bridge crossing the river, and forms a very picturesque object. A corn mill adjoins the bridge, and between it and the summer-house is a bark mill. This part of the river is called Rattle Gill, <pb n="41"/> probably on account of the turbulence of its waters in wet weather.</p>
<p>SCANDALE BECK, which crosses the Keswick road, at Scandale Bridge, about half a mile from Ambleside, is a rivulet which rises between Scandale Fell and High Pike, and forms numerous pretty water-falls in its course to the Rothay. Few of the falls are high, but the best are between Scandale Bridge and Nook End Bridge. This little river, though pretty, is far inferior to Stock Gill in the character of its scenery.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">LANGDALE.</head>
<p>The vales of Great and Little Langdale may be visited more advantageously from Ambleside than from any other place. They both abound with picturesque scenery, which many persons consider equal, if not superior, to any in the North of England. Both vallies are best viewed by looking at their heads respectively, and those who have leisure and taste for such rambles may proceed so as to see them in both directions. When, however, only one day can be spared for a sight of the Langdales, the approach should be made by Little Langdale, and the return by Great Langdale. The excursion is usually arranged in the following manner: --</p>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ambleside to Skelwith Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Skelwith Bridge to Colwith Force</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Colwith Force to Blea Tarn</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Blea Tarn to Dungeon Gill</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Dungeon Gill to Langdale Chapel Stile</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Return by High Close and Rydal to Ambleside</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">18</td>
</tr>
</table>
<pb n="42"/>
<p>The best mode of performing it is on horseback, many parts of it not admitting the use of carriage. It is, however, by no means unusual to perform the whole excursion in a cart, and in this way it will occupy 8 or 9 hours.</p>
<p>Most of the beauties of this tour are faced by beginning with Little Langdale, and the principal part of the beauties not faced are those in Great Langdale, which are viewed from the road between Mill Beck and the slate quarry at Thrang Crag, and this is only about two miles out of the whole eighteen. Another reason for going first to Little Langdale, is, that the scenery of Great Langdale is best seen in the afternoon and evening.</p>
<p>On leaving Ambleside, the tourist crosses the Rothay over a stone bridge of one arch, and passes by CROFT LODGE, situated at the southern extremity of Loughrigg Fell, and surrounded by trees. In front is seen the junction of the rivers Rothay and Brathay. Thence he proceeds through the hamlet of CLAPPERGATE, whence slate, charcoal, and other articles are sent down the lake of Windermere. Here there are several charming villas. A little beyond Clappergate appears the river Brathay dashing over a stony bed, having on each side, swelling grounds interspersed with trees: on the left are seen the Tilberthwaite mountains, and on the right, those of Langdale. Brathay Bridge, which consists of two arches over the river of that name, forms a very picturesque object. It is about a mile from Ambleside.</p>
<p>Hence he may proceed, with the river on the left, to Skelwith Bridge; or, crossing Brathay Bridge, take <pb n="43"/>the river on the right by Skelwith Fold; the latter road commands a more extensive view of Great Langdale.</p>
<p>Pursuing the former, the tourist leaves Brathay Bridge to the left, and approaching SKELWITH FORCE, enjoys a very fine view towards the west. He then stops just in site of the bridge, and walks up to SKELWITH FORCE, about a quarter of a mile distant. Here the river tumbles down between two crags, and immediately afterwards spreads into a wide stream scattered with rocky fragments. From a spot a few yards beyond the fall, a fine view is obtained of Elter Water and the Langdale Pikes.</p>
<p>ELTER WATER is a small lake of irregular form, abounding with fish, and surrounded by patches of wood. The house at its head is called ELTER WATER HALL.</p>
<p>The tourist then returns to Skelwith Bridge, beyond which a steep ascent leads through a close lane to a terrace of considerable elevation, from which there is a grand view of Elter water and of Great and Little Langdale, separated by Lingmire mountain. A steep winding path then descends to COLWITH BRIDGE, and so precipitously, that it will be advisable to walk. The bridge is a single arch over the rivulet of that name, which rises in the neighbouring fells. Just above it is the cataract called COLWITH FORCE, beyond which is seen Wedderlamb Mountain. Here the torrent forms a succession of falls, altogether about 140 feet in depth. The view is particularly fine from the bed of the river, and from the side of the rocky walls which border it.</p>
<pb n="44"/>
<p>About 1 &#189; mile beyond Colwith Bridge is LITTLE LANGDALE TARN, backed by some beautifully-formed mountains; the principal of which are the Great and Little Carrs. The space between the eye and the lake is in Westmoreland, and the remainder in Lancashire.</p>
<p>We then arrive at Blea Tarn, a placid little lake, lying between the heads of Great and Little Langdale, and surrounded by a grand assemblage of mountains. The highest pike, called Harrison's Stickle, is about 3 miles from the eye, and Stickle Pike, with its round head, receding towards the pass in Borrowdale, more than four. The bases of the mountains cannot here be seen, being cut off by a projecting portion of Blakerigg on the left, and Lingmire on the right. Near the lake is a solitary farm-house. This is the scene described by Mr. Wordsworth, in his poem of the 'Excursion:'</p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line>'Beneath our feet, a little lowly Vale,</line>
<line>A lowly Vale, and yet uplifted high</line>
<line>Among the mountains; even as if the spot</line>
<line>Had been, from eldest time, by which of theirs</line>
<line>So placed, --to be shut out from all the world!</line>
<line>Uru-like it was in shape, deep as an Urn;</line>
<line>With rocks encompass'd, save that to the South</line>
<line>Was one small opening, where a heath-clad ridge</line>
<line>Supplied a boundary less abrupt and close;</line>
<line>A quiet tree-less nook, with two green fields,</line>
<line>A liquid pool that glitter'd in the sun,</line>
<line>And one bare Dwelling; one Abode, no more!</line>
<line>It seem'd the home of poverty and toil,</line>
<line>Though no of want: the little fields, made green</line>
<line>By husbandry of many thrifty years,</line>
<line>Paid cheerful tribute to the moorland House.</line>
<line>-- There crows the Cock, single in his domain:</line>
<pb n="45"/>
<line>The small birds find in spring no thicket there</line>
<line>To shroud them; only from the neighbouring Vales</line>
<line>The Cuckoo, straggling up to the hill tops,</line>
<line>Shouteth faint tidings of some gladder place.'</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>Returning to the road and passing by the farmhouse, to a little beyond the foot of the lake, a fine view is obtained. In the back-ground are seen the mountains which have fronted the view coming from Ambleside, but they here assume a different form. The principal is Wedderlamb, and Blakerigg is now seen on the right. On a part of Blakerigg, at the foot of the gill issuing from the tarn, is a steep rock called Blakerigg Scar, near which is a fine echo.</p>
<p>From Blea Tarn, the tourist has Bow Fell in prospect, till he arrives at a spot where he looks down a hill to the head of GREAT LANGDALE, and obtains a fine view of a circular valley of rich enclosures, scattered with trees, and apparently shut in by high mountains, amongst which, Bow Fell and the Langdale Pikes appear the most conspicuous.</p>
<p>Thence he descends steeply to WALL END, the highest house on the west side of the valley, and proceeds into the valley of MILL BECK, the name given to a few farm-houses about 300 hundred yards from the road. If the tourist wishes to ascend to the top of HARRISON'S STICKLE, or to STICKLE TARN, he should commence at Mill Beck, taking a guide with him. The tarn is a small circular piece of water, noted for the excellence of its trout. Three-fourths of its margin are bordered by soft turf; from the other fourth, rises a fine range of rocks called Pavey Ark. The best point to view them is from the outlet of the <pb n="46"/> tarn, a small stream which rolls over many a rock in its descent to Mill Beck. There is a peat road from Mill Beck to the tarn, which the tourist will find the best mode of ascent, unless he wish to visit Dungeon Gill in his way.</p>
<p>DUNGEON GILL, which is also visited from Mill Beck, on account of its romantic water-fall, is a stream issuing between the two Pikes, to the north of that just mentioned, as proceeding from the tarn, and falling among rocks of a peculiarly flinty appearance. Here Mr. Wordsworth has laid the scene of his pleasing pastoral poem, entitled, 'The Idle Shepherd Boys.'</p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line>'It was a spot which you may see</line>
<line>If ever you to Langdale go;</line>
<line>Into a chasm a mighty block</line>
<line>Hath fallen, and made a bridge of rock:</line>
<line>The gulf is deep below;</line>
<line>And in a basin black and small</line>
<line>Receives a lofty water-fall.'</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>Continuing down Great Langdale, the tourist will recollect that, between Mill Beck and the slate quarry at Thrang Crag, it will be well to take a retrospective glance at the mountains. Lingmire may be observed intersecting the base of the Pikes, and Bow Fell is seen in the distance through an opening. A little beyond the slate quarry is LANGDALE CHAPEL, and near it a public-house. Here, taking the road to the left, he will obtain a second view of Elter Water; and, at a little distance in the valley to the right, perceive a gunpowder manufactory. He may then cross the hill by <i>High Close Farm,</i> from which there is a very fine view, embracing three lakes, Elter Water, Loughrigg <pb n="47"/> Tarn, and Windermere; and, leaving Grasmere and Rydal Lakes to the left, enter the high road a short distance from Ambleside.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<p>This excursion may be abridged by going only to Skelwith Force, crossing Great Langdale, and passing into Grasmere; or it ay be lengthened by ascending Bow Fell, from Wall End Farm, in Great Langdale, or passing the Stake into Borrowdale.</p>
<p>Another variation may be made by pursuing the first course pointed out, and turning to the left beyond High Close Farm, adding to the excursion a tour round Grasmere and Rydal Lakes. This will lengthen the tour about 2 miles, but add very much to its interest, as the lake and vale of Grasmere present a complete contrast to the views already obtained in this day's excursion.</p>
<p>Various other excursions may be made from Ambleside, if the tourist have time and inclination.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">1. TO GRASMERE, UNDER LOUGHRIGG FELL.</head>
<p>Leaving Ambleside, pass Rothay Bridge -- Miller Bridge Cottage -- enter Fox How Wood -- Fox Gill, at the foot of a wooded rock, beyond which is seen Loughrigg Fell, with Holm Scar hanging on its side -- Peter Bridge -- Coat How farm-house -- Dearbought Hill, commanding a fine view of Grasmere -- Tail End, from which also there is a beautiful view of Grasmere -- the Wyke -- Gell's Cottage, a very tasteful villa of recent erection, embosomed in trees -- Grasmere Church <pb n="48"/> -- and thence, by Rydal Water, to Ambleside, --altogether about 10 miles.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">2. TO LOUGHRIGG TARN OVER LOUGHRIGG FELL.</head>
<p>From Rothay Bridge, proceed nearly as far as the woods at Fox How, to a gate from which the path ascends, passing a barn, and enters a wood. At the end of the wood the path crosses a gate and leads over a common to Loughrigg Tarn, a small sheet of water encompassed by meadow-ground and woods, backed by Lingmire, the Langdale Pikes, and Bow Fell. The road skirts the border of this little lake, and passes by two houses called the How. It then joins the road from Langdale, and proceeds by Pelter Bridge, keeping the lakes of Grasmere and Rydal on the left, to Ambleside, -- a walking excursion of 7 or 8 miles.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">3. TO LOUGHRIGG TARN AND GRASMERE.</head>
<p>From Ambleside, proceed through Clappergate -- at the Guide-post, 2 miles from Ambleside, turn to the right by the Ellers and Tarn Foot -- Loughrigg Fold -- Loughrigg Tarn -- the Oaks -- Grasmere Church -- Ambleside, -- an excursion of 10 miles, which may be made in a carriage.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">4. TO IVY CRAG.</head>
<p>Ivy Crag is an elevated rock, nearly half a mile south-east of Loughrigg Tarn, and about 3 miles from Ambleside. It commands a very fine view. The <pb n="49"/> tourist may go to it through Clappergate, and return by Coat How and Pelter Bridge, --altogether a walk of about 6 miles.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">5. TO ROUND KNOTT.</head>
<p>Round Knott, or Pincushion Hill, as it is sometimes called, is a small knoll at the top of the hill above Fox Gill. The summit commands a good panoramic view. It is about 2 miles from Ambleside.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">6. TO WANSFELL PIKE.</head>
<p>Proceed by Low Fold -- under Strawberry Bank -- Skelgill -- Wansfell Pike, from which there is a fine view -- return by Waterfall Lane to Ambleside, -- not quite 5 miles. This walk presents a great variety of interesting scenery.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">7. TO FAIRFIELD.</head>
<p>Proceed to Rydal -- turn to the right between Rydal Hall and Rydal Mount -- to Nab Scar, whence there is an extensive prospect, embracing no less than eight lakes, namely, Windermere, Blelham Tarn, Esthwaite Water, Rydal Water, Coniston Water, Elter Water, Grasmere Lake, and Easedale Tarn -- Fairfield -- over High and Low Pikes, to Nook End Bridge -- Amblesidee, -- a walk of 10 miles.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">8. TO YEWDALE AND TILBERTHWAITE.</head>
<p>This excursion must be made on foot or in a cart. Proceed along the Little Langdale road as far as Skelwith Bridge, and then turn to the left at the top of the hill between Skelwith and Colwih Bridges -- Pass some <pb n="50"/> houses, called Oxen Fell, near which a good view is obtained of the mountains of Little Langdale and Bow Fell -- Hodge Close, with a large slate quarry -- Fine view of the Langdale mountains near Holm Ground -- Thence descend to Shepherd's Bridge in Yewdale, which is about 7 miles from Ambleside, and is so called from a large yew tree. --Return by the slate quarry at Penny Rigg -- Tilberthwaite -- Little Langdale -- Colwith Bridge -- Skelwith Bridge, -- to Ambleside, altogether about 15 miles.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="VI. FROM AMBLESIDE TO KESWICK">
<pb n="51"/>
<head level="3" align="center">VI. FROM AMBLESIDE TO KESWICK, by RYDAL WATER, GRASMERE, and THIRLMERE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ambleside to Rydal</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Rydal to Grasmere</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Grasmere to Dunmel Raise</td>
<td width="20%">2 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Dunmel Raise to Wythburn</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Smalthwaite Bridge to Castle Rigg</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Castle Rigg to Keswick</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">16</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>The road from Ambleside to Keswick presents a charming variety of hill, dale, and water; and if much rain has fallen, the tourist will be gratified with the site of innumerable cascades falling down the mountains on each side of his route.</p>
<p>Should he wish only to take a cursory glance of the scenery, he cannot do better than mount the front of the stage-coach which every morning passes through Ambleside to Keswick. He will then have an opportunity of viewing the best combinations, which are almost always those in prospect. On returning, however, from Keswick to Ambleside, he should ascend the hinder part of the coach and sit with his back to the vehicle, in order to enjoy this charming ride.</p>
<p>RYDAL is a small but very neat village, with a Church, erected in 1826. On the right, about 200 yards each of the road, is Rydal Hall, the seat of the Le Fleming family, a noble mansion, situated on a gentle eminence near the road, at the junction of two valleys. It is sheltered by tall oaks and other trees, <pb n="52"/> which occupy the surrounding heights. Behind it rises the rocky mountain of Rydal Head, and, in front, the house commmands a fine view of Windermere and the intervening vale. In the grounds are two beautiful cascades. One is in a small glen, half a mile from the house, and is approached by a convenient path. This is a considerable stream, which makes a fall of about 25 feet in one unbroken sheet, besides several of less height. It is on a smaller scale, and is seen through a kind of summer-house, bursting at once upon the eye when the door is opened.</p>
<p>From the summit of Rydal Head, there is a fine view of the vales of Grasmere and Rydal, the small lake of Elter Water, and the majestic Windermere. Esthwaite and Coniston Lakes are seen further to the right, an in the distance appears the Irish Sea.</p>
<p>A short distance higher up the hill than the mansion just mentioned, is RYDAL MOUNT, the residence of Mr. Wordsworth, the celebrated author of 'The Excursion,' and other poems. It is delightfully situated, commanding prospects of Windermere and Rydal Lakes. The grounds are laid out with great taste. Strangers may obtain permission to go on the mount in front of the house, from which there is a charming view.</p>
<p>On the right of the road, about half a mile beyond the village of Rydal, is the WHITE MOSS SLATE-QUARRY. Here the old and new roads to the vale of Grasmere separate. The former crossed a steep hill. The latter, which the tourist will pursue, as it is far more beautiful, proceeds along the margin of Rydal <pb n="53"/>and Grasmere lakes, and is a perfect level. To the left, over Rydal Water, is seen Loughrigg Fell, and to the right, rises still more abruptly, Nab Scar.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">RYDAL WATER</head>
<p>Is a small lake, being only about a mile in length, and little more than a quarter of a mile in breadth. Its shores are picturesque, and its surface is spotted with two well-wooded islets, which form pleasing features in the views obtained from the sides and summits of the surrounding heights. It communicates by a narrow channel, about half a mile long, with Grasmere Water. Over this stream is a wooden bridge, erected for the use of the White Moss slaters, who reside in Langdale and Loughrigg.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">GRASMERE WATER.</head>
<p>This lake is also about a mile in length, but is more extensive than that of Rydal, spreading out in some parts to half a mile in breadth. It is surrounded by mountains of various singular forms, and in whatever direction it is seen presents splendid views. Near the centre is an island of about four acres, covered with verdant pasture, and adorned with a small clump of trees. At the head of the lake is seen a village of Grasmere, with its near white church, --the burial-place of the Le Fleming family. Near the church are the Parsonage House and the School. A swelling bank above these presents Allan Bank, and on the left, Pavement End, both beautifully embowered. Helm Crag rises to a fine apex. The Carrs and Wythburn Head, on the left of Helm Crag and Steel <pb n="54"/> Fell, and Seat Sandal on the right, are the most distant mountains.</p>
<p>The best situations for viewing the Vale of Grasmere, are Dearbought Hill, at the south-west extremity of the lake, close to the road leading from Loughrigg Tarn; the field behind the house, called Town End, at the north-east side of the lake; and Dunmel Raise.</p>
<p>At the upper end of the vale is HELM CRAG, a lofty pyramidal-shaped hill, the summit of which is covered with ragged pieces of rock. In the highest point, some poetical minds have discovered a resemblance to a lion and a lamb, and to an old woman stooping down; but neither of these forms can be observed to till the tourist has passed by the village towards Dunmel Raise. The latter has been alluded to by Mr. Wordsworth, in the following lines, describing the effects of echo amongst the mountains of Grasmere and its vicinity:--</p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line>"When I had gazed perhaps two minutes' space,</line>
<line>Joanna, looking in my eyes, beheld</line>
<line>The ravishment of mine, and laugh'd aloud.</line>
<line>The rock<ptr target="n1"/>, like something starting from a sleep,</line>
<line>Took up the lady's voice, and laugh'd again:</line>
<line>That ancient woman, seated on Helm Crag,</line>
<line>Was ready with her cavern; Hammer Scar,</line>
<line>And the tall steep of Silver How, sent forth</line>
<line>A noise of laughter; southern Loughrigg heard,</line>
<line>And Fairfield answer'd with a mountain tone:</line>
<line>Helvellyn far into the clear blue sky</line>
<line>Carried the lady's voice, --old Skiddaw blow</line>
<line>His speaking-trumpet; --back out of the clouds</line>
<line>Of Glaramara southward came the voice,</line>
<line>And Kirkstone toss'd it from his misty head."</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<note id="n1">A tall rock on the banks of Rothay, between Grasmere and Rydal Lakes.</note>
<pb n="54.6"/><!-- still not that clear on what to do with unnumbered pages; leaving this here till I can clarify -->
<gap desc="Map of Westmoreland"/>
<gap desc="blank page"/>
<pb n="55"/>
<p>SOUR MILK GILL, which falls into Grasmere at its North Extremity, issues from EASEDALE TARN, a small lake situated on the mountains about 3 miles distant, and sheltered by Colddale Fell and Blakerigg. After heavy rains, it is seen from the road pouring down the mountain-side like a stream of molten silver. Connected with Easedale Tarn by a small runner is COLDDALE TARN, containing a few perch and eels.</p>
<p>The principal fish found in the lakes of Grasmere and Rydal are pike, perch (here called bass), eels, and trout.</p>
<p>The derivation of Grasmere is uncertain. Some have supposed that its name originated in grassy mere or lake here; but others think it is derived from the grise or wild swine with which this country formerly abounded.</p>
<p>There are two good inns for the accommodation of travellers; the Red Lion, in the village of Grasmere, and the Swan, on the high road, about a quarter of a mile beyond it.</p>
<p>The pedestrian may make an excursion from Grasmere to the summit of HELM CRAG, going by Goody Bridge and Thornyhow, and returning by Turn How to the village, altogether about 4 miles. The summit is covered with rugged stones, heaped together in every possible variety. Two of these form what are called the Lion and the Lamb, when seen from the valley. The view from this spot embraces a grand range of mountains.</p>
<p>From Grasmere, the road ascends a hill to Dunmel Raise; Helm Crag gradually loses its fine form, and the views on each side become less pleasing. In rainy <pb n="56"/>weather, an uninteresting mountain gap, called Green Burn, situated between Helm Crag and Steel Fell, is relieved by the sparkling whiteness of a cataract.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">DUNMEL, or DUNMEL RAISE,</head>
<p>Is a large heap or <i>raise</i> of stones, situated at the side of the road, at the gap or pass which separates the counties of Cumberland and Westmoreland. The history of this monument is by no means certain. It is generally supposed to have been formed by Edmund I., to commemorate his defeat of Dunmail, a petty king of Cumbria, A.D. 945. The king and his two sons were put to death, and his territory bestowed on Malcolm of Scotland.</p>
<p>From this spot there are very extensive views. In one direction is seen the beautiful vale of Grasmere, and in the other, the vale of Thirlmere, with Helvellyn on the right, the Borrowdale Fells on the left, and Skiddaw and Saddleback in the back-ground.</p>
<p>The view of the vale of Grasmere, from Dunmel Raise, has been thus described by Mr, Gray: --"Just beyond it (Helm Crag) opens one of the sweetest landscapes that art ever attempted to imitate. The bosom of the mountains spreading here into a broad basin, discovers in the midst Grasmere Water: its margin is hollowed into small bays with bold eminences; some of rock, some of turf, that half conceal and vary the figure of the little lake they command: from the shore, a low promontory pushes itself far into the water, and on it stands a white village, with the parish church rising in the midst of it; hanging inclosures, corn-fields, and meadows, green as an emerald, <pb n="57"/> with their trees, and hedges, and cattle, fill up the whole space from the edge of the water: just opposite to youis a large farm-house, at the bottom of a deep, smooth lawn, embossed in old woods, which climb half way up the mountain's side, and discover above them a broken line of crags, that crown the scene. Not a single red tile, no gentleman's flaring house or garden walls, break in upon the repose of this little unsuspected paradise; but all is peace, rusticity, and happy poverty, in its neatest, most becoming attire."</p>
<p>The gap through which the road proceeds is 720 feet above the level of the sea, and is the lowest pass in the chain of mountains which extends from Black Comb into the county of Durham.</p>
<p>From Dunmel Raise all the way to Thirlmere, the road is bounded on the right by craggy mountains, forming the base of the might Helvellyn. A river, which, near the Raise, divides the counties of Westmoreland and Cumberland, presents in wet weather a number of waterfalls. Thirlmere, bounded on the left by hills, is seen at the extremity of the valley. The rocks on the right beyond Dunmel Raise are called Riggle Knots, Black Crag, and Fell Side; and those on the left, Steel Fell and Nab Crag, between which is a green gap called Dale Head.</p>
<p>At WYTHBURN is the Horse's Head public-house, situated halfway between Ambleside and Keswick. This is the best station from which to ascend Helvellyn, and here guides may be procured. The summit of the mountain cannot be seen from the public-house, nor from any part of the road till within about <pb n="58"/> three miles from Keswick; but the mountain track approaching it may be observed from the door: this track winds precipitously up the Middle Tongue between Fell Side and Whelp Side.</p>
<p>Opposite the Horse's Head is a small chapel; and looking directly across the valley from the back of the house, may be observed Dob Gill, a stream amongst the rocks, which proceeds from a little lake called HARROP TARN, situated under Tarn Crag, a rock seen beyond the rivulet. This stream joins that in the vale a little before it reaches Thirlmere.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">HELVELLYN.</head>
<p>This stupendous mountain is situated partly in Cumberland and partly in Westmoreland, on the eastern side of Thirlmere Water. According to the trigonometrical survey, it rises 3055 feet above the level of the sea. Its summit is not visible from the valley through which the road passes. The ascent is very steep, so that horses are never employed, but an active pedestrian will experience no great difficulty. He may reach the summit in about two hours, and descend in half that time. The tourist will, of course, provide himself with some refreshment.</p>
<p>The views obtained in the ascent are not so striking as those from Skiddaw, but that from the top is very extensive and magnificent. Mountains, valleys, and lakes, in all their various forms, stretch before the eye; while here and there the view is interrupted by projections of the hill on which the spectator stands. Immediately beneath are the Borrowdale Fells, the Langdale Pikes, with the adjoining hills, and beyond <pb n="59"/>them the Irish Sea. Towards the south are seen Coniston Water, and portions of Windermere, as well as the estuaries of the Kent and the Leven, and the whole of Morecambe Bay. To the north-west appear Saddleback and Skiddaw, and to the right and left of the latter, but far distant, the mountains of Scotland. To the north-east is seen the lofty Cross Fell, and to the south-east, the broad head of Ingleborough, between which are the mountains, separating Westmoreland from Durham and Yorkshire.</p>
<p>Helvellyn might also be visited from Patterdale, but the ascent is not so easy as from Wythburn, and one part, called Striden Edge, is dangerous. This, however, may be avoided by going along Swirrel Edge. It was in attempting to cross this spot that a young gentleman, named Gough, lost his life, in the spring of 1805. <!-- not that sure of the date; it is mentioned in Wordsworth's guide, which makes 1805 plausible; only concerned because the text could either be an 8 or a 6.-->At Patterdale, he had inquired for a guide, but in vain, and snow having fallen, he was recommended to wait till the next day. He set out, however, in the hope of reaching Wythburn, attended only by his dog, and perished by falling down the precipice. His remains were there discovered three months afterwards, guarded by his faithful companion. His fate has been commemorated in the well-known lines of Scott and Wordsworth.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">THIRLMERE, LEATHES WATER, or WYTHBURN WATER,</head>
<p>Is a lake of irregular form, about 4 miles in length, and in no part more than 1 mile in breadth. Its shores are deeply indented with bays, but almost entirely destitute of trees. It is bounded on the east <pb n="60"/>side by the lofty and rugged Helvellyn, and on the west by the naked and gloomy crags of Borrowdale Fells. Its whole appearance is that of savage desolation.</p>
<p>Thirlmere is situated on a higher level than any of the other lakes, being nearly 500 feet above the sea. Its depth is about 18 fathoms. Near the middle of the lake the shores approach so near each other as to leave only a small channel, over which is thrown a rustic bridge. In the northern part of the lake is a wooded island of about half an acre; and on the east side of the lake, close to the road, is a rock called 'Clark's Leap,' a person of that name having, it is said, thrown himself from it into the water, at his wife's recommendation.</p>
<p>The best situations for viewing Thirlmere are a small eminence on the left of the road, near the sixth mile post; the hill behind Dale-head House; and the road along the western shore, which is only passable for horsemen and pedestrians.</p>
<p>The high road which passes along the Eastern margin of the lake, proceeds over many rugged knolls and under the steep and shaggy brow of Helvellyn which rises on the right. It commands views of Bull Crag, Fisher Crag, and Raven Crag.</p>
<p>Thirlmere derives its name of Leathes, from the family to whose estate it belongs, and that of Wythburn, from the valley in which part of it is situated.</p>
<p>The road then leads through the narrow valley of LEGBERTHWAITE, interspersed with cottages and inclosures, and bounded on the right by rocks and precipices. From a field on the right side of the road, <pb n="61"/> about 1&#190; mile beyond Wythburn, there is a beautiful view of St. John's Vale, bounded on the left by a conspicuous solitary hill called the Great How, and on the right by Helvellyn. The bottom of the vale, which is narrow, is still more contracted, where the south end of Naddle Fell projects towards the Rock of St. John, scarcely leaving room for the river and the road upon its margin. Wanthwaite Crags are seen over St. John's Rock, and Saddleback appears in the distance.</p>
<p>At SMALLTHWAITE, or SMEATHWAITE BRIDGE, the road crosses the river Greta, or Bure, which runs from Thirlmere through part of the Vale of St. John, and joins the Derwent at Keswick. On the right beyond the bridge is a road leading down St. John's Vale to Threlkeld.</p>
<p>From Smallthwaite Bridge the road towards Keswick is steep, but as it rises, affords a good retrospective view of Helvellyn. On the left is Shoulthwaite Moss, above which rises a hill, called the Bend; and on the right appears the craggy surface of Naddle Fell. A little further on is Rougha Bridge, and beyond it on the right are seen Iron Crags. Various other prominences between these are Gate Crag and Dodd. The mountain called Calva is seen between Skiddaw and Saddleback; and on the left, still nearer to Keswick, is a house called Scott How, above which Dodd is seen. From a spot about 2 &#188; miles on this side of Keswick, the three mountains of Saddleback, Skiddaw, and Helvellyn may be seen: the first is partly concealed by Skelthwaite Crag.</p>
<pb n="62"/>
<p>The road then ascends to the ridge called CASTLERIGG. From this eminence there is an enchanting view of the vale of Keswick, including the lakes of Derwent and Bassenthwaite, the river serpentining through the meadows between them, the town of Keswick, Crosthwaite church, and the vale of Newlands. The whole is encircled by bold and lofty mountains. To the right are seen Saddleback and Skiddaw; in front Grisdale Pike, Causey Pike, and Grasmoor; and to the left the commencement of Borrowdale.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">KESWICK</head>
<p>Is a small market town, with 2159 inhabitants, delightfully situated on the banks of the Greta or Bure, which joins the river Derwent at a short distance. It stands on the eastern side of a fertile vale, between the foot of Skiddaw and the north end of Derwent Water. Its general appearance is by no means prepossessing. The streets are narrow, and most of the houses low and inconvenient. The market-place is small, and the town-hall insignificant. The houses are chiefly built in one street, through which runs the high road from Ambleside to Cockermouth. Out of this street another leads to Penrith, and a third, along the side of Derwent Water, to Borrowdale.</p>
<p>The climate here differs considerably from other parts of England, being neither so hot in summer nor so cold in winter, but always more rainy, on account of its vicinity to lakes and mountains.</p>
<p>The central situation of Keswick renders it the metropolis of the lakes, and many tourists make it their head-quarters. The Royal Oak, and the Queen's Head, are the principal Inns; but there are others where small parties may be accommodated, as well as many neatly-furnished private lodgings. Guides, horses, and carriages may also be obtained here, and pleasure boats for excursions on Derwent Water, which is about half a mile distant.</p>
<p>The coach from Kendal to Whitehaven passes through Keswick every day, except Sunday, about 11 o'clock; and that from Whitehaven to Kendal leaves Keswick about 3 in the afternoon. There is also a coach from Keswick to Penrith.</p>
<p>Keswick possesses two museums, containing specimens of the minerals found in the vicinity, various kinds of plants, British and Roman antiquities, coins, &#38;c. One was founded in 1779, by Mr. Crosthwaite, and is continued by his son; and the other belongs to Mr. Hutton. Both contain articles for sale. There is also a Circulating Library.</p>
<p>Keswick, more properly called Crossthwaite, Church, is not quite a mile from the centre of the town, with which it is connected by a low and flat road: it contains several monuments; the tower forms an excellent object from the roads, foot-paths, and seats in the vicinity. The Vicar's house, on a hill between the church and the town, commands a fine view of Derwent Water and its vicinity. This town also contains Meeting-houses for the Independents and Wesleyans.</p>
<p>The Poor-house was founded in the time of Charles I., by Chief Justice Banks, a native of this place. The market, held on Saturday, was established as far back as the reign of Edward I., who granted this <pb n="64"/>privilege on application from one of the Derwentwater family, to whom the manor belonged.</p>
<p>Keswick Bridge will be interesting to the artist as the subject of the first original picture by the late Sir George Beaumont.</p>
<p>The chief manufacture carried on here is that of woollens, blankets, kerseys, &#38;. There are also manufactories of black-lead pencils, the mineral being found in the mines of Borrowdale. Scythes, shovels, and edge tools are likewise made here.</p>
<p>Amongst the villas near Keswick is <i>Greta Hall,</i> the seat of Robert Southey, Esq. the poet-laureate. It is situated on the right hand, between the town and the church.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">DERWENT WATER.</head>
<p>The distance from the inns at Keswick to that part of the lake where the boats are moored, is rather more than half a mile.</p>
<p>Derwent water is a beautiful lake, of irregular form, extending, from north to south, rather more than 3 miles; and in breadth, about a mile and a half. Its depth varies from 3 to 14 fathoms. The principal feeders of the lake are the Derwent and the Lowdore, which descend from the valleys of Borrowdale and Watendlath. The former flows through it. The principal fish found here are trout, perch, pike, and eels. The trout are caught during April and May, and the perch and pike throughout the summer.</p>
<p>The distinguishing characteristic of Derwent Water is, that, from whatever point it is viewed, it presents the same form, and never assumes the appearance of <pb n="64.5"/><!-- same again, page numbers --> <gap desc="map of Derwent Water"/><gap desc="blank page"/><pb n="65"/> a river. More than half of the immediate boundary of the lake is rich pasture land, on which the trees are so sparingly scattered as little to impede the progress of agriculture, but the rest is closely environed by wood. The lake is bounded on the east by the fells of Castlerigg and Barrow, amongst which Wallow Crag, Falcon Crag, and Eve Crag appear conspicuous. On this side, also, are Gowder Crag, Hollow Stones, and Blea Crag. On the south side, are seen Grange Crag and Castle Crag in the valley of Borrowdale; and, on the west, appear Cat Bells and Causey Pike, between which is the Vale of Newlands. The north side of the valley is bounded by Skiddaw, the summit of which, in a straight line from the lake, is between 3 and 4 miles distant. The scenery formed by the combination of these objects is varied and magnificent. It has been thus described by Mr. Pennant, who viewed it from the water: --</p>
<p>"The views on every side are very different; here all the possible variety of Alpine scenery is exhibited, with the horror of precipice, broken crag, overhanging rock, or insulated pyramidal hills, contrasted with others, whose smooth and verdant sides, swelling into immense aerial heights, at once please and surprise the eye."</p>
<p>"The two extremities of the lake afford most discordant prospects: the southern is a composition of all that is horrible; and immense chasm opens, whose entrance is divided by a rude conic hill, once topt with a castle, the habitation of the tyrant of the rocks; beyond, a series of broken mountainous crags, now <pb n="66"/>patched with snow, soar one above the other, overshadowing the dark-winding deep of Borrowdale."</p>
<p>"But the opposite, or northern view, is, in all respects, a strong and beautiful contrast. Skiddaw shows its vast base; and, bounding that part of the vale, rises gently to a height that sinks the neighbouring hills; opens a pleasing front, smooth and verdant, smiling over the country like a gentle, generous lord, while the fells of Borrowdale frown on it like a hardened tyrant."</p>
<p>"Each boundary of the lake seems to take part with the extremities, and emulate their appearance; the southern varies in rocks of different forms, from the tremendous precipice of Lady's Leap, the broken front of Falcon's Nest, to the more distanct concave curvature of Lowdore, an extent of precipitous rocks, with trees vegetating from their numerous fissures, and the foam of a cataract precipitating amidst."</p>
<p>"The entrance into Borrowdale divides the scene, and the norther side alters into milder forms; a salt spring, once the property of the monks of Furness, trickles along the shore: hills, the resort of shepherds, with downy fronts and lofty summits, succeed, with wood clothing their bases to the water's edge."</p>
<p>Derwent Water is adorned with several islands of considerable extent, which rise with gentle and regular curvatures above the surface, covered with verdure, and richly clothed with wood.</p>
<p>LORD'S ISLAND, consisting of six acres, is the largest, and is situated near the shore. It is so called from having been the site of the house of the Earl of <pb n="67"/>Derwentwater, traces of which are still visible. In consequence of the active part which the last Earl took in the rebellion of 1715, it was forfeited to the crown, together with the other estates of that family in the vicinity. The whole is now appropriated to the support of Greenwich Hospital.</p>
<p>VICAR'S, or DERWENT ISLE, containing about 5<unclear>&#189;</unclear> acres, belongs to General Peachy, and is beautifully laid out in pleasure-grounds, surrounding a handsome house. It is said to have derived its name from having been the property of Fountains Abbey. It was for some years called Pocklington's Island, from the gentleman who formerly possessed it; and is occasionally styled Derwent Isle.</p>
<p>St. HERBERT'S ISLAND, consisting of four acres, near the centre of the lake, is celebrated as having been the residence of St. Herbert, who, according to the venerable Bede, died in 687. Vestiges of his chapel and cell are still shown; and near them is a small grotto built by the late Sir Wilfred Lawson, to whose successor the island now belongs. Mr. Gilpin says, "If a painter were desirous of studying the whole circumference of the lake, from one station, St. Herbert's Island is the spot he should choose; from whence, as from a centre, he might see it in rotation."</p>
<p>RAMPSHOLME is a smaller island, not being more than an acre, covered with wood. It belongs to the Derwent Water estate.</p>
<p>There are also other small islets, named OTTER ISLE, in a bay near the head of the lake; TRIPOTHOLME, and LINGHOLMES.</p>
<pb n="68"/>
<p>At the south-east corner of the lake, about 150 yards from the shore, is the FLOATING ISLAND, a mass of earth, about six feet in thickness, which is generally under water, but sometimes rises to the surface for weeks or months. It has appeared seven or eight times during the last thirty years, but always towards the close of a warm summer. Several attempts have been made to explain this phenomenon, but none of them appear very satisfactory. "The most rational conclusion," says Mr. Otley, "seems to be, that air or gas is generated in the body of the island, by the decomposition of the vegetable matter of which it is composed, and being produced most copiously in hot weather, the earth at length becomes so impregnated therewith, as to render the whole specifically lighter than the water, which, then insinuating itself between the substratum of clay, and the peat earth forming the island, bears it to the surface, where it continues for some time, till the volume of gas being reduced, the earth gradually sinks to its former level, to remain till a sufficient quantity of gas is again accumulated."</p>
<p>Mr. Gilpin does not appear to have admired this lake as much as many other tourists. He says, "In the first place, its form, which in appearance is circular, is less interesting, I think, than the winding sweep of Windermere, and some other lakes, which, losing themselves in vast reaches, behind some cape or promontory, add to their other beauties, the varieties of distance and perspective. Some people object to this as touching rather on the character of the river. But does not that injure its very beauty? and yet I believe that there are very few rivers which form such reaches as those of Windermere."</p>
<pb n="69"/>
<p>"To the formality of its shores, may be added the formality of its islands. They are round, regular, and similar spots, as they appear from most points of view: formal in their situation as well as in their shape, and of little advantage to the scene. The islands of Windermere are, in themselves, better shaped, more varied, and, uniting together, add beauty, contrast, and a peculiar feature to the whole. But, among the great objections to this lake, are abrupt and broken lines in several of the mountains, which compose its screens, especially on the western and part of the southern shore, which is more remarkable, than in any of the other lakes. We have little of the easy sweep of a mountain line; at least, the eye is hurt with too many tops of the mountains, which injure the ideas of simplicity and grandeur. I would be understood, however, to speak chiefly of the appearance which the lines of these mountains occasionally make. When we change our point of view, the mountain line changes also, and may be beautiful in one point, though it is displeasing in another."</p>
<p>The surface of Derwent Water is sometimes violently agitated by what has been termed a <i>bottom wind,</i> because it is supposed to be air pent up at the bottom of the lake. This phenomenon varies as to its duration; sometimes the swell of the waves continuing only for an hour or two, and sometimes nearly a whole day, although no wind whatever is perceptible above the surface of the water.</p>
<p>In wet weather, the lake frequently rises six or seven feet above the ordinary level; and, during severe winters, it is often frozen over. The water is remarkably <pb n="70"/>transparent. The scenery of Derwent Water may be viewed to most advantage from the surface of the lake, and from the following stations: --</p>
<p>CASTLEHEAD, a wooded rock, about half a mile from Keswick, rising 250 feet above the level of the lake. From this eminence, a very fine general view of Derwent Water, Keswick, and the adjacent valley, is obtained. A winding path, commencing on the left of Borrowdale road, half a mile from Keswick, forms a pleasant and safe avenue to the summit of Castlehead.</p>
<p>CROW PARK, a gentle eminence on the brink of the lake, about 300 yards from Keswick. This was formerly a wood of oaks, but it is now a verdant pasture, part of which was converted into a race-course in 1818. It commands the whole of the lake, from end to end, looking directly into the valley of Borrowdale.</p>
<p>COCKSHOT HILL, at a short distance from Crow Park, was formerly much recommended for a general view; but the prospect is now quite obstructed by trees.</p>
<p>THE VICARAGE, between Keswick and the Church. This is the situation with which Mr. Gray was so much delighted. It should be visited in the evening.</p>
<p>LATRIGG, a smooth and verdant hill at the base of Skiddaw. From the crown of this eminence may be seen the following mountains, which are the lofiest in England: Skiddaw, Saddelback, Helvellyn, Bow Fell, Scawfell, High Man or Pikes, Gable or Gavel, and Grasmere.</p>
<p>A walk to FRIAR CRAG, three-quarters of a mile from Keswick, also affords fine views of Crow Park, Cockshot Hill, Castlehead, and the lake. This is a <pb n="71"/>favourite promenade. The way to it from the town is by the little hills, to the road passing on the right, Crow Park, and on the left, Cockshot Hill; thence by a field called Strand's Hagg, to the last of the piers on the lake. Adjoining the pier is the north end of Friar Crag, to the south extremity of which, the walk leads through a grove of oaks and fir trees. Here a bench is placed commanding of a view of nearly the whole circumference of the lake.</p>
<p>Mr. Southey, in his Colloquies, says, "the best general view of Derwent Water is from the terrace, between Applethwaite and Milbeck, a little beyond the former hamlet. The old roofs and chimneys of that hamlet come finely in the foreground; and the trees upon the Ormathwaite estate give there a richness to the middle ground which is wanting in other parts of the vale."</p>
<p>Those who admire prospects from mountain tops, may ascend Causey Pike, Grisedale Pike, Cat Bells, and Skiddaw.</p>
<p>Several writers recommend a voyage on the lake by moonlight, as they scenery then exhibits quite a new style of beauty. The best time for such an excursion is a little before, or at, full moon, and on a still evening, when the ear may be gratified with the sound of the distant waterfalls.</p>
<p>Those who visit the lake in a boat, may be landed at the various islands, as well as to view the cascades of Barrow and Lowdore. A cannon is kept at the public-house near the latter, to show the effect of the echo. The price of a boat, with a single pair of oars, to go up the lake, is about 5<i>s.</i></p><pb n="72"/>
<head level="3" align="center">EXCURSION ON DERWENT WATER.</head>
<p>From Keswick, walk to the strand where the boats are moored, rather more than half a mile, and there take boat -- pass along the front of the rocky promontory called Friar Crag -- the between the farm-house of Stable Hills and Lord's Island -- Broom Hill, a wooded headland -- land at Barrow House, and see the waterfall -- walk to Lowdore Fall, or return to the boat, and proceed to the fall by water. If the weather be favourable, hear the echo produced by the discharge of the cannon at Lowdore -- Floating Island, only occasionally visible -- Mouth of the Derwent River -- St. Herbert's Island -- Water End Bay -- land, and see the grounds of Water End, belonging to Lord William Gordon -- Vicar's, or Derwent Isle, round which strangers are permitted to walk -- return to the strand, and walk back to Keswick; altogether about 8 miles.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">EXCURSION TO WATENDLATH.</head>
<p>Leaving Keswick, proceed along the road towards Borrowdale -- turn to the left at the end of Barrow Common -- at Ashness Bridge, across the stream which forms Barrow Cascade -- proceed by the wooden bridge between High Lowdore and Watendlath, to Watendlath. This village consists of about a dozen cottages, situated at the foot of a tarn fringed with trees, and guarded by rocky eminences, one of which is named Coatbarrow. The water of this tarn is derived from another called BLEA TARN, situated about 2 miles distant on the heathy mountain between Thirlmere and Borrowdale. <pb n="73"/>The stream which runs successively through these two tarns, afterwards forms the cataract at Lowdore. The adjacent vale of Watendlath is extremely picturesque, and has been extolled by some as superior to Borrowdale and Gatesgarth Dale. Mr. Gilpin says, "We fell into a piece of scenery, which, for beauty and grandeur, was equal, if not superior, to any thing we had yet seen." Hence proceed to the charming vale of Rossthwaite, of which a fine view may be obtained from the road -- return by Bowder Stone, Lowdore, and Barrow, to Keswick; altogether about 13 miles, which may be performed on horseback.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">EXCURSION TO ST. JOHN VALE.</head>
<p>Leaving Keswick, proceed along the road towards Ambleside for nearly 5 miles -- pass Legberthwaite Mill -- St. John's Rock, or Green Crag -- Brame Crag -- Lowthwaite -- Threlkeld -- thence to Keswick; altogether about 14 miles, which may be performed in a carriage.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">EXCURSION TO THE DRUID'S TEMPLE.</head>
<p>This remarkable monument is situated in the middle of a field, on the right-hand side of the old road to Penrith, about a mile from Keswick. It consists of an oval circle, 336 feet in circumference, formed by 38 rude stones, varying from 3 to 8 feet in height. Within this circle are 10 other stones, disposed in the shape of a square, supposed to have formed the altar. -- Return to Keswick by Castle Rigg; altogether about 3 miles.</p>
<pb n="74"/>
<p>From Keswick, tourists frequently make an excursion to the summit of</p>
<head level="3" align="center">SKIDDAW.</head>
<p>This distance from the town to the base of the mountain is about 1 mile, and thence a winding road of 5 miles more leads to the summit, which, according to Colonel Mudge, is 3022 feet above the level of the sea. This is an excursion of considerable fatique; but if, on reaching the top, the weather should prove favourable, the tourist will be amply compensated by the view. Persons who would find the exertion of walking too fatiquing, may ride the whole of the way, excellent horses for this purpose being kept at Keswick. A guide will be absolutely necessary, as the mountain is frequently visited by sudden mists. Great-coats and cloaks will be found very pleasant companions at the summit of the mountain, where the air is remarkably keen. The party should also be provided with sandwiches and brandy, to recruit their strength previous to the descent.</p>
<p>It is not easy to recommend the best time of the day for ascending the mountain, as that must depend so much on the state of the weather. Generally speaking, however, the morning is the best time, as soon after sunrise as possible. The whole excursion may be accomplished in about six hours.</p>
<p>Leaving Keswick to ascend the mountain, the road passes Monk's Hall, with Ormathwaite on the left, and then winds round Latrigg, at the base of Skiddaw. The views unfolded in the ascent are of unparalleled beauty; and that obtained from the summit, if the <pb n="75"/>weather be favourable, is varied and magnificent. It cannot be better described than in the language of Mrs. Radcliffe: --</p>
<p>"We stood on a pinnacle commanding the whole dome of the sky. The prospects below, each of which had been before considered separately as a great scene, were now miniature parts of the immense landscape.</p>
<p>"To the north lay, like a map, the vast tract of low country which extends between Bassenthwaite and the Irish Channel, marked with the silver circles of the river Derwent, in its progress from the lake. Whitehaven, and its white coast, were distinctly seen; and Cockermouth seemed almost under the eye. A long blackish line, more to the west, resembling a faintly-formed cloud, was said, by the guide, to be the Isle of Man, who, however, had the honesty to confess, that the mountains of Down, in Ireland, which sometimes have been thought visible, had never been seen by him in the clearest weather. Bounding the low country to the north, the wide Solway Frith, with its indented stones, looked like a grey horizon; and the double range of Scottish mountains, seen dimly through the mist beyond, like lines of dark clouds above it. The Solway appeared suprisingly near us, though at 50 miles distance; and the guide said, that on a bright day, its shipping would be plainly discerned.</p>
<p>"Nearly in the north, the heights seemed to soften into plains, for no object was there visible through the obscurity that had begun to draw over the farther distance; but towards the east, they appeared to swell again; and what we were told were the Cheviot hills, <pb n="76"/>dawned feebly beyond Northumberland. We now spanned the narrowest part of England, looking from the Irish Channel on one side, to the German Ocean on the other; which latter, however, was so far off as to be discernable only like a mist.</p>
<p>"Nearer than the country of Durham, stretched the ridge of Crossfell, and an indistinct multitude of the Westmoreland and Yorkshire highlands, whose lines disappeared behind Saddleback, now evidently preeminent over Skiddaw -- so much so, as to exclude many a height beyond it. Passing the mountain in our course to the south, we saw, immediately below, the fells round Derwent Water, the lake itself still remaining concealed in their deep rocky bosom. Southward and westward, the whole prospect was a "turbulent chaos of dark mountains;" all individual dignity was now lost in the immensity of the whole; and every variety of character was overpowered by the astonishing and gloomy grandeur.</p>
<p>"Over the fells of Borrowdale, and far to the south, the northern end of Windermere appeared, like a wreath of grey smoke that spreads along a mountain's side. More southward still, and beyond all the fells of the lakes, Lancaster Sands extended to the faintly seen waters of the sea. Then, to the west, Duddon Sands gleamed in a long line among the fells of High Furness.</p>
<p>"Immediately under the eye lay Bassenthwaite, surrounded by many ranges of mountains, invisible from below. We overlooked all these dark mountains; and saw green cultivated vales over the tops of lofty rocks; and other mountains over these vales, in <pb n="77"/>many ridges: whilst innumerable narrow glens were traced in all their windings, and seen uniting behind the hills with others that also upwards from the lake.</p>
<p>"The air on this summit was boisterous, intensely cold, and difficult to be inspired; though, below, the day was warm and serene."</p>
<head level="3" align="center">SADDLEBACK</head>
<p>May also be visited from Keswick, though it is not so frequently the object of attraction to strangers as Skiddaw, being at a greater distance from the town and not so easy of ascent. The tourist may proceed to the summit on foot or on horseback, but in either case he should take a guide.</p>
<p>The foot way is by Greta Bank, Brundholm, Derwent Fold, High Row End, round High Row Fell to Lile Fell, and thence by Priest Man to Linthwaite Pike. Then passing the foot of Scales Tarn, by Sharpe Edge to Atkinson's Man and Linthwaite Pike, return to Keswick, altogether about 12 miles.</p>
<p>If on horseback, the tourist must proceed along the Penrith road as far as Threlkeld, and there turn abruptly to the left to High Row End, Linthwaite Pike, and Atkinson's Man, returning by the same route to Keswick, altogether about 16 miles.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="VII. From KESWICK to BORROWDALE, and round DERWENT WATER.">
<pb n="78"/>
<head level="3" align="center">VII. From KESWICK to BORROWDALE, and round DERWENT WATER.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Keswick to Barrow House</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Barrow House to Lowdore</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lowdore to Grange</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Grange to Bowder Stone</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Return from Bowder Stone to Grange</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Grange to Porting Scales</td>
<td width="20%">4 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Porting Scales</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">12</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>This excursion may be made either on horseback or in a carriage.</p>
<p>On leaving Keswick, the road passes along the eastern shore of Derwent Water to BARROW HOUSE, which was built by the late Mr. Pocklington, and commands a good view of the lake. Behind this mansion is a beautiful waterfall, called BARROW CASCADE. It is surrounded by trees, and descends altogether, in several falls, 122 feet. Strangers are allowed to view it on application at the lodge.</p>
<p>At LOWDORE is a small inn, the apartments of which command good views of Derwent Water and Skiddaw. Behind the inn is the noted</p>
<head level="3" align="center">WATERFALL of LOWDORE.</head>
<p>This cascade is situated in a wild glen; and, after heavy rain, forms one of the finest scenes amidst the lakes. It is then a stream of considerable size, bounding on the rocks with tremendous fury, and falling altogether, in its numerous cascades, about 150 feet. The effect is very much enhanced by the commanding <pb n="79"/>aspect of the crags between which it is situated. On the left, Gowder Crag rises nearly 500 feet in height; and, on the right, is Shepherd's Crag, from the fissures of which spring numerous trees, with their branches hanging in the most fantastic forms. In a calm evening, and after wet weather, it is said that this waterfall can be heard at a distance of 10 miles. In dry weather, it dwindles to a small and insignificant stream. It forms a conspicuous object from the surface of the lake.</p>
<p>Mr. Gilpin makes the following observations on Lowdore: -- "This waterfall is a noble object, both in itself, and as an ornament to the lake. It appears more as an object connected with the lake, as we approach by water. By land, we see it over a promontory of low ground, which in some degree hides its grandeur. At the distance of a mile it begins to appear with dignity. But, of whatever advantage the fall of Lowdore may be as a piece of distant scenery, its effect is very noble when examined on the spot. As a single object, it wants no accompaniments of offskip, which would rather injure than assist it. They would disturb its simplicity and repose. The greatness of its parts affords scenery enough. Some instruments please in concert, --others you wish to hear alone.</p>
<p>"The stream falls through a chasm between two towering perpendicular rocks; the immediate part, broken into large fragments, forms the rough bed of cascade. Some of these fragments, stretching out in shelves, hold a depth of soil sufficient for large trees. Among these broken rocks, the stream finds its way <pb n="80"/>through a fall of at least a hundred feet; and in heavy rains, the water is every way suited to the grandeur of the scene. Rocks and water in opposition can hardly produce a more animated strife. The ground at the bottom, also, is very much broken, and overgrown with trees and thickets, amongst which the water is swallowed up into an abyss, and at length finds its way through deep channels to the lake."</p>
<p>Lowdore is shown by person belonging to the inn. The way to it is through a small gate on the left of the road from Keswick.</p>
<p>In a meadow fronting the inn, and sloping down to the water's edge, may be heard a very fine echo. A cannon is kept here for the purpose of gratifying those who are willing to pay 3<i>s.</i> 6<i>d.</i> for its discharge. The reverberation may, in still weather, be distinctly heard nine times. Much of the effect, however, will be lost if the full charge of powder is not put into the cannon, and properly rammed down.</p>
<p>The road then proceeds to GRANGE, a small but ancient and picturesque village, consisting of a few farm-houses. A little out of the road, beyond the gate under Grange Crag, is a scene greatly admired. It is a view of Grange Bridge and the village of Grange, upon the banks of the river, having the wooded Holm Crag, and other knolls swelling above the buildings, over which ascend Gate Crag, the Knitting Hows, and Blea Crag. On the left, a part of Grange Crag fills up the composition.</p>
<p>Grange is situated on the west bank of the pellucid Derwent, just at the entrance of the narrow portion of BORROWDALE, which here assumes the character of a <pb n="81"/>mountain pass, and is known by the name of the Straits of Borrowdale. The mountains and crags on each side approach so close, as only to leave a narrow channel for the Derwent, whilst immense rocks, and fragments of rock, are seen strewn around in every direction. Passing through this wild scene for about a mile, we arrive at the</p>
<head level="3" align="center">BOWDER, or BOWDAR STONE.</head>
<p>This is a huge rock, which appears to have been broken from the neighbouring crags by some violent convulsion. It stands at the edge of a precipice, on which it has fallen in so singular a position, that persons on opposite sides may shake hands through a hole underneath it. The shape of this stone is said to resemble a ship resting on its keel. It is supposed to weigh 1971 tons 13 cwt., and to contain 23,090 solid feet. It is 62 feet long, 36 in height, an 89 in circumference. From this spot there is a good prospect of the upper part of Borrowdale, with Castle Crag on the right, Eagle Crag, Glaramara, Bull Crag, and Serjeant Crag in the centre, and Scawfell Pikes in the distance.</p>
<p>CASTLE CRAG is a lofty and precipitous rock, partially covered with wood. It derived its name from a fortress which once stood on its summit, and guarded the pass of Borrowdale. This castle is said to have been built by the Romans, occupied by the Saxons, and afterwards given by one of the lords of Derwentwater to the monks of Furness. Of these facts, however, there is but slight evidence. Traces of this fortress were visible till within a few years, when they <pb n="82"/>were destroyed by the working of a slate-quarry. On the side of Castle Crag are paths by which the tourist may ascend to the top, where there is a monument in memory of Lord William Gordon. The summit commands a fine view of Derwent Water, the vale of Keswick, and Skiddaw, in one direction, and of Borrowdale, with its rugged rocks, in the opposite.</p>
<p>The tourist then returns to Grange, and crossing the Derwent, proceeds along a height above the woods of the late Lord W. Gordon, whose house, called WATER END, is situated on a bay of the lake. The road commands good views of the lake, along the western side of which it proceeds, and crossing the entrance of the vale of Newlands, joins the road from Cockermouth to Keswick, at PORTING SCALES, a village consisting of about twenty houses. It is situated on the gentle swell of a hill which rises from the lake.</p>
<p>The DERWENT, over which the tourist passes in this route, has its rise in Sprinkling Tarn on Borrowdale Fell, from which it passes in a steep descent of three-quarters of a mile to Styhead or Sparkling Tarn. At Taylor's Gill Band, it falls into the vale of Seathwaite, forming a noble waterfall, fringed by trees. It is joined below Stockley Bridge by a stream descending between the Aron End of the mountain, called Sprinkling and Allan Crags; and after that junction it passes the village of Seathwaite, and the Wad Mines, and under Seathwaite, Strand, Folly, Langthwaite and New Bridges to its junction with another branch, which runs by Stonethwaite.</p>
<p>This latter arm of the Derwent rises under Bowfell and Hanging Knott, and falls rapidly from Angle Tarn <pb n="83"/>into Langstreth, down which it murmurs under Serjeant Crag and Coorn Head, to the foot of Eagle Crag, where it is joined by a more turbulent stream from the valley of Greenup, from which junction it passes of Stonethwaite and Rossthwaite Bridges. A little below the latter it joins the Seathwaite branch already described, and thence hurries over a stony bed between Castle Crag and Bowder Stone to Grange, beyond which it expands into the lake of Derwent Water. Emerging from Derwent Water, it again becomes a river, but soon forms the lake of Bassenthwaite. It then contracts itself once more to a river, and pursues its course, by Cockermouth and Workington, to the sea.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="VIII. From KESWICK, round BASSENTHWAITE WATER.">
<head level="3" align="center">VIII. From KESWICK, round BASSENTHWAITE WATER.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Keswick, along the east side of the lake, to Castle Inn</td>
<td width="20%">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Castle Inn to Peel Wyke</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Peel Wyke, by the west side of the lake to Keswick</td>
<td width="20%">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">18</td>
</tr>
</table>
<head level="3" align="center">BASSENTHWAITE, or BROADWATER,</head>
<p>Is situated about four miles to the north of Derwent Water. It is rather more than four miles in length from the northern to the southern extremity, and varies in breadth from one mile to a quarter of a mile. It is formed by the river Derwent in its passage to the sea.</p>
<p>Bassenthwaite is not so picturesque as the other lakes, but occasionally present pleasing viewing. The eastern shore is deeply indented with three bays, at some distance behind which rises the lofty Skiddaw. The intervening space consists of cultivated ground. The western side of the lake is bounded by a range of bills falling abruptly to the water's edge. These are called WYTHROP BROWS, and are partly rock, and partly clothed with woods.</p>
<p>Mr. Hutchinson gives the following description of Bassenthwaite in his History of Cumberland: -- "This lake affords many bays, where you may, in some parts, push under the cover of a lofty overhanging grove, and in others, rocky coves, where you may find the gentler echo favourable to music and a song. The painter has tamer landscape heres, but they are warmer and <pb n="85"/>more serene than those of Keswick. Soft pastoral scenes margin the lake on the eastern side, over which Skiddaw lifts an august brow, to give the boldest contrast to the green and gently rising eminences, the scattered coppices, the velvet-dressed lawn, the rich verdure of the mead, the tranquil cottage, and the serene and shining mirror which the lake expands. The boldest landscape found here, consists of irregular eminences, clothed with oaks, at whose feet a grassy margin lies to the water's brink, and holds some farm-hold; whilst the sublimer mountains, pile upon pile, lift up their heads, and from western sun cast long shades upon the lake, whose distance shores catch the surpassing beams, and glow with additional beauty, from the contrasting shades, over which the distant eminences mix their brows with the azure of the atmosphere."</p>
<p>This lake is not so deep as Derwent Water, but the water is nearly as transparent. It abounds with pike, perch, trout, and eels. Salmon is also sometimes found here; and the shores are frequented by a variety of water-fowl.</p>
<p>The ride round Bassenthwaite may be enjoyed either on horseback or in a carriage. The road passes along the eastern side of the lake, but at some distance from it. The best views are to be obtained from BRAIDNESS and SCARENESS, both situated at a short distance to the left of the road.</p>
<p>Thence the tourist proceeds by a few scattered houses, called BASSENTHWAITE HALLS, to CASTLE INN. In the immediate vicinity is ARMATHWAITE <pb n="86"/> HALL, a mansion delightfully situated, and commanding a good view of the lake.</p>
<p>About two miles north of Armathwaite is the verdant hill of CAER-MOT, on which are traces of two square entrenchments used by the Romans and the ancient Britons.</p>
<p>At the foot of Bassenthwaite Water, where the Derwent emerges from the lake, is OUSE BRIDGE, from which there is a fine prospect of both shores. This is a handsome structure, consisting of three stone arches. It was erected by Sir F. F. Vane, Bart., near the site of the old bridge, which was carried away by a flood.</p>
<p>The tourist may then proceed to PEEL WYKE, where there is a public-house, and along the western shore of the lake, returning to Keswick through Thornthwaite and Porting Scales. The road affords many pretty views: that, however, from BECK-WYTHROP, recommended by Mr. West, is now obscured by woods. This is a charming ride, particularly in the evening, when the declining sun gilds the surface of the water.</p>
</chap>
<chap title="IX. From KESWICK to BORROWDALE, BUTTERMERE, and CRUMMOCK WATER.">
<head level="3" align="center">IX. From KESWICK to BORROWDALE, BUTTERMERE, and CRUMMOCK WATER.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Keswick to Barrow House</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Barrow House to Lowdore</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lowdore to Grange</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Grange to Bowder Stone</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Bowder Stone to Rossthwaite</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Rossthwaite to Seatallor</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Seatallor to Honister Crag (summit of road)</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Honister Crag to Gatesgarth</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Gatesgarth to Buttermere</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Buttermere to Porting Scales, through the vale of Newlands</td>
<td width="20%">7 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Porting Scales to Keswick</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">23</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>This excursion must be made either on horseback, in a cart, or on foot, as a carriage cannot go farther than SEATALLOR. Those who wish to visit Buttermere and Crummock Water in a carriage must take the course pointed out in the next route.</p>
<p>As far as BOWDER STONE, the tourist proceeds by the road already described, and then, having CASTLE CRAG on the right and BOWDER CRAG on the left, to ROSSTHWAITE, romantically situated in the middle of the valley, and surrounded by overhanging mountains. At this village is a small public-house.</p>
<p>From the top of a green hill, in the vicinity, the valleys of Rossthwaite, Stonethwaite, and Seathwaite, with the bordering mountains, form a series of grand views.</p>
<p>To the left of the road, beyond Rossthwaite, is seen the small Chapel of Borrowdale, erected about 1826; and behind it, the valley of STONETHWAITE, bounded by Eagle Crag. Stonethwaite, one mile south of Rossthwaite, consists of about half a dozen buildings picturesquely interspersed with trees. The bridge also, crossing the stream, a little to the east of the houses, and backed by the neighbouring heights, is a pleasing subject for the artist.</p>
<p>EAGLE CRAG is an immense pile of perpendicular rocks raised one above another by horizontal spaces of variously coloured vegetation. Its form is fine, and it makes a good back-ground to many neighbouring objects. On that part of Eagle Crag, opposite to Greenup, eagles occasionally built their nests, and hence the name of the eminence. These birds, however, destroyed so many lambs that their extermination became absolutely necessary, and this was effected many years ago by lowering a man down the front of the rock to take their nests. He was rewarded for his toil and danger by the neighbouring shepherds.</p>
<p>The road then turns to the right, to SEATALLOR, or SEATOLLER, where it begins to ascend a long and steep hill called BORROWDALE HAWSE, and is no longer passable for carriages. On reaching the summit of the Hawse, which rises 880 feet above the level of Derwent Water, a fine view is obtained of HONISTER CRAG, on the left of the road. This immense and rugged rock rises abruptly from the valley 1600 feet in height. On the opposite side of the road is YEW CRAG. Both are famous for slate. From many quarries, where the descent is not particularly steep, the slate is conveyed to the valley below in carts; but <pb n="89"/>in other places it is brought down by men, in hurdles placed at their backs, over ground so precipitous, that those not witnessing the act would deep it impossible.</p>
<p>The tourist then descends to the farm of GATESGARTH; GATESGARTH-DALE, through which he passes, is a narrow valley, bounded by precipitous craggy rocks, the ruins of which are scattered in every direction. Along the bottom runs the mountain stream, which falls into Buttermere Water. About half way down the dale, at the end of the stones which have fallen from Yew Crag, the hill is smooth and verdant. By ascending this hill two or three hundred yards, a good retrospective view of Honister Crag is obtained.</p>
<p>Mr. Gilpin thus beautifully describes Gatesgarth Dale. "The river, also, which runs through it, and is the principal supply of the lake, is as wild as the valley itself. It has no banks, but the fragments of rocks; no bed, but a channel, composed of rocky strata, among which the water forces its course. Its channel, as well as its bank, is formed of loose stones, and fragments, which break and divide the stream into a succession of wild impetuous eddies. A stream, which is the natural source of plenty, is, perhaps, when unaccompanied with verdure, the strongest emblem of desolation. It shows the spot to be so barren, that even the greatest source of abundance can produce nothing. The whole valley, indeed, joined in impressing the same idea. Fruitful nature, making, in every part of her ample range, unremitting efforts to vegetate, could not here produce a single germ." One side of the dale, however, does afford pasture for <pb n="90"/>sheep, but Mr. Gilpin saw the valley in misty weather, and this accounts for his error.</p>
<p>The tourist then proceeds parallel with the lake, and passes the mansion called HASSNESS, a mile beyond which is the village of BUTTERMERE, situated between Buttermere and Crummock Waters. It has a small chapel and an inn, called the Fish. The mountains visible from the door of the inn, beginning Eastward, are Rannerdale Knot, Grasmere, Whiteless Pike, and Whiteless; and beyond the intersections of the latter two, Wandup. Buttermere Moss appears on the right, and between it and Whiteless, Knott Rigg.</p>
<p>From an eminence, called Hartley Hill, behind the village, there is a fine view of the two lakes, the valley, and the adjacent hills. In front is seen SOUR MILK GILL, so called from its frothy whiteness, resembling buttermilk from the churn. It has its rise in BURTNESS, BLEABERRY or BLEBBA TARN, between Red Pike and High Stile, and falls down the mountain side into Buttermere Lake. The artist, who wishes to study rocks and headlong waters, cannot do better than scramble up the margin of this waterfall. BURTNESS COVE, a grand circular range of rocks between High Stile and High Crag, was formerly noted for eagles' nests.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">BUTTERMERE WATER</head>
<p>Is situated in the vale of the same name, and is nearly surrounded by rocky mountains. It is about a mile and a half in length, a quarter of a mile in breadth, and 15 fathoms in depth.</p>
<p>On the western side is a long range of mountainous <pb n="91"/> declivities, including Hay Stacks, High Crag, High Stile, and Red Pike. On the eastern are Buttermere Moss and Robinson, with meadows and woods, affording a fine contrast. One extremity of the lake sweeps round a fine wooded promontory. Buttermere contains trout and char.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">CRUMMOCK, or CROMACK WATER</head>
<p>Is separated from that of Buttermere by a piece of arable land, about three-quarters of a mile in length, through which flows the river Cocker. This lake is of an oblong form, three miles in length, three-quarters of a mile in breadth, and 22 fathoms in depth.</p>
<p>It is situated between two lofty mountains. Grasmere, or Grasmoor, on the eastern, and Melbreak on the western side; the latter descends abruptly to the water's edge, and leaves but few tracts for cultivation. The opposite shore is pleasingly diversified by bays, arable land, and coppices. The head and foot of the lake are adorned with wood, but the sides are distinguished only by their boldness. There are several islands, but being situated near the shore, they add but little to the beauty of the lake.</p>
<p>Crummock Water abounds with trout and char. The outlet is at the north-east corner, where a stone bridge of four arches crosses the river Cocker.</p>
<p>The best situations for viewing the lake are from Buttermere Hawse, a rock on the east side, a mile and a half from Buttermere, and from the road between Scale Hill and Lowes Water.</p>
<pb n="92"/>
<p>Near the south-west extremity of Crummock Water, is</p>
<head level="3" align="center">SCALE FORCE.</head>
<p>The best way of approaching this water-fall is to hire a boat at Buttermere, and row down Crummock Water for about a mile. The distance from the landing-place to the cascade is rather more than half a mile, and the path is remarkably rugged. It may also be visited by land, but the distance by this latter method is a mile and a half, and the ground is extremely swampy. The charge made for the boat is 3<i>s.</i> 6<i>d.</i></p>
<p>Scale Force falls a greater height than any other cascade in Cumberland or Westmoreland. It makes one clear leap of 156 feet, besides a smaller fall of 44 feet. It is situated in a deep chasm from 12 to 20 feet in width, bounded by perpendicular rocks, which rise to an immense height. Both sides are covered with a variety of moss, fern, ash, and oak, which are kept in constant verdure by the spray of the fall. The quantity of water is not great except after heavy rains, when the cascade swells to an immense size, and pours over the rock with a noise as loud as thunder.</p>
<p>An interesting story is connected with the vale of Buttermere, and is frequently related to travellers in their passage through it. It is entitled MARY of BUTTERMERE, and has its foundation in the following circumstances: -- Mary Robinson, the daughter of the innkeeper at the village of Buttermere, was seen by the author of "A Fortnight's Ramble," in 1792, and <pb n="93"/>described as a very beautiful but artless girl of fifteen, -- a very Lavinia, --</p>
<poem>
<line>"Seeming, when unadorn'd. adorn'd the most."</line>
</poem>
<p>The encomium attracted many travellers to Buttermere, and flattery destroyed the simplicity though not the virtue of its interesting peasant. In 1802, she was inveigled into marriage with an outlaw named Hatfield, who, under the assumed character of the Honourable Colonel Hope, had long violated the laws of his country, and was executed for forgery in 1803. After some years she was married again to a young man from the neighbourhood of Carlisle, and lived for a considerable time in the inn at Buttermere, which had been her father's. She has since removed to the vicinity of Bassenthwaite Water.</p>
<p>From Buttermere, the tourist will return to Keswick, by the Vale of Newlands. The road has within a few years been much improved, and is now practicable for a carriage, though still so steep that it will occasionally be necessary for the tourist to alight and walk. It first ascends a very steep and lofty hill, called the HAWSE, from the top of which there is a good view of the Vale. In the middle ground, amongst other summits, are the two Cat Bells, and the ridge extending towards Causey Pike, the top of which is not visible from this spot: at some distance appears Saddleback, and still further, the Blue Mountains whence the rivers Tyne and Tees flow. The Hawse forms the termination of the upper part of the Vale of Newlands, here called KESKADALE. This portion is a mountain recess, environed by smooth sloping hills, which are <pb n="94"/>adorned neither with wood, nor rock, nor broken ground, by sweep down from side to side with the greatest regularity. At the bottom is a narrow dell, down which rolls a torrent. A cascade of considerable size falls down the mountain side, at the head of the dale, and after heavy rain, has a majestic appearance, dashing from rock to rock, and foaming and fretting down the rough declivity. The mountain called Robinson is here a fine object, being the only one of rugged aspect.</p>
<p>The VALE of NEWLANDS, which succeeds, is a lovely scene, adorned with all the beauties of luxuriant Nature. It is richly decorated with wood, and is traversed through its whole extent by a sparkling stream. At its extremity is a considerable eminence, which divides it into two portions, one opening directly on the beautiful expanse of Derwent Water, and the other turning towards Bassenthwaite Water.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="X. From KESWICK to CRUMMOCK and BUTTERMERE WATERS">
<pb n="95"/>
<head level="3" align="center">From KESWICK to CRUMMOCK and BUTTERMERE WATERS,</head>
<head level="3" align="center">IN A CARRIAGE</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Keswick to Braithwaite</td>
<td width="20%">2 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Braithwaite to Whinlatter (summit)</td>
<td width="20%">2 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Whinlatter to Lorton</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lorton to Scale Hill</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Scale Hill to Buttermere</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Return to Keswick by the same route, (or through the Vale of Newlands, 9 miles)</td>
<td width="20%">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">32</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>Leaving Keswick, the tourist passes through the village of BRAITHWAITE, and ascends the hill of WHINLATTER, which rises at least 800 feet above the adjacent vale. This road commands fine views of Bassenthwaite, Derwent Water, and Skiddaw. Beyond the sixth mile stone it turns to the left, and, winding round the hill, presents a charming prospect of the vale of Lorton, and a distant view of the Scottish mountains. In the extreme distance is seen Ben Garon, and more in advance Scrifell, with a range of inferior heights between them. The village of High Lorton, nearest the spectator, is seen on the east side of the vale; and Low Lorton, standing under Low Fell on the banks of the river Cocker, on the west. The church, in the midst of a wood, appears between these villages.</p>
<p>The VALE of LORTON is about 2 &#189; miles in length, and is watered by the Cocker. It has been thus beautifully described by Mr. Gilpin: -- "No lakes, no rocks, are here, to blend the ideas of dignity and <pb n="96"/>grandeur with that of beauty. All is simplicity and repose. Nature, in this scene, lays totally aside her majestic frown, and wears only a lovely smile.</p>
<p>"The vale of Lorton is of the extended kind, running a considerable way between mountains, which range at about a mile's distance. They are near enough to screen it from the storm, and yet not so impending as to exclude the sun. Their sides, though not smooth, are not much diversified. A few knolls and hollows just give a little variety to the broad lights and shades which overspread them.</p>
<p>"This vale, which enjoys a rich soil, is in general a rural, cultivated scene; though in many parts the ground is beautifully broken and abrupt. A bright stream, which might almost take the name of a river, pours along a rocky channel, and sparkles down in numberless little cascades. Its banks are adorned with wood, and varied with different objects; a bridge, a mill, a hamlet; a glade overhung with wood; or some little sweet recess, or natural vista, through which the eye ranges, between irregular trees, along the windings of the stream."</p>
<p>At STANGER, about 2 miles north of Lorton, is a mineral spring, said to resemble those of Cheltenham.</p>
<p>At SCALE HILL, about 1 mile from the foot of Crummock Water, is a commodious Inn. Here the tourist may hire a boat and row along the lake to visit the cascade of Scale Force, and the lake of Buttermere, already described in the preceding route. Or, he may drive by Buttermere Hawse, from which there is a fine view of the two lakes, to the village of Buttermere, <pb n="97"/>and thence visit Scale Force and the lake of Buttermere.</p>
<p>From Buttermere, he may return to Scale Hill, and thence to Keswick, by the Whinlatter road; or proceed to Keswick, through the Vale of Newlands, as described in the former route.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="XI. From KESWICK to WAST WATER, ENNERDALE WATER, LOWES WATER, CRUMMOCK WATER, and BUTTERMERE WATER,">
<head level="3" align="center">XI. From KESWICK to WAST WATER, ENNERDALE WATER, LOWES WATER, CRUMMOCK WATER, and BUTTERMERE WATER,</head>
<head level="3" align="center">ON HORSEBACK IN TWO DAYS.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Keswick to Lowdore</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lowdore to Grange</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Grange to Bowder Stone</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Bowder Stone to Rossthwaite</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Rossthwaite to Seatallor</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Seatallor to Seathwaite</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Seathwaite to Stye Head</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Stye Head to Wastdale Head</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Wastdale Head to Strands</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Strands to Gosforth</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Gosforth to Calder Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%" align="right">First Day</td>
<td width="20%">27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Calder Bridge to Ennerdale Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ennderdale Bridge to Lamplugh</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lamplugh to Lowes Water</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lowes Water to Scale Hill</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Scale Hill to Keswick by Buttermere and Vale of Newlands</td>
<td width="20%">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%" align="right">Second Day</td>
<td width="20%">29</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>This is the most convenient plan of an excursion for persons who prefer riding on horseback, as it enables them to view Borrowdale as well as these five lakes in two days. On the first day, they will see Borrowdale and Wast Water; and, on the second, Ennerdale Water, Lowes Water, Crummock Water, and Buttermere. The road is in many places over very rugged <pb n="99"/>ground, particularly in the descent from Stye Head to Wastdale, so as to be not only difficult to travel, but, to delicate persons, laborious and alarming. Being passed, however, in the early part of the first day, the remainder of the ride from Wastdale Head to Calder Bridge is generally over smooth ground. The second day's ride from Calder Bridge is over a good road, though occasionally hilly. Those who think two days are not sufficient for this excursion, may occupy three, sleeping the first night at Strands, and the second at Scale Hill.</p>
<p>The road from Keswick to Seatallor has already been described. Half a mile beyond Seatallor Bridge is Seathwaite Bridge, crossing an arm of the river Derwent. Beyond it is seen the village of Seathwaite, and crossing the head of the vale, appear Aaron End and Sparkling, with the shaggy surface of Great End rising above them. Keppel Crag and Hind Crag are on the left, and Bay's Brown on the right.</p>
<p>SEATHWAITE is a small village at the extremity of Borrowdale, completely shut in by mountains, which exclude the sun for a considerable part of the year. In Gillercoom, a circular recess in the hill to the right of Seathwaite, are the</p>
<head level="3" align="center">WAD, or BLACK LEAD MINES.</head>
<p>They are situated on the south-eastern side of SEATALLOR FELL, a lofty mountain covered with hazels, except at the summit, where it is completely naked. These are the only mines of the kind in England. The period of their discovery is unknown, but they were certainly worked previous to the seventeeth <pb n="100"/>century, and have been occasionally open ever since. The mineral has also been found in Ayrshire, Inverness-shire, and in foreign countries, but of a very inferior quality.</p>
<p>Various names have been given to the mineral found here, but as many of them denote other substances, they do not appear very appropriate. It is called on the spot, wad, and in other places plumbago, or black lead, though lead forms no part of its composition. The terms black cawke and graphite have likewise been applied to it. It is principally used for the manufacture of pencils, great quantities of which are made at Keswick; but is also employed in making crucibles, polishing iron, diminishing the friction of machinery, &#38;c.</p>
<p>The mine was formerly worked only at intervals, a sufficient quantity being procured in a short time to last for several years; but the market being considerably extended, and the difficulty of finding the mineral increased, the working has lately been carried on more constantly.</p>
<p>The wad is not found in veins, but in irregular masses, some of which weigh four or five pounds. Many of these pieces are of little value, being hard and gritty; but those which are soft and of fine texture are worth several guineas a pound. These masses are usually found in the form of a tree, the trunk being of the finest quality, and the branches inferior to it. When taken out of the mine, the wad is sorted according to its various qualities, and the best sent to London, where it is sold to the dealers once a month. The pencil-makers of Keswick receive their supply from <pb n="101"/>the metropolis, as the proprietors of the article will not allow any to be sold till it has been deposited in their own warehouse.</p>
<p>At the entrance of the mine is a house, built for the residence of the overseer, and here the labourers are examined on leaving their work.</p>
<p>The way from Seathwaite to the Mine is over a rustic bridge, called Far Bridge.</p>
<p>Beyond Seathwaite, the road dwindles to a mountain track, passable only by horses accustomed to the country. To the right is a waterfall, called TAYLOR'S HILL, which, after heavy rains, is a fine object, dashing from rock to rock with resistless fury. The avenue to this fall is through a profusion of trees, which assist in forming good subjects for the artist. After the tourist has proceeded about a mile, he crosses STOCKLEY BRIDGE, a single arch of stone, and begins the ascent of the mountain called Sparkling or Stye Head. The road winds steeply up that part of the mountain called Aaron End, having, on the right, Bay's Brown, and Taylor's Gill Band. A retrospective glance will command Borrowdale, Grange Fell, and Wallow Crag, above which appears Saddleback. Taylor's Gill murmurs by the side of the tourist's path all the way to Stye Head Tarn.</p>
<p>STYE HEAD is a steep and precipitous crag, situated between the two lofty mountains of Scaw Fell and Great Gavel. The summit rises about 1250 feet above the adjacent vale: it is a rocky plain, about three-quarters of a mile in length, bounded on each side by slaty crags. In its centre is SPARKLING or STYE HEAD TARN, a deep lake, nearly a mile in circumference, <pb n="102"/>abounding with trout. Passing by this lake, the lofty crag of Great End is seen on the left; and, beyond it, the highest of the Scawfell Pikes. To the right is Great Gavel.</p>
<p>If the tourist has leisure, he may deviate a little from his route to visit SPRINKLING TARN, which is connected with Stye Head Tarn by a stream about a mile long. It is situated beneath the Great End Crag, and abounds with excellent trout. The ascent to it is steep.</p>
<p>From the side towards Seathwaite, Stye Head commands a complete view of Borrowdale, and of the vale of Keswick. The prospect from the opposite side of the hill is magnificent. In front rises the might SCAW FELL, towering above the intervening space, which comprehends the fertile valley of Wastdale; and, in the distance, appears the sea.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">SCAW FELL, or SCA FELL,</head>
<p>The highest mountain in England, is divided into two summits, separate from each other by a deep chasm called Mickle Door. Both are surrounded by frightful precipices; and the highest is surmounted by a pile of stones, raised for the purpose of the trigonometrical survey. The "PIKES," as it is here called, on the summit nearest to Stye Head, rises, according to the Trigonometrical Survey, 3166 feet above the level of the sea. The southern summit, called SCAW FELL, is only 3092 feet.</p>
<p>Both the summits, but particularly the highest, command fine views: the Pikes may be most easily ascended from Seathwaite; and Scaw Fell, from Wastdale <pb n="103"/>Head or Eskdale. A guide will be absolutely necessary, as the mountain is far more difficult of access than Helvellyn or Skiddaw.</p>
<p>From Stye Head, the tourist descends by a steep and narrow track into the valley of Wastdale. The road is well defined, and kept in tolerable repair: it is full of sharp turns and bends, which, though they lengthen the journey, render it much easier than if carried forward in a straight line. From the top of the Stye is seen the vale of Wastdale, and in the distance Yewbarrow. The road is carried down the side of Great Gavel, whose surface is one series of huge projecting rocks. On the left, over the deep ravine below the road, appear Great End and the Pikes, the latter being gradually lost behind Broad Crag. Nearer the bottom of the valley, projecting from the top of Lingmell, are Lingmell Crags. Over the lower end of Lingmell, is seen a small portion of the lake, and beyond it, the sea. At the foot of the pass, rude rocks are exchanged for soft verdure and easy passage to Wastdale Head.</p>
<p>WASTDALE HEAD is a small and very rural hamlet, consisting of not more than a dozen houses, and a small chapel. It is surrounded by about 400 acres of level land, which is divided into fields by stone walls. There is no inn, by strangers may readily obtain refreshment of the farmers residing here, whose kindness they will, of course, acknowledge by a suitable donation.</p>
<p>The tourist then proceeds along the northern shore of Wast Water, passing Over Beck Bridge, Nether <pb n="104"/>Beck Bridge, and a few houses called Crook. An excursion up the stream from Over Beck Bridge would present some pretty scenery and a waterfall. The retrospective views from the road along the lake should not be forgotten, as the mountains afford many good combinations.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">WAST WATER.</head>
<p>This lake is about 3 miles in length, and three-quarters of a mile at its greatest breadth. It is remarkable for its depth, which is between 40 and 50 fathoms, and is never frozen over. The mountains surrounding Wast Water are lofty and majestic; but its immediate banks present but little variety. The whole of the south-east shore consists of a high ridge called the SCREES, fragments of which are constantly falling into the water. The north-west shore is not so lofty, and gradually loses its mountainous character as it approaches the foot of the lake, which is adorned with wood. The mountains bounded the West side of the lake are Buckbarrow, Middle Fell, and Yewbarrow. On the North of Middle Fell runs Nether Beck, and on the South of Yewbarrow, Over Beck; these rivers and the lake enclosing three sides of an extensive plot of cultivated land, called Bowderdale: on the four sides rise rugged mountains, the most prominent of which is Knott End. Lingmell, which is the base of Scallfell and the Pikes, lies at the northern end or head of the lake; and Latterbarrow on the South.</p>
<p>Wast Water abounds with trout, and char are occasionally caught in it.</p>
<pb n="105"/>
<p>STRANDS, about a mile beyond the foot of the lake, is a small village, with two neat inns, where beds may be obtained.</p>
<p>GOSFORTH is a small, but well-built village, with a church, by the side of which the road passes. In the churchyard is a column curiously carved with unknown characters.</p>
<p>The road then joins the highway from Ulverstone to Whitehaven, and passes over a more cultivated and level country, commanding views of the sea, to</p>
<p>CALDER BRIDGE. -- Here are two small inns, at one of which the tourist may sleep. The mountain called Seat Allan, is visible from the bridge, three miles below which the river Calder falls into the sea.</p>
<p>A mile from the bridge are the ruins of CALDER ABBEY, a considerable portion of which is still entire, though more than seven hundred years old. It is situated close to a modern mansion belonging to the Senhouse family. This abbey was formerly dependant on that of Furness. It was founded in the early part of the twelth century, by Ranulph de Meschines, and appropriated to Cistercian monks. The footpath from the Bridge to the Abbey is partly over fields and partly through a shady lane, at the end of which is a grove of sycamores. Beyond them the ruins are seen in the best point of view.</p>
<p>About half a mile west of Calder Bridge, on a high and commanding bank, rising from the river, stands PONSONRY HALL, the seat of the Stanley family.</p>
<p>From Calder Bridge, there is a good road to Whitehaven, which is 10 miles distant; but the tourist will pursue that which inclines towards the mountains, and <pb n="106"/>then cross the barren fells of Copeland Forest, Cold Fell being on the right, and Dent Hill on the left.</p>
<p>Commencing at the Bridge, the tourist proceeds along the carriage road towards the Abbey for half a mile, then leaves it, and in another half mile passes a house called the Flat, whence the whole distance, to within half a mile of Ennderdale Bridge, is over a common. From this common, about 2 miles beyond the Flat, are seen the Ennerdale and Wastdale mountains, amongst which the Chair, Seat Allan, and Cold Fell appear conspicuous: at the south angle of the latter is a piked summit, called the Hay Cocks, having at one end of it a round knott called Little Gowder Crag, and at the other, a range of rocks, called the Great Gowder Crag. Wastdale Screes are seen here, and to their left, Scaw Fell and the Pikes, with their separating chasm, Mickle Door. Two miles further, the town of Egremont is seen through a narrow vale on the left, and sometimes the Isle of Man is visible in the distant sea.</p>
<p>Previous to reaching Ennerdale Bridge, a part of the lake and the valley called Ennerdale are presented to the view, encircled by mountains, amidst which the Pillar is conspicuous.</p>
<p>ENNERDALE BRIDGE is a small hamlet, with a church, and two public-houses of an inferior description. It takes its name from the bridge over the Ehen, a river which issues from Ennerdale Water, and passing by this place and Egremont, enters the sea, not a mile from the mouth of the river Calder.</p>
<p>From the west sside of the river, between the bridge and the lake, which is a mile and a half distant, rises <pb n="107"/>a steep hill called Crag Fell, which at the lake becomes more abrupt, particularly at Angling Stone, a huge rock, rising perpendicularly out of the water, and overshadowed by Anglebarrow Crag. A foot road from Ennerdale Bridge is continued along the margins of the lake to its head, and thence to Gillerthwaite, affording some pleasing views.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">ENNERDALE WATER</head>
<p>Is 2 &#189; miles in length, and varies from a quarter to three-quarters of a mile in breadth. It is completely enclosed, except on the west side, by mountains, which descend rapidly to the water. It abounds with trout, and contains char, but of an inferior kind to those found in the other lakes.</p>
<p>At the eastern extremity of the lake is a narrow tract of cultivated ground called GILLERTHWAITE, which forms a remarkable contrast to the barren mountains surrounding it. It contains but one or two farm-houses, situated a mile and a half from Ennerdale Water, and 5 &#189; miles from Ennerdale Bridge. The river which runs through this tract is here called the Liza, though, after passing through the lake, it takes the name of Ehen. In its course between Gillerthwaite and the lake, it receives a stream, on which, about two miles from the lake, are several small water-falls; they are, however, difficult to access.</p>
<p>The best view of Ennerdale Water is procured at How Hall, but tourists are usually satisfied with that obtained in the road from Calder Bridge. HOW HALL is delightfully situated on the hill-side, near the east end of the lake, about 4 miles from Ennerdale Bridge. <pb n="108"/>It was once a mansion of some note, belonging to the Patricksons, and afterwards to the Senhouse family. According to the inscription in Saxon characters, placed over the principal door, it was erected about the middle of the sixteenth century.</p>
<p>From Ennerdale Water, the pedestrian might proceed through the valley of Gillerthwaite, by the pass called the Scarf Gap, to Buttermere, or by the Black Sail to Wastdale Head. Amongst the mountains of this dreary region, Stye Head, Honister Crag, the Pillar, and Red Pike, are conspicuous.</p>
<p>Proceeding on his route for a mile and a half, the tourist passes by a few houses called Kirkland, and in another mile and a half reaches LAMPLUGH CROSS, where there is a public-house. About a mile farther is the village of LAMPLUGH, with its Church and Hall. The latter has been rebuilt as a farm-house, and the only vestige of the original edifice is a gateway. A short distance beyond the church, the road enters a common, from which there is a view of the mountains Ben Garon and Scrifell in Scotland. The little lake on the left is Moucheron Tarn; and the heights on the right are Knock Morton and Blake Fell. The road then turns round a hill to the right, and commands a good view of Lowes Water, along the western side of which it proceeds to Scale Hill.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">LOWES WATER</head>
<p>Is a mile in length, and about a quarter of a mile in breadth. It is surrounded by noble mountains, the lower parts of which are covered with wood. It differs from the other lakes, having its course from north to <pb n="109"/>south, and falls into Crummock Water. Viewed from the north end, Lowes Water presents a prospect of mountain grandeur; but, when seen from the lofty Melbreak, at its southern extremity, it assumes a totally different character, and exhibits a scene of rural beauty, the sloping hills being well cultivated, and adorned with farm-houses. A fine evening view of Lowes Water and Crummock Water may be obtained from the side of Melbreak, in the road towards Ennerdale.</p>
<p>Lowes Water abounds with pike and perch. It also contains trout, but no char.</p>
<p>The following excursion may be made round Lowes Water from Scale Hill, if the tourist wishes to examine its various aspects. Pass Lowes Water Church, and several farm houses, to the Gill falling down the side of Carling Knott into the lake. Thence by High Water End -- Low Water End -- Crabtree Beck, back to Scale Hill, altogether about 7 miles.</p>
<p>From Scale Hill the tourist may visit Crummock and Buttermere Waters, if he has not yet seen them, and return to Keswick either by the Vale of Newlands, or by Lorton and Whinlatter, as before described.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="XII. From KESWICK to PENRITH.">
<head level="3" align="center">XII. From KESWICK to PENRITH.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Keswick to Threlkeld</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Threlkeld to Penruddock</td>
<td width="20%">7 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Penruddock to Penrith</td>
<td width="20%">6 &#190;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">18</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>The road, on leaving Keswick, skirts for about half a mile the borders of the river Greta.</p>
<p>To the left of the village of THRELKELD, SADDLEBACK rises 2787 feet in height; and to the right is the VALE OF ST. JOHN, an interesting object to every admirer of romantic beauty. It does not, however, appear so beautiful from this spot as from the road between Ambleside and Keswick. At its extremity is an immense rock, which, at a distance, bears a striking resemblance to an ancient fortress in ruins; hence it is called the Castle Rock of St. John's. This is the scene of Sir W. Scott's "Bridal of Triermain."</p>
<p>PENRUDDOCK. About 3 miles to the north, and visible from the high road, is GRAYSTROKE CASTLE, a seat belonging to the Honourable Mr. Howard. It is an ancient mansion, with an extensive park.</p>
<p>To the right of the road from Keswick to Penrith is situated Wester Mell Fell, a round hill of considerable elevation, from the top of which there is an extensive prospect. It forms a prominent object for some distance.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">PENRITH</head>
<p>Is a neat town, with about 6059 inhabitants. It is pleasantly situated in an open valley, a mile from the <pb n="111"/>junction of the Lowther and the Eamont. The houses are generally well-built, particularly near the centre of the principal street, which runs north and south, and forms part of the great high-road to Glasgow. There are several commodious inns, the principal of which are the New Crown and the George.</p>
<p>The Church was rebuilt in 1722, adjoining the ancient tower. It contains two chandeliers given to the inhabitants of Penrith by the Duke of Portland, as a reward for their loyalty in 1745. On one of the walls is an inscription commemorative of the ravages made by the plague in the reign of Elizabeth.</p>
<p>In the churchyard is a curious monument, called the Giant's Grave. It consists of two upright stone pillars, 10 feet in height, and 15 feet from each other, In the direction of east and west; and four semicircular stones, two on each side of the grave, sunk into the ground. Various opinions have been entertained respecting the origin of this tomb, but none of them have been very satisfactory. Tradition asserts it to have been formed in memory of C&#230;sareus, a gigantic hero, whose body is said to have extended from stone to stone. He is supposed to have lived in the time of Ida, one of the Saxon kings, and to have cleared Inglewood Forest of the wild boars with which it was infested. Near this monument is another pillar, called the Giant's Thumb. It is about 6 feet in height.</p>
<p>The Castle stands upon an eminence on the west side of the town. It was built about the time of Edward IV., and was formerly a place of great strength. It was for some time the residence of Richard III.; and, in the civil war, was dismantled by the troops of <pb n="112"/>the Commonwealth. It belongs, together with the honour of Penrith, to the Duke of Devonshire, who purchased it of the Duke of Portland in 1783.</p>
<p>The Beacon, a square stone building on a hill, about a mile north of the town, commands a view of extra-ordinary extent and beauty, presenting one vast theatre, upwards of 100 miles in circumference, encircled with stupendous mountains. The Northern window of the Beacon affords a prospect of Cross Fell, with the Dufton Pikes, and a chain of mountains extending from east to west about thirty miles; the western point sinking into the plain where the city of Carlisle lies. In the distance is a ridge of Scotch mountains. From the East window are seen the hills of Stainmore, Wildbore Fell, and its neighbouring mountains about Kirkby Stephen. The South window commands a view of Brougham Castle, with its plains of pasture, and Lowther Castle, with its spreading woods and undulating grounds. Some portions of Ullswater are also seen, with the mountains around its head. The West window overlooks the town and castle of Penrith, adn the windings of the river Eamont. In the extreme distance, Skiddaw rears its majestic summit. Six English, and several Scotch counties, may be seen from this spot. This building was erected as a watch-tower during the wars between the two kingdoms.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">ENVIRONS OF PENRITH.</head>
<p>The principal objects of curiosity in the immediate vicinity of Penrith may be viewed by making the following excursion: --</p>
<pb n="113"/>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Eamont Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Arthur's Round Table</td>
<td width="20%">&#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Mayburgh</td>
<td width="20%">&#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Return to Arthur's Round Table</td>
<td width="20%">&#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lowther Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">&#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Brougham Hall</td>
<td width="20%">&#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Countess's Pillar</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Brougham Castle</td>
<td width="20%">&#190;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Penrith</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>EAMONT BRIDGE crosses the river of the same name, which here forms the boundary between Cumberland and Westmoreland. On each side of it are houses, which together form a considerable village.</p>
<p>Contiguous to the road is ARTHUR'S ROUND TABLE, a curious monument of ancient times. It is a circular green spot, 29 yards in diameter, enclosed by a ditch and mound, both in sufficient preservation to show its original form. It is supposed to have been the scene of tournaments in the days of chivalry.</p>
<p>MAYBURGH, or MAYBOROUGH, to the west of Arthur's Round Table on the right of the summit of which is a circular enclosure, 100 yards in diameter, formed by a ridge of pebble-stones curiously constructed. Near the centre of the circle is a massive column of unhewn stone, 11 feet in height, and 22 feet in circumference about the middle. Some have supposed that Mayburgh was a Roman ampitheatre; and others, that it was a druidical temple or court of judicature.</p>
<p>The tourist then returns to Arthur's Round Table, a quarter of a mile beyond which is Lowther Bridge, crossing the river Lowther. Passing from the bridge <pb n="114"/>on the Appleby road, in front is seen Brougham Hall, partially obscured by trees.</p>
<p>BROUGHAM HALL, the seat of the celebrated statesman and orator, is a venerable fabric, erected at various periods, and surrounded by shrubberies and pleasure-grounds. From the terrace in front of the house, there are fine views.</p>
<p>Half a mile from Brougham Hall, is CLIPTON HALL, once the residence of the Wyberghs, now reduced to a solitary tower. From the rectory-house of Clifton there is a good view.</p>
<p>The COUNTESS's PILLAR is situated in Whinfield Park, about fifty yards beyond the third mile-stone on the old road of Appleby. It was erected in 1656, by Ann, Countess Dowager of Pembroke, in honour of her mother, Mary, Countess Dowager of Cumberland.</p>
<p>BROUGHAM CASTLE is a noble ruin, standing on the site of the ancient Brovoniacum, at the junction of the Eamont and the Lowther. This was formerly the castle of the Viponts, from whom it descended to the Cliffords, and thence to the Tuftons, Earls of Thanet, in whose family it still remains.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<p>Other Excursions may be made from Penrith to the following places: --GIANT'S CAVE, 3&#189; miles distant, situated on the banks of the Eamont. This cavern is said to have been inhabited, in former times, by a notorious robber.</p>
<p>LONG MEG AND HER DAUGHTERS, at Little Salkeld, 6 miles north-east from Penrith. This is one of the <pb n="115"/>most remarkable druidical circles in the north of England. It is situated on the top of a small hill, and is formed by 67 stones, many of which are 10 feet in height, and one of them 15.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">LOWTHER CASTLE,</head>
<p>The magnificent seat of the Earl of Lonsdale, and one of the finest mansions of England, is situated about 5 miles from Penrith. It is surrounded by an extensive and well-wooded park, on the banks of the river Lowther.</p>
<p>Lowther Castle was erected a few years since on the site of an old and decayed mansion, which had been partly destroyed by fire. The principal front, towards the north, presents numerous towers of different forms and elevation, surmounted with battlements, and pierced with slit windows, so as to resemble an ancient castle: it is 420 feet in length. That towards the south has a totally different character, being adorned with niches, pinnacles, and cloisters in the Gothic style. The views from the terrace, along the principal front, are beautiful.</p>
<p>The interior is fitted up in the Gothic style, and all the principal apartments display great taste. The staircase, which is 90 feet in height and 60 feet square, is particularly splendid; and many of the rooms are adorned with choice specimens of painting and sculpture. Strangers are allowed to see the interior every day.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="XIII. From PENRITH to ULLSWATER and PATTERDALE.">
<pb n="116"/>
<head level="3" align="center">XIII. From PENRITH to ULLSWATER and PATTERDALE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Penrith to Pooley Bridge, by Dalemain</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Pooley Bridge, by Watermillock, to Gowbarrow Park</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Gowbarrow Park to Patterdale</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Return to Penrith</td>
<td width="20%">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">30</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>From Penrith the tourist may proceed to Pooley Bridge, either by Eamont Bridge, Yanwath, and Tyrril, 5 miles; or along the Keswick road, and through the beautiful grounds of DALEMAIN, 6 miles. Of course, he may see both roads, by going one way and returning the other.</p>
<p>POOLEY BRIDGE, at the foot of Ullswater, is a small village, situated on the river Eamont, and much resorted to by fly-fishers during the fishing season. It has an inn called the Sun, where the tourist may be well accommodated. No post-horses, however, are kept; but saddle-horses and jaunting-cars may be obtained here, as well as boats for the lake. The charge for a boat with sculls to go up to the head of the lake and return, is 7<i>s.</i> 6<i>d.</i> or with oars, 10<i>s.</i></p>
<p>EUSEMERE, situated on the edge of the water a quarter of a mile from Pooley Bridge, is remarkable as having been built by Thomas Clarkson, Esq., whose exertions for the abolition of the Slave Trade are well known. He sold it to the Earl of Lonsdale. It commands a fine view of the first reach of the lake, backed by Hallen Fell and the receding mountains of Martindale and Glenridding.</p>
<pb n="117"/>
<p>Near Pooley Bridge is DUNMALLET, or DUNMALLARD, a small hill of conical shape, clothed with wood, forming a conspicuous feature in the scenery of Ullswater. Upon the summit are vestiges of a Roman fort, surrounded by a fosse, 100 paces by 37. This fort guarded the lake, and maintained the connexion between Ambleside and Brougham.</p>
<p>The summit of Dunmallet formerly commanded a fine view of Ullswater, but this is now completely obstructed by the woods. Mr. Gray's description of the lake is equally applicable, with a slight alteration, to the view obtained at the foot of this hill.</p>
<p>"The lake opened directly at my feet, majestic in its calmness, clear and smooth as a blue mirror, with winding shores, and low points of land, covered with green enclosures, white farm-houses looking out among the trees, and cattle feeding. The water is almost every where bordered with cultivated lands, gently sloping upwards, from a mile to a quarter of a mile in breadth, till they reach the feet of the mountains, which rise very rude and awful, with their broken tops on each hand. Directly in front, at better than three miles' distance, Hallen Fell, one of the bravest amongst them, pushes its bold breast into the midst of the lake, and forces it to alter its course, forming first a large bay to the left, and then bending to the right."</p>
<head level="3" align="center">ULLSWATER, or ULLESWATER,</head>
<p>Is the largest of the lakes, with the exception of Windermere; and is by many thought to combine the beauties of all the others. It has also the greatest <pb n="118"/>average depth; many parts, particularly towards the head, being from 20 to 35 fathoms. The lake is about 9 miles in length, and 1 in breadth, and abounds with fish, the principal of which are trout, eels, and skelly or gwiniads. A few char are likewise caught here, but they are not of the best quality. The water is clear, but not so transparent as that of Derwent Water, Buttermere, and Crummock.</p>
<p>Ullswater is surrounded on all sides, except the east, by ranges of mountains. Those towards the foot are of no great height, and chiefly cultivated and divided into farms; but, approaching the head of the lake, they assume a majestic form, rearing their rocky summits to the clouds. Here the mountains are intersected by several glens or small valleys, and their sides adorned with wood, producing a magnificent scene.</p>
<p>Part of the north shore of Ullswater is in Cumberland; the remaining portion, and the whole of the southern coast, are in Westmoreland.</p>
<p>The principal feeders of Ullswater are Grysdale Beck, at the western corner, and Goldrill Beck, which descends from Kirkstone Fell. The superfluous waters of the lake have their egress by the Eamont, at the north-east extremity.</p>
<p>The lake is of a zig-zag form, and may be said to be divided into three reaches, gradually improving in grandeur as the tourist advances towards the southern extremity.</p>
<p>The first is a fine sheet of water, about 3 miles in length, bounded on each side by gentle hills, the bases of which are enclosed and skirted with trees. On <pb n="118.3"/> <gap desc="Map of Ulls Water"/><gap desc="blank page"/><pb n="119"/>the left, proceeding up the lake from Pooley Bridge, is seen Swarth Fell -- in front, Hallen Fell, and on the right, a sloping shore, adorned with villas, amongst which appear Ramsbach or Rempsbeck Lodge, Beau Thorn, Lemon House, and Watermillock.</p>
<p>Passing round the promontory formed by Hallen Fell, we enter the second or middle reach, which is about 4 miles in length. On the right are seen Hall-steads, the seat of John Marshall, Esq., M.P.; Gowbarrow Park, belonging to the Honourable Mr. Howard; and Lyulph's Tower: on the left are Hallen Fell, Birk Fell, and Place Fell. In front rises the lofty Helvellyn.</p>
<p>The third, or upper reach, which is 2 miles in length, presents an exquisite combination of mountain and valley, lake and wood, far transcending in beauty the other parts of Ullswater. On the left is the dark and steep Place Fell; on the right, Stybarrow Crag, and some ridges of Helvellyn and Fairfield, amongst which a bold hill, called St. Sunday Crag, appears conspicuous; and in front, at the head of the lake, the valley of Patterdale. In this part of Ullswater are four small islands, called Cherry Holme, Wall Holme, Ling Holme, and House Holme. The last is a good station for viewing the adjacent scenery.</p>
<p>From Pooley Bridge the tourist may either take a boat and go up to the lake to Patterdale, as just described, landing at Lyulph's Tower, and visiting Airey Force, which is half a mile distant; or he may proceed by the carriage-road, which passes along the north-west shore of the lake, to Patterdale.</p>
<p>Pursuing the latter course, he leaves the village of <pb n="120"/>Pooley; and, crossing the bridge over the Eamont, arrives at the foot of DUNMALLET, already described. From this spot, there is a good view of the lake, along the margin of which the road passes. On the right is WATERFOOT, a handsome villa, rebuilt in 1829. Beyond, appears SOULBY FELL, clothed with wood; and behind it, MAIDEN CASTLE, formerly occupied as a Benedictine nunnery.</p>
<p>In his progress, the tourist passes several handsome villas, particularly RAMSBACH or REMPSBECK LODGE, in front of which is a lawn, sloping towards a wood on the shore of the lake.</p>
<p>About a mile farther is WATERMILLOCK, a most beautiful mansion, surrounded by beech and sycamore trees. The views from the several windows are said to differ both in objects and character.</p>
<p>A little beyond is BEAU THORN, sheltered by a plantation of white thorns, from which it derives its name. Half a mile further is LEMON HOUSE, fronting the opening into Martindale.</p>
<p>The road then leaves on the left the farm of OLD CHURCH, so called from having been erected on the site of an ancient place of worship. On the opposite side of the lake is seen the barren and almost perpendicular mountain of SWARTH FELL, down which the Swarth Beck pours its waters. In wet weather, the torrent forms numerous cascades, the noise of which may be heard at a considerable distance. The mountain is rendered remarkable by the almost miraculous escape of the late E. Hasell, Esq., the proprietor of Dalemain. Having, in the ardour of the chase, descending into a perilous situation, from which it was <pb n="121"/>impossible to return, he dismounted, and leaning against the side of his horse, supported by and supporting each other, they slid down the side of the mountain, and reached the bottom in safety. No person is known to have descended the mountain either before or since that time.</p>
<p>On a fine promontory to the left of the road, is HALLSTEADS, the seat of John Marshall, Esq., M.P., an elegant mansion, surrounded by beautifully undulated grounds. It stands upon a gentle eminence and commands a fine view of the lake. Beyond Hallsteads, the road runs at first near, and seldom far from the lake, till it again approaches it closely at YEW CRAG, a noble rocky prominence, about half way between the head and foot of Ullswater, covered with picturesque trees, forming a fine subject for the sketch book.</p>
<p>GOWBARROW PARK, through which the road passes for about 3 miles, was formerly the property of the Duke of Norfolk, who bequeathed it to the Honourable Mr. Howard. It comprises about 1800 acres, and contains several hundred deer, besides sheep and cattle. Many of the oaks and thorns with which it is adorned are of great age.</p>
<p>In Gowbarrow Park is LYULPH'S TOWER, a hunting box, erected by the late Duke of Norfolk. It is a plain building, in the castellated style, having four towers, battlements, and Gothic windows. Its name is said to be derived from Lyulphus, an Anglo-Saxon, who was killed at the time of the Conquest. It is now occupied by the keeper of the park, to whom <pb n="122"/>application must be made in order to see Airey Force. The views from this station are beautiful.</p>
<p>From Lyulph's Tower a path winds, for about half a mile, through a deep glen, to</p>
<head level="3" align="center">AIREY, or ARA FORCE.</head>
<p>This cascade is entirely the work of nature, and is completely secluded by rocks and trees. The whole height of the fall is about 80 feet. The water being previously compressed in a chasm of the rock, rushes forth with great violence: in dry weather, it is divided at the top into two streams, which unite before they have fallen half way down, and dash against a projecting rock, from which they are thrown off in sheets of foam. In wet weather it forms but one stream. When the sun is shining in a favourable direction, the spray exhibits all the colours of the rainbow. A circuitous path leads to the top of the fall, from which the view is fearful. The visiter may return by a different path to Lyulph's Tower.</p>
<p>The whole space from Gowbarrow Park to Patterdale is one rich but varied display of luxuriant foliage: oak, ash, birch, and alder here flourish in the wildest manner, overhanging with their branches the rocky projections which start from the mountains in every direction.</p>
<p>At the end of Gowbarrow Park is the farm of GLENCOYNE, or GLENCOIN, situated in a beautiful valley, through which flows a streamlet, dividing the counties of Cumberland and Westmoreland. Glencoyne signifies glen in a corner.</p>
<p>STYBARROW CRAG then comes in view. This is <pb n="123"/>a rugged and lofty hill, covered with oaks, which grow out of its crevices. It forms a fine object when seen from the lake, out of which it rises abruptly.</p>
<p>A little further, at the foot of the valley of GLENRIDDING, is the tasteful cottage of Rev. Mr. Askew, beyond which the road winds round the head of Ullswater to the village of Patterdale. The little stream, which runs down the valley of Glenridding, forms several pretty cascades. It is supplied from KEPPLE COVE TARN and RED TARN, two little lakes near the top of Helvellyn.</p>
<p>PATTERDALE HALL, at the head of the lake, is a modern-built mansion, surrounded by plantations. It was formerly the residence of the Mounseys, who were styled Kings of Patterdale. This appellation, it is said, they received on account of the gallant action performed by one of the family, who, assisted by a few shepherds, defeated a numerous band of Scotch robbers at the pass of Stybarrow Crag.</p>
<p>PATTERDALE has a good inn, where post-horses are kept, situated about half a mile from the head of the lake. Opposite to it, on the side of Place Fell, and only half a mile distant, is a slate-quarry, from the edge of which there is a fine view of the mountains and of a part of the lake. From this spot may be seen the summit of Helvellyn. On the rock immediately behind the inn, and a small cannon is kept for the purpose of showing the effect of the echo. The sound of each discharge is repeated six or seven times. Mr. Hutchinson, who visited Ullswater some years ago, when the Duke of Portland's pleasure barge was <pb n="124"/>there, thus describes the impression produced by a discharge of cannon: -- </p>
<p>"Whilst we sat to regale, the barge put off from shore to a station where the finest echoes were to be obtained from the surrounding mountains. The vessel was provided with six brass cannon mounted on swivels: on discharging one of these pieces, the report was echoed from the opposite rocks, where, by reverberation, it seemed to roll from cliff to cliff, and return through every cave and valley, till the decreasing tumult gradually died away upon the ear. The instant it had ceased, the sound of every distant waterfall was heard but for an instant only; for the momentary stillness was interrupted by the returning echo on the hills behind; where the report was repeated like a peal of thunder bursting over our heads, continuing for several seconds, flying from haunt to haunt, till once more the sounds gradually declined; again the voice of waterfalls possessed the interval, till, to the right, the more distant thunder arose upon some other mountain, and seemed to take its way up every winding fell and creek, sometimes behind, on this side or on that, in wondrous speed running its dreadful course. When the echo reached the mountains within the line and channel of the breeze, it was heard at once on the right and left, at the extremities of the lake. In this manner was the report of every discharge re-echoed seven times distinctly."</p>
<p>From Patterdale, an excursion may be made on foot to GRISEDALE, or GRAYDALE TARN, 4 miles distant, situated at the junction of the three mountains <pb n="125"/>Helvellyn, Seatsandal, and Fairfield; and thence to Grasmere Church, 4 miles more.</p>
<p>The tourist may return to Penrith by the same route that he came; or proceed by BROTHER'S WATER, and across KESWICK to Ambleside, as described in Supplement No. 1.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="XIV. From PENRITH to HAWES WATER.">
<pb n="126"/>
<head level="3" align="center">XIV. From PENRITH to HAWES WATER.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Penrith to Eamont Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Eamont Bridge to Askham</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Askham to Bampton</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Bampton to Hawes Water</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Return to Penrith</td>
<td width="20%">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">24</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>Leaving Penrith, the tourist turns to the right at Arthur's Round Table, between the rivers Eamont and Lowther, and passes through ASKHAM, to the left of which is Lowther Castle, BUTTERWICK, and BAMPTON, long celebrated for its free-school, which was founded in 1623, by Dr. Sutton, a native of this parish. The church at Bampton is a neat building, erected in 1726. There are two inns.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">HAWES WATER</head>
<p>Is about 3 miles in length, and varies in breadth from a quarter a half a mile. Near the middle, at a place called Measand, the banks approach so near to each other that the lake is almost divided into two distinct parts. On the side of the promontory which is thus formed, rushes Fordingdale Beck, a stream abounding with picturesque waterfalls. This lake is seldom visited, though it is distinguished by the solemn grandeur of its rock and mountain scenery. Amongst the mountains which rise above the head of the lake are Harter Fell, Kidsey Pike, and High Street. The country below the foot of the lake consists of gentle <pb n="127"/>eminences covered with wood, and extending the Lowther and Askham.</p>
<p>Hawes Water may be viewed to most advantage by passing along the horse road upon the common a little above the carriage road. It presents, however, some fine views from the latter, as well as from many situations in the enclosures between the two roads.</p>
<p>A mile beyond the head of Hawes Water is CHAPEL HILL, consisting of the few modern houses, and a little further is MARDALE GREEN, where there is an inn called the White Bull. The views from the parsonage at Mardale are interesting. It is remarkable that the Holme family has resided here ever since the reign of King John.</p>
<p>RIGGENDALE forms a craggy descent from the mountain of High Street down to the Bridge between Chapel Hill and Mardale Green. It may be said to divide the vale of desolation from that of fertility; for between Riggendale and the lake the river passes through level and cultivated lands. These are succeeded by easy undulations and rocky knolls, over which the native trees are scattered, while others climb the rugged steeps towards the top of the adjacent mountains.</p>
<p>Hawes Water belongs to the Earl of Lonsdale. It abounds with perch, trout, eels, and chub. The char caught here are few in number and inferior in quality.</p>
<p>The tourist may then return to Penrith by the same route, of, if on horseback, take that across Dovack Moor, indicated in Supplement No. 16.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<p>In the preceding pages we have given a "Tour of the Lakes," which points out the best mode of viewing them; but as many persons may wish to deviate from this plan, we shall subjoin, in a Supplement, an account of other routes, and thus render this volume a complete Guide for the Tourist, whatever course he may wish to pursue.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="SUPPLEMENT">
<head level="3" align="center">SUPPLEMENT.</head>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">1. From AMBLESIDE to ULLSWATER, and PENRITH.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ambleside to Kirkstone</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Kirkstone to Brothers' Water</td>
<td width="20%">2 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Brothers' Water to Patterdale</td>
<td width="20%">3 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Patterdale to Gowbarrow Park</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Gowbarrow Park to Pooley Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Pooley Bridge to Penrith</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">25</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>This route is no so favourable for viewing Ullswater as that previously described; because it leads the tourist at once to the head of the lake, from which the beauty of the scenery gradually declines towards the foot.</p>
<p>The road is rough, but passable for carriages. It crosses the mountain to KIRKSTONE, the ascent and descent of which are very steep. At the brow of the hill, on the left of the road, is a large stone, said to resemble a church without a spire, and hence it has received the name of Kirk Stone. From the small moor at the summit of Kirkstone, which is 1200 feet above Ambleside, there is a fine view, including the head of Windermere, and the mountains of Langdale.</p>
<p>After descending the hill about four hundred yards, the tourist perceives, on the left, a part of Scandale Fell with bold projecting rocks hanging on its side, <pb n="130"/>and on the right Colddale Fell, presenting steep shiverings of stone. In a deep bottom between the two, lies Brothers' Water, with stripes of enclosed land at each extremity, and woods of Hartshope Hall rising from it. The distance is formed by Place Fell and other mountains near the head of Ullswater. From this spot the lake is alternately seen and lost all the way to the bottom of the hill, where a retrospective view is obtained from a projection of Scandale Fell, on the conical summit of which is a <i>pike</i> called Kirkstone Dodd. In the opening on the left is seen a large mass of rock called Dove Crag.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">BROTHERS' WATER.</head>
<p>This small lake is situated in that part of Patterdale called Hartshope. It is said to have derived its name from the circumstance of two brothers having been drowned together, many years ago, by the breaking of the ice. This, however, seems doubtful, as the ancient name of the lake was Broader Water, and the present is not unlikely to be a corruption. The views surrounding Brothers' Water are grand; and the adjacent vale is fertile and well-wooded.</p>
<p>The principal feeders of Brothers' Water are Kirkstone Beck, which forms a number of little waterfalls on the right and left as the traveller proceeds down the road to the valley; and the beck, which rises at Dove Crag, an immense rock, 3 miles to the west of the lake, and passes by Hartshope Hall.</p>
<p>Beyond Brothers' Water the road leaves the village of HARTSHOPE on the right, and twice crosses the Goldrill in its passage down the valley to Patterdale.</p>
<pb n="131"/>
<p>About 2 miles east of Brothers' Water is situated HAYS WATER, which is much frequented by anglers. A small stream descending from it, passes Low Hartshope, and joins the rivulet issuing from Brothers' Water shortly after its egress. ANGLE TARN, lying to the north of Hays Water, also supplies a stream which makes a rapid descent to the valley, half a mile lower down. Both these tarns are famous for trout.</p>
<p>From Patterdale the tourist may hire a boat to go down the lake, or proceed along the shore to Pooley Bridge, reversing the description given in Route XIII.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">From BOWNESS to CONISTON WATER and AMBLESIDE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Bowness to Ferry House</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ferry House to Sawrey</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Sawrey to Hawkshead</td>
<td width="20%">2 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Hawkshead to Coniston Water Head</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Waterhead to Borwick</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Borwick to Ambleside</td>
<td width="20%">4 &#190;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">16 &#189;</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>Or,</p>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%">Hawkshead direct to Ambleside</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
</table>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">3. From KENDAL to AMBLESIDE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%">Kendal to Stavely</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Stavely to Ings</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ings to Orrest Head</td>
<td width="20%">2 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Orrest Head to Troutbeck Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#190;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Troutbeck Bridge to Low Wood Inn</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Low Wood Inn to Ambleside</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">14</td>
</tr>
</table>
<pb n="132"/>
<p>From ORREST HEAD there is a fine view of Windermere, with all its mazy windings and massive woods, its verdant plains and rocky mountains. About a mile to the right is ELLERAY, belonging to Professor Wilson. "Here," says the Ettick Shepherd, "a number of my very best things were written." Elleray commands a view of both ends of Windermere, a circumstance with distinguishes it from every other villa in the neighbourhood.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">4. From KENDAL to BOWNESS.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Kendal to Bonning Yate</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Bonning Yate to Quakers' Meeting House</td>
<td width="20%">2 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Quakers' Meeting House to Clay Barrow</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Clay Barrow to Bowness</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">9</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>This route presents many pleasing views. The lake of Windermere first bursts upon the eye about a mile and a quarter on this side of Bowness. Here it is seen spotted with its pretty islands, and skirted by shores ornamented with a luxuriant abundance of wood. Proceeding, the traveller will soon perceive Bowness and the lake beyond it, lying in the valley beneath; the Rydal mountains raise their heads at a considerable distance.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<pb n="133"/>
<head level="3" align="center">From KENDAL to HAWES WATER, by LONG SLEDDALE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Kendal to Watch Gate</td>
<td width="20%">4 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Watch Gate to Long Sleddale Chapel</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Long Sleddale Chapel to Sadgill Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Sadgill Bridge to Chapel Hill at the head of Hawes Water</td>
<td width="20%">4 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">14</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>In taking this route to Hawes Water, the tourist must pursue the high road towards Penrith as far as WATCH GATE, and there turn into a bye road, on the left, which leads to Long Sleddale.</p>
<p>LONG SLEDDALE is a long, narrow, and deep vale, enclosed by high ridges of rocky mountains. At the bottom is a strip of meadow ground, through which flows a large brook. Near the entrance of the valley is a small Chapel, for the neighbouring peasantry; and towards its head are seen many conspicuous rocks, one of which, on the right, called CROWBARROW, or BACKBARROW, had a grand appearance. After wet weather, cascades are seen tumbling down the heights in various directions. Many of the farm-houses and cottages in this dale would form pretty subjects for the artist.</p>
<p>Great quantities of blue slate are obtained in Long Sleddale. The tourist, on approaching the quarries, may perhaps deem it worth while to turn a little out of the way in order to visit them. They are very easy of access, as the levels made for the conveyance of the <pb n="134"/>slate are not so silly as in some other places. On ascending from the quarries there is a fine retrospective view of Long Sleddale, with Lancaster Sands in the distance.</p>
<p>The tourist then passes SADGILL BRIDGE, and some distance beyond it sees on the left the road which descends from Kentmere Tarn to Hawes Water. From the junction of the two roads to CHAPEL HILL it is about a mile.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">6. From KENDAL to PENRITH.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Kendal to Demmings</td>
<td width="20%">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Demmings to Shap</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Shap to Lowther Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">8 &#190;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lowther Bridge to Eamont Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">&#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Eamont to Bridge to Penrith</td>
<td width="20%">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">26 &#188;</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>SHAP is a small market-town of Westmoreland, with about 1061 inhabitants. It is situated at a short distance from the source of the Lowther. <i>Inns,</i> the Greyhound and the King's Arms.</p>
<p>About a mile distant are the remains of SHAP or HEPPE ABBEY, which was erected in the reign of King John. The ruins are inconsiderable, but picturesque. Near them are a number of upright stones, which appear to have formed a Druidical temple.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<pb n="135"/>
<head level="3" align="center">7. From KENDAL to ULVERSTONE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Kendal to Crossthwaite Green</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Crossthwaite Green to Stavely</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Stavely to Ulverstone</td>
<td width="20%">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">19</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>About a mile and half from Kendal, on the roa towards Crossthwaite Green, is <i>Scout-Scar,</i> a high rock, on which is a terrace, about a mile in length, facing the west, and commanding a fine view.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">8. From KESWICK to BUTTERMERE, CRUMMOCK WATER, LOWES WATER, ENNERDALE WATER, and WAST WATER,</head>
<p align="center">IN A CARRIAGE IN THREE DAYS.</p>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%">Keswick to Buttermere, by Vale of Newlands</td>
<td width="20%">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Buttermere to Scale Hill</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Scale Hill to Lowes Water</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lowes Water to Lamplugh</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lamplugh to Ennerdale Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ennerdale Bridge to Calder Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">First day</td>
<td width="20%" align="right">29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Calder Bridge to Gosforth</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Gosforth to Strands</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Strands, along the north side of Wast Water</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Return to Calder Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%" align="right">Second Day</td>
<td width="20%">26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Return to Keswick, Third Day</td>
<td width="20%">29</td>
</tr>
</table>
<pb n="136"/>
<p>From Buttermere the tourist may visit SCALE FORCE, on the side of Crummock Water.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">9. From KESWICK to ULLSWATER and PENRITH, by DACRE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Keswick to Threlkeld</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Threlkeld to Penruddock</td>
<td width="20%">7 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Penruddock to Dacre</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Dacre to Pooley Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Pooley Bridge to Penrith</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">23 &#188;</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>DACRE CASTLE is a building of considerable antiquity, in a tolerably perfect state. It was for ages the baronial seat of the Dacre family. The Church is at a short distance.</p>
<p>Or,</p>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%">Pooley Bridge to Lowther</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lowther to Penrith</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">10</td>
</tr>
</table>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">10. From KESWICK to ULLSWATER and PENRITH, by PATTERDALE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%">Keswick to Threlkeld</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Threlkeld to Beckses</td>
<td width="20%">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Beckses to Gowbarrow Park</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Gowbarrow Park to Patterdale</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Patterdale to Pooley Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Pooley Bridge to Penrith</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">37</td>
</tr>
</table>
<pb n="137"/>
<head level="3" align="center">11. From LANCASTER to KENDAL, by BOLTON LE SANDS.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lancaster to Bolton by the Sands</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Bolton to Carnforth</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Carnforth to Millthorpe</td>
<td width="20%">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Millthorpe to Levens</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Levens to Sizergh</td>
<td width="20%">1 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Sizergh to Kendal</td>
<td width="20%">3 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">20 &#190;</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>On leaving Lancaster, the road crosses the Lune, and, about a mile from the town, passes over the Lancaster Canal.</p>
<p>BOLTON BY THE SANDS is so called from its situation near the Lancaster Sands. Near it the tourist will obtain fine views of Morecambe Bay and the surrounding mountains.</p>
<p>CARNFORTH. About 2 miles from this village is DUNALD MILL HOLE, a subterranean cavern, resembling those of Derbyshire. A brook runs in at its mouth, forming several pretty cascades, and continues its course under the mountain as far as Carnforth. Persons may descend into this cave, and follow the stream for some distance. The sides and roof are adorned with curious petrifactions.</p>
<p>MILLTHORPE, or MILNTHORPE, is a small market-town, with 1509 inhabitants. It is the only sea-port in Westmoreland having the advantage of the tide, which flows from the Kent up the Betha. The principal shipping business consists in the conveyance of <pb n="138"/>goods to Liverpool, Glasgow, and London. <i>Inn,</i> the Cross Keys.</p>
<p>At LEVENE, the tourist crosses the Kent. This river takes its rise in the Vale of Kentmere, where small springs issue from the mountains which surround the dale, and are collected in a small lake or mere, whence the name of Kentmere is derived. From this lake proceeds the river Kent, which, being joined by the rivers of Applethwaite, Longsleddale, and Grayrigg, becomes a powerful stream when it arrives near Kendal, where it is employed in giving motion to several mills. As t descends Southwards towards Levens, its banks are ornamented by beautiful woods and rich grounds, which afford a variety of delightful walks and picturesque scenery. The river abounds with excellent trout. LEVENS HALL, the property of the Honourable Mr. Howard, is a charming residence, surrounded by a park, through which there is a beautiful walk to Kendal. This mansion was built in the reign of Elizabeth. It was the ancient seat of the Bellinghams.</p>
<p><i>Sizergh Hall,</i> the family-seat of the Stricklands, is a fine specimen of the ancient castellated hall, and is surrounded by splendid woods.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">KENDAL.</head>
<p>Kendal, or Kirkby in Kendal, (the church in the vale of Ken,) is the largest town in Westmoreland. It is situated in a pleasant valley on the banks of the Ken or Kent, and contains about 10,015 inhabitants. The prinicpal street is about a mile in length. The houses are all built of stone, and roofed with blue slates.</p>
<pb n="139"/>
<p>The church is a spacious Gothic structure, with a square tower, containing ten bells. It has three chapels, memorials of the ancient dignity of three neighbouring families, the Bellinghams, Stricklands, and Parrs. On a brass-plate before the communion-table is the following very curious inscription, in memory of the Rev. R. Tirer, the vicar of Kendal, who died in 1627. It was written by himself: --</p>
<poem>
<line>London bred me, Westminster fed me,</line>
<line>Cambridge sped me, my Sister wed me,</line>
<line>Study taught me, Living sought me,</line>
<line>Learning brought me, Kendal caught me,</line>
<line>Labour pressed me, Sickness distressed me,</line>
<line>Death oppressed me, and Grave possessed me,</line>
<line>God first gave me, Christ did save me,</line>
<line>Earth did crave me, and Heaven would have me.</line>
</poem>
<p>There are also monuments in honour of Judge Wilson, and Romney the painter.</p>
<p>Upon a hill on the east side of the river are the remains of the Castle, beautifully situated, and commanding a fine prospect. It is supposed to occupy the site of a Roman fort. This castle formerly belonged the the Parr family, and was the birth-place of Catherine, the last queen of Henry VIII.</p>
<p>On the western side of the town is CASTLELAW HILL, an artificial mount, about 30 feet in height, supposed by some to be of Saxon, and by others, or Roman origin. On its summit is an Obelisk, erected in 1788, by the inhabitants of Kendal, to commemorate the Glorious Revolution of 1688. This hill was probably one of those on which justice was formerly administered.</p>
<p>Mr. Todhunter's Museum is another object worthy <pb n="140"/> of the tourist's attention. It contains specimens of minerals and vegetables found in Cumberland and Westmoreland, as well as collection of shells.</p>
<p>The Free School was founded in 1525 by Adam Pennyngton, and rebuilt in 1592.</p>
<p>Kendal has long been noted for its manufacture of coarse woollens, called Kendal cottons, linseys, serges, druggets, knit worsted stockings, hats, and leather. The manufacture of finer articles, such as fancy waist-coats, has also been introduced; and the marble obtained in the vicinity is cut and polished here.</p>
<p>The Canal opened between Lancaster and Kendal in 1819, enables the town to communicate with the principal rivers and towns of Lancashire, Yorkshire, and other parts of England.</p>
<p>Kendal is a corporate town, governed by a mayor, 12 aldermen, and 20 burgesses. It has a well-supplied market, held on Saturday; and two good Inns, the King's Arms, and the Commercial Inn.</p>
<p>From Kendal there is a stage-coach every morning, except Sunday, passing through Ambleside and Keswick to Whitehaven.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<pb n="141"/>
<head level="3" align="center">12. LANCASTER to KENDAL by BURTON.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lancaster to Burton</td>
<td width="20%">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Burton to Kendal</td>
<td width="20%">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">22</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p><i>Burton</i> is a small town of Westmoreland, with about 733 inhabitants. <i>Inns,</i> the King's Arms, the Royal Oak.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">13. From LANCASTER to KENDAL by KIRKBY LONSDALE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lancaster to Hornby</td>
<td width="20%">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Hornby to Kirkby Lonsdale</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Kirkby Lonsdale to Kendal</td>
<td width="20%">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">29</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>From a spot on the south side of the road, 3 miles beyond Lancaster, there is a fine view of the valley of the Lune, with Ingleborough towering over its head.</p>
<p>HORNBY, in Lancashire, is situated on the Lune. About half a mile distant is HORNBY CASTLE, which once belonged to the Barons Mounteagle, is allusion to whom one of its towers is surmounted by the figure of an eagle. This castle commands a fine view.</p>
<p>KIRKBY LONSDALE, in Westmoreland, is a small but neat town, with about 1686 inhabitants. It is situated on the Lune, over which is an ancient but elegant <pb n="142"/>bridge. The church is old, and the churchyard is celebrated for its commanding situation: it affords a fine view of the valley of the Lune. The free-school was founded in 1591 and rebuilt in 1628. Here also are several mills, worked by a brook, the waters of which give motion to seven wheels, placed one above another.</p>
<p><i>Inns, </i>the Rose and Crown; the Green Dragon.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">14. From LANCASTER to ULVERSTONE, AVOIDING THE SANDS.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Lancaster to Millthorpe, by the New Road</td>
<td width="20%">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Millthorpe to Levens</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Levens to Witherslack</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Witherslack to Newton</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Newton to Newby Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Newby Bridge to Bouth</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Bouth to Penny Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Penny Bridge to Ulverstone</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">36</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>This route abounds with interesting landscapes, and commands several fine views of the sea.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<pb n="143"/>
<head level="3" align="center">15. From PENRITH to CARLISLE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Penrith to Plumpton Wall</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Plumpton Wall to High Hesket</td>
<td width="20%">4 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">High Hesket to Carleton</td>
<td width="20%">6 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Carleton to Carlisle</td>
<td width="20%">2 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">18</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>On the left of PLUMPTON are the ruins of OLD PENRITH, formerly a Roman station. Traces of the fort are still visible. It was 168 paces from south to north, and 110 from east to west. It is situated about 200 yards from the river Peterill. Some have supposed that it was this station which was called Petriana. The Roman road leading to Pict's Wall took the same direction as the present road.</p>
<p>HIGH HESKET is a large village half-way between Penrith and Carlisle. On its east side is Tarn Wadling, a lake covering about a hundred acres of land. On the top of this eminence, on the N.E. side of this lake, are the ruins of a fortress, called Castle Hewins, from which there is a good view. The period at which this building was erected is unknown.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">CARLISLE,</head>
<p>the capital of Cumberland, is an ancient city, pleasantly situated amidst extensive and fertile meadows, watered by the Eden, the Caldew, and the Peteril, which nearly surrounding it. It was a Roman station, and an important military post during the wars between the Scotch and the English. The streets are spacious and well-built, and there are about 20,006 inhabitants.</p>
<pb n="144"/>
<p>The Castle is said to have been originally built towards the end of the seventh century. Some portions of it, erected in the reign of William II., still remain. In the apartments of this castle, Mary Queen of Scots was confined.</p>
<p>The Court-houses at the south entrance of the city, give it a majestic appearance. They were erected in 1810, from designs by Smirke, and are adorned with two noble circular towers, erected on the site of similar ones which formerly defended the city gate. Contiguous to them is the gaol.</p>
<p>The Catherdral is a venerable structure, partly of Saxon and partly of Gothic architecture. The choir, erected in the reigns of Edward III. and Richard II., is a fine specimen of the pointed style. On the screens of the aisles are some paintings representing events in the legendary histories of St. Anthony and St. Augustine. Here Dr. Paley was buried.</p>
<p>The Bridge over the Eden is a handsome structure, built in 1817.</p>
<p>Carlisle has improved very much in wealth and population during the last century, and now holds a respectable rank among the trading towns. It has manufactures of cotton articles, printed linens, hats, whips, leather, fish-hooks, and soap.</p>
<p>From Carlisle there is a ship-canal to the Solway Frith, by means of which the commerce of the city is much facilitated. The market-days are Wednesday and Saturday.</p>
<p>The principal <i>Inns</i>are the Bush, the Blue Bell, and the Coffee House.</p>
<pb n="145"/>
<head level="3" align="center">16. From PENRITH to HAWES WATER,  and return by POOLEY BRIDGE.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Penrith to Askham</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Askham, by Bampton, to Hawes Water</td>
<td width="20%">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Hawes Water, by Bampton, to Butterwick</td>
<td width="20%">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Butterwick, over Dovack Moor, to Pooley Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Pooley Bridge, by Dalemain, to Penrith</td>
<td width="20%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">27</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>The route across Dovack Moor is only practicable on horseback or on foot.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">17. From POOLEY BRIDGE to HAWES WATER.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%">Pooley Bridge to Askham</td>
<td width="20%">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Askham to Hawes Water</td>
<td width="20%">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Return to Pooley Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">20</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>This route will be found available for those persons who wish to go in a carriage from Pooley Bridge to Hawes Water.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">18. From ULVERSTONE to BOWNESS.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%">Ulverstone to Newby Bridge</td>
<td width="20%">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Newby Bridge to Bowness</td>
<td width="20%">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">17</td>
</tr>
</table>
<pb n="146"/>
<p>About 3 miles from Ulverstone the road crosses the river Crake, near its junction with the Leven; and 3 miles farther, passes a gunpowder-manufactory.</p>
<p>At BACKBARROW, a mile farther, are iron-works and a cotton-factory. Here the road passes over the Leven.</p>
<p>NEWBY BRIDGE crosses the Leven just at is egress from Windermere. <i>Inn.</i> --The Swan; where boats, post-horses, and a chaise may be hired. This bridge is delightfully situated at the foot of a wooded hill of considerable elevation. The Leven is here a noble stream, from this place, in a course of four miles, winds between lofty side-screens to the river Crake on Leven Sands. It is a good stream for fly-fishing.</p>
<p>The tourist then proceeds to Bowness, the road commanding fine views of Windermere and of the neighbouring mountains.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">19. From WHITEHAVEN to KESWICK.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Whitehaven to Cockermouth</td>
<td width="20%">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Cockermouth to Keswick, by the New Road</td>
<td width="20%">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">27</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>This and the following route are given for the benefit of travellers who arrive at the lake district by steam-packets which proceed from Liverpool to Workington and Whitehaven.</p>
<p>WHITEHAVEN is a handsome and well-built town of Cumberland, with about 11,393 inhabitants. During <pb n="147"/>the last two centuries, it has risen into importance in consequence of its vicinity to the collieries belonging to the Lowther family. The pits are the deepest that have hitherto been worked, and they produce annually about 90,000 chaldrons of coals. The harbour is defended by stone piers. The Earl of Lonsdale has a handsome mansion here, called the Castle.</p>
<p>Whitehaven has three Episcopal Chapels, several Meeting Houses and Charitable Institutions, a Market-house, built from a design by Mr. Smirke, and a Theatre. Its chief manufactures are sailcloth and rope. Ships are also built here. The market is held on Tuesday.</p>
<p><i>Inns.</i> The George, the Globe, the King's Arms.</p>
<p>COCKERMOUTH, in Cumberland, containing 4536 inhabitants, derives its name from its situation at the mouth of the Cocker, which here falls into the Derwent. The streets are spacious, though irregular, but many of the houses are neatly built. The chief manufactures are hats, coarse woollens, shalloons, and coarse linens.</p>
<p>On the top of an artificial mount are the ruins of an ancient Castle, originally the baronial residence of the Lords of Allerdale; and, during the civil wars, garrisoned for Charles I. <i>Inns:</i> the Globe, the Sun.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<pb n="148"/>
<head level="3" align="center">20. From WORKINGTON to KESWICK.</head>
<table width="70%">
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Workington to Cockermouth</td>
<td width="20%">8 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%">Cockermouth to Keswick, by New Road</td>
<td width="20%">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="80%"></td>
<td width="20%">21 &#189;</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>WORKINGTON is a considerable town of Cumberland, with 6415 inhabitants. It is situated on the south bank of the Derwent, which flows into the sea about a mile distant. It carries on a considerable trade in the export of coals to Ireland, the Baltic, &#38;c.; and employs several vessels in the salmon fishery.</p>
<p>The old part of the town is narrow and irregular, but the modern part is well laid out, and contains several good public buildings. In the church is an altar-piece, representing the Descent from the Cross. Workington has several Meeting-houses, a Theatre, and Assembly Rooms. On the east side of the town is WORKINGTON HALL, the manor-house of the Curwen family. It is remarkable as having afforded an asylum to Mary, Queen of Scots, when she landed at Workington. The room in which she slept is still denominated the Queen's chamber; but the house has undergone various alterations during the last century.</p>
<p><i>Inns.</i> The Dragon, the King's Arms.</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="Table of Heights">
<pb n="149"/>
<head level="3" align="center">A</head>
<head level="2" align="center">TABLE OF THE HEIGHTS</head>
<head level="3" align="center">OF</head>
<head level="2" align="center">MOUNTAINS AND LAKES</head>
<head level="3" align="center">IN</head>
<head level="2" align="center">LANCASHIRE, WESTMORELAND, AND CUMBERLAND;</head>
<head level="3" align="center">TAKEN FROM THE LEVEL OF THE SEA.</head>
<gap desc="line"/>
<table width="90%">
<tr>
<td width="70%"></td>
<td width="30%">According to</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%"></td>
<td width="15%">Mr. Dalton.</td>
<td width="15%">Mr. Otley.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%"></td>
<td width="15%">Feet.</td>
<td width="15%">Feet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">SCAWFELL PIKES</td>
<td width="15%">-</td>
<td width="15%">3160</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Scawfell</td>
<td width="15%">3240</td>
<td width="15%">3100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Helvellyn<ptr target="n2"/></td>
<td width="15%">3210</td>
<td width="15%">3070</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Skiddaw</td>
<td width="15%">3180</td>
<td width="15%">3022</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Great Gabel, or Gavel</td>
<td width="15%">-</td>
<td width="15%">2925</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Bow Fell, in Langdale</td>
<td width="15%">3090</td>
<td width="15%">2911</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Rydal Head</td>
<td width="15%">3090</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Fairfield</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
<td width="15%">2950</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Cross Fell</td>
<td width="15%">2901</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Pillar</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
<td width="15%">2893</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Saddleback</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
<td width="15%">2787</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Grasmere or Grassmore, near Crommock Water</td>
<td width="15%">2865</td>
<td width="15%">2756</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Red Pike, near Buttermere</td>
<td width="15%">2850</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Kentmere High Street</td>
<td width="15%">2736</td>
<td width="15%">2700</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Grisedale Pike</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
<td width="15%">2580</td>
</tr>
</table>
<note id="n2">According to Colonel Mudge, 3055 feet.</note>
<pb n="150"/>
<!-- I restarted the table here, as the headers are repeated over the page break -->
<table width="80%">
<tr>
<td width="70%"></td>
<td width="30%">According to</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%"></td>
<td width="15%">Mr. Dalton.</td>
<td width="15%">Mr. Otley.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Coniston Old Man</td>
<td width="15%">2580</td>
<td width="15%">2577</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Wharnside, near Dent</td>
<td width="15%">2475</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Hill Bell, north-west of Kendal</td>
<td width="15%">2436</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Harrison Stickle, or Langdale Pikes</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
<td width="15%">2400</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Carrock, West Pike, Cold Beck</td>
<td width="15%">2232</td>
<td width="15%">2110</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Knoutberry Hill, near Dent</td>
<td width="15%">2184</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Causey Pike</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
<td width="15%">2030</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Goat Scar, summit of road from Hawes Water to Kendal</td>
<td width="15%">1989</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Black Combe</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
<td width="15%">1919</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Lord's Seat</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
<td width="15%">1728</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Pendale Hill</td>
<td width="15%">1644</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Wansfell</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
<td width="15%">1590</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Whinfell Beacon, north-east of Kendal</td>
<td width="15%">1500</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Cat Bell</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
<td width="15%">1448</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Riverton Pike, between Chorley and Bolton</td>
<td width="15%">1200</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Latrigg</td>
<td width="15%">1160</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Benson-knot, near Kendal</td>
<td width="15%">1098</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Penrith Beacon</td>
<td width="15%">1020</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Kendal Fell</td>
<td width="15%">648</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="70%">Town of Kendal</td>
<td width="15%">138</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
</table>
<head level="3" align="center">LAKES.</head>
<table width="80%">
<tr>
<td width="85%"></td>
<td width="15%">According to Mr. Dalton.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%"></td>
<td width="15%">Feet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Hawes Water</td>
<td width="15%">714</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Leathes Water</td>
<td width="15%">546</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ullswater</td>
<td width="15%">318</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Crummock Water</td>
<td width="15%">273</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Derwent Water</td>
<td width="15%">228</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Bassenthwaite Water</td>
<td width="15%">210</td>
</tr>
</table>
<pb n="151"/>
<table width="80%">
<tr>
<td width="85%"></td>
<td width="15%">According to Mr. Dalton.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%"></td>
<td width="15%">Feet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Esthwaite Water</td>
<td width="15%">198</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Grasmere Water</td>
<td width="15%">180</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Rydal Water</td>
<td width="15%">156</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Windermere Water</td>
<td width="15%">108</td>
</tr>
</table>
<head level="3" align="center">IN OTHER PARTS.</head>
<table width="80%">
<tr>
<td width="85%">Mont Blanc, Switzerland</td>
<td width="15%">15,662</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Mount Etna, Sicily</td>
<td width="15%">11,000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ben Nevis, Scotland</td>
<td width="15%">4370</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Mount Vesuvius, Italy</td>
<td width="15%">3600</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Snowdon, Wales</td>
<td width="15%">3571</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ben Lomond, Scotland</td>
<td width="15%">3262</td>
</tr>
</table>
<gap desc="line"/>
<pb n="152"/>
<head level="3" align="center">PLAN of a TOUR to the LAKES from LANCASTER.</head>
<table width="80%">
<tr>
<td width="85%"></td>
<td width="15%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Lancaster, across the Sands, to Ulverstone</td>
<td width="15%">21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Or by Millthorpe, avoiding the Sands</td>
<td width="15%">36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ulverstone to Furness Abbey, and return</td>
<td width="15%">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ulverstone to Coniston Water Head</td>
<td width="15%">14 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Coniston Water Head, across Windermere to Bowness</td>
<td width="15%">8 &#190;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Bowness to Ambleside</td>
<td width="15%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Or from Coniston Waterhead, directed to Ambleside. Windermere must then by visited from Ambleside.</td>
<td width="15%">7 &#190;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ambleside to Langdale, and return</td>
<td width="15%">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ambleside to Brothers' Water, and return</td>
<td width="15%">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ambleside, by Rydal, Grasmere, and Thirlmere, to Keswick</td>
<td width="15%">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ascent of Skiddaw, and return</td>
<td width="15%">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Keswick to Borrowdale, and round Derwent Water</td>
<td width="15%">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Keswick, by Scale Hill, to Crummock Water and Buttermere</td>
<td width="15%">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Or, if on horseback or walking, the tourist may go through Borrowdale and Gatesgarth Dale to Buttermere and Crummock Water, returning through the Vale of Newlands.</td>
<td width="15%">23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Buttermere, by Vale of Newlands, to Keswick</td>
<td width="15%">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Keswick, by Stye Head and Wast Water, to Calder Bridge, (on horseback)</td>
<td width="15%">27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Calder Bridge, by Ennerdale Water, Lowes Water, Buttermere, and Vale of Newlands, to Keswick</td>
<td width="15%">29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Keswick to Penrith</td>
<td width="15%">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Or Keswick to Pooley Bridge, at the foot of Ullswater</td>
<td width="15%">17 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">And thence to Lowther Castle and Penrith</td>
<td width="15%">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Penrith to Ullswater and Patterdale, and return</td>
<td width="15%">30</td>
</tr>
</table>
<pb n="153"/>
<!-- again, table overlaps the page break, so creating a new one to retain header line -->
<table width="80%">
<tr>
<td width="85%"></td>
<td width="15%">Miles.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Penrith to Lowther Castle and Hawes Water, and return</td>
<td width="15%">24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Penrith to Kendal</td>
<td width="15%">26 &#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Kendal, by Levens to Sizergh, to Lancaster</td>
<td width="15%">20 &#190;</td>
</tr>
</table>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">PLAN of a TOUR from KENDAL.</head>
<table width="80%">
<tr>
<td width="85%">Kendal to Ulverstone</td>
<td width="15%">19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Thence to Coniston and the other lakes, as in the preceding tour, or,</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Kendal to Bowness</td>
<td width="15%">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Bowness, acros Windermere to Coniston Water Head</td>
<td width="15%">8 &#190;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Coniston Water Head to Ulverstone</td>
<td width="15%">14 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ulverstone to Furness Abbey, and return</td>
<td width="15%">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ulverstone to Coniston Water Head</td>
<td width="15%">14 &#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Coniston Water to Ambleside</td>
<td width="15%">7 &#190;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Thence to the other lakes, as in the preceding tour, or</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ambleside, over Kirkstone to Ullswater and Penrith</td>
<td width="15%">25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Thence to the other lakes, as in the following tour.</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
</table>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">PLAN of a TOUR from PENRITH.</head>
<table width="80%">
<tr>
<td width="85%">Penrith to Lowther Castle an Hawes Water, and return</td>
<td width="15%">24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Penrith to Ullswater and Patterdale</td>
<td width="15%">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Patterdale to Keswick</td>
<td width="15%">22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Thence to Derwent Water, Skiddaw, Borrowdale, Basenthwaite, Buttermere, Crummock Water, Lowes Water, Wast Water, and the Vale of Newlands, as in the tour from Lancaster.</td>
<td width="15%"></td>
</tr>
</table>
<pb n="154"/>
<!-- same again; table overlaps page break -->
<table width="80%">
<tr>
<td width="85%">Kendal to Ambleside, by Thirlmere, Grasmere, and Rydal</td>
<td width="15%">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ambleside to Langdale, and return</td>
<td width="15%">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ambleside to Brothers' Water, and return</td>
<td width="15%">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ambleside to Bowness</td>
<td width="15%">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Bowness, across Windermere to Coniston Water Head</td>
<td width="15%">8 &#190;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Coniston Water Head to Ulverstone</td>
<td width="15%">14 &#189;&#188;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ulverstone to Furness Abbey, and return</td>
<td width="15%">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Ulverstone, across the Sands to Lancaster</td>
<td width="15%">21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="85%">Or by Millthorpe, avoiding the Sands</td>
<td width="15%">36</td>
</tr>
</table>
<gap desc="line"/>
<pb n="155"/>
<head level="2" align="center">GLOSSARY,</head>
<head level="3" align="center">OR</head>
<head level="3" align="center">EXPLORATION OF TERMS USED IN THE VICINITY OF THE LAKES, EITHER</head>
<head level="3" align="center">BY THEMSELVES OR IN CONNECTION WITH OTHER WORDS.</head>
<gap desc="line"/>
<p><i>Barrow,</i> a term usually designated artificial, but here applied to natural hills.</p>
<p><i>Beck,</i> a rivulet or brook running along the bottom of a vale, and receiving gills.</p>
<p><i>Cam,</i> the comb or crest of a mountain.</p>
<p><i>Coom,</i> or <i>Cove,</i> a hollow scooped out of the side of a mountain.</p>
<p><i>Dod,</i> a small mountain on the side of a larger one, with a round head.</p>
<p><i>Dore,</i> or <i>Door,</i> a cleft or opening between two perpendicular rocks.</p>
<p><i>Fell,</i> a hill.</p>
<p><i>Gill, </i>or <i>Ghyll,</i> a mountain stream confined between steep banks, and descending rapidly.</p>
<p><i>Holm,</i> or <i>Holme,</i> an island.</p>
<p><i>How,</i> a small hill rising in a valley.</p>
<p><i>Lough,</i> a lake.</p>
<p><i>Man, </i>a pile or obelisk of stones upon the top of a hill.</p>
<p><i>Mere, </i>a lake.</p>
<p><i>Neese,</i> or <i>Nose,</i> a steep ridge descending from the top of a mountain.</p>
<p><i>Rigg,</i> a ridge or hill.</p>
<p><i>Scar,</i> a brow of naked rocks.</p>
<p><i>Screes,</i> loose stones, or fragments of rock, resting upon a steep declivity, and adhering to it so slightly, that the least agitation of any part of them puts the whole in motion.</p>
<p><i>Syke,</i> a very small stream.</p>
<p><i>Tarn,</i> a small lake.</p>
</chap>
<gap desc="index and back matter, not digitized"/>
</text>
