<text id= "1805_b">
<chap title="Chapter 15, excerpt">
<gap desc="The first x pages are front matter and have not been digitised" />
<pb n="192" /> 
<p>The accidental barking of a roving harrier, amidst the various echoes in the woods and dells of this picturesque country, made us for a moment fancy what delights must in such scenes attend the ardour of the chace, with the tumultuous notes of the hound's sweet thunder--</p>
<poem>
<line>"-- for besides the groves,</line>                                                                                                                                                                    <line>"The skies, the fountains, every region near</line>	                    <line>"Would seem one mutual cry."</line>                                                                 
</poem>
<p>From these falls we proceeded towards the lakes in Cumberland. The road is altogether uninteresting. The Clyde flows almost the whole way by the way-side, but is nearly without banks and every where a shallow contemptible stream. It's sprightly activity disappears, it no longer winds through groves or along a diversified channel: it glitters not in the sun, nor sparkles amongst overhanging leaves: it does not even arrest the attention of the traveler, and being un accompanied with verdure be-
<pb n="193" />
comes an additional object of naked desolation. But this is only the infancy of the Clyde, whose course may be compared to that of human life. In childhood man is feeble; with his years his strength increases,  and he gives the promise of mighty powers; then comes the meridian of life, when hurried by impetuous passions, and roused by war of the chace, he rushes through woods and down precipices with irresistible impetuosity. But anon his spirits begin to flag, and his activity slackens: he moves with leaden pace, bending toward the grave, his body dull and heavy, "fashioned for the journey;" and, finally, he is swallowed up in the ocean of eternity. So it is with the Clyde; here it rises, silently and weakly creeping forward; in it's progress "swollen with many tributary tide," it glories in it's wild career, through forests and over rocks and down the sublimest steeps; then does it's force abate, and it moves with lessened activity
<pb n="194" />
by Glasgow, Dunbarton, and Greenock till it is lost in the boundless deep!</p>
<p>The face of the country is wild, exhibiting large though not majestic features; the hills generally afford good pasturage, particularly for sheep. We were surprised not to see more cattle, as there seemed sufficient herbage for them, and as the vicinity of England would give the farmers a great advantage over their rivals of the north. </p>
<p>Gold-mines originally existed in this country, supposed to be what Camden calls Crawford-muir; and it is said that the Scots permitted Germans, then the most skilful mineralogists in Europe, to drain them of ore to the value of one hundred thousand pounds!</p>
<p>Near Elvan-foot are the celebrated lead-mines, infinitely more profitable than those of the gold. A miner, John Taylor, is recorded to have died in 1770, who worked in them till he was one hundred and twelve years old, and lives twenty years after he had discontinued his labours.</p>
<pb n="195" />
<p>We travelled over Errickstone-brae, near which, on the opposite sides of the ridge, rise the Clyde, the Tweed and the Annan. The first, running north-west, falls into the Atlantic; the second, by an eastern course, seeks the German Ocean; and the last winding southward, falls into the Solway Firth, an arm of the Irish Sea.</p>
<p>Moffat, we marked, had much the appearance of an English town, from the number of people in the streets, and from their being generally, even on their lower extremities, well clothed. But our inquiries showed, that these appearances were accidental. It's populousness arose from there being two hundred and fifty invalids, who had come thither to enjoy a salubrious air, and to drink a mineral water; the neat style of dress, from it's being a particular day, upon which the inhabitants received the sacrament.</p>
<p>Upon the ground, which we were now treading (the confines of England and
 <pb n="196" />
Scotland) it was impossible not to recollect the continental scenes of warfare, which subsisted among the borderers for many centuries. This perpetual state of depredation rendered them the most courageous and expert horsemen in Europe. Ten thousand of them, it is said, were wont to rise in a single day at the blaze of their beacons.</p>
<p>When we reflect on the pillage and slaughter by which they were constantly harassed, and the numbers that fell by the hand of the executioner, we may indeed wonder that any thing should have been left for pillage, or that any men should have been left to profit by it.</p>
<p>At Gretna-green, we had the curiosity to call upon the high-priest of Hymen. It was at an early hour in the morning and we could not be favoured with his society, without paying it's price in whiskey. A quart of this fiery spirit he drank before his breakfast. He told us, that he had married upwards of fifty couples in a year that
<pb n="197" />
sometimes they came in coaches and six, sometimes on foot; and that his charge for performing the ceremony varied, from fifty guineas to a bottle of his favourite liquor.</p>
<p>We rejoiced to find, that these disgraceful marriages were looked upon by the inhabitants as vile and scandalous. A father, who may be doubtful of his daughter's discretion, could not act more wisely than in taking her to hear their humiliating sceffs and nauseous anecdotes told by the pontiff himself. If, after this, she should lose the delicacy which is the proper guardian of every virtue, she might indeed be regarded as above all shame.</p>
<p>That sex, whose generous minds set no bounds to their affection, little suspect, while they are flying on the wings of love and in the arms of some needy adventurer, that, excluded from the only respectable inn at the place, they are to descend into a mise-
<pb n="198" />
rable pot-house; or, that the connubial knot is to be tied by an old drunkard, without the slightest pretence to the sacerdotal character; without even a syllable of the marriage ceremony, and in the presence, if needed any witnesses are thought necessary, of the very dregs of society.</p>
<p>Carlisle seemed not to afford any thing particularly worthy of our notice, excepting it's elevated situation, commanding a luxurious plain watered by the Eden. It was however it's manufactures; checks, printed cottons, osnaburghs and coarse linens. It is also noted for fish-hooks, whips and chamois or oiled leather. The Eden, so early as the months of December and January, abounds with salmon, which are generally sent to London.</p>
<p>Placed on the confines of two hostile nations, this city has often felt the calamities of war. It's origin is very remote. The town was utterly ruined by the  
<pb n="199" />
Danes, and lay desolate for a long tract of years, till William Rufus re-peopled it with a colony of Flemings, and built the castle.</p>
<p>From Gretna to Carlisle and Penrith we found the face of the country nearly the same, but not so much overgrown with moss, as that which we had crossed the day preceding.</p>
<p>Penrith is a pleasant place, and has some manufactures of checks and fancy pieces of waistcoats. In the church-yard are two very ancient rude stone obelisks, called the Giant's-grave. The son of Anak is said to have been one sir Evan Caesarious, a great destroyer of robbers and wild boars in Inglewood-forest.</p>
<p>On quitting Penrith, we noticed it's old and ruinous castle on the left, built upon a high hill, in the midst of a vale. Our attention was soon arrested by a barn-looking building, inscribed with letters of a foot in length; on the right of the front "Stage," on the left "Entrance," and on
<pb n="200" />
the middle "Theatre." At the stage-door appeared a pale-faced actor; at the entrance, the door-keeper of course; at the third, a well-looking man, whom we concluded to be the manager, for over his appeared in legible characters "Money paid here." The two side-figures were standing, the manager seated on a chair, with his elbows fixed upon a desk, his chin resting upon his thumbs, and in his general appearance by far the most melancholy figure of the three. Not a being was entering, or approaching for entrance. Only a few idle children were witnessing his anxiety for "to-morrow." The people of the town seemed as insensible to his allurement, as if they had though with Prynne, that "the play-house was Satan's chapel, play-hunters little better than incarnate devils, and so many steps in a dance so many paces in hell."</p>
<p>For six miles the country is rich and beautiful, enlivened on all sides with good
<pb n="201" />
farm-houses, neat cottages, and barns like palaces, if compared with Caledonian huts. Here we first beheld the return of full-clothed blooming children, of the merry milk-maid, with her master's full-fed mastiff, proudly guarding her from insult, and of the sleek herd, with their brawny male murmuring in his mighty strength. Proceeding along the narrow but luxuriant vale of St. John, we arrived at the close of the evening at Keswick.</p>
</chap>
<chap title="CHAP. 16.">
<gap desc="The first x pages are front matter and have not been digitised" />
<pb n="203" />
<head level="2" align="center">CHAP. 16.</head>
<p>Gowbarrow-park--Lyulph's -tower--Ullswater--Airey-force--Herd of deer--Blood-hound--Glenrudding--Patterdale-- Mr. Dobson's farm-house--Saddle-back--Skiddaw--Druidical temple--Derwent-water--It's  islands and scenery--Lord William Gordon's cottage.</p>
<p>Next morning, by six o'clock, we mounted ponies (the roads, on which we were about to travel, not admitting of carriages) and accompanied by a guide set off for Patterdale. On our way, we admired Mr. Wilkinson's house, and Castle-rock, in Wanford-vale. There the mountains and crags have much the same appearance, though on a scale not so magnificent as those which we had seen in the Highlands. Skiddaw and Saddle-back were enveloped in clouds, some of which, of a fleecy
<pb n="204" />
whiteness, were creeping lightly along, and half resting on the sides of the hills.</p>
<p>After proceeding many miles over uninteresting, inhospitable mountains, and dreary wastes, we arrived at Gowbarrow-park, an extensive tract of land well stocked with deer. Buffon mentions one extraordinary circumstance relative to this race of animals, which we believe belongs to no other--that "two fawns are generally produced together, and being nourished together acquire mutual affection, and, exclusive of misfortune, are inseparable lovers." The male might with more veracity promise to his female, than ever Lysander did to his Hermione, that</p>
<poem>
<line>"One turf shall serve as pillow to us both,</line>                                                                                                                                                                    <line>"One heart, one bed, two bosoms and one troth."</line>	                                             
</poem>
<p>Descending a rugged road, we reached the bank of Ullswater.</p>
<p>We first rode up to Lyulph's tower, a gothic building, supposed to be thus denomi-
<pb n="205" />
nated from Lyulphus, an Anglo-Saxon of distinction, who was murdered, during the distraction that raged at the Conquest, at Chester-le-street near Durham; and whose monument still remains in the church at that place. This castle is sometimes visited by its possessour, the duke of Norfolk, though it by no means seems fitted internally to afford him much comfort. The views of the lake seen from this station both to the north and west, including the surrounding mountains, exhibit a soft and harmonious beauty. Though the water however is extensive, and it's accompaniment magnificent, the impression here produced is very different from that which is made by the Highland lakes. There the sweeping nakedness, unbroken by vegetation or brushwood, gives an awful idea of wildness and desolation; here the eye is refreshed by the intervention of trees, villages and scattered habitations; the ge-
<pb n="206" />
neral scenery is less sublime, and the picture is beautified and enriched by occasional luxuriancy.</p>
<p>We were delighted with the thick, winding and uneven walk up the rocky vale to the waterfall. After crossing a narrow wooden bridge thrown over a wild mountain stream, we had a full view of Airey-force, which was then inconsiderable, from there having lately been little rain: but the deep fall down the black rock, as if into a cavern, and the small chink through which the stream impetuously disengages itself, convinced us that the full effect must be singularly grand.</p>
<p>We clambered to the highest point of the rock, whence the fall commenced, and seizing the branch of a tree, which hung over the craggy cheeks of the bank, were struck, upon looking down into the yawning deep, with the perpendicular narrow channel which the continual dashing of the
<pb n="207" />
water had excavated in the solid stone. The view itself was exceedingly terrific, and we powerfully felt</p>
<poem>
<line>"--How fearful</line>                                                                                                                                                                    <line>"And dizzy 'tis to cast one's eyes so low."</line>	                                             
</poem>
<p>A herd of deer, which had rambled close to the gate, through which we re-entered the park, fled from us with precipitation. We were impressed with the admirable provision of nature, in bestowing upon timid animals the instinct of going in troops, which she has happily denied to the bold and ferocious tribes. Where would have been the "paragon of animals," had it been his lot, when men and beast were "joint tenants of the shade," to contend against the united strength of the fierce creatures as the lion "whose cry, when enraged, is more terrible than his roaring; who then beats his sides and the ground with his tail, agitates his mane, moves the skin on his face and his large eyebrows,
<pb n="208" />
shows his dreadful tusks, and thrusts out his tongue, which is armed with prickles so hard, that it alone is sufficient to tear to the skin and the flesh, without the assistance of either teeth or claws?"</p>
<p>We particularly noticed in the park one of the now almost extinct breed of dogs, the blood-hound, which is kept for the purpose of hunting down the wounded deer. He was much taller and much handsomer, with his dew-lap ears, deep sonorous voice, than any fox-hound we had ever seen.</p>
<p>The landscape at Glen-rudding was extremely rich, the fields well cultivated, the farm-houses and mountains enclosing the view highly picturesque.</p>
<p>Skirting the side of Ullswater, through tickets, openings, and windings, we arrived at Patterdale. Hence we took a walk of about three miles up Griesedale, round Mr. Mounsey's place--as he is "the king." The glen is filled with trees on each side of a rocky brook brawling below.
<gap desc="Landscape Image of Patterdale" />
<pb n="209" />
On our left, keeping close to the south side of the stream, we passed near the entrance of a valley exhibiting dreadful precipices, and a degree of raggedness almost as terrific as that of Glen-croe.</p>
<p>We admired the situation and structure of Mr. Dobson's farm-house surrounded by trees, and commanding from the side of a hill a fine prospect of the vale. The house, adjoining barns, garden-fence, &#38;c. are built of loose stones ingeniously placed, composing walls of immense thickness; the roof of the barns in front is supported by round pillars of similar flat stones, cemented however with mortar: the whole had the most rude and gothic appearance imaginable.</p>
<p>In our rambles about Patterdale, from a rising ground behind the village, we caught a beautiful view of the lake (as represented in the annexed plate) with the interesting fore-ground of a quiet and romantic groupe of cottages scattered round
<pb n="212" />
<gap desc="Pages 210 and 211 are missing from version of text available via Google Books. The original text needs to be consulted in the Wordsworth Library, Grasmere."/>
appeared about two miles in circumference, and had an agreeable roundness of form; but it's islands, after those of Loch-lomond, with beheld with indifference. The varied scenery of the surrounding mountains, intermixed with wood and cultivated fields, gave as much pleasure. And the view from the middle of the lake, the near and distant hills, the church of Crosthwaite, the town of Keswick with the two giant brothers, Saddleback and Skiddaw, formed a landscape at once beautiful and majestic. The sun set sweetly in the west, and a crimson cloud was resting on one of the rocks leading into Borrowdale.</p>
<p>On the west side of the Derwentwater we passed close to the elegantly simple cottage of Lord William Gordon, situated on a sloping ground at the head of a peninsula near the margin of the lake, with it's bath on one side and kitchen on the other, embowered in trees and sheltered by Causeway-pike towering immediately above it.
<pb n="213" />
This house with it's sylvan scenery, it's mountains, and the lake in front, forms the most picturesque cottage that fancy can pourtray. Here is exhibited the admirable effect produced in the construction of a house by it's fitness to surrounding objects, an effect unhappily not exemplified in the houses of Mr. Pocklington and Colonel Peachy.</p>
</chap>
<chap title="CHAP. 17.">
<gap desc="The first x pages are front matter and have not been digitised" />
<pb n="215" />
<head level="2" align="center">CHAP. 17.</head>
<p>Borrwocascade--Lodore--Borrowdale--Bowder stone--Terrified peasant--Lake of Wattenlath--Scenery around it--Rosthwaite--Honistar and New-crag--Method of conveying slate down the sides of a mountain--Buttermere--Female waiter at the inn--Cromack water--Newlands--Ormathwaite-house.</p>
<p>At six o'clock next morning we mounted our ponies, with full confidence, from the uncommon brightness of the sky, that we should enjoy a calm and splendid day, and set forward in high spirits for Buttermere. After riding a short way on the side of Derwentwater, we stopped to see Barrowcascade, with the views behind Mr. Pocklington's house. The fall is considerable, the walks deeply embowered, and the view from the summer-house extensive. Here we enjoyed all the variety of lawn, wood, and water. The lake was perfectly

<pb n="216" />
smooth, and the harmonizing serenity of the surrounding objects truly delightful.</p>
<p>From Mr. Pocklington's house we rode to Lodore, and from a bridge on the road (over the Derwent) viewed the waterfall; but the descent of a whole river (the Clyde) down tremendous precipices was too fresh in our remembrance to permit us to feel any interest in the scene before us. We afterwards, however, regretted we had not more attentively inspected this celebrated cataract.</p>
<p>As we approached the entrance of Borrowdale, it seemed as if we were to be admitted into a deep ravine cut through those singularly formed craggy mountains, whose hideous naked ruggedness produced the strongest impression of sublime desolation.</p>
<p>After winding for some time along the side of the river Derwent,  we were much surprised by the magnitude and situation of Bowder stone; a mass which has undoubtedly, after being loosened by filter-
<pb n="217" />
ing rains, rolled from the neighbouring eminence (as appears from the conformity of strata) and accidentally stuck in this, it's ship-like position.</p>
<p>We were shown a large fragment which, some years since, had nearly proved the destruction of terrified peasant. He heard a tremendous rushing sound above him, and soon beheld the mighty ruin precipitating itself with increased velocity down the side of the mountain; but it fortunately passed at the distance of a few yards from him, and continued it's progress till it reached the deepest part of the vale.</p>
<p>At Rosthwaite we turned to the left, to view the lake of Wattenlath. The whole of this way is rough beyond description, and the acclivity more steep and toil-some than can easily be conceived. To ride we thought dangerous, as well as inhuman; but our guide proceeded carelessly forward, and his poney seemed to advance as easily with him on it's back, as ours
<pb n="218" />
without us. In labouring up this ascent of nearly two miles, we frequently paused for breath; and the fatigue and heat, which we endured in climbing to the summit, seemed almost intolerable; but we were amply rewarded for our toil.</p>
<p>The sky not being dimmed with a single speck, the lake of Wattenlath (small when compared with the immense objects around it) appeared, from the eminence whence we viewed it, transparent as a perfect mirror, and reflected with charming effect the green fields, trees and sloping mountains.</p>
<p>On our right lay the sparkling river, a pure crystalline stream, winding with serpentine coils in it's progress toward the lake. On the left the lake contracting itself into a river, closed on each side by steep towering rocks, and bending to the fall which we had observed on our entrance into Borrowdale, gave life and spirit to the hole. On every side the scene is terminated by the boundary, near or remote,
<pb n="219" />
of rugged and broken steeps, presenting themselves in chaotic confusion to the awestruck spectator.</p>
<p>The day was unusually hot. To breathe the noon-tide air more pure and cool, and to elude the persecution of the flies, we beheld here and there a horse or a cow standing on the rocky pinnacles above, as if suspended in the clouds.</p>
<p>The lake of Wattenlath, with rich verdure on it's sides, and the wild irregular magnificence of the surrounding mountains, exhibited the strong contrast of barrenness and vegetation: and the condensation of the whole, which brought it nearly within the compass of one view, caused us to look round with admiration at the wonder-working hand of nature; and by infusing a confidence in the infinite power and majesty of the Deity, spread a most agreeable calm over the breast, and excited in us a more powerful interest than any scene that had occurred in our tour.</p>
<pb n="220" />
<p>On our return to Rosthwaite we commenced our toil up Borrowdale-hawse. When we had reached the summit, on a road of loose stones of various dimensions, to which our ponies most actively adapted their steps, we felt ourselves powerfully impressed with the appearance of Honistar, rising in proud dignity from the bottom of the mountain which we were about to descend.</p>
<p>Our guide dismounted from his poney, to which he had hitherto stuck as close as if he had been glued to it's back; nor did we delay to imitate his example, for the descent was frightful. Steep, rugged and dangerous, even beyond what we had seen in the Highlands, it wound along the edge of tremendous precipices, and we looked down the unprotected sides of the hills with horrour. Thin shoes feebly defended our feet against the sharp pointed stones upon which we every instant trod. One of our companions being more cautious in his pro-
<pb n="221" />
gress, we had repeatedly to wait and watch for his appearance at the zig-zag turnings, not without apprehension that he might have slid off the shelving road into the abyss below.</p>
<p>The care necessary to ensure our steps afforded little leisure for meditation; yet were we here impressed with an agreeable feeling of security, on having before us any thing like a road amidst these narrow impending cliffs.</p>
<p>Our exhaustion was so excessive that we found it necessary to rest ourselves awhile at the bottom of the mountain. We took time to survey Honistar, and it's opposite but less lofty and perpendicular companion New-crag. Standing under the shade of one of those immense stones, which have tumbled from their parent rocks into the vale, Honistar seemed in horrible grandeur to elevate himself to the skies: and, disdaining to be incumbered with a blade of grass, wore a most dreary and inhos-
<pb n="222" />
pitable aspect. Raising our eyes up his dark-grey sides, we looked at him with terror, and beheld his dreadful summit above our heads, as the pale mariner on an unknown shore observes the dark clouds which bear the tempest in their bosom. The scenery around exhibits a view of sterility as wild and frightful, probably, as can be met with in any part of the United Kingdom.</p>
<p>Here our guide pointed out to us tracks down the declivity opposite to Honistar, which are made by a man bringing slate from the top of the mountain into the vale below. This hardy and industrious creature, having attained at the summit of a mountain hundreds of feet high,  fastens together a large quantity of the slate; and placing it behind him, to preserve it from being shattered to pieces by an unprotected descent, slides down the precipice with his burthen pressing him forward, and thus, like Sisyphus, incurs the daily 
<pb n="223" />
risk of being crushed to death, with the additional horror of yawning abyss before his eyes.</p>
<p>Continuing our route from Honistar, amidst craggy mountain, we passed by a mansion with it's out-houses, surrounding walls, and circular area, lately built by a gentleman of Cockermouth. The sudden appearance of o much art, amidst those scenes of desolation, was deeply impressive.</p>
<p>Proceeding through the valley along an improving road, we arrived at Buttermere; but neither in it's small lake, nor in that of Cromack, nor in the scenery around, did we observe any thing particularly interesting. We should have visited the water-fall at Scale-force, but were told that there had been so little rain as to prevent the effect.</p>
<p>At Buttermere we dined, and admired of course our water, the female whose recent injuries have excited so much public
<pb n="224" />
attention. She is somewhat above the middle size, with symmetry of person and a good figure, but rather to be deemed handsome than beautiful. It is her general deportment,  so very superior to her condition, that has produced such a lively interest in her favour. She has in her manner a plaintive softness and agreeable melancholy, which would dignify any situation; while at the same time she maintains a modest reserve, that sets all rudeness at defiance.</p>
<p>The barbarous project, devised against the family at this little inn, seems almost to have exceeded human depravity. Not content with the basest imposition on the daughter, her deceiver had planned, and nearly effected, the total ruin of her aged parents. Had his forgeries for a few days longer escaped detection, he would have persuaded them to sell everything they possessed, and after obtaining the produce, he
<pb n="225" />
would have sent them to manage his domains in the north!</p>
<p>We had fresh-water trout and char of delicious flavour or dinner. The pure air and exercise gave excellent tone to our stomachs, and our appetites were so god during our short repasts (for we fed not for the sake of eating, but for the impulse of nature) that we swallowed with avidity,</p>
<poem>
<line>"As if increase of appetite had grown</line>
<line>"By what it fed on."</line>
</poem>
<p>Wine we could not procure, but drank our shrub and water with those agreeable sensations which rest and contentment, after severe labour, always excite.</p>
<p>In the course of conversation we observed, that the Egyptians seem to have thought that land the best, which "flowed with milk and honey;" that in the opinion of the Greeks the internal use of honey, and oil applied to the surface of the body, were highly conductive to health; and that the 
<pb n="226" />
Goths, our ancestors, devoured their meat half-raw, supposing the juices to contain the best nourishment. In many respects those, who have preceded us, were probably wiser than ourselves. We substitute tea for milk, prefer made dishes to plain meat, and load our stomachs with drugs and stimulants, instead of the wholesome diet which satisfied the simpler appetites of our uncourtly forefathers.</p>
<p>We could not help recollecting, and as citizens we claim some credit for our disinterestedness in the remark, that Hermsprong (in the late Mr. Bage's ingenious novel of that name) has censured English dinners in his usual strain of spirited invective. "If to dine were only to eat, twenty minutes would be ample. You sit usually a couple of hours; and you talk and call it conversation. You make learned remarks on wind and weather, on roads, on dearness provisions, and your essays on cookery are amazingly edifying. Not much less
<pb n="227" />
so are your histories of your catarrhs and tooth-achs. Not content with this mass of amusement, you continue your beneficence to that unfortunate viscus the stomach, under the name of desert, till it almost faints under the obligation. No matter: spur it on with wine. It is said, physicians have much increased in your country; one great reason may be, because you dine."</p>
<p>In our walk to view Cromack-water, pleasantly connected by a rivulet with that of Buttermere, we observed the young women busily employed in making hay. Some of them to quench their thirst, without the least consciousness of indelicacy, lay flat on their faces upon the ground, and, as not unusual there, quaffed nature's beverage from the brook. We were much struck with the appearance of the females about these lakes, as well as of those about Keswick. All walked gracefully, all had an air of superiority which sat easy upon them;
<pb n="228" />
and an impressive beauty, with few exceptions, characterizes the whole race.</p>
<p>We knew not how to account for this general excellence. Have they, fortunately, by their peculiar situation been excluded from intercourse with strangers? Their manners are, probably, improved by copying those of the travellers who visit these lakes; and their mien is certainly benefited by dancing, an accomplishment in which the very poorest amongst them are instructed.</p>
<p>In the evening we set off on our return to Keswick by Newlands. Passing the church of Buttermere, we ascended Moss-hill, and riding along the sloping side of Whitley's-pike, covered with fine pasturage, became giddy in looking down it's declivity. The road, which is very good, continues for some space winding about the centre of the hills; and the views above, below, and around are exceedingly interesting.</p>
<p>We passed by Robinson's-crag, which
<pb n="229" />
seemed half impending over our heads. Hence for about a mile the scenery flattens, but on our arrival amongst the enclosures, the fertile and diversified country formed a striking contrast with the desolate region which we had just quitted.</p>
<p>The fields toward Keswick, gently sloping into the vale of Newlands, are charming. As we approached Keswick, every object became soft, attractive, and beautiful. The luxuriant foliage, and the lake glowing with the blush of the setting sun, which shed a fine mellowness over the whole, produced an impression at once soothing and delightful.</p>
<p>About three miles from Keswick, we crossed a bridge over the river Spires. From a deep shady lane we had a transient view of Bassenthwaite, seen through rich sylvan scenery; and lastly, we enjoyed a full prospect of Derwent-water, with Keswick, sheltered by Skiddaw, Saddle-back, and other surrounding mountains.</p>
<pb n="230" />
<p>At Keswick church we quitted our horses, and walked to the parsonage; where we viewed the picture, of which Gray fervidly pronounced that "fixed in all the softness of it's living colour, it would fairly sell for a thousand pounds." Hence we proceeded to the Ormathwaite-house, and from a seat in the grounds beheld one of the loveliest evening scenes that can be imagined; trees highly ornamental, fields carefully cultivated, and hedge-rows lengthened into deep streaks along the plain. Keswick, with it's magnificent accompaniments, terminated the landscape. We continued our walk amidst a soothing stillness, when not a breath disturbed the air, till we crossed a narrow wooden bridge, thrown over the Greta, which brought us to the road from Penrith.</p>
<p>Keswick is situated in a deep vale. It has it's linen and woollen manufactories; but it has neither the bustle of a trading-town, nor the attractions of a place of plea-
<pb n="231" />
surable resort. The number, however, of it's high and opulent visitors in the summer season is very considerable: in the year 1793, they amounted to fifteen hundred. Were the lands around the town freehold property, instead of being held under tenure from Greenwich-hospital (to which they were transferred, on the attainder of the last earl of Derwentwater) family-residences would be built, the ground would be beautified, and the town would increase in affluence and population.</p>
<p>Upon comparing in our minds the rides and scenes, which we had lately enjoyed, we were disposed to think this the most interesting.</p>
<p>Thus terminated our two day's excursion from Keswick. We congratulated ourselves almost equally on our industry, and on our good fortune with regards to the weather. The fatigue however which we had undergone, particularly on the last of those days, diminished that elasticity of
 <pb n="232" />
mind and body, which forms the chief basis of human happiness. We seemed to have forgotten, that</p>
<poem>
<line>"The fire that mounts the liquor till it runs o'er,</line>
<line>"In seeming to augment it, waste it."</line>
</poem>
</chap>
<chap title="CHAP. 18.">
<pb n="233" />
<head level="2" align="center">CHAP. 18.</head>
<p>Departure from Keswick--Grasmere--Rydale--Low-wood-inn--Windermere--Scenery around the lake  --Farm-house--Contended husbandman--Reflections on happiness--Kendal.</p>
<p>The early rising, after less than usual rest, the motion on horseback (to which we had lately been unaccustomed) over rough and hilly roads, our exertions in walking to the tops of the mountains, and in descending rapidly into the vallies, exposed to a meridian sun, produced such exhaustion as left a considerable degree of languor. Accordingly next morning we found ourselves more disposed to rest than to proceed, on our journey.</p>
<p>We left Keswick, however, at seven o'clock for Low-wood-inn, on the lake of
<pb n="234" />
Windermere. In our progress we noticed a rude pile of stones, called Dunmail-rise, designed to perpetuate the memory of a victory obtained there in 946, over Dunmail a petty king of Cumberland, by Edmund I. Similar monuments, accumulated by mighty and continued exertions, are observable throughout Europe; reared as grateful monuments to departed friendship and merit, or intended to distinguish the places of national assemblies, of great achievements, and of religious celebrations.</p>
<p>Passing through a beautiful country, and by the lake of Thirlmere, we enjoyed, in our entrance into Westmoreland, a delightful prospect of the village of Grasmere, it's lake, and it's vale. We walked round the water, which is about four miles in circumference, and were gratified with the view of sweet and varied landscapes at every turn.</p>
<p>A public road seems to have no right to disturb this sequestered village, which
<pb n="235" />
might justly claim an exclusion from noise, as the chosen asylum of peaceful meditation.</p>
<p>From Grasmere we enjoyed the company of a gentleman and two ladies to Low-wood. We stopped at Rydale, walked over the pleasure-grounds, and beheld from the summer-house the lower water-fall rushing under an old bridge down steep rocks. The picturesque beauty of this bridge is much diminished by the height of it's sides, raised in consequence of the fatal accident of a servant and his horse, who fell over it in a dark night.</p>
<p>We walked amongst avenues of trees, overtopped by stupendous mountains; the sun was shining in meridian splendour, and we heightened our pleasure by using Claude-Lorraine glasses, the mellow tint of which softened the glare.</p>
<p>Throughout the whole of this ride, it appeared to us, that the trees had no where attained their full growth, which makes the
<pb n="236" />
scenery betray an appearance of having been lately under the hands of the "beautifier." It seems impossible, that wood should not naturally exist in these vallies; but there may have been a great destruction of it, or it may not have been permitted to arrive at maturity, or the soil may not be genial. This last supposition, however, we were least disposed to admit, chiefly from observing that all the younger trees were thriving and healthy.</p>
<p>Greater luxuriancy appears in many parts of England, particularly in the west, than about these lakes; but the chief source of their superior attraction is to be found in their interesting diversity of water, woods, and mountains. At every turn a new picture is presented, and the mind is enlivened by a constant alteration of objects soft and beautiful, or majestic and sublime.</p>
<p>Proceeding amongst these romantic scenes, of which the enjoyment was heightened by the presence of our fair companions, 
<pb n="237" />
We reached Low-wood (probably the most delightfully situated inn in England) about midday. Soon after our arrival, we embarked in a boat upon the lake of Windermere, in the middle of which we were highly delighted with it's extent, it's reach meadows, the beautiful woods skirting it's borders, and it's grand accompaniment of surrounding mountains, particularly those which divide Westmoreland and Cumberland. These from their distance become softened. We admired the depth and brightness of the water, confined by it's perpendicular margin; and as the fishes glided past our boat, sporting in the sun, we could not but consider them as birds flying in a different region, through a thicker atmosphere.</p>
<p>Here we found it infinitely more difficult to describe the beauties of nature, than we had previously found it to depict her sublimities. The fine tints, the rich colouring, can only be enjoyed by the
<pb n="238" />
eye; it is in vain either for the fancy of the bard, or the pencil of the artist, to attempt her softer touches. The powers of poetry and painting fall short of those sculpture. The beholders of the Venus of Praxiteles lent their feelings to the marble, and seemed to hear it sigh. But all that the sister arts can do in describing beauties like those, which we were now enjoying, is to please us with the recollection of having enjoyed them.</p>
<p>In the evening, after the departure of our friends, we walked to a neat farm-house, at a short distance from the inn, delightfully situated on the brow of a hill, and commanding a noble view of nearly the whole lake to the south. We found the possessour in his garden, and were received by him with an open and dignified kindness, only to be rivalled by that elegance of manners which is formed by refined and enlightened society. The conversation we had with this very respectable farmer, and the
<pb n="239" />
excellent character we heard of him from his neighbours, convinced us that he was not without his share of that good sense and active benevolence, which we found throughout our journey, so generally diffused amongst all classes of people.</p>
<p>On our return to the inn we beheld a young husbandman, with a sprightly face, his arm thrown carelessly across the shoulder of his wife, who had met him after the labours of the day, on his return to his cottage. How enviable seemed those employments, which require exercise in the open air; and how strongly were depicted the felicity and innocence of these lowly peasants!</p>
<p>The contentment here displayed, in harmony with the soothing quiet  which prevailed all around, disposed us to reflect seriously upon that interminable question, "What state of life is best fitted for happiness?" And we concurred in opinion, that more health and less anxiety are to be found
<pb n="240" />
in the agricultural, than in the mercantile life.</p>
<p>Universal experience shows that in satiety there is a limit, beyond which happiness cannot have any long continuance: and perhaps the beggar who suns himself by the road-side, and the monarch who stalks upon his terrace, may have nearly equal enjoyment.  As the small stature of man allows him to command but a narrow prospect, so must his happiness be measured by his feelings and powers. These are in all nearly the same; and that species of gratification is the sweetest, which is the least constrained. Ambition, by producing eternal contentions, as if the world were not large enough for a little creature to creep upon, brings along with it nothing but irritation and disappointment.</p>
<p>A great portion of human enjoyment is derived, not from the pleasure actually felt by individuals, but from their viewing themselves with other men's eyes, and fan-
<pb n="241" />
cying how happy they are thought by those around them. As scarcely one can be found, who does not deem numbers of his fellow-creatures inferiour to himself, all men must possess nearly an equal share of happiness.</p>
<p>Next morning we left these delightful scenes, and proceeded on our way to Liverpool. It was rainy and dark; and a gloom hung over the lakes, strongly reminding us how much depends upon a bright atmosphere. "All is well as long as the sun shines, and the fair breath of heaven gently wafts to our own purposes."</p>
<p>After travelling about two miles and a half, we stopped the chaise at the point where the narrow road to Bowness begins, walked forward a short way, and had the most extensive view of Windermere we had yet enjoyed; for here we beheld it from end to end, about twelve miles in 
<pb n="242" />
length, and seldom much more or less than one mile in breadth.</p>
<p>Kendal, our first stage from the lakes towards Liverpool, is a neat town, pleasantly situated upon a rising ground in a vale through which runs the small river Kent. The town-house stands in the middle of the principal street, which is above a mile in length. Here are manufactured coarse woollens (Kendal) cottons, worsted-knit stockings, paper, &#38;c.</p>
</chap>
<chap title="CHAP. 19.">
<pb n="243" />
<head level="2" align="center">CHAP. 19.</head>
<p>Lancaster--It's sublime appearance--Garstang--Preston--It's penitentiary prison--Bustle on the roads--Liverpool--It's extraordinary increase in wealth and population--The exchange--View from it's dome--Chester--Singular construction of the houses--Jura regalia.</p>
<p>As we approached Lancaster, we quitted the mountain scenery. At this city, said to have been built by Agricola, we stopped but a short time. From the castle there is a very extensive view over the river Lune, and across the sea as far even as the Isle of Man: but the prospect is dreary and unpleasant; and it is with difficulty that vessels of considerable burden can approach the town. At a distance we observed the stream widening as it approached the ocean.</p>
<p>The merchants of Lancaster trade chiefly <pb n="244" />with the West Indies, America, and the Baltic. The principal exports are hardware, woollen-goods, and cabinet-work; quantities of sail-cloth are manufactured here.</p>
<p>After we had left this place about two miles, we enjoyed a most sublime view of it; the massive towers of the castle, situated on a high hill, with the town rising on it's sides, the fine steeple of the church, elevated above the whole, and the mountains of Furness and Cumberland, seen distinctly on each side, leaving an open space, so as fully to display (as if by art) the pyramidical appearance formed by the town, the castle, the new gaol, and the church. Near the town is an extensive quarry of excellent free-stone which admits of a fine polish, and of which the houses are wholly built.</p>
<p>On our approach to Garstang, we noticed the miserable ruins of Grenehough-castle. This town is famous for producing
</p>
</chap>
</text>
