<text id="1823_a">

<gap desc="The first six pages are front matter and have not been digitised." />

<pb n="1.1" />

<gap desc="In the centre of the page spread over two lines 'OTLEY'S GUIDE TO THE LAKES, &#38;c.', framed by a horizontal line above and underneath the text." />

<pb n="1.2" />

<gap desc="Upper half of the page blank." />

<p>The visitors of the delightful scenery of the LAKE DISTRICT of Cumberland and Westmorland, will derive considerable assistance and pleasure, and the general reader much amusement, from a neat and perspicuous description of this district, by Jonathan Otley, of Keswick. -- The work is accompanied by an accurate small sheet Map, and the whole has a character of originality, not often met with in similar works.</p>

<p align="right">MONTHLY MAGAZINE, JULY, 1823.</p>

<gap desc="At the bottom of the page has been printed 'PRINTED BY ARTHUR FOSTER, KIRBY LONSDALE'." />

<pb n="1.3" />

<gap desc="Bank page, at the bottom a hand-written entry '8 82.'." />

<pb n="1.4" />

<gap desc="The folded sheet map." />

<pb n="1.5" />

<p align="center">A </p>
<head level="1" align="center">CONCISE DESCRIPTION</head>

<p align="center">OF </p>

<head level="2" align="center">THE ENGLISH LAKES,</head>

<p align="center">AND </p>

<head level="3" align="center">Adjacent Mountains,</head>

<p align="center">WITH </p>

<head level="3" align="center">WITH GENERAL DIRECTIONS TO TOURISTS; </head>

<p align="center"> AND OBSERVATIONS </p>

<p align="center">ON THE MINERALOGY AND GEOLOGY OF THE DISTRICT; </p>

<p align="center">ON METEOROLOGY; </p>

<p align="center">THE FLOATING ISLAND IN DERWENT LAKE; AND THE BLACK-LEAD MINE IN BORROWDALE. </p>

<gap desc="Two horizontal lines." />

<p align="center">BY JONATHAN OTLEY. </p>

<gap desc="Two horizontal lines." />

<p align="center"> SECOND EDITION. </p>

<gap desc="Symbol, to the right stamp of the Bodlean Library." />

<p align="center">KESWICK: </p>

<p align="center">PUBLISHED BY THE AUTHOR. </p>

<p align="center">BY JOHN RICHARDSON, ROYAL EXCHANGE LONDON; AND ARTHUR FOSTER, KIRBY LONSDALE. </p>

<p align="center">1825. </p>

<gap desc="Hand-written note at the bottom of the page 'Gough Adds Cumberland 8 82."/>

<pb n="1.6" />

<gap desc="Blank page." />

<pb n="1.7" />

<head level="1" align="center">PREFACE.</head>

<gap desc="short horizontal line." />

<p>Before this little manual made its appearance, the public had been supplied with Guides to the Lakes in various forms; but wholly devoted to the picturesque appearance of the country, in exclusion of other important considerations. </p>

<p>It was therefore suggested, that a short description of the several Lakes and principal Mountains, accompanied with an approved Map, directing the tourist through the most eligible paths for viewing the varied scenery, and at the same time affording some information on the structure and component materials of these interesting regions, would be acceptable; and the ready sale of the first edition has proved that the expectation was not unfounded. </p>

<p>A second edition is now offered to the public, with such improvements as have been judged likely to render it a more useful companion, without making it more cumbrous, or more expensive. </p>

<pb n="1.8" />

<gap desc="A blank page." />

<pb n="7" />

<head level="1" align="center">DESCRIPTION OF <b>THE ENGLISH LAKES.</b></head>

<gap desc="Two horizontal lines, the top line thicker than the bottom line." />

<chap title="THE LAKES.">

<head level="2" align="center">THE LAKES.</head>

<p>THE District of the Lakes comprehends a part or each of the three Counties, Cumberland, Westmorland, and Lancashire, which form their junction at a point upon the mountain Wrynose, near the road side. Lancashire is separated from Cumberland by the river Duddon, from Westmorland by the stream falling into Little Langdale; and the latter county is parted from Cumberland by the mountain ridge leading from hence to Dunmail Raise. Windermere Lake is said to belong to Westmorland, at least its islands are claimed by that county, although all its western and part of its eastern shore belong to Lancashire. Coniston and Esthwaite Lakes, with Blelham and the tarns of Coniston, are wholly in Lancashire. Grasmere, Rydal, and Hawes Water, with several tarns, lie in Westmorland. The head of Ullswater is in Westmorland, but its

<pb n="8" />

greater part lies in the boundary between that and Cumberland. Derwent, Bassenthwaite, Buttermere, Ennerdale, and Wast Water, are in Cumberland. </p>

<p>Before this country became so much the resort of strangers, the word LAKE was little known to the native inhabitants; but to the ancient termination <i>mere</i>, WATER was usually superadded, as Windermere-Water, Grasmere-Water. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>WINDERMERE is the largest of the English Lakes, being upwards of ten miles in length, measured upon the water; by the road on its banks considerably more. Its greatest breadth is about a mile; and depth nearly forty fathoms. Having given its name to an adjoining parish, it was found necessary to add the word "water" or "lake," by way of distinction. It is situated in a country beautifully diversified by hanging woods and cultivated grounds, with lofty mountains in the distance. Its banks are adorned with buildings, which combine better with the scenery of this, than they would with that of the more northern lakes. A strait near the middle of the lake, has a public ferry-boat, on the way between Kendal and Hawkshead. Windermere is enriched by numerous islands; but their effect is lessened by being grouped in a narrow part of the lake.

<pb n="9" />

On the north of the ferry is the great island, called Belle Isle, belonging to Mr. Curwen, (on which he has a house.) It contains upwards of thirty acres, and has a gravel walk on its margin, of nearly two miles in circuit; on which strangers are freely permitted to walk. Besides this, are Crow-Holm, two Lilly of the Valley-Holms, Thompsons-Holm, House-Holm, Hen-Holm, Lady-Holm, and Rough-Holm. To the south of the Ferry are Berkshire-Island, Ling-Holm, Grass-Holm, Silver-Holm, and Blake-Holm. </p>

<p>Windermere is stocked with a variety of fish, of which char are the most esteemed. Char being taken by nets in the winter months, are potted, and sent to different parts of the kingdom. The principal feeders of the lake are the Rothay, having its source in Grasmere; and the Brathay, issuing from Langdale. These two rivers unite their streams about half a mile before entering the lake; and a remarkable circumstance is, that the trout and char, both leaving the lake about the same time to deposite their spawn, separate themselves into the two different rivers; the trout making the choice of the Rothay, and the char taking the Brathay. </p>

<p>Some would like to commence their survey of Windermere at Newby Bridge, and have the scenery to unfold itself as they advance. Others

<pb n="10" />

will be more gratified by the prospect bursting upon them at once in full expansion, as it does from the elevated ground, on either of the roads leading to Bowness or Ambleside. From some parts of the lake, the summit of Helvellyn may be just seen in the distance. -- When south of Low Wood, the Pikes on Scawfell (the highest land in England) appear to the left of Bowfell; between which last and Langdale Pikes, are seen Great End, and Gable, guarding the pass at Sty-Head; and a peep at Skiddaw is obtained from the road, at the guide-post, a mile and a half south of Bowness. </p>

<p>All the way from two miles south of Bowness, to the head of the lake, the views are excellent, and every rising ground affords something new in the combination. About Troutbeck Bridge, the distant mountains appear to great advantage. -- The view from the Station-house, above the Ferry, is much admired. -- A walk or a ride along the sequestered road from the Ferry towards Ambleside, will be found agreeable to the contemplative mind; and during a voyage on the higher part of the lake (which ought not to be omitted) a variety of both near and distant scenes are presented to the view in delightful succession. And as the boat proceeds from the landing place at Low Wood, a person previously acquainted with the

<pb n="11" />

distant mountains will feel a pleasure in observing how the highest Pike on Scawfell seems to march forth from behind Bowfell; and the Gable, from behind Langdale Pikes. </p>

<p>At Newby Bridge, on the foot of the lake, is a small inn, where boats, post-horses, and chaise are kept. Another, at the Ferry on the western side, where a pair of post-horses may also be had. And at Bowness, Low Wood, and Ambleside, are spacious inns, furnished with every requisite accommodation. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>ULLSWATER ranks next in point of size, being nine miles long, and rather narrow: yet on account of its winding form, the disproportion is not so much observed. It has the greatest average depth of any of the lakes, being in many places from 20 to 35 fathoms. The country about its foot is rather tame; but its head is situated among some of the most majestic mountains, which are intersected by several glens or small vallies; and their sides enriched by a variety of native wood, and rock scenery. </p>

<p>Three rocky islets ornament the upper reach of the lake; they are called Cherry-Holm, Wall-Holm, and House-Holm, the last of which, though houseless, is a fine station for viewing the surrounding scenery. -- This lake abounds with trout,

<pb n="12" />

which are sometimes caught of very large size; here are also some char, but they are neither numerous nor of the best quality. Large shoals of a peculiar kind of fish are met with, called here the skelly; and great quantities of eels are taken in the river Eamont, a little below Pooley Bridge, as they migrate from the lake in autumn. </p>

<p>The only carriage road lies on the north-west side of the water, sometimes on a level with its surface and commanding an unobstructed view; at other times deeply shaded in ancient woods, permitting only occasional glimpses of the lake; but on the opposite side the pedestrian will be well repaid for a ramble along Placefell and Birkfell; where from different parts of the foot-path the views are truly picturesque; and if he aspire to more extensive prospects, they may be attained by climbing the mountain to a certain height; where the lower extremity of the lake may be seen over the beautiful grounds of Hallsteads. </p>

<p>There is a comfortable inn at Pooley Bridge, on the foot of the lake; and another at Patterdale near its head; both of which furnish boats upon the lake: but those who employ post horses must have them from Penrith, Keswick, or some of the inns on Windermere. </p>

<pb n="13" />

<p>BROTHER WATER -- so called from the circumstance of two brothers being drowned together, by the breaking of the ice -- is a small lake, situate in that part of Patterdale called Hartshope, on the road leading to Ambleside. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." /> 

<p>HAWES WATER is about three miles in length, and half a mile in breadth; its head is encompassed by a grand assemblage of mountains, and its eastern side is screened by finely wooded rocks: the western side exhibits here and there a little cultivation, and a few small farm houses sheltered by trees. At Measand, a low cultivated promontory projects far into the lake, so as almost to divide it into two parts. Mardale, at the head of this lake, is one of the most sequestered of the vales: it has indeed its small chapel, embowered among yews and sycamores; but that other place, so often associated with a house of prayer, is not found here; the nearest public house being at Bampton, a distance of six miles. </p>

<p>There are various mountain passes by which Hawes Water may be approached on foot, and a way on horseback through Long-sleddale has been described, with a high degree of colouring by West and Housman; but, in planning an excursion, several things are to be taken into consideration; as, what kind of conveyance the road will

<pb n="14" />

admit of, how that conveyance is to be supplied; and at what places refreshment may be obtained: there is no public house in Long-sleddale, nor in Mardale, and the one in Kentmere is of the very smallest class; so, that it will generally be found most convenient, to visit Hawes Water from Penrith, returning either thither, or to Pooley Bridge, or in some cases to Shap. Lowther Castle, the magnificent seat of the Earl of Lonsdale, may also be visited in this route. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>CONISTON WATER, called in some old books THURSTON WATER, is a lake of considerable magnitude, being six miles in length; but wanting in that agreeable flexure of shores so conducive to the beauty of a lake. Near its foot however, are some fine wooded, rocky promontories; which from certain points add greatly to the prospect. It has two small islands, but they are placed too near the shore to appear of much consequence. </p>

<p>As the principal mountains lie on the western side, and at its head, the best views are in consequence obtained in a progress from its foot, on the eastern side; or from a boat on its surface: but those who have leisure, may be gratified by the variety afforded in an excursion quite round the lake. </p>

<p>Its greatest depth is twenty-seven fathoms. It

<pb n="15" />

is well supplied with trout and char, the latter are larger here than in any other lake; they are taken by nets in winter, and it was formerly supposed they could not be tempted by any kind of bait; however, of late several have been taken by angling, with a hook baited in a peculiar manner with a minnow. </p>

<p>The inn, at Waterhead, stands close on the margin of the lake, and furnishes parties with pleasure boats, and here, a chaise and pair of post horses may also be had. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>ESTHWAITE WATER is a small placid lake, nearly two miles in length, and distinguished by a fine swelling peninsula, which reaches far into the water from the western side. It is situated near the small market town of Hawkshead, in a beautiful open valley, which is crowned with gentle eminences, and decorated with an agreeable composition of houses, fields and trees. </p>

<p>A Floating Island on this lake has been mentioned, but differing from one on Derwent Lake, hereafter to be described. That, rises occasionally from the bottom; this, remains always upon the surface, being a piece of turfy earth, held together by roots of grass and willows, and at some period forming a part of the bank against which it generally rests. </p>

<pb n="16" />

<p>From no point of view do the mountains of Langdale, Grasmere, and Rydal, appear in nobler forms, than from the side of Esthwaite Water. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>GRASMERE LAKE is not large, but well formed; and placed in a beautifully expanded valley, perfectly encircled by mountains. The island, containing about four acres of verdant pasture, forms a striking contrast to the massive wooded islands on some of the neighbouring lakes. It rises boldly from the water, in a fine swelling form; and its smooth green surface, when spotted with cattle grazing upon it, has a beautiful appearance. Should it, however, be thought wanting in trees, there is scarcely an island in Windermere or Derwent, but might spare as many as would supply the deficiency. Most of the lakes, in order to be seen to advantage, require the progress to be made from the foot, towards the head of the lake; yet the view of Grasmere, from Dunmail Raise, was much admired by Mr.Gray; others have spoken highly of that from Townend; and Mr. West chose his station on Dearbought hill, on the opposite side. In short, from whatever point the approach to Grasmere is made, the prospect is always pleasing. </p>

<p>There are two good houses for the accommodation of travellers: the Red Lion, near the Church; and the Swan on the turnpike road. </p>

<pb n="17" />

<p>RYDAL WATER is of smaller dimensions, and formed in a more contracted part of the valley; it receives the river flowing from Grasmere lake after a course of about half a mile. It is ornamented by two picturesque islands, and bordered by meadows and hanging woods, surmounted by rocky mountains. </p>

<p> The fish, in Grasmere and Rydal Waters, are pike, perch, (provincially called bass,) and eels, with a few trout. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>THIRLMERE -- commonly called LEATHES' WATER, from the family to whose estate it belongs; and sometimes WYTHBURN WATER, from the valley in which it is partly situated -- lies at the foot of the "mighty Helvellyn;" upon the highest level of any of the lakes, being 500 feet above the sea; is upwards of two miles and a half in length, and intersected by several rocky promontories. It is nearly divided into two parts; and over the strait, there is a picturesque wooden bridge, leading to Armboth House. The depth of this lake, which has been reported to be very great, has not been found to exceed eighteen fathoms. A wooded island, of half an acre, lies near the shore, on the lower or northern part of the lake; and the surface of the water being of late somewhat lowered by opening its outlet, a 

<pb n="18" />

small rock in the upper part has become more conspicuous. </p>

<p>Travellers generally content themselves with a sight of this lake from the road; but those who have leisure, may obtain better views of the lower and finer part of the lake, from different stations in the grounds near Dalehead House; and finer still from the other side of the water. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>DERWENT LAKE, near Keswick, is of the most agreeable proportions. In breadth it exceeds any of the neighbouring lakes, being near a mile and a half; although its length is little more than three miles. Lakes of greater length generally extend too far from that mountain scenery, which is so conducive to their importance. But Derwent Lake appears entirely encircled; and visitors are at a loss which to admire most, the broken rocky mountains of Borrowdale on the one hand, or the smooth flowing lines of Newlands on the other; while the majestic Skiddaw closes up the view to the north. </p>

<p>The islands are of a more proportionate size, and disposed at better distance than those on any other lake. The largest, called Lord's Island, contains about six acres, now entirely covered with wood. It is situated near the shore, on which account probably it was selected for the 

<pb n="19" />

residence of the family of Derwentwater; but the house has long been in ruins, and nothing now remains but the foundation. </p>

<p>The Vicar's Isle, belonging to General Peachy, contains about five acres and a half, beautifully laid out in pleasure grounds, interspersed with a variety of trees, and crowned with a house in the centre. For some years it was called Pocklington's Island, while it belonged to a gentleman of that name; and is sometimes by way of pre-eminence called Derwent Isle. </p>

<p>One nearer the middle of the lake, is called Saint Herbert's Isle, from being the residence of that holy man, who lived in the seventh century; some particulars of whom are recorded by the Venerable Bede. And it appears that several centuries after his death, the place was resorted to, and the hermit's memory celebrated in religious offices. It belongs to Mr. Lawson, of Brayton House; and is now entirely covered with trees. There are some remains of an ancient building; and about twenty years since, a small grotto, or fishing cot, was built by the late Sir Wilfred Lawson. </p>

<p>A smaller island, called Rampsholm, is also covered with wood. This and Lord's Isle -- being part of the late Lord Derwentwater's sequestrated estate -- belong to Greenwich Hospital. </p>

<pb n="20" />

<p>There are other small islets; as Otter Isle, situated in a bay near the head of the lake, the views from which have been much admired. A piece of rock, called Tripotholm, and two others known by the name of Lingholms. </p>

<p>Besides these permanent islands, an occasional one is sometimes observed, called the Floating Island: being a piece of earth, which at uncertain intervals of time, rises from the bottom to the surface of the lake; but still adhering by its sides to the adjacent earth, is never removed from its place. Within the last twenty years it has emerged five times; remaining upon the surface for longer or shorter periods. In a succeeding part of this work the discussion of this subject will be resumed at greater length. </p>

<p>Another peculiarity has been attributed to this lake in what is called the Bottom wind: which has been described as an agitation of the water occurring when no wind can be felt on any part of the lake. It has been supposed to originate at the bottom of the water; and some have associated this with the last mentioned phenomenon; and ascribed both to those subterranean convulsions by which earthquakes are produced. Admitting, that the waves are sometimes greater than could be reasonably expected, from any wind which can be perceived at the time; yet, I

<pb n="21" />

doubt, whether they are ever formed when no wind is stirring: and if such a term as Bottom wind must still be retained, I think it ought to be referred to the bottom of the atmosphere, rather than the bottom of the lake. </p>

<p>The depth of Derwent Lake does not in any part exceed fourteen fathoms; a great portion of it scarcely one fourth of that measure. It is supplied chiefly from Borrowdale, and forms a reservoir for the water, which in heavy rains pours down the steep mountains on every side; by which means its surface is often raised six or seven feet; and in an extraordinary case has been known to rise a perpendicular height of eight feet, above its lowest water mark. At such times the meadows are overflowed, all the way between this lake and Bassenthwaite. Its surface being large in proportion to its depth, causes it to be sooner cooled down to the freezing point; and it frequently affords a fine field for the skaiter. In January 1814, the ice attained the thickness of ten inches. </p>

<p>The fish of this lake are trout, pike, perch, and eels. The trout, which are very good, are taken by angling, in the months of April and May; the pike and perch during the whole of summer. </p>

<p>It is not intended here to enter into a description or enumeration of the different views on this

<pb n="22" />

lake. Many attempts have been made to describe them: but they must be seen to be duly appreciated. </p>

<p>At Lowdore, is a public house, where the key to the Cascade is kept; and also a cannon for the echo, which is very fine; but as Dr. Southey says, "English echoes appear to be the most expensive luxuries in which a traveller can indulge." </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>BASSENTHWAITE LAKE is of somewhat greater length than Derwent, but of less breadth, and without islands. Being further from the mountains, it is not viewed with the same interest as some other lakes. Its western side is rather too uniformly wooded, the eastern has a greater breadth of cultivation, on which side are some fine bays and promontories; but here the road recedes too far from the lake to exhibit it to advantage. However tourists who have leisure for a ride, or a drive of eighteen miles round this lake, may obtain some pleasing views; especially from the foot of the lake, and from some points in Wythop woods. The lake is of less depth than Derwent: pike and perch are the principal fish; salmon pass through it, to deposite their spawn in the rivers Derwent and Greta, but are seldom met with in the lake. </p>

<pb n="23" />

<p>BUTTERMERE LAKE, situated in the valley of that name, is nearly encompassed by superb rocky mountains. It is about a mile and a quarter in length, scarcely half a mile in breadth, and fifteen fathoms deep. Tourists visiting Buttermere, by way of Borrowdale, pass along the side of this lake; those who travel in carriages generally content themselves with the view of it from a hill near the village. The distance, between this and Crummock lake, is about three quarters of a mile, comprising some excellent arable land. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>CRUMMOCK LAKE is nearly three miles in length, three quarters of a mile in breadth, and twenty-two fathoms deep. It is situated between the two lofty mountains, Grasmire or Grasmoor, on the eastern, and Melbreak on the western side; and in combination with the more distant hills, it affords some excellent views. It has three or four small islands, but they are placed too near the shore to add much to its beauty. The best general views of the lake, are from the rocky point on the eastern side, called the Hause; and from the road between Scale Hill and Loweswater: and the views of the mountains, from the bosom of the lake, are excellent. </p>

<p>Both these lakes are well stocked with trout and char, the latter of which are smaller in size, 

<pb n="24" />

but perhaps not inferior in quality, to those of Windermere or Coniston. There is a comfortable inn at Buttermere, between the two lakes, and another at Scale Hill on the foot of Crummock; at one of which places a boat is usually taken, as well for a survey of the scenery, as being the most convenient way of seeing the noted waterfall of Scale Force, on the opposite side of the lake. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>LOWES WATER, a small lake of about a mile in length, has given name to the parish or chapelry in which it is situated. It differs from all the other lakes, in that, they generally exhibit the most interesting mountain scenery, in looking towards the head of the lake; this, on the contrary, is more tame towards its head, while at its foot the mountains appear of bolder forms. It is not the difference between one piece of water and another, but the endless variety of scenery with which they are associated, that gives to every lake its peculiar character. Lowes Water, viewed from the end of Melbreak, exhibits a sweet rural landscape, the cultivated slopes being ornamented by neat farm houses: but taking the view in an opposite direction the lake makes a middle distance to a combination of mountains scarcely to be equalled. </p>

<p>The water, issuing from Buttermere, Crum-

<pb n="25" />

mock and Lowes Water, forms the river Cocker, which falls into the Derwent, at the town called from this circumstance Cockermouth. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>ENNERDALE LAKE is about two miles and a half in length, and three quarters of a mile in breadth. It is more difficult to obtain a good view of this, than any other lake. The best general view may be had near How Hall: but, as the principal mountain scenery, with part of the lake, is seen to advantage from the road, by which tourists generally pass from Wast Water, to Lowes Water and Buttermere; few like to extend the journey two or three miles for any improvement that can be made to the view. Pedestrians, anxious to explore the inmost recesses of the mountains, may follow the lake to its head, and after passing the sequestered farm of Gillerthwaite, continue their route four or five miles along the narrow dale, by the transparent stream of the Lisa, which is fed by the crystal springs issuing from the side of the mountain; they may then make their way over one of the mountains, either by the pass called Scarf Gap, to Buttermere, or the Black Sail, to Wasdale head: this way a horse might be taken, but it would be found more troublesome than useful. </p>

<p>This lake is well stocked with trout: here is

<pb n="26" />

also an inferior kind of char, which enter the river in autumn to deposite their spawn; contrary to the habits of those in the lakes of Buttermere and Crummock. There are two small public houses at Ennerdale Bridge, neither of which affords much accommodation to travellers. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />
<note id="n1">SCREES a provincial term signifying a profusion of loose stones, the debris of the rocks above, resting upon a declivity as steep as is possible for them to remain; so that the least disturbance in any part communicates a motion, somewhat between sliding and rolling, which frequently extends to a considerable distance, and takes some time before quiet is restored.</note>
<p>WAST WATER is a lake full three miles in length and more than half a mile in breadth. Its depth is not ascertained; attempts have been made to fathom it with a very long line, but without reaching the bottom. It has never been known to freeze, owing probably to its great depth, in proportion to its extent of surface; so that during the continuance of winter, the whole mass of water is never cooled down to its maximum density. We have before seen lakes situated at the very feet of mountains, yet still admitting of a road, or at least a path between them; but now we are arrived at one where there is not the least appearance of either; nor scarcely a possibility of ever forming one, should it be wanted. Roads can be cut through rocks or formed over morasses, but through the Screes,<ptr target="n1"/> which bound


<pb n="27" />

this lake on the south east side, they could hardly be effected. These screes extend in some places, from near the summit of the mountain, quite into the lake; which cannot be passed on that side without considerable difficulty and some danger. </p>

<p>The mountains environing Wast Water are few, but bold and majestic; Yewbarrow, from some points, appears as a conical hill, from others as a lengthened ridge; viewed from the lower part of the lake, the Hay Cock and Pillar occupy the back ground; Kirkfell pushes forward its bold front to the left; at the head of the dale the pyramidical Gable appears conspicuous: and to the right, Scawfell reigns pre-eminent: Middlefell running along the margin of the lake on the spectator's side, and the screes on the opposite, complete the panorama. In short, Wast Water affords many peculiarities well worth visiting once, but not sufficient to yield that encreased degree of pleasure, in a second, and a third visit, that would be experienced on Derwent, Ullswater or Windermere. </p>

<p>The fish of Wast Water are chiefly trout, with which it is well stored: it also contains a few char. Boats are kept by neighbouring gentlemen for the diversion of angling; and the appearance of the screes from the lake is magnificent. At Nether Wasdale, about a mile and a half from the foot of 

<pb n="28" />

the lake, there are two public houses where travellers may have refreshment for themselves and horses: there is no other between this and Rosthwaite in Borrowdale, a distance of fourteen miles, one third of which is very difficult mountain road. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>Three kinds of verdant plants, <i>Littorella lacustris</i>, <i>Lobelia dortmanna</i> and <i>Isoetes lacustris</i>, growing in all the lakes, constitute what is called a grassy bottom. In a dry summer, the <i>Littorella</i> left upon the shore puts forth its long stamina; when under water it is viviparous: the <i>Lobelia</i> spreads its recurved radical leaves upon the bottom, and in July, shoots up its spike of delicate pale flowers above the surface of the water; in winter, the leaves of the <i>Isoetes</i> are pulled up by the water fowl, to extract the seeds which lie concealed at their base. Various other aquatic plants are found in these lakes: in some sheltered bays, a profusion of water lilies, with their broad leaves, and snow white flowers, interspersed with a few of golden yellow, richly bedeck the surface of the water; while the reeds, bulrushes, and <i>Typha latifolia</i>, are waving over them with the wind. </p>

</chap>

<pb n="29" />

<chap title="THE TARNS.">

<head level="2" align="center">THE TARNS.</head>

<p>There are numerous other receptacles of still water, which, being too small to merit the appellation of lakes, are called TARNS. When placed in a principal valley, (which however is not often the case,) they contribute little to its importance; and being in such situations often environed with swampy ground, seem to represent the feeble remains of a once more considerable lake. But in a circular recess on the side of a vale, or on a mountain, as they are generally placed, their margins being well defined, they become more interesting. Reposing frequently at the feet of lofty precipices, and sometimes appearing as if embanked by a collection of materials excavated from the basin which they occupy; they afford ample room for conjecture as to their mode of formation. Being sheltered from the winds, their surface often exhibits the finest reflections of the rocks, and surrounding scenery, highly pleasing to the eye of such as view them with regard to the picturesque; but it is more agreeable to the wishes of the angler, to see their surface ruffled by the breeze. </p>

<pb n="30" />

<p><i>Tarns in the Feeders of Coniston Water.</i> -- Two or three pools, between the hills on the north of Coniston Waterhead, are called simply the Tarns; while those in the western quarter have received the more dignified appellation of Waters. -- Levers Water, the largest, is situated in a wide valley, between the mountains Old Man and Wetherlam. -- Low Water, placed on the Old Man's side, belies its name, as it occupies the highest level. Their united streams, after a succession of pretty waterfalls, pass Coniston Church in their way to the lake. -- Gates Water, [Goats Water,] reposes on the Old Man's western side, and at the foot of the precipitous Dow Cragg; [Dove Cragg.] Besides being, in common with the other tarns, stocked with trout; it also contains some char. Its stream forms the rivulet of Torver. -- Blind Tarn, a small reservoir of water without a stream, lies near the road to Seathwaite, by Walna Scar. -- Beacon Tarn is a small one, near the foot of the lake. </p>

<p>Belonging to the river Duddon, is Seathwaite Tarn, separated from Levers Water, only by a narrow mountain ridge. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>Tarns appertaining to the river Kent.</i> -- Kentmere Tarn, in the vale of Kentmere, bor-

<pb n="31" />

dered by morass; and Skeggles Water, on the heath-clad mountain between that and Long-sleddale; are neither of them possessed of any striking features. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>Tarns connected with Hawes Water.</i> -- Small Water, rightly named, lies between Harter fell, and High Street; and is passed by a mountain track leading from Kentmere to Mardale. -- Blea Water, separated from the last by a projection of High Street, lies at the foot of a lofty rock called Blea Water Cragg. Before reaching the valley of Mardale their two streams become united. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>Tarns in the environs of Ullswater.</i> -- Hays Water is of more extended dimensions than most of those called tarns; and is much frequented by anglers. The stream from it passes Low Hartshope, joining that from Brether Water near the foot of the latter. -- Angle Tarn, lying north of the last, upon the mountain separating Patterdale from Martindale; is one of the smaller class; but famed for excellent trout. Its stream in a quick descent, reaches the vale about half a mile further down. -- Grisedale Tarn, one of the larger class, lies in the junction of the three mountains Helvellyn, Seatsandal, and Fairfield. The road

<pb n="32" />

over the Hause, from Grasmere to Patterdale, passing the tarn, is accompanied by its stream down the vale of Grisedale; which unites with the parent valley near the Church. -- Red Tarn, also of considerable extent, containing about twenty-four acres, is upon the highest level of any of the mountain tarns; being upwards of two thousand four hundred feet above the level of the sea, little more than six hundred feet below the summit of Helvellyn; from whence into it you might almost cast a stone. -- Keppel Cove Tarn is posited in a singular manner, not in the bottom of the glen, but in a kind of recess formed on one side; it is separated from Red Tarn by a narrow mountain ridge, which branches off from Helvellyn and is terminated by a peak called Catsty Cam, modernized into Catchedecam; below which the two streams unite to form the brook of Glenridding. All these tarns afford good diversion for the angler; but the trout of Keppel Cove is superior to some of the preceding. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>Harrop Tarn, though but a small piece of water, is the principal one belonging to <i>Thirlmere</i>. It lies on the western side of Wythburn, and its stream, called Dob Gill, passing a few houses, joins the principal river a little before it reaches the lake. </p>

<pb n="33" />

<p><i>Tarns in the tributary streams of Windermere.</i> -- Elterwater is one of the largest of the Tarns; and having given its name to a small hamlet in Langdale, it became necessary in speaking of the water itself, to add the word tarn by way of distinction. It is nearly a mile in length, and divided into three parts. By the sudden influx of water from the two Langdales, the low meadows on its margin are frequently overflowed, and rendered wet and swampy: to obviate this, great pains have lately been taken in opening its outlet; by which means the dimensions of the water have been greatly contracted. And the fishery of trout has been nearly annihilated by the introduction of that voracious fish the pike. -- Loughrigg Tarn is nearly a circular piece of water of about a dozen acres, environed by green meadows, intermixed with rocky woods and cultivated grounds. Seldom ruffled by winds, it displays beautiful reflections of farm-houses, fields, and trees, surmounted by rocky steeps; and when taken in combination with Langdale Pikes in the distance, it makes an excellent picture. -- Little Langdale Tarn, in the valley of that name, is one whose importance is lessened by the swampiness of its shores. -- Blea Tarn, lying on the high ground between the heads of the two vales of Little and Great Langdale, has a small seques-

<pb n="34" />

tered farm adjoining, called by its name. Langdale Pikes viewed in combination with this piece of water have their most sublime effect. -- Stickle Tarn, at the foot of a huge rock in connection with Langdale Pikes called Paveyark, is famous for the quality of its trout. The stream issuing from it, at Millbeck, in a foaming cataract, may be seen at a distance. -- Codale Tarn is a small piece of water, containing a few perch and eels. It sends a small stream down a rocky channel into Easdale Tarn, which is one of the largest mountain tarns, seated in the western branch of Grasmere vale among rocky precipices, of which Blakerigg, or Blea Crag, is the principal. Its stream -- from its frothy whiteness called Sourmilk Gill -- is a striking object from the road. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>Tarns tributary to Derwent Lake.</i> -- A second Blea Tarn is situated on the heathy mountain between Wythburn and Borrowdale. The water after leaving it nearly two miles, is received by the small Tarn of Watendlath, in a circular valley of that name, which is not unworthy of being visited. It is the stream from these tarns, which after running two miles further along a narrow valley, forms the famed cataract of Lowdore. -- Angle Tarn, stocked only with a few perch, is at the head of the stream belonging to 

<pb n="35" />

the branch of Borrowdale called Langstreth. At the foot of Eagle Cragg, this is joined by another stream from the branch of Greenup; and after passing Stonethwaite and Rosthwaite, joins the Seathwaite branch a little further down the vale. -- Sprinkling Tarn, of irregular shape, reposes under Great End Cragg; it abounds with excellent trout; but the most experienced angler often practices his deceptions here in vain. -- Sty-head Tarn, in some maps called Sparkling Tarn, lies about three quarters of a mile below the last, near the road to Wasdale. The water, which it receives from Sprinkling Tarn, seems to have been deprived of its nutritive qualities; as its fish are of a very inferior kind. The stream running from hence towards Seathwaite, has some fine frothy breaks, and one grand waterfall. -- Dock Tarn, and Tarn of Leaves; one on the east side of Stonethwaite, the other between Seathwaite and Langthwaite; are scarcely entitled to be mentioned. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>Scales Tarn, on the east end of the mountain Saddleback, is nearly encompassed by steep rocks, one of which, called Sharp Edge, is worthy of its name. This tarn is by some represented to have been the crater of an ancient volcano; and its being the only tarn uninhabited by the finny tribe, gives some countenance to the conjecture:

<pb n="36" />

but the report of quantities of lava being found near it, as well as that of the reflection of the stars being seen in it at noon-day, are manifest exaggerations. The stream from this tarn, after nearly encompassing Souterfell, forms the small river Glenderamaken, which joining that from Thirlmere becomes the Greta, and a little below Keswick is absorbed in the Derwent. </p>

<p>Bowscale Tarn, which empties itself into the Caldew, is seated in a basin singularly scooped out of the side of a hill. -- Over Water lies to the north of Skiddaw, in the rise of the river Ellen; which passing Ellenborough enters the sea at Maryport. -- Burtness Tarn, or Bleaberry Tarn, lies on the south-west side of Buttermere, in a recess between High Stile and Red Pike: its stream forms the cataract called Sour-milk gill. -- Floutern Tarn serves as a landmark in passing between Buttermere and Ennerdale; as Burnmoor Tarn does between Wasdale-head and Eskdale. -- Devoke Water, connected with the Esk near Ravenglass, is famous for the excellence of its trout; and as a resort of water fowls. </p>

<p>There are some other small tarns, of little consequence in themselves, and seldom seen by strangers; therefore they scarcely require to be noticed. Such are Eel Tarn, Stony Tarn, and Blea Tarn, in Eskdale, and the two tarns above Bowderdale in the Wasdale mountains. </p>

</chap>


<pb n="37" />

<chap title="THE RIVERS.">

<head level="2" align="center">THE RIVERS.</head>

<p>The rivers in this mountainous district are not large, but remarkable for the clearness and purity of their water. From the central cluster of mountains about Bowfell, Scawfell, and Gable, many of them derive their origin; others have their source in the neighbourhood of Helvellyn and High Street. </p>

<p><i>The Derwent,</i> proceeding from Derwent Lake, falls into the sea at Workington. </p>

<p><i>The Duddon</i> rises on the south of Bowfell, and separates Cumberland from Lancashire. Forming no lake on its way, it pursues an unretarded course till it enters the sea on the north of the Isle of Walney. </p>

<p><i>The Esk</i>, rising on the east of Scawfell, retains its name till it enters the sea at Ravenglass; where <i>the Irt</i> from Wasdale, and <i>the Mite</i> from Miterdale, also join upon the sands. -- <i>The Bleng</i> passing Gosforth, is absorbed in the Irt above Santon Bridge. </p>

<p>The water flowing from the north side of Gable, passes down Ennerdale; is called <i>the Lissa</i> till it enters the lake; afterwards it is <i>the Enn</i> till it falls into the sea half way between Ravenglass and St. Bees. -- <i>The Calder</i>, rising in Copeland forest, enters the sea near the same place. </p>

<pb n="38" />

<p>Whitehaven, the principal sea-port in Cumberland, stands on a bay of the sea, unsupplied by any river of consequence. </p>

<p>The several becks of Patterdale unite in Ullswater. The water issuing thence, is called <i>the Eamont</i>, till it is absorbed in <i>the Eden</i>, which enters the Solway Frith a little below Carlisle; having first received <i>the Caldew</i> which rises on the east of Skiddaw, and <i>the Petteril</i> rising near Greystoke. -- <i>The Lowther</i> from Hawes Water, Swindale, and Wet Sleddale, enters the Eamont near Brougham Castle. </p>

<p><i>The Kent</i> rising in Kentmere, receives <i>the Sprint</i> from Longsleddale, and <i>the Mint</i> from Bannisdale. It washes the skirts of Kendal, and enters the sea near Milnthorp, where it is joined by <i>the Belo</i>. </p>

<p>The various becks of Langdale unite to form <i>the Brathay</i>, and those of Grasmere <i>the Rothay</i>; which unite in Windermere: after leaving which it is <i>the Leven</i>, which joins <i>the Crake</i> from Coniston on the sands between Penny Bridge and Ulverston. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space, smaller than the others. The remaining paragraphs of the chapter (chapter end on p. 39) in smaller font." />

<p>In alliance with this subject, we may add an explanation of a few terms of frequent occurrence in our provincial dialect: </p>

<p>A SYKE is a stream of the smallest class: as Heron-Syke, near Burton, dividing the counties of Westmorland and Lancashire. </p>

<p>A GILL (sometimes wrote GHYLL to ensure the hard sound of the G) is a mountain stream confined between steep banks, and running generally in a rapid descent. The soil brought

<pb n="39" />

from a mountain side by one of these gills, often forms a plot of ground of superior quality on the side of a valley; or sometimes a low promontory sweeping with a bold curve into a lake. </p>

<p>BECK is a word used promiscuously for river, rivulet, or brook. It is a stream in the bottom of a vale, and to which the gills are tributary. These becks mostly take their name from some dale, hamlet, or remarkable place which they pass; and frequently change it in their course: for instance, a stream running north from Bowfell, and receiving several augmentations in its progress down Borrowdale is called Langstreth-beck; then Stonethwaite-beck, Rosthwaite-beck, and Grange-beck, till it enters Derwent Lake: thence it has the name of Derwent to Workington, where it falls into the sea. </p>

<gap desc="Two horizontal lines, the bottom line slightly thicker than the top line." />

</chap>

<chap title="THE WATERFALLS.">

<head level="2" align="center">THE WATERFALLS.</head>

<p>LOW DOOR, softened into Lowdore, three miles from Keswick, is called by Mr. West "the Niagara of the lakes." It cannot boast of one great perpendicular fall, but it is a very considerable stream, rushing through an immense chasm, and bounding with great fury over and among the huge blocks of stone, with which the channel is filled. To the left, the perpendicular Gowdar Crag near five hundred feet high, towers proudly pre-eminent; while from the fissures of Shepherd's Crag on the right, the oak, ash, birch, holly, and wild-rose, hang in wanton luxuriance. As a whole, it constitutes one of the most magnificent scenes among the lakes, and has often afforded exercise for the pencil and pen. </p>

<pb n="40" />

<p>BARROW CASCADE, two miles from Keswick, is composed of an upper and lower fall, more perpendicular than that of Lowdore, and exhibits to advantage a smaller quantity of water. From the top of the fall the lake and vale are seen in fine perspective. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>SCALE FORCE near Buttermere, is the deepest in all the region of the lakes: Mr. Crosthwaite says it falls one hundred and fifty-six feet within six degrees of the perpendicular; besides being connected with a smaller fall below. The water is precipitated into a tremendous chasm, between two mural rocks of sienite beautifully overhung with trees which have fixed their roots in the crevices; the sides clad with a profusion of plants which glitter with the spray of the fall. Visitors generally enter from below, into this chasm, where the air, filled with moisture and shaded from the sun, feels cool and damp as in a cellar. Passing the lower, they may proceed towards the foot of the principal fall; till the more copious sprinkling of the spray compels them to retrace their steps. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>AIREY FORCE, on Ullswater, is concealed by ancient trees, in a deep glen in Gowbarrow Park. The water, compressed between two cheeks of

<pb n="41" />

rock, rushes forth with great violence; and dashing from rock to rock, forms a spray, which, with the sun in a favourable position, exhibits all the colours of the rainbow. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>STOCK GILL FORCE, at Ambleside, is a combination of four falls in one; the water is divided into two streams, and after a moment's rest in the middle of the rock, is finally precipitated into the deep, shaded channel below. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>RYDAL WATERFALLS are two in number, the upper of which is a considerable cascade; pouring out its water, first in a contracted stream, down a perpendicular rock; and then, at a little distance, in a broader sheet, it dashes into a deep stony channel. The lower fall, being near the house, forms a beautiful garden scene. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>DUNGEON GILL is a stream issuing between the two Pikes of Langdale. This waterfall partakes of the character of Scale Force; but of smaller dimensions. The water falls into an awful chasm, with overhanging sides of rock, between which, a large block of stone is impended over the basin, like the key-stone of an arch. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>THE FORCE above Skelwith Bridge, if not the greatest fall, is a fall of the greatest quantity of 

<pb n="42" />

water, of any amongst the lakes. When the river is full, it makes a thundering noise; but is not seen to great advantage. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>COLWITH FORCE in Little Langdale is also a tolerable fall. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>On the south side of Eskdale there are two noted falls, viz. BIRKER FORCE, and STANLEY GILL. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>There is Sour-Milk<ptr target="n2"/> Gill, at Buttermere -- Sour-Milk Gill in Grasmere -- and Sour-Milk Gill near the Black-lead mine. And a little further up Borrowdale, there is a fine fall, in Tarn Gill, at the foot of Taylor Gill. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>The above enumerated, are some of the most noted of the falls: but tracing the mountain streams, into their deep recesses, they present an inexhaustible variety: smaller indeed, but frequently of very interesting features. </p>

<note id="n2">From its frothy whiteness resembling buttermilk from the churn.</note>

<gap desc="Two horizontal lines, the top line thicker than the bottom line." />

</chap>

<pb n="43" />

<chap title="THE MOUNTAINS.">

<head level="2" align="center">THE MOUNTAINS.</head>

<p>SKIDDAW. -- A view of the country, from at least one of the high mountains with which this country abounds, is considered as forming part of the tour, by those who can muster strength and resolution for the undertaking, and for this purpose Skiddaw is, on several accounts, generally selected. It is nearest to the station at Keswick, most easy of access, (as ladies can ride on horseback to the very summit,) and standing in some measure detached, the view, especially to the north and west, is less intercepted by other mountains. </p>

<p>An extensive prospect being the principal motive for ascending a mountain, it is a question frequently asked, which is the best time of day for going up Skiddaw? It is not easy to give a precise answer to this question. The morning is often recommended; and generally, the sooner you are there after the sun has shone out and the cloud left the mountain, the better. It is a grievous, though not an uncommon circumstance, to be enveloped in a cloud, which seems to be continually passing on, yet never leaves the mountain during the time appropriated for the stay; but those who are fortunate enough to be upon the summit at the very time of the cloud's depar-

<pb n="44" />

ture, will experience a gratification of no common kind -- when, like the rising of the curtain in a theatre, the country in a moment bursts upon the eye. </p>

<p>It will always be better to seize a favourable opportunity, than to fix any certain time for the undertaking. A starry night is apt to lead to the expectation of a fine morning for the excursion; and indeed very early in such a morning the view of the surrounding mountains is often grandly displayed; but, during a clear, cold night, too much vapour is generally precipitated from the higher into the lower parts of the atmosphere; in consequence of which, the air in the vallies, and more particularly over the sea, appears thick and hazy. After a succession of dry and hot days, the air is seldom favourable. But, between showers, or when clouds prevail, (provided they are above the altitude of the mountains,) the distant objects are frequently most distinctly seen. Sometimes when clouds have formed below the summit, the country as viewed from above, resembles a sea of mist; a few of the highest peaks having the appearance of islands, on which the sun seems to shine with unusual splendour. To such as are well acquainted with it under other circumstances, this may be considered a magnificent spectacle; but a stranger will naturally wish to behold the 

<pb n="45" />

features of the country in a more distinct kind of view. </p>

<p>It is only by those who have been accustomed to such sights, that the value of a fine day for the purpose, can be duly esteemed. Some will look with wonder and delight, upon what others will deem a very indifferent prospect; and many are not satisfied with the most favourable state of the atmosphere, because however clear and extensive the prospect may be, still so much more falls under the eye than it is able clearly to distinguish. A telescope is of less use here than is generally imagined. In the hands of a person previously acquainted with the country, it may assist in the recognition of a particular building or object: further than this, it can render little service; when the air is thick and hazy, it cannot disperse the vapour; and when clear, the eye has too large a field to range over, and either the cold air or want of time prevents the contemplation of individual objects. </p>

<p>The exhibition from Skiddaw comprehends the principal part of Cumberland -- the coast from St. Bees' Head to the head of Solway Frith, with its several bays and promontories -- more distant, the Isle of Man, and a considerable portion of the southern part of Scotland. The summit of Ingleborough in Yorkshire, is just seen over the 

<pb n="46" />

range of hills bounding the head of Ullswater; and a glimpse of the sea, near Lancaster, through the gap of Dunmail Raise. Derwent and Bassenthwaite are the only lakes seen, and but one of these from the summit. Numerous objects visible from Skiddaw are particularized in Mr. Green's large work; but as few ascend the mountain without a guide, they are best pointed out as they present themselves, and as the state of the atmosphere renders them discernible. The value of a prospect of this kind, consists not in straining the eye to see what (according to the strength of the imagination) may be either mountains of Ireland, or a fog-bank -- a distant gleam of sunshine, or the reflection from the German ocean -- a speck of condensed vapour, or a ship on the glittering sea: it consists rather in beholding a country richly variegated, with fields of corn fit for the sickle -- meadows, green as an emerald -- hills, clad with purple heath -- lakes, with winding shores, and beautiful islands -- rivers, shining like silver, as they shape their serpentine courses towards the sea; -- and in tracing the effects of light and shade upon mountains, rising behind mountains, in every imaginable diversity of form: in short, it consists in viewing such objects as can be distinctly known, and properly appreciated. </p>

<p>The views from the summits of some of the 

<pb n="47" />

neighbouring mountains, may rival, or (in the opinion of some) exceed in grandeur the view from the <i>summit</i> of this; but in no other ascent, are the prospects equalled, which unfold themselves in the <i>ascent</i> of Skiddaw, when overlooking the lake and vale of Derwent, with the Borrowdale and Newlands mountains. </p>

<p>A portion of ground, connected with this mountain on the north and east, consisting of inferior elevations and heathy ground, is generally overlooked as uninteresting; though in fact it is quite the reverse. It is interesting to the geologist, as shewing the granite rock, and its junction with the slate; -- to the mineralogist, as containing veins of lead and copper, also molybdena, tungsten, apatite, and some other scarce and curious minerals; -- it is interesting to the sportsman, as affording the best grouse shooting in the neighbourhood; -- and to the shepherd, as affording excellent pasturage for his flocks. </p>

<p>Some have imagined, that on these heights a difficulty of breathing would be the consequence of a diminished pressure of the atmosphere; experience, however, warrants no such conclusion. The air here feels colder than the thermometer would seem to indicate: this may be owing partly to the previous degree of heat acquired by the exertion; and partly to the current mostly pre- 

<pb n="48" />

vailing, by which the heat evolved by the body is more rapidly dissipated from the clothing. </p>

<p>Amongst the various mountain plants observed in the ascent, are the different species of <i>Lycopodium</i> and <i>Vaccinium</i>, the <i>Erica vulgaris</i> and <i>Empetrum nigrum</i>; and on the summit the <i>Salix herbacea</i> peeps forth among the stones. -- The rock is chiefly a dark coloured clay-slate, in which are discovered small imbedded crystals of <i>chiastolite</i> -- in some parts of the mountain this mineral is more abundant, </p>

<p>The height of Skiddaw, as calculated by Col. Mudge, is 3022 feet above the level of the sea. In September 1817, I assisted Mr. Greatorex in the laborious process of measuring its height, with a spirit level and perpendicular staves: the result was 2808 feet above the level of Derwent Lake. The mean of five different trials with the barometer, in 1809, 1811, 1813, 1817, and 1820, was 2800 feet above the lake, which (according to the calculation of the late Mr. Crosthwaite) is 228 feet above the level of the sea. -- The distance from Keswick to the top of Skiddaw, by the different windings of the road, is nearly six miles. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>SADDLEBACK -- being at a greater distance from the station at Keswick than Skiddaw, of somewhat inferior elevation, and the ascent not quite

<pb n="49" />

so easy -- is seldom visited by strangers. It is better situated than Skiddaw for a view towards the south, and also of the neighbourhood of Lowther and Penrith; but the western view is greatly intercepted. -- It has been called Threlkeld Fell, and sometimes Blencrater, or Blenk-arthur; and it is from its form, as seen from the vicinity of Penrith, that it has received the name of Saddleback. Its height is 2787 feet, and its rock is a primitive clay slate, similar to that of Skiddaw. In walking along the ridge it is worth while to notice, how the southern side is formed into a series of deep ravines and rocky projections; while to the north, it descends in a smooth grassy slope. And deeply below a rocky precipice on its eastern end, a small tarn is singularly placed. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />



<p>CARROCK FELL makes one of the flanks of that cluster of mountains of which Skiddaw forms the crown. It is upwards of 2000 feet in height; and shews a double pointed summit, on which a space appears to have been once inclosed by a wall. Its basis is a crystalline rock composed of a curious variety of materials; and in its neighbourhood are veins of lead and copper, with other mineral substances highly interesting to the mineralogist and geologist. </p>

<pb n="50" />

<note id="n3">MAN is the provincial term for one of those rude obelisks, or piles of stones, which are commonly built by the country people upon the summits of remarkable hills.</note>
<p>HELVELLYN. -- Different portions of this mountain have been known by different names, and it is to one of those portions that the name of Helvellyn has originally been given. Latterly however the word has been used in a more extended sense; and it is to the highest point of the mountain that travellers are now conducted as the summit of Helvellyn; although it was formerly known by another name. And that which was anciently called the top of Helvellyn, or Helvellyn Man,<ptr target="n3"/> is situated near half a mile to the northward, and now called the Lower Man. -- Helvellyn is most conveniently ascended from the public-house at Wythburn, half way between Ambleside and Keswick; where the necessary guides may be had. The ascent is so steep that horses are never made use of; but to an active person on foot it presents no great difficulty. The views in the ascent are not to be compared to those obtained in the ascent of Skiddaw; but from the summit, on a favourable day, they cannot fail to be gratifying. Mountains, vallies, and lakes, stretched out before you in all their varied forms -- while here and there the view is interrupted by bold projections of the hill on which



<pb n="51" />

you are stationed. A great portion of Windermere and Ullswater may be seen; and Esthwaite and Coniston Lakes are shewn in full perspective: beyond them, the deeply indented bays of the Lancashire coast. Several mountain tarns are also visible from hence: the one named Red Tarn appears under the eye, at the depth of little more than 200 yards. It is environed on the right by a singular ridge called Striding Edge; and on the left by Swirrel Edge, crested by Catchedecam; beyond which lies Keppel Cove Tarn. All the principal mountains of the district can be distinctly enumerated; and between their summits in several places may be observed a glimpse of the distant sea. The Isle of Man seems elevated between the mountains Gable and the Pillar; and to the right and left of Skiddaw, appear the Scottish mountains. The cultivated country about Penrith is terminated by the lofty Crossfell, to the right of which is the range of mountains separating Westmorland from Durham and Yorkshire; and further still to the right the crowntopt Ingleborough appears conspicuous. </p>

<p>Helvellyn may also be ascended from Patterdale; but it would yield the most interesting variety to begin the ascent between the fifth and sixth mile from Keswick, and finish the descent at Grasmere: or the reverse. Commencing the 

<pb n="52" />

 ascent at Fisher Place, with Brotto Gill on the left, some pleasing waterfalls are seen; with views of Thirlmere and Bassenthwaite Lakes; by pursuing the range of summits, a fine succession of views of the vale of Patterdale is obtained; and in the descent the lake and vale of Grasmere expand before us. </p>

<p>Some have extended this excursion from mountain to mountain over Fairfield to Ambleside; but after descending so low as Grisedale tarn, a second ascent is generally thought too fatiguing. By long continued exertion the mind as well as the body becomes tired, and loses its relish. I have known a gentleman, who in passing through Borrowdale in a morning, would not neglect the most trifling object; yet in the latter part of the same day, he would pass some of the most interesting scenes on Wast Water, without any other enquiry than "How far is it to the inn?" </p>


<p>The height of Helvellyn, according to Mudge, is 3055 feet: I have called it 3070. On the western side, 300 feet perpendicular below the summit, is a spring called Brownrigg Well, where the water issues in all seasons in a copious stream. Its temperature, in the summer months, is from 41&#176; to 42&#176;. All the eastern side of the principal ridge is a series of rocky precipices; while the western exhibits a smooth easy slope; producing 

<pb n="53" />

however (except moss) but little vegetation. The rock on the summit is of a grey colour, and exhibits a coarse slaty structure. The lower part is more porphyritic, with a dark coloured base, and small white crystals; and between these is a more compact rock, which, from its appearance, may be called Hornstone. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>SCAWFELL AND THE PIKES. -- One of these points being the most elevated of all this mountainous district, and indeed the highest in any part of England, some misunderstanding has taken place respecting its proper name. In Donald's original map of Cumberland, the name Scafell extends over a range comprising several lofty points; this has been copied into all succeeding maps, and Colonel Mudge taking Donald for his guide, has designated the two rival points by the names of Sca-fell high-point, and Sca-fell low-point, or highest and lower top. This might seem a sufficient authority, but the shepherds best acquainted with the mountain, say, that Scawfell extends no farther towards the north-east than the deep chasm called Mickle Door, which divides the two principal points; and the highest point or that nearer Borrowdale, is by them called simply "The Pikes." A trifling misnomer like this may be thought of little consequence, and in such a moun-

<pb n="54" />

tain as Skiddaw or Hevellyn, where from one peak to another is but a pleasant walk, it would not signify much; but here the passage between the two points it attended with considerable difficulty, although they are not more than three quarters of a mile asunder; and to a stranger wishing to ascend one of these elevations, it becomes of importance to be able to make his enquiries intelligible to those from whom he may seek information. </p>

<p>The altitude of the higher point according to Mudge, is 3166 feet, of the lower 3092. From observations made between the two points, I calculated the difference to be only 50 feet, instead of 74; therefore taking a mean, I have marked them 3160, and 3100 feet above the level of the sea. </p>


<p>Both these points afford extensive views, as well of the surrounding mountains, as of a considerable part of the Lancashire and Cumberland coasts, the Isle of Man and a portion of the coast of Scotland, and on a very favourable day the mountains of North Wales may be seen on the right of Black Comb. That part which is called the Pikes, has a view of Windermere and Derwent lakes, and upon the whole affords the more complete panorama; besides the gratification of being on the highest land in England. It is also the highest mountain, as measured from the val-

<pb n="55" />

ley immediately at its base; being three thousand feet above Wastwater. The highest point, or Pike, may be most conveniently ascended from Borrowdale, the lower from Wasdale head, or Eskdale; but the distance from any house of entertainment, the rugged ground, and the danger of being caught by a cloud in such a situation, altogether conspire against its being much visited. And strangers are cautioned, so to calculate their time, as not to run the risk of being benighted on such places; to be caught in a cloud is disagreeable; -- cloud and night would be terrible. Very little vegetation is here to be seen, rocks and large blocks of stone piled one upon another is the principal feature. It seems that the process by which these blocks were separated from their native rock, has long since ceased; as their weather-worn surfaces prove that they have remained in their present state for ages. The rock is formed in layers of finer and coarser materials, and long exposure gives to the surface a ribbed or furrowed appearance. Great End, the north-eastern limit of the range, presents its broad rocky front towards Keswick. The rain water falling upon it, divides into Eskdale, Wasdale, and Borrowdale. Part of this rock is as compact as flint, and on its surface <i>Lichen geographicus</i> appears in peculiar beauty. </p>

<pb n="56" />

<p>BOWFELL rises proudly in view from Windermere and Esthwaite Lakes. It is 2911 feet in height, and sheds the rain water into Borrowdale, Langdale, Ulpha, and Eskdale. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>GABLE, OR GREAT GAVEL -- so called from its shape -- is a fine object as viewed from Wasdale, from Ennerdale, or from Crummock Lake; it is also seen from Windermere. It is 2925 feet in height, and is remarkable for a well of pure water on the very summit. This is not a spring issuing in the common way out of the earth; but is supplied immediately from the atmosphere, in the shape of rains and dews. It is a triangular cistern in the rock, six inches deep, and capable of holding about three gallons; and by containing water in the driest seasons, shews how slight a degree of evaporation is carried on at this altitude. By the force of the sun's rays, I have known the temperature of the water raised to 70&#176;, the air in the shade being 65&#176;; yet the thin clouds at the same time fleeting past the summit, shewed that the air was then nearly saturated with moisture. The rock of Gable is a very hard, compact, dark coloured stone, with garnets imbedded. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>THE PILLAR -- a mountain rivalling the Gable in height -- is situated between the vale of Enner-

<pb n="57" />

dale and that part of Wasdale head called Mosedale. It presents, towards Ennerdale one of the grandest rocky fronts any where to be met with. We have seen several mountain rocks inaccessible on one side; but here is one projecting from the side of this mountain which is inaccessible on all: this was originally called the Pillar, or Pillar-stone, and from it the mountain has taken its name; and viewed from above or from beneath, it has a grand and singular effect. The rock is more porphyritic than that of Gable. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>BLACK COMB, or COMBE, stands near the southern boundary of Cumberland. Forming the extremity of the mountain chain, it may be seen at a great distance; and is a fine station both for land and sea prospects. In 1808, it was made one of Colonel Mudge's stations, in the process of the Trigonometrical survey. He calculated its height to be 1919 feet above the level of the sea. Its basis is a rock of clay slate similar to that of Skiddaw; and it is covered by a large tract of peat earth, which is cut for fuel and brought down on different sides of the mountain. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>CONISTON FELL. -- The highest point of Coniston Fell, is called THE OLD MAN, from the pile of stones conspicuous on its summit. It is

<pb n="58" />

2577 feet in height, and has a good view of the rocky mountains, Scawfell and Bowfell, and at a distance, the highest point of Skiddaw. Coniston Lake is seen in full proportion, with a part of Windermere. Two tarns are seen upon the mountain, the smaller, called Low Water, although on the higher level; the larger, Levers Water; and on the western side of the hill, but not seen from the summit, is Gates Water, lying at the foot of the precipitous Dow Crag. Standing open to the south, unincumbered by other mountains, the Old Man commands a complete view of all the fine bays and estuaries of the Lancashire, and part of the Cumberland coast -- the Isles of Walney and Man -- and, in the direction of the river Duddon, on a favourable day, may be distinguished Snowdon, and the neighbouring mountains of North Wales. </p>

<p>By commencing the ascent near Coniston Church, the Black Bull and the stream on the left, some pretty waterfalls may be observed. The copper mines near Levers Water, and slate quarries between Low Water and the summit, may also be seen; and the descent may be made at choice more in front of the mountain. Those who admire a lengthened mountain excursion, may commence the ascent at Fellfoot, in Little Langdale, and surmounting the Carrs [scarrs] pass 

<pb n="59" />


on from point to point, over the Old Man, and so descend at Coniston. </p>

<p>The summit of the hill, as well as the quarries on its sides, are of a fine, pale blue, roofing slate. A considerable portion of the mountain is formed of a very hard rock, which some have denominated Petro-silex; and between this and Coniston Church, on the western side of the stream, may be observed the commencement of the darker coloured slate. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>LANGDALE PIKES,<ptr target="n4"/> called Pike of Stickle, and Harrison Stickle, are by their peculiar form distinguished at a great distance. They afford some good views to the south east; but being encompassed on other sides by higher mountains, the prospect is somewhat limited. Harrison Stickle the higher, is 2400 feet above the level of the sea: it is more easily ascended, and has the better prospect towards Rydal and Ambleside; but the Pike of Stickle has the advantage of catching through an opening in the hills, a view of Bassenthwaite lake, and the foot of Skiddaw; from which Harrison Stickle is by higher grounds excluded. </p>

<note id="n4">These Pikes should always be distinguished from the Pikes of Wasdale Head, by some called the Pikes of Scawfell.</note>

<pb n="60" />

<p>FAIRFIELD -- 2950 feet above the level of the sea -- makes a fine mountain excursion from Ambleside, commencing the ascent at Rydal, encircling Rydal head, and returning to Ambleside by Nook end. Lakes and Tarns to the number of ten, may be enumerated in this excursion; viz. Ullswater, Windermere, Esthwaite, Coniston, Grasmere, and Rydal lakes; and Elterwater, Blelham, Easdale, and Grisedale tarns: oftener than once, may eight of them be reckoned from one station. Here is likewise a good view of the different creeks and inlets of the sea towards Lancaster and Ulverston. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>HIGHSTREET may have taken its name from an ancient road which now appears as a broad green path over this mountain. It is probably the highest road ever formed in England, being 2700 feet above the level of the sea. -- On account of its central situation between the vales of Patterdale, Martindale, Mardale, Kentmere, and Troutbeck, and being connected with others at a little distance; an annual meeting was formerly held here, when the shepherds of the several vales reciprocally communicated intelligence of such sheep as might have strayed beyond their proper bounds; and to enliven the meeting, races and other diversions were instituted; ale and cake being supplied

<pb n="61" />

from the neighbouring villages. -- Highstreet affords some good prospects, but being at a distance from any place of entertainment it is seldom visited by strangers. Pedestrians fond of mountain rambles might, with a guide, pass over it from Patterdale into Troutbeck, or Kentmere, or into Mardale, and thence by Hawes Water to Bampton, from whence are roads to Pooley Bridge, Lowther, Penrith, and Shap. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>WANSFELL PIKE rises to the height of 1500 feet above Windermere Lake -- a moderate elevation compared with many of its neighbours; yet it is not deficient in prospects. It affords excellent views of Windermere, Grasmere, and Rydal lakes; the towns of Ambleside and Hawkshead, with the beautifully diversified scenery in the neighbourhood. Further distant are seen the sands of Milnthorp, Lancaster, and Ulverston, with the majestic mountains of Coniston and Langdale. In a walk from the pike, towards Kirkstone, it is curious to observe, Great Gable start out, as it were, from behind Langdale Pikes, and appearing to separate itself from them still further as the spectator makes his progress along this ridge. Wansfell may be conveniently visited either from Ambleside or Low Wood Inn; and in passing between the Pike and Skelgill, the 

<pb n="62" />

transition from the grey to the dark coloured slate rock, may be observed, with the limestone forming the separation or boundary between them. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>LOUGHRIGG FELL<ptr target="n5"/> is last and lowest, but not least in my estimation, being only 1050 feet above Windermere, and 910 above Grasmere lake. The moderate degree of exertion required to climb it, will be amply repaid by the prospects. By traversing its different points, a considerable portion of Windermere, may be seen, with Blelham, Esthwaite, Grasmere and Rydal waters, as also Elter Water, Loughrigg Tarn, and a small portion of Coniston and Thirlmere lakes, with other interesting scenery, scarcely to be equalled on so moderate an elevation. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space, bigger that usual." />

<p align="center">SOME NAMES OF FREQUENT OCCURRENCE AMONG THE MOUNTAINS. </p>	

<gap desc="A blank space. The following text in smaller font than usual." />

<note id="n5">The ridge of loughs, being almost encompassed by lakes and waters.</note>
<p>DOD is generally applied to a secondary elevation attached to one of the larger mountains; and mostly having a rounded summit. There is the Dod on the western side of Skiddaw, and also in front of Red Pike; and Starling Dod, nearer Ennerdale. In the mountain range proceeding north from Hel-

<pb n="63" />

vellyn, are Stybarrow Dod, Watson Dod, and Great Dod. And in Patterdale, Glenridden Dod, and Hartshope Dod. </p>


<p>BARROW, a term often intended to signify an artificial hill, is also applied to natural ones. There is Barrow on the West side of Derwent lake, a hill 1200 feet high; there is Whitbarrow near Penrith, and Whitbarrow near Witherslack: there is also Yewbarrow in Witherslack, and Yewbarrow in Wasdale. Latterbarrow explains itself, a hill branching from the side of a mountain: there is Latterbarrow at the foot of Wast Water, and Latterbarrow in Ennderdale. </p>

<p>HOW, generally implies a hill rising in a valley; (the sides of such hills are frequently ornamented with dwellings.) There is the How half way between the lakes of Derwent and Bassenthwaite; Powterhow, at the head of Bassenthwaite lake; and Castlehow, at its foot: Great How near Rosthwaite, and Great How near Leathes Water: the How and Butterlip How in Grasmere -- the How in Ennerdale, and the How near Loughrigg Tarn, with several others. Numerous alluvial hills of a parabolic form, and of a few yards in diameter and height, are sometimes called Small Hows; they are found in the heads of several vales -- in both the Langdales, in Greenup vale in Borrowdale, and are most remarkable in the head of Ennerdale. To such as accustom themselves to reason upon the effects of natural causes, they are peculiarly interesting.</p>

<p>CAM [comb] the crest of a mountain as well as of a cock: as Catsty Cam -- Rosthwaite Cam. </p>

<p>NEESE [nose] a ridge running from the summit of a mountain steeply downwards: as Gavel neese -- Lingmel neese. </p>

<p>COOM in some districts, and COVE in others, denotes a place scooped out of the side of a mountain; there is Coom, and Gillercoom in Borrowdale; Keppel Cove, Brown Cove, Red Cove, Ruthwaite Cove and others in the sides of Helvellyn. </p>

<p>DOOR, an opening between two perpendicular cheeks of rock: as Mickle Door -- Coom Door -- Low Door. </p>

<gap desc="Two horizontal lines, the bottom line being thicker than the top one." />

</chap>

<pb n="64" />

<chap title="THE CRAGS.">

<head level="2" align="center">THE CRAGS.</head>

<p>Some of the most remarkable Crags are, the Pillar, in Ennerdale -- Honister Crag, near Buttermere -- Scawfell Crags, between Wasdale head and Eskdale -- Broad Crag, on the Wasdale side, and Broad Crag, on the Eskdale side of the highest Pikes -- Paveyark, in Langdale -- Rainsbarrow Crag, in Kentmere -- St. Sunday Crag, in Patterdale -- Wallow Crag, near Keswick; and Wallow Crag, near Hawes Water -- Castle Crag, in Mardale -- Castle Crag, in Borrowdale, (said to have been a Roman Station) -- Castlehead, near Keswick -- Gait Crag, [Goat Cragg] in Borrowdale -- Gait Crag, near Shoulthwaite -- and Gait Crag, in Langdale -- Dow Crag, [Dove Crag] in Coniston Fells, Dow Crag, in Patterdale, and Dow Crag, in Eskdale -- Eagle Crag, in Borrowdale -- Eagle Crag, in Buttermere -- and Eagle Crag, in Patterdale -- Falcon Crag, near Derwent Lake, and a Raven Crag in almost every vale; one of the most conspicuous of which is that overlooking Leathes Water. </p>

<gap desc="Two horizontal lines, the bottom line being thicker than the top one." />

</chap>

<pb n="65" />

<chap title="ANTIQUITIES.">

<head level="2" align="center">ANTIQUITIES.</head>

<p>A Druids' Temple one mile and a half from Keswick, in a field adjoining the old road towards Penrith. It is a circle 112 yards in circumference, formed by 38 rough stones from 3 to 8 feet in height; 10 other stones forming a square within, on the eastern side. </p>

<p>King Arthur's Round Table, a piece of ground supposed to have been formed for martial exercises; and Mayburgh a place of doubtful use -- are both near Eamont Bridge. </p>

<p>The principal Monastic remains are Furness Abbey, in Lancashire; and Calder Abbey near the road from Ravenglass to Whitehaven. And a smaller one near Shap. </p>

<p>Remains of ancient Castles are to be seen at Cockermouth, Egremont, Penrith, Brougham, and Kendal. Part of that at Cockermouth has been repaired and is inhabited, the others are in various stages of decay. </p>

<p>On Hardknot, and on Carrock Fell, are some mystic remains of inclosure walls. And near Devoke water, the ruins of a place called Barnscar. </p>

<gap desc="Two horizontal lines, the bottom line being thicker than the top one." />

</chap>

<pb n="66" />

<chap title="GENERAL DIRECTIONS TO TOURISTS.">

<head level="2" align="center">GENERAL DIRECTIONS TO TOURISTS.</head>

<head level="3" align="center">STATION I. -- SCAWFELL highest point, THE PIKES.</head>

<p align="center">Latitude 54&#176; 27' 24" N. Longitude 3&#176; 12' W. Height 3160 Feet. </p>

<table align="center">

<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Bearings.</b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Dist. in Miles.</b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Height in Feet.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Skiddaw</td>
	<td>10&#176; NE</td>
	<td align="right">14</td>
	<td align="right">3022</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Ingleborough, <i>Yorkshire</i></td>
	<td>58 SE</td>
	<td align="right">38</td>
	<td align="right">2361</td>

</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Black Comb, <i>Cumberland</i></td>
	<td>19 SW</td>
	<td align="right">15</td>
	<td align="right">1919</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Snowdon, <i>Caernarvonshire</i></td>
	<td>20 SW</td>
	<td align="right">103</td>
	<td align="right">3571</td>
</tr>
<tr>

	<td>Holyhead Mountain, <i>Anglesea</i></td>
	<td>37 SW</td>
	<td align="right">100</td>
	<td align="right">709</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>North Barule, <i>Isle of Man</i></td>
	<td>78 SW</td>
	<td align="right">49</td>
	<td align="right">1804</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Mourne Mountains, <i>Ireland</i></td>
	<td>79 SW</td>
	<td align="right">116</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Mull of Galloway, <i>Scotland</i></td>
	<td>77 NW</td>
	<td align="right">68</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Burrow Head, <i>do.</i></td>
	<td>68 NW</td>
	<td align="right">51</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Crif Fell, <i>do.</i></td>
	<td>26 NW</td>
	<td align="right">38</td>
	<td align="right">1831</td>
</tr>
</table>

<gap desc="A horizontal line." />

<head level="3" align="center">STATION II. -- SKIDDAW.</head>

<p align="center">Latitude 54&#176; 39' 12" N. Longitude 3&#176; 8' 9" W. Height 3022 Feet. </p>

<table align="center">

<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Bearings.</b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Dist. in Miles.</b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Height in Feet.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>	
	<td>Wisp Hill, near <i>Mospaul Inn</i></td>
	<td align="right">9 &#176; NE</td>
	<td align="right">45</td>
	<td align="right">1940</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Carlisle</td>
	<td>26 NE</td>
	<td align="right">19</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Cheviot, <i>Northumberland</i></td>
	<td>85 NE</td>
	<td align="right">70</td>
	<td align="right">2658</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Cross Fell, <i>Cumberland</i></td>
	<td>82 NE</td>
	<td align="right">27</td>

	<td align="right">2901</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Saddleback</td>
	<td>78 SE</td>
	<td align="right">4</td>
	<td align="right">2787</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Nine Standards, <i>Westmorland</i></td>
	<td>68 SE</td>
	<td align="right">38</td>
	<td align="right">2136</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Ingleborough</td>
	<td>42 SE</td>
	<td align="right">46</td>
	<td align="right">2361</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Helvellyn</td>
	<td>32 SE</td>
	<td align="right">10</td>
	<td align="right">3070</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Black Comb</td>
	<td>15 SW</td>
	<td align="right">29</td>
	<td align="right">1919</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Snowdon</td>
	<td>19 SW</td>
	<td align="right">118</td>
	<td align="right">3571</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Snea Fell, <i>Isle of Man</i></td>
	<td>64 SW</td>
	<td align="right">59</td>
	<td align="right">2004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Mourne Mountains</td>
	<td>73 SW</td>
	<td align="right">124</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Bryal Point, <i>nearest in Ireland</i></td>
	<td>82 SW</td>
	<td align="right">91</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Mull of Galloway</td>
	<td>89 NW</td>
	<td align="right">69</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Burrow Head</td>
	<td>84 NW</td>
	<td align="right">50</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Crif Fell</td>
	<td>43 NW</td>
	<td align="right">28</td>
	<td align="right">1831</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Queensberry Hill</td>
	<td>22 NW</td>
	<td align="right">48</td>
	<td align="right">2259</td>
</tr>
</table>

<pb n="67" />

<head level="3" align="center">STATION III. -- HELVELLYN.</head>

<p align="center">Latitude 54&#176; 31' 43" N. Longitude 3&#176; 0' 21" W. Height 3070 Feet. </p>

<table align="center"> 
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Bearings.</b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Dist. in Miles.</b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Height in Feet.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Cheviot</td>
	<td>28&#176; NE</td>
	<td align="right">75</td>
	<td align="right">2658</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Cross Fell</td>
	<td>60 NE</td>
	<td align="right">24</td>
	<td align="right">2901</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Stainmoor</td>
	<td>88 SE</td>
	<td align="right">34</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Ingleborough</td>
	<td>45 SE</td>
	<td align="right">36</td>
	<td align="right">2361</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Bidston Light House, <i>Cheshire</i></td>
	<td align="right">1 SW</td>
	<td align="right">79</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>

</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Garreg Mountain, <i>Flintshire</i></td>
	<td align="right">8 SW</td>
	<td align="right">87</td>
	<td align="right">835</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Old Man, <i>Coniston</i></td>
	<td>21 SW</td>
	<td align="right">12</td>
	<td align="right">2577</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Snowdon</td>
	<td>24 SW</td>
	<td align="right">112</td>
	<td align="right">3571</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Snea Fell, <i>Isle of Man</i></td>
	<td>74 SW</td>
	<td align="right">61</td>
	<td align="right">2004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Crif Fell</td>
	<td>40 NW</td>
	<td align="right">38</td>
	<td align="right">1831</td>
</tr>
</table>

<gap desc="A horizontal line." />

<head level="3" align="center">STATION I.V. -- OLD MAN, CONISTON.</head>

<p align="center">Latitude 54&#176; 22' 20" N. Longitude 3&#176; 6' 34" W. Height 2577 Feet. </p>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Bearings.</b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Dist. in Miles.</b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Height in Feet.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Calf, <i>near Sedberg</i></td>
	<td align="center">East</td>
	<td align="right">25</td>
	<td align="right">2188</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Great Whernside, <i>near Kettlewell</i></td>
	<td>72&#176; SE</td>
	<td align="right">48</td>
	<td align="right">2263</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Whernside, <i>near Dent</i></td>
	<td>71 SE</td>
	<td align="right">31</td>
	<td align="right">2384</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Pennygant</td>
	<td>70 SE</td>
	<td align="right">38</td>
	<td align="right">2270</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Ingleborough</td>
	<td>64 SE</td>
	<td align="right">33</td>
	<td align="right">2361</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Pendle Hill</td>
	<td>44 SE</td>
	<td align="right">49</td>
	<td align="right">1803</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Lancaster</td>
	<td>31 SE</td>
	<td align="right">25</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>M&#339;l Fammau, <i>Denbighshire</i></td>
	<td align="right">4 SW</td>
	<td align="right">85</td>
	<td align="right">1845</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Carnedd Llewellyn, <i>Caernarvon</i></td>
	<td>23 SW</td>
	<td align="right">92</td>
	<td align="right">3469</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Carnedd David, <i>do.</i></td>
	<td>23 30&#8217;</td>
	<td align="right">93</td>
	<td align="right">3427</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Snowdon, <i>do.</i></td>
	<td>23 40&#8217;</td>
	<td align="right">99</td>
	<td align="right">3571</td>
</tr>

<tr>
	<td>Penmaen Mawr, <i>do.</i></td>
	<td>24 SW</td>
	<td align="right">85</td>
	<td align="right">1540</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Holyhead Mountain, <i>Anglesea</i></td>
	<td>41 SW</td>
	<td align="right">98</td>
	<td align="right">709</td>
</tr>

<tr>
	<td>Black Comb</td>
	<td>46 SW</td>
	<td align="right">12</td>
	<td align="right">1919</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Snea Fell</td>
	<td>84 SW</td>
	<td align="right">55</td>
	<td align="right">2004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Burrow Head</td>
	<td>64 NW</td>
	<td align="right">56</td>
	<td align="center">--</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Skiddaw</td>
	<td align="right">4 NW</td>
	<td align="right">20</td>
	<td align="right">3022</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>[The foregoing Tables are inserted, to shew the relative positions and height of some of the principal mountains beyond the limits of this map; without intending to say, that all of them may be descerned from the station under which they are placed.] </p>

<pb n="68" />

<p align="center"><i>Stages in the District of the Lakes.</i> </p>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Lancaster, over Sands, to Flookborough</td>
	<td align="right">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Flookborough, over Sands, to Ulverston</td>
	<td align="right">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Lancaster to Milnthorp, <i>New Road</i></td>
	<td align="right">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Milnthorp to Newby-Bridge</td>
	<td align="right">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Newby-Bridge to Ulverston</td>
	<td align="right">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Ulverston to Hawkshead</td>
	<td align="right">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Hawkshead to Bowness, by the Ferry</td>
	<td align="right">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Ulverston to Ambleside, by Coniston</td>
	<td align="right">22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Milnthorp to Kendal</td>
	<td align="right">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Lancaster to Burton</td>
	<td align="right">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Burton to Kendal</td>
	<td align="right">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Kendal to Bowness</td>
	<td align="right">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Bowness to Ambleside</td>
	<td align="right">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Kendal to Low Wood Inn</td>
	<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Kendal to Ambleside</td>
	<td align="right">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Bowness to Newby Bridge</td>
	<td align="right">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Newby Bridge to Hawkshead</td>
	<td align="right">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Hawkshead to Ambleside</td>
	<td align="right">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Low Wood Inn to Penrith</td>
	<td align="right">27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Low Wood Inn to Keswick</td>
	<td align="right">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Ambleside to Penrith</td>
	<td align="right">25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Ambleside to Keswick</td>
	<td align="right">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Keswick to Cockermouth</td>
	<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Cockermouth to Whitehaven</td>
	<td align="right">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Keswick to Penrith</td>
	<td align="right">18</td>
</tr>

<tr>

	<td>Penrith to Carlisle</td>
	<td align="right">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Keswick to Wigton</td>
	<td align="right">22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td>Wigton to Carlisle</td>
	<td align="right">11</td>
</tr>
</table>

<pb n="69" />

<p align="center"><i>Excursions among the Lakes.</i> </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p align="center">Houses that sell Wine &#8727; --- Other Public Houses &#8224; </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." /> 

<head level="3" align="center">THE CONISTON EXCURSION, FROM BOWNESS.</head>


<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">2</td>
	<td>Cross Windermere to Ferry House &#8727;</td>
	<td align="right">2</td>
</tr>

<tr>
	<td align="right">4</td>
	<td>By Esthwaite Water to Hawkshead &#8727; &#8727; &#8224;&#8224;&#8224; </td>
	<td align="right">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">3</td>
	<td>Coniston Water-head &#8727;</td>
	<td align="right">9</td>

</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">3</td>
	<td>Borwick Ground</td>
	<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">5</td>
	<td>AMBLESIDE, <i>Salutation</i> &#8727; &#8224;&#8224;&#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">17</td>
</tr>
</table>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<head level="3" align="center">THE LANGDALE EXCURSION, FROM AMBLESIDE.</head>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">3</td>
	<td>Skelwith Bridge &#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">2</td>
	<td>Colwith Cascade</td>
	<td align="right">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">3</td>
	<td>Blea Tarn</td>
	<td align="right">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">3</td>
	<td>Dungeon Gill</td>
	<td align="right">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">2</td>
	<td>Langdale Chapel &#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">5</td>
	<td>By Highclose, and Rydal, to Ambleside</td>
	<td align="right">18</td>
</tr>
</table>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<head level="3" align="center">ULLSWATER, FROM AMBLESIDE.</head>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">10</td>
	<td>Patterdale &#8727;</td>
	<td align="right">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">9&#189;</td>
	<td>Pooley Bridge &#8727; &#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">19&#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">4&#189;</td>
	<td>Eamont Bridge &#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">1</td>
	<td>PENRITH, <i>Crown</i>, <i>George</i></td>
	<td align="right">25</td>
</tr>
</table>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<head level="3" align="center">HAWES WATER, FROM PENRITH.</head>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">5</td>
	<td>Lowther, or Askham &#8224;&#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">7</td>
	<td>By Bampton, to Hawes Water</td>
	<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">4</td>
	<td>Return by Bampton, to Butterswick</td>
	<td align="right">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">5</td>
	<td>Over Moor Dovack to Pooley &#8727; &#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">6</td>
	<td>By Dalemain to Penrith</td>
	<td align="right">27</td>
</tr>
</table>

<pb n="70" />

<p align="center"><i>Excursions from Keswick.</i> </p>

<gap desc="A blank space, smaller than usual." />

<p align="center">INNS -- <i>Royal Oak</i>, <i>Queen's Head</i>, &#8727; &#8727; &#8727; &#8224;&#8224;&#8224;&#8224;&#8224;&#8224;&#8224;&#8224; </p>

<gap desc="A blank space, smaller than usual." />

<p align="center">A Mail by way of Penrith every morning, returns in the night. -- </p>

<p align="center">Coaches to and from Kendal and Whitehaven every day except Sunday. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space, smaller than usual." />

<head level="3" align="center">A DRIVE ROUND DERWENT LAKE.</head>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">2</td>

	<td>Barrow House, and Cascade</td>
	<td align="right">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">1</td>
	<td>Lowdore, &#8224; and Ditto</td>
	<td align="right">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">1</td>
	<td> Grange</td>
	<td align="right">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">1</td>
	<td>Bowder Stone</td>
	<td align="right">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">1</td>
	<td>Return and cross the River at Grange</td>
	<td align="right">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">4&#189;</td>
	<td>Portinscale &#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">10&#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">1&#189;</td>
	<td>Keswick</td>
	<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
</table>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<head level="3" align="center">A RIDE TO BUTTERMERE</head>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">5</td>
	<td>Bowder Stone</td>
	<td align="right">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">1</td>
	<td>Rosthwaite &#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">2</td>
	<td>Seatollar</td>
	<td align="right">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">2</td>
	<td>Honistar Crag</td>
	<td align="right">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">2</td>
	<td>Gatesgarth</td>
	<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">2</td>
	<td>Buttermere &#8727;</td>
	<td align="right">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td><gap desc="empty cell" /></td>
	<td align="center">Boat on Crummock Lake; see Scale Force and return 5 miles.</td>
	<td><gap desc="empty cell" /></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">9</td>
	<td>Through Newlands to Keswick</td>
	<td align="right">23</td>
</tr>
</table>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<head level="3" align="center">A DRIVE TO BUTTERMERE.</head>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">8</td>
	<td>Lorton</td>
	<td align="right">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">8</td>
	<td>Buttermere &#8727;</td>
	<td align="right">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">16</td>
	<td>Return to Keswick</td>
	<td align="right">32</td>
</tr>
</table>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<head level="3" align="center">OR, BY SCALE HILL.</head>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">8</td>
	<td>To Lorton</td>
	<td align="right">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">4</td>
	<td>Scale Hill &#8727;</td>
	<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td></td>
	<td align="center">Boat on Crummock Lake; see Scale Force and Buttermere, and return 10 miles.</td>
	<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">12</td>
	<td>Return to Keswick</td>
	<td align="right">24</td>
</tr>
</table>

<pb n="71" />

<p align="center"><i>Excursions from Keswick.</i> </p>

<gap desc="A blank space."/>

<head level="3" align="center">A TWO DAYS'S RIDE.</head>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">8</td>
	<td>To Seatollar</td>
	<td align="right">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">1</td>
	<td>Seathwaite</td>
	<td align="right">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">3</td>
	<td>Sty Head</td>

	<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">2</td>
	<td>Wasdale Head</td>
	<td align="right">14</td>
</tr>

<tr>
	<td align="right">6</td>
	<td>Strands, <i>Nether Wasdale</i> &#8224;&#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">20</td>
</tr>

<tr>
	<td align="right">4</td>
	<td>Gosforth &#8224;&#8224;&#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">24</td>
</tr>

<tr>
	<td align="right">3</td>
	<td>Calder Bridge &#8727;&#8727;</td>
	<td align="right">27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td></td>
	<td align="center">SECOND DAY.</td>
	<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">7</td>
	<td>Ennerdale Bridge &#8224;&#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">3</td>
	<td>Lamplugh Cross &#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">4</td>
	<td>Loweswater</td>
	<td align="right">14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">2</td>
	<td>Scale Hill &#8727;</td>
	<td align="right">16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">4</td>
	<td>Buttermere &#8727;</td>
	<td align="right">20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">9</td>
	<td>KESWICK</td>
	<td align="right">29</td>
</tr>
</table>

<gap desc="A blank space"/>

<head level="3" align="center">A DRIVE TO PATTERDALE.</head>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">11</td>
	<td>To Becksis</td>
	<td align="right">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">7</td>
	<td>Gowbarrow Park</td>
	<td align="right">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">4</td>
	<td>Patterdale &#8727;</td>
	<td align="right">22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td></td>
	<td align="center">Return same day; or,</td>
	<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">10</td>
	<td>To Pooley Bridge &#8727; &#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">32</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">6</td>
	<td>PENRITH</td>

	<td align="right">38</td>

</tr>
</table>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<head level="3" align="center">A DRIVE TO POOLEY BRIDGE.</head>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">12</td>
	<td>Penruddock</td>
	<td align="right">12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">3</td>
	<td>Dacre</td>
	<td align="right">15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">3</td>
	<td>Pooley Bridge &#8727; &#8224;</td>
	<td align="right">18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">6</td>
	<td>PENRITH</td>
	<td align="right">24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">5</td>
	<td>Or, Pooley Bridge to Lowther</td>
	<td align="right">23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">5</td>
	<td>Lowther to PENRITH</td>
	<td align="right">28</td>
</tr>
</table>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<head level="3" align="center">A DRIVE ROUND BASSENTHWAITE LAKE.</head>

<table align="center">
<tr>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b></b></td>
	<td align="center"><b>Computed Miles.</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">5</td>
	<td>To Bassenthwaite Sandbed</td>
	<td align="right">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">3&#189;</td>
	<td>Ouse Bridge</td>
	<td align="right">8&#189;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td align="right">9&#189;</td>
	<td>Through Wythop Woods to KESWICK</td>
	<td align="right">18</td>
</tr>
</table>

<pb n="72" />

<p><i>From Lancaster, by way of Furness Abbey, Coniston, &#38;c. to Windermere.</i> -- In approaching the Lakes from the south, a great variety of routes presents themselves, the choice of which must depend upon circumstances of taste, convenience, and modes of travelling. When the Tourist shall have arrived at Lancaster, should the ruins of Furness Abbey be an object of contemplation, the shortest way is to cross the Lancaster and Ulverston Sands, which on a fine day, may be considered a very interesting ride of 22 miles to Ulverston; from whence it is 7 miles to the Abbey. Those who want courage to venture upon the sands, may take the new turnpike road to Milnthorp. Opposite the village of Bolton, about 2 miles to the right, is a natural cavern, called Dunald Mill Hole; and further onwards the two remarkable hills of limestone -- Warton Crag on the left, and Farleton Knot to the right. From Lancaster to Milnthorp is 14 miles: and here is the option of the Ulverston or Kendal roads. The Ulverston road after passing Heversham and Levens, turns to the left, over some large tracts of peatmoss, having on the right the isolated ridges of limestone, called Whitbarrow, [the white hill] and Yewbarrow, forming lofty scars, [escarpments] on their western sides, and reposing on the slaty rock upon which the road

<pb n="73" />

in part is formed. From Milnthorp to Newby Bridge is 15 Miles; and here is the choice of continuing the Ulverston road, or proceeding along the banks of Windermere, by Bowness and Low Wood to Ambleside. </p>


<p>The new road to Ulverston follows the course of the Leven to Backbarrow, where it crosses the river by a bridge situated among manufactories of cotton, of iron, of pyroligneous acid, and of gunpowder. Leaving Hollow Oak on the left, it passes over some peatmoss, and presently approaches the sands, where it is interesting to meet the flowing tide, as it washes against the breastwork of the road. Crossing the river Crake, which issues from Coniston Water, by a bridge under which the tide flows, it joins the old road a little below Penny Bridge. From Newby Bridge to Ulverston is 8 miles, Ulverston to Dalton 5, and thence to Furness Abbey 2 miles. This Monastery was founded in 1127, the Monks were Benedictines of the order of Savigny; they afterwards became Cistertians, and continued till the dissolution in 1537. Ulverston is upon the slaty rock, Dalton upon mountain limestone, and the valley in which Furness Abbey is placed is flanked by red sandstone, from which the Abbey has been built. Iron ore is procured in large quantities from veins in the limestone; good specimens of red hematite 

<pb n="74" />

may here be obtained, with specular iron ore, and quartz crystals. </p>

<p>Two miles from Ulverston is Conishead, generally called the Priory, a place highly extolled by Mr. West, who says "it is a great omission in the curious traveller, to be in Furness and not to see so wonderfully pretty a place, to which nature has been so profuse in noble gifts, and where art has lent its best assistance, under the regulation of an elegant fancy, and a refined taste." The house is now undergoing a complete renovation. </p>

<p>After visiting Furness Abbey, the road generally preferred from Ulverston, is by Lowick Hall and Chapel, where there is a good view of Coniston Lake, with the mountains at its head, and Helvellyn in the distance. And after crossing Lowick Bridge, to proceed up the eastern side of the lake to Waterhead Inn, distant from Ulverston 14 miles. </p>

<p>At Coniston besides the views of the lake from its banks, and from its bosom in a boat, the lovers of landscape beauties may find some pretty walks, in the vales of Yewdale and Tilberthwaite. A full length view of the lake is obtained in passing over the hill called Tarnhows, on the road towards Elterwater; and an excursion to Levers Water, and the Old Man, on a fine day, would not be thought uninteresting. The geologist may amuse

<pb n="75" />

himself by tracing a stratum of transition limestone, alternating with slate, as it bassets out upon the hills, on the north-west of the road leading towards Borwick Ground; and beyond which place it is quarried, and a kiln built, on the left of the road to Ambleside. The slate quarries about Tilberthwaite, and the copper mines on Tilberthwaite Fell, and near Levers Water, may also be visited; and on the road to Ambleside, the Brathay flag quarry may be considered worth notice. </p>

<p>From Coniston, those who feel no hesitation in crossing the Ferry on Windermere, may proceed through Hawkshead, by the side of Esthwaite Water, to the Ferry; and after taking a view of Windermere, from Mr. Curwen's Station-house, cross the water to Bowness, distant from Coniston Water-head 9 miles. Those who object to crossing the water, may either proceed from Coniston to Ambleside direct, 8 miles; or from the Ferry, by the western banks of the lake to Ambleside, distant from Coniston by this route 14 miles. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>From Milnthorp direct to Windermere.</i> -- Putting Furness Abbey out of the question, some will rather proceed from Milnthorp to Kendal, and from thence to Windermere Lake at Bowness, Low Wood, or Ambleside. At Ken-

<pb n="76" />

dal, a museum kept by Mr. Todhunter deserves attention, as exhibiting the natural history and antiquities of the country. Here is also a marble manufactory carried on by Mr. Webster, where several varieties of limestone are worked and polished as marble. From Milnthorp to Kendal, is 8 miles; Kendal to Bowness, 9. For such as wish to arrive at once upon the centre of Windermere, there is a shorter, but inferior road from Milnthorp to Bowness, through Crosthwaite and Winster, in one stage of 14 miles. From Kendal to Low Wood Inn is 12, and to Ambleside 14 miles. About 8 miles from Kendal, on either the Bowness or Ambleside road, there is a grand view of Windermere Lake. Near Bowness, are eminences of various degrees of elevation; where according to the taste of the party, the views may be taken either from a higher or a lower station. -- At Low Wood, while the admirer of landscape takes his views of the lakes and mountains from the rising grounds; and the angler amuses himself upon the water; the geologist may be employed in examining the position of the transition limestone, and the slate, where they have been worked, in two adjoining quarries near the road, about 300 yards north of the inn. And the neighbourhood of Ambleside affords many pleasing excursions. </p>

<pb n="77" />

<p>Coniston and its environs may be visited from Bowness, first crossing the Ferry on Windermere. It is very pleasant over the rising grounds of Sawrey, and by the side of Esthwaite Water, over which there are sweet views of the vale of Hawkshead, spotted with neat houses, and its church on an elevated site; the mountains of Langdale and Grasmere, with Helvellyn, and those of Rydal, rising proudly in the distance. Passing through the little town of Hawkshead, (where a post-chaise is kept at the Red Lion,) and over the high grounds to the inn at Coniston Waterhead, the distance from Bowness is 9 miles. The return may be made by the head of Windermere to Bowness 13, or to Ambleside 8 miles; but it would be a great omission to forego the beautiful views that might be had on the road from Bowness, by Troutbeck bridge and Low Wood, to Ambleside. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />


<p><i>Ambleside.</i> -- The Langdale excursion from Ambleside or Low Wood, presents a variety of lake and mountain scenery, scarcely to be equalled in a journey of the same length, during the whole tour. It may be performed on horseback; but many parts of the road will not admit of any kind of carriage, except a cart. Passing Clappersgate, the party may either proceed with the river on 

<pb n="78" />

the left, to Skelwith Bridge; or crossing Brathay Bridge, take the river on the right, by Skelwith Fold. At Skelwith Bridge, is a public-house, and a little further up the river, a considerable waterfall; but the road by Skelwith Fold, being on a higher elevation, commands a fuller view into Great Langdale. After the junction of the two roads, there is a view of Elterwater. The road entering Lancashire at Brathay, or at Skelwith Bridge, leaves it again at Colwith Bridge; a little above which, is a pretty cascade. After passing Little Langdale Tarn, the road over Wrynose takes the left hand; the one to be pursued, turns to the right, ascending the common to Blea Tarn, where the appearance of Langdale Pikes is singularly grand and impressive. Leaving the tarn and solitary farm house on the left, proceed to the edge of the hill, where you will have a fine view of the head of Great Langdale, into which the road steeply descends. A curious waterfall may be seen in Dungeon Gill, a stream issuing between the two Pikes. The rocks hereabout exhibit a peculiarly flinty appearance. Mill Beck is the stream flowing from Stickle Tarn, and gives name to two farm-houses, at one of which it may be convenient to leave the horses, while visiting Dungeon Gill. Pursuing the road down Great Langdale, the traveller will arrive at Thrang

<pb n="79" />

Crag, where the rock in a slate quarry is excavated in an awful manner; and soon after pass the chapel, near which is a small alehouse. Here, taking the road to the left, you come to a second prospect of Elterwater; and near the farm-house called High Close, you have a view over Loughrigg Tarn, with Windermere in the distance; and soon after, a sight of the lake and beautiful vale of Grasmere, near the station recommended by Mr. West. Leaving the lakes of Grasmere and Rydal, on the left, join the turnpike road, and conclude the excursion at Ambleside after a most pleasing circuit of eighteen miles. </p>

<p>A variety of shorter excursions may be made from Ambleside; a walk of half a mile from the inn, to the waterfall of Stock Gill, will not be neglected; and one of a mile and a half may be taken to the falls at Rydal. A ramble round the lakes of Rydal, and Grasmere; round, or over Loughrigg Fell; a more elevated walk to Wansfell Pike; or the still more lofty circuit of Fairfield, on a favourable opportunity, will not fail to please such as delight in extensive prospects. Those who have not already seen Coniston, may make an excursion thither: and Ullswater may also be visited from hence, by the steep carriage road over Kirkstone, (which rises 1200 feet above Ambleside,) to Patterdale 10 miles; and either

<pb n="80" />

return the same way, or proceed to Penrith 15 miles more. Or stop at Pooley Bridge, if that be preferred; from whence Hawes Water, and Lowther Castle may be visited. And some who travel on horseback might choose a ride over the mountains Wrynose and Hardknot, through the vale of Eskdale to Nether Wasdale, about 22 miles; and next day by Wast Water, Styhead, and Borrowdale, to Keswick 20 miles. </p>


<p>At Ambleside is an exhibition of drawings, and prints, begun by the late Mr. Green, and continued by his family. Mr. Green depicted the varied scenery of this interesting region, with an ability and industry seldom united in one person. In the entrance upon a tour, these delineations may be useful, in shewing the character of the several parts of the country about to be visited; and on the conclusion, a selection -- which can be purchased at a moderate expense -- may revive at a future period the pleasing recollection of some favourite scenes. And, Green's Guide will long remain a monument of the assiduity with which he pryed into the arcana of these mountains. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>From Ambleside to Keswick.</i> -- The road from Ambleside to Keswick affords a charming variety; it passes, first Rydal Water, and the extensive slate quarry at White Moss; and then, leads 

<pb n="81" />

through the beautiful vale of Grasmere, so much extolled by Mr. Gray. Crossing the hill called Dunmail Raise, where a large heap of stones marks the boundary of Westmorland and Cumberland, the lofty Skiddaw shews his venerable head in the distance; and presently a view of Thirlmere or Leathes' Water is obtained. The gap of Dunmail Raise, 720 feet above the level of the sea, is the lowest pass from north to south, through the mountain chain which extends from Black Combe into the county of Durham. The roads over Shap Fells, and Stainmoor, being each above 1400 feet. After passing the small inn and Chapel of Wythburn, and approaching the margin of the lake, Helvellyn is upon the right; but the road lies so near its base, that the full height of the mountain cannot be seen. A little beyond the sixth mile stone from Keswick, the summit of Skiddaw again appears to the left of the wooded hill called Great How; to the right of which, and more in front, is a delightful view of the vale of Legberthwaite, through which the road leads; a continuation of this valley takes the names of Fornside, and Wanthwaite, together constituting what is called St. John's Vale; beyond which the lofty Saddleback, with its furrowed front, closes the scene. A road turns off on the right towards Threlkeld, and passes under the

<pb n="82" />

bold castle-like rock of Green Crag, sometimes called the Castle rock of St. John's.  Surmounting the cultivated ridge called Castlerigg, at one mile from Keswick, there is a full view of Derwent Lake, with part of that of Bassenthwaite, the town and vale of Keswick, with its surrounding mountains. It was here, that Mr. Gray on leaving Keswick, found the view so enchanting, that he "had almost a mind to have gone back again." From Ambleside to Keswick is 16 miles. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>From Penrith, by Ullswater to Patterdale.</i> -- Those who approach the lakes, by the way of Penrith, may visit Ullswater from thence; either driving the length of the lake to Patterdale, or taking a boat at Pooley Bridge. On every reach of the lake, the prospects improve in grandeur as the traveller advances towards the mountains. At Hallsteads, on a fine promontory, with beautifully undulating grounds, Mr. Marshall has built an elegant house. About Lyulphs Tower, (a hunting seat built by the late Duke of Norfolk,) the views are excellent, and Airey Force may be seen by application to the keeper, who resides here. Glencoin is a farm placed in a sweet recess, where a brook divides the counties of Cumberland and Westmorland. At the foot of Glenridden, the Rev. Mr. Askew has a tasteful cot-

<pb n="83" />

tage. And towards the foot of Grisedale, stands the mansion anciently called Patterdale Hall. The inn at Patterdale is a little above the head of the lake, and opposite to it, on the side of Place Fell, there is a slate quarry excavated to a considerable extent; from the banks of which you have a grand view of the mountains and part of the lake; the highest point of Helvellyn may be just seen from hence, or from Lyulphs Tower; but not from any place nearer the inn. From Penrith to the inn at Patterdale is 15 miles; from whence the party may either return to Penrith, or proceed over Kirkstone to Ambleside, 10 miles. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>Hawes Water.</i> -- This lake, on account of its distance from the main roads, is often omitted in the tour; but such as are desirous, may visit it from Penrith, by Eamont Bridge. Turning to the right at Arthur's Round Table, between the rivers Eamont and Lowther, pass Askham, Butterswick and Bampton; proceeding as far along the banks of the lake as may be thought expedient: and in returning, if on horseback or on foot, taking the track over the common called Moor Dovack, from whence there is a fine view of the greater part of Ullswater. From thence descend to Pooley Bridge, and for variety cross the river, returning by Dalemain to Penrith. Sup-

<pb n="84" />

posing this excursion extended as far as Chapel hill at the head of Hawes Water, the whole circuit will be near 30 miles. But those who take up their quarters for a time at Pooley Bridge, may visit Hawes Water from thence. Near Pooley Bridge, a remarkable hill called Dunmallard stands at the foot of Ullswater; it appears to be formed of a conglomerated mass, which may be seen on the sides of the road, and by which the lake seems to be embanked. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>From Carlisle to Keswick.</i> -- Tourists from the north, when at Carlisle, may proceed towards the lakes, either by Penrith or Wigton: from Carlisle to Penrith is 18 miles; Penrith to Keswick 18 more. Or Carlisle to Wigton 11, and Wigton to Keswick 22 miles. On the road from Wigton towards Keswick, there are some good views over the Solway frith; and Bassenthwaite Lake (which some say should be first visited) is seen without deviating from the road -- one of the richest views that it affords, being from the top of the hill called the Hause, about four miles after leaving Ireby; there is also a good retrospective view, about five miles before entering Keswick. </p>


<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>Keswick.</i> -- Having now by different roads conducted the several parties to Keswick, it must

<pb n="85" />

be made head-quarters for a while, to examine the curiosities of the place -- to enjoy the rich scenery in its neighbourhood -- and to make excursions, some of a few hours, some of a day, and others perhaps of more than one day. </p>

<p>Keswick has a population of 1900 inhabitants; its principal trade is in the woollen manufactory; here are also considerable manufactories of black lead pencils, by Mr. Banks, Mr. Airey, and others. The principal inns are the Royal Oak and Queen's Head; there are other houses where small parties may be accommodated, besides a variety of private lodgings neatly furnished. Here are two museums, exhibiting the natural history of the country, and many foreign curiosities: one was established by the late Mr. Crosthwaite, (who published his Maps of the lakes about forty years ago,) and is now kept by his son; the other is kept by Mr. Hutton, who has for many years acted as guide to the gentry frequenting the Royal Oak inn, and who has assiduously applied himself to the pursuits of botany and mineralogy, as each in its turn became the fashion of the day. At both the museums and at other places, the various mineral productions of the country are kept on sale. Post chaise and ponies may be had at the inns, with experienced guides for excursions by land; and neat pleasure-boats, with intelligent boatmen for the water. </p>

<pb n="86" />

<p>For an introduction to the beauties of Keswick vale, a good station will be found on Castlehead -- a wooded rock in the centre of the Derwentwater estate, at the distance of half a mile from the inn, and rising to the height of 280 feet above the lake of Derwent, which is here finely displayed with its numerous bays and islands. Lord's Island, near the shore, was once the residence of the fafamily of Derwentwater; the smaller Island of Rampsholm lies beyond it, St. Herbert's Isle nearer the middle of the lake, and to the right Vicar's Isle on which General Peachy has a house. The circumjacent mountains of Borrowdale and Newlands make a fine panorama. At the head of Borrowdale appears Great End Crag, beyond it a part of Scawfell and the highest of the Pikes. Looking through the vale of Newlands, Red Pike, distinguished by its colour, rises over Buttermere. To the eastward, Wanthwaite Crags, and Great Dod, form the end of the mountain range extending from Helvellyn. To the north Skiddaw rises finely, and Saddleback may be seen over the trees. Crosthwaite Church is a good object in the vale, and over the rising ground beyond Bassenthwaite Lake, the mountain Criffel in Scotland shews his head. This may be thought too elevated a station for the eye of a painter; but as a general view of the lake, the town, and valley, it is excellent. 

<pb n="87" />

Some of the lower stations formerly recommended are rendered less inviting by the too great profusion of wood upon the shores of the lake, and upon the islands; but this rock will always remain sufficiently prominent for a prospect; and in itself it offers a study for the geologist. </p>

<p>A walk by the water side, to Friar Crag, at the distance of three quarters of a mile, is the favourite promenade of the inhabitants of the town, and affords much gratification to strangers. On leaving the street the prospect is over Crow Park, which at the time of the attainder of the late Earl of Derwentwater, was a wood of stately oaks; but now a fine, swelling, verdant field, on which races are annually held. Beyond this the view embraces the vale and mountains of Newlands, with High-stile presiding over Buttermere in the distance: in retrospect Skiddaw rises majestically over the town. On the left, lies Cockshot, a hill thickly covered with oaks, and a tall silver fir upon its crest; the trees intercept the views from its summit, but a walk round its margin may sometimes be taken on account of the shelter it affords. Coming in sight of the lake, Vicar's Isle is most happily placed, the house just appearing among a variety of forest trees with which the island seems wholly covered; but on inspection, it is found to be beautifully laid out in pleasure 

<pb n="88" />

grounds, and kept in the neatest order. Along the margin of the water numerous boats are moored, some belonging to private individuals, others kept for the accommodation of visitors; and at the termination of the walk on the low promontory of Friar Crag, the eye is saluted with a full prospect of the lake, bounded by the far famed mountains of Borrowdale. To the left, near the shore, Stable Hills farm is reared, upon the site where stood Lord Derwentwater's stables at the time his mansion was upon the adjacent island. The Parks, part cultivated, part wooded, occupy the rising ground, over which Wallow Crag shews his massive rocky front; those, with the lands betwixt the town and lake, form the Derwentwater estate, now belonging to Greenwich Hospital. Further on lies Barrow House, and above it the pastoral farm of Ashness; beyond the small island of Rampsholm pours the famed cataract of Lowdore; and Castle Crag appears between more lofty mountains, like a centinel placed to guard the entrance of Borrowdale. To the right of St. Herbert's Isle, Catbells with a front of lighter green, shelve into the lake; which is chiefly bordered on that side by the woods of the late Lord William Gordon. Looking through the lateral vale of Newlands Red Pike appears beyond Buttermere, and more to the right Causey Pike, and Grisedale Pike, shew their aspiring peaks. </p>

<pb n="89" />

<p>Excellent views of the vale and mountains are also obtained from the Vicarage, from Ormathwaite, from many parts of the road a little elevated on the foot of Skiddaw, and from the side of Latrigg. Those who admire higher elevations, may climb to the top of Latrigg -- Wallow Crag -- Swinside -- Catbells -- Causey Pike, or Grisedale Pike; -- and to crown the whole, for once, to the summit of Skiddaw. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>Round Derwent Lake.</i> -- A delightful excursion may be made round Derwent Lake, either on horseback or in a carriage. Two miles from Keswick, with the lake on the right, a road turns off to Watendlath; a little further is Barrow House, behind which is a fine cascade. Barrow House, the property of Roger Pocklington, Esq. of Muskham House, Nottinghamshire; as also that upon the Island, now General Peachy's; and one at Derwent Bank, afterwards purchased by Lord William Gordon; -- were built by the late Mr. Pocklington. His style of building was rather singular, and has occasioned many severe remarks. At the time of his first becoming acquainted with the neighbourhood of Keswick it was comparatively little known, and he was desirous of contributing to its celebrity; and though his attempts to improve the face of the country 

<pb n="90" />

failed to meet with general approbation; yet, his errors of judgment were fully compensated by the liberality of his motives, and Keswick may long remember his name as one of its first benefactors. Three miles from Keswick is Lowdore, famous for its waterfall. A mile further is the Grange, which is a name of frequent occurrence in situations near some river; as, Grange, in Cartmel parish -- Grange, at Bampton -- and Marsh Grange, near the river Duddon. About Lowdore and Grange, the draftsman will find employment for his pencil, and the geologist will observe the transition from the dark coloured clay slate to the more variously aggregated and paler coloured slaty rocks. The river may be crossed at Grange, but to proceed a mile further to the Bowder Stone will generally be preferred; not altogether for a sight of the stone itself, (though it is considered as a curiosity, being a large fragment of rock pitched in a singular position,) but more especially for a prospect here displayed of the higher parts of Borrowdale. Returning to Grange, the road then crosses the river, and is carried along a pleasant elevation above the woods of the late Lord William Gordon, which, with the house standing on a sheltered bay of the lake, have lately been offered for sale. From this elevation, the lake -- with its islands, bays, and 

<pb n="91" />

promontories -- is seen to great advantage. The road then crossing the pleasant vale of Newlands, joins the Cockermouth road at Portinscale, and reaches Keswick in a circuit of 12 miles. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>Keswick to Borrowdale.</i> -- On a second excursion to Borrowdale, on foot or on horseback, the road by Ashness to Watendlath may be taken: it affords some fine bird's-eye views of Derwent Lake, with Bassenthwaite in the distance. After losing sight of the lakes, the road lies along a contracted valley, by the side of the stream which supplies the cataract of Lowdore. At the distance of five miles from Keswick it reaches Watendlath, where the valley expands and shows a few farm-houses, and a small tarn bordered by meadows and encompassed by elevated grounds. A track leads from thence over the hill, from which there is a fine view of the head of Borrowdale; it then descends steeply to Rosthwaite, whence the return may be made by Bowder Stone to Keswick; a circuit of 14 miles. To contract this excursion, the stream from Watendlath may be crossed about a mile beyond Ashness; then, turning towards Lowdore, one of the finest views the country affords is through the opening above the waterfall. </p>

<pb n="92" />

<p><i>Keswick to Buttermere.</i> -- An excursion through Borrowdale to Buttermere may be made on horseback, taking the road as before described as far as Bowder Stone: a mile beyond which, at Rosthwaite, is a small public-house. A little further, a road on the left leads by Stonethwaite, over the steep mountain pass called the Stake, to Langdale. Tourists have sometimes been advised, by this track to connect Borrowdale with Langdale, in one excursion; but the better way is to explore Langdale from Ambleside, and Borrowdale from Keswick. </p>

<p>At Seatollar, about eight miles from Keswick, a road on the left leads to the Blacklead Mine, and to Wast Water; and here the Buttermere road, turning to the right, ascends (by the side of a stream broken into pretty waterfalls,) up a steep hill; from which there are some fine retrospective views of the upper parts of Borrowdale; and Helvellyn soon begins to shew his head, over the mountains of Watendlath. In passing the hause, (which rises 880 feet above the level of Derwent Lake,) Honister Crag in majestic grandeur is presented to the view; between which, and Yew Crag, the road now sharply descends: both these rocks are famed for producing roofing slate of the best quality. Here the edges of the road are beautifully tufted with <i>Alchemilla alpina</i>, 

<pb n="93" />

and on the side of the stream is a small vein of specular iron ore. Gatesgarth dale, through which the road now goes, (twice crossing and re-crossing the stream) is a narrow valley, strewed with large blocks of stone, fallen from the rocks above; and solemnly shaded by the lofty Honister, which towers to the height of 1700 feet above the vale. We now re-enter upon the same soft clay-slate rock, which we parted from at Grange, and the change is soon apparent in the smoothness of the road. </p>

<p>Opposite to the farm of Gatesgarth, which is two miles from the inn at Buttermere, a shepherd's path leads over the mountain, by a pass called Scarf-gap, and after crossing the narrow dale of Ennerdale, proceeds to Wasdale head over a second and higher mountain called the Sail. The crags on the left of Scarf-gap are, from their form, called Haystacks; and to the right three adjoining summits are called High-crag, High-stile, and Red-pike. The two first are composed of what some would call a porphyritic greenstone rock, the third of a reddish sienite. Between the second and third is a small tarn, described by Mr. West, as "a large crater, that from the parched colour of the conical mountains in whose bosom it is formed, appears to have been the focus of a volcano at some distant period 

<pb n="94" />

of time when the cones were produced by the explosion!" The road, after passing Gatesgarth, touches upon the margin of Buttermere Lake, where a vein of lead ore is opened by the wayside, and a little further upon the left is the neat sheltered cottage of Haseness. From Keswick to the inn at Buttermere by this route is 14 miles. </p>

<p>When at Buttermere, a boat is usually taken upon Crummock Lake, as well for the views of the lake, as being the most convenient way of seeing Scale Force. It is an agreeable walk of half a mile to the water, and after a pleasant little voyage of nearly a mile, there is three quarters of a mile to walk to the fall. Travellers may indeed walk from the inn to Scale Force; but it being a wet and unpleasant path, the boat is greatly to be preferred. If the weather be unfavourable for taking boat, a good view of Crummock Lake may be had, by riding a mile and a half to the rocky point called the hause. After the necessary refreshment at Buttermere, it is an agreeable ride of 9 miles through the peaceful vale of Newlands, and by Portinscale to Keswick. </p>

<p>Those who travel in carriages to Buttermere, must take the Cockermouth road, over the steep mountain Whinlatter, which, in the length of two miles, rises to the height of 800 feet above 

<pb n="95" />

the vale. After passing the sixth mile-stone, a road turns to the left, which winding round the hill, presents a fine view of the cultivated vale of Lorton, and a distant prospect of the mountains of Kircudbright. If the day be favourable for a voyage on Crummock Lake, the carriage may be driven to the inn at Scale Hill, 12 miles from Keswick. Here by taking a boat upon the lake, the mountains are seen to great advantage; and the boat may be landed for a walk to Scale Force, and again, for a walk to the village, and a view of the lake of Buttermere; then returning the same way to Keswick. If any objection should arise to taking a boat, the carriage may be driven along the banks of Crummock Lake to Buttermere, (16 miles;) and after the necessary stay at Buttermere, return by the same road. It is indeed practicable to take a carriage through the vale of Newlands, but it is a road not to be recommended, as entirely free from danger. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<note id="n6">There is a great discordancy in the spelling and pronounciation of local names: this is provincially pronounced <i>Seewhaite</i>, while a place near the source of the river Duddon, with the same spelling, is called <i>Se&#228;thet</i>.</note>
<p><i>Keswick to Wast Water, &#38;c. &#38;c.</i> -- Those tourists who visit Wast Water from Keswick, generally make an excursion on horseback for two days: by which plan, Borrowdale and Wast Water are seen on the first day; and Ennerdale, Lowes Water, Crummock, and Buttermere on the second. The road up Borrowdale as far as 

<pb n="96" />

Seatollar, has already been described; from whence the Wasdale road is on the left to Seathwaite;<ptr target="n6"/> opposite to which on the right, lies the famous Black-lead Mine. Beyond Seathwaite, the road becomes a mere track, fit only for horses accustomed to the country. A waterfall presents itself to view on the right; and after crossing a rude bridge, the ascent of the mountain is commenced by a winding path. On passing a piece of water called Sty-head Tarn, the bold and lofty crag of Great-end, appears conspicuous on the left; and beyond it, in towering majesty, the highest of the Pikes. Great Gable is close upon the right; but the grandeur of its form is better appreciated at a distance. The highest part of  the road at Sty-head is 1250 feet above the first house in the vale, and here a magnificent view presents itself; the small valley of Wasdale head appearing as if sunk below the general level, and the sea at a distance seeming to rise in the horizon. The lake of Wast Water is not yet in sight, being hid by a projecting mountain on the left, called Lingmel. A steep zigzag track now descends on the side of Gable, down which the horses



<pb n="97" />

may be led; as it is neither quite safe nor agreeable to ride; crags of the most grotesque forms overlook the road, and the side of the hill is profusely strewed with stones, in some of which garnets may be found imbedded: and in crossing the stream which issues between Gable and Kirkfell, a rock of reddish granite may be seen, where it is denudated by the waters on both sides of the road. </p>

<p>Wasdale head consists of half a dozen tenements, comprising about 400 acres of land, which is divided by stone walls into small irregular fields, and has been cleared with great industry and labour; as appears from the enormous heaps of stones, piled up from the surplus after completing the inclosures. These six or seven families have their Chapel of a size proportionate to the number of inhabitants, and in a style according with the situation; and what Mr. Gray formerly said of Grasmere, may with equal propriety be applied to this vale: "Not a single red tile, no gentleman's flaring house, or garden walls, break in upon the repose of this little unsuspected paradise; but all is peace, rusticity, and happy poverty, in its neatest, most becoming attire." </p>

<p>After passing the inhabited part of the valley, the road approaches the lake, which shews the purity of its water, by the clean blue gravel washed upon its shores. As the road proceeds along 

<pb n="98" />

the margin of the lake, the screes on the opposite side form a striking object, and the mountains left behind should not be forgotten: retrospective views taken at short intervals, will shew the majestic and varied forms they assume on being viewed from different points. </p>

<p>It has been suggested, that Wast Water would be more advantageously seen, by reversing the excursion, so that the principal mountain views would be always in prospect on advancing up the vale. As far as relates to Wast Water alone, this is certainly true; but as it concerns Borrowdale, Lowes Water, and Crummock, they are seen to more advantage by this route: besides, tourists generally congratulate themselves, on having passed over the most difficult part of the road on the first day. </p>

<p>Towards the lower parts of the lake, the shores are more rocky; and the composition of the rock is changed, from a kind of greenstone, to a reddish sienite. About a mile after passing the foot of the lake, a road turns on the left to Ravenglass; and a little further on near the Church, there are two small public-houses, at one of which it may be necessary to take some refreshment, after a morning's ride of 20 miles, and none of the best road. </p>

<p>About four miles further, in the village of Gos-

<pb n="99" />

forth, a tall column carved with rude characters is seen in the church-yard near the road. We have now left the mountainous district, and entered upon one more cultivated, where the principal views are towards the sea, to which the road seems fast approaching; and the mountain rocks are exchanged for a red sandstone. The roads, from Wasdale, Eskdale, and Ravenglass, unite at Gosforth; from whence it is nearly three miles of excellent road to Calder Bridge. There are two neat small inns at Calder Bridge, at one of which, lodgings are generally taken for the night. Three quarters of a mile above the bridge, are situated the remains of Calder Abbey, (a dependant on Furness Abbey,) founded by the second Ranulph de Meschines in the year 1134, for Cistercian Monks. The arches supporting the tower, and part of the colonnade, are still perfect; but its value as a ruin is somewhat deteriorated, by a part of its site being taken for the family mansion of the Senhouses, to whom it now belongs. </p>

<p>From Calder Bridge there is an excellent road of ten miles to Whitehaven; but that generally taken by tourists inclines more towards the mountains, which however on this side present no very interesting features. For some miles the principal prospect is over a cultivated country to the sea, with the Isle of Man, and the Scotch mountains in the distance. About three miles 


<pb n="100" />

from Calder Bridge, the two rival points of Scawfell, appear over the neighbouring mountains, separated by the yawning chasm Mickle Door; and two miles further, the town of Egremont is seen through a narrow vale on the left. Seven miles from Calder Bridge, a part of Ennerdale Lake appears in sight, and after passing the hamlet of Ennerdale Bridge, in which stands the Church, and two small public-houses; the lake is observed from the rising ground in another point of view, accompanied by the grand mountain scenery of Ennerdale; among which the Pillar stands conspicuous. The road here for a short distance is formed upon the limestone rock, which skirts the mountains. Turning to the right, by the public-house at Lamplugh Cross, the road in a mile further passes the Church, and the hall of Lamplugh. The hall is now rebuilt in the shape of a modern farm-house; the only remains of its ancient grandeur being a gateway with the inscription, "John Lamplugh, 1595." Two miles further, on turning round the end of the hill to the right, the small lake of Lowes Water comes in view, accompanied by a rich assemblage of mountains. Soon after passing this lake, that of Crummock presents itself in one of its best combinations: and crossing the river Cocker, we shortly arrive at Scale-Hill, distant from Calder Bridge rather more than 16 miles. </p>

<pb n="101" />

<p>If Buttermere has not been previously visited, a boat may be taken upon Crummock Lake, which, with a walk from the lake to Scale Force, will make a pleasing variety. In the meantime the horses may meet the party at Buttermere, and the return to Keswick be made through Newlands -- making this day's journey nearly 30 miles. Those who have seen Buttermere, may save above a mile, by taking the carriage road from Scale-hill; along which there is a pleasant view of the vale of Lorton, and also a fine view of the vale of Keswick in descending the hill from Whinlatter. Those who think this circuit too much for two days, may extend it to three, by stopping one night at Nether Wasdale, and another at Scale-hill. </p>

<p>To visit Wast Water in a carriage from Keswick, it will be necessary to go by Scale-hill and Ennerdale Bridge or Egremont -- stopping two nights at Calder Bridge, and returning the same way, or by Whitehaven. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p><i>Keswick to Bassenthwaite.</i> -- This being thought less interesting than most of the other lakes, is often reserved to the last; but some have remarked that it ought to be visited first, or before the imagination was too much elated by the more prominent features of the other lakes. However tourists who prefer an easy journey, will find ob-

<pb n="102" />

jects to please, in a perambulation of this lake. On the eastern side the traveller would sometimes wish for a nearer approach; and Mr. West has spoken highly of the views from the promontories of Scarness and Bradness; but as there is no very convenient access to those places, few would think themselves repaid for the trouble of visiting them. There is a pleasant halting place at Castle Inn, eight miles from Keswick; between this and Ouse Bridge at the foot of the lake, the view is more extended; and from some stations on the western side, the different projections of Skiddaw appear to great advantage. From Keswick to Ouse Bridge on the eastern side is eight miles and a half; the western side is a mile more, making a circuit of 18 miles. </p>

<p>Those who are not inclined to make the whole circuit of the lake, may be gratified in a ride of five miles by the foot of Skiddaw, to a station recommended by Mr. Crosthwaite, a little above the road on the common at the end of a wood of larches: and in returning (if on horseback) take the upper road by Milbeck, Applethwaite, and Ormathwaite, where some of the best views of Derwent and its environs will be found. From thence either take the nearest road to Keswick; or proceed by Mr. Calvert's occupation way along the side of Latrigg, and enter the town by the Penrith road. </p>

<pb n="103" />



<p><i>Keswick to Ullswater.</i> -- Ullswater may be visited from Keswick on horseback or on foot; leaving the Penrith road a little beyond the second mile-stone, crossing the vale of Wanthwaite, and passing over a bleak mountain side to Matterdale. Carriages are obliged to continue on the turnpike for more than ten miles. Neither of these roads offers any thing interesting, except the views of St. John's vale, and the mountain Saddleback; till they unite at Dockray: but after entering Gowbarrow Park, the prospect of Ullswater is presented in one of its richest points of view. Airey Force and Lyulphs Tower lie a little to the left, and it is then five miles of delightful road to the inn at Patterdale. Some who travel in carriages, go from Keswick to Pooley Bridge, and thence to Penrith or Ambleside; but the want of post-horses at Pooley Bridge is sometimes an inconvenience. </p>

<p>An attempt to enumerate all the permutations, that might be made in these excursions; or all the pleasing points, from which the varied scenery of this interesting region might be viewed; would be an endless and in fact an useless task. Persons who delight in exploring a country, need only be made acquainted with the outlines: they will feel more pleasure in finding out the rest. </p>

<pb n="104" />

<p><i>Season for visiting the Lakes.</i> -- Every season has its peculiarities. -- In spring, all nature is in its most cheerful mood. It is pleasing to observe the daily progress of the different kinds of trees as they spread out their leaves, and the different plants as they expand their blossoms; while the feathered choir enliven the air with their morning and evening songs. In the middle of summer, all is gay; the heat of the sun may at times incommode, but the lengthened days will afford a few hours for retirement in the shade, and the evenings are free from the chilling blasts prevalent at other seasons. -- In autumn, the fields, the woods, and the mountain sides, display their most splendid variety of colouring, and the air is often favourable for distant prospects; but the days are somewhat contracted, and for long excursions more early rising is required. -- In winter, though deserted, the lakes still exhibit the same expanse of water, or else a glassy sheet of ice; the mountains -- whether naked, or partially or wholly covered with a spotless mantle of snow -- still reign in their wonted majesty; the rocks have lost nothing of their grandeur; and the waterfalls are occasionally rendered more striking by the fantastic forms in which their spray is congealed. </p>

<gap desc="Two horizontal lines, the bottom line of which is thicker than the top one." />

</chap>

<pb n="105" />

<chap title="ON THE GEOLOGY OF THE LAKE DISTRICT.">


<head level="2" align="center">ON THE GEOLOGY OF THE LAKE DISTRICT.</head>

<p>At the time this essay was first published, the structure of the mountainous district of Cumberland, Westmorland, and Lancashire, was but little understood; scientific travellers had contented themselves with procuring specimens of the different rocks, without taking time to become acquinted with their relative position. Since then, it has received more attention from persons conversant with geological inquiries; but the result of their labours has not yet been given to the public. Therefore, the following observations may still be acceptable to such as require only a general outline; and to those who feel disposed to explore for themselves, they may be useful, in directing them more readily to the objects of their research. </p>

<p>It is a question not fully determined among geologists, as to what rocks the term primitive, and to which that of transition or secondary, ought to be applied; and it has also been disputed whether the rocks of this district should be regarded as stratified or unstratified. This may arise partly from a want of sufficient observation, and partly through want of a precise definition of the term stratification. It is true they present little of that regularity of appearance which is observable in the rocks of many other districts; yet

<pb n="106" />

they cannot be said to be devoid of all traces of stratification; and, if a qualified term be admissible, they may be said to be imperfectly stratified. </p>

<p>Granite is understood to occupy the lowest place in the series of rocks hitherto exposed to human observation, and appears to be the foundation upon which all the others have been deposited; also in some countries constitutes the peaks of the highest mountains, protruding itself through all the upper or newer formations: that however is not the case in the district under consideration: it is here only laid bare in the excavated parts of some of the mountains; or where it rises so far as to form hills or ridges, they are of inferior elevation. </p>

<p>That rock of granite which seems best entitled to the distinction of primitive, may be seen denudated in the bed of the river Caldew, near the north-east side of Skiddaw; and in a branch of the river Greta between Skiddaw and Saddleback, about 1200 feet above the level of the sea. This granite is of a grey kind, composed of quartz, white felspar, and black mica: it is traversed in various directions by veins of quartz, in some of which, molybdena, apatite, tungsten, wolfram, and other minerals have been found. </p>

<p>A variety of granite with reddish felspar, and which from its paucity of mica, has sometimes been called sienite, forms the two inferior mountain ridges, called Irton fell and Muncaster fell; 

<pb n="107" />

it extends to some distance on both sides of the river Esk, and may be seen in places almost as far as Bootle, and also at Wasdale head. At Netherwasdale it becomes a finer grained sienite, in which form it extends through the mountains quite across Ennerdale, as far as Scale Force, and to the side of Buttermere Lake. It contains veins of red hematite and micaceous iron ore. Another variety of granite with reddish felspar in large crystals, is found on Shap Fells, and may be observed <i>in situ</i> on the road side near Wasdale Bridge, about four miles south of Shap. </p>

<p>Carrock Fell consists of a rock generally referred to the class of sienite, varying its appearance in different parts of the mountain; it contains (besides the usual ingredients of quartz and felspar) hypersthene and magnetic or titaniferous iron ore in various proportions. Here a considerable quantity of lead ore and some copper have been procured: the lead is smelted and refined near the place, and yields a good portion of silver. </p>

<p>A reddish porphyritic rock occurs on both sides of St. John's Vale, from two to three miles east of Keswick; and a vein or dyke apparently related to the same, but far more beautiful, (being composed of crystals of quartz and bright red felspar, imbedded in a brownish red compact felspar,) is found on Armboth Fell, six miles SSE of Keswick. </p>

<p>It is not well known what place some of these

<pb n="108" />

granites, sienites, and porphyries hold in the series of rocks: from the scarcity of places at which their junction with the slate rocks can be seen, it is not easy to ascertain whether they have been deposited upon that substance or protruded through it; but the change in the appearance of the slate, and the alternations which take place near their junction, would give countenance to the latter supposition. </p>

<p>The rocks of which these mountains are principally formed, have commonly been included under the general appellation of slaty rocks; although many of them shew no disposition to the slaty cleavage. They may be classed in three principal divisions. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>Of these divisions, the FIRST or lowest in the series, forms Skiddaw, Saddleback, Grasmoor, and Grisedale Pike, with the mountains of Thornthwaite and Newlands; it extends across Crummock Lake, and by the foot of Ennerdale as far as Dent Hill; and after being lost for several miles, it is elevated again at Black Combe. </p>

<p>If we regard the granite of Skiddaw as a nucleus, upon which these rocks are deposited in mantle-shaped strata, the first incumbent upon it is a slaty rock sometimes called gneiss; but perhaps less related to granite than is the gneiss of some other countries. More distant from the gra-

<pb n="109" />

nite, the quantity of mica in the slate decreases, and it is marked with darker coloured spots; it is then provincially called whintin, and is quarried for flooring flags and other useful purposes. This again is succeeded by a slate of softer kind, in which crystals of chiastolite are plentifully imbedded; these crystals are gradually lost in a more homogenous clay-slate, which contrary to general observation, has its outgoing at a higher elevation than either the granite or the gneiss. </p>

<p>These rocks are of a blackish colour, and divide by natural partings into slates of various thickness, which are sometimes curiously bent and waved: when these partings are very numerous, though indistinct at first, they open by exposure to the weather, and in time it becomes shivered into thin flakes, which lessens its value as a roofing slate. In some places the thin lamina alternate with others of a few inches in thickness; these are harder, and of a lighter colour, containing a considerable portion of quartz; they have been by some taken for greywack&#233; slate, though apparently belonging to a different formation. </p>

<p>Rocks of this description have generally been represented as stratified, and the strata parallel to the slaty cleavage; but this proposition should not be received without some hesitation. If it be supposed that these varieties of rock (between which there is no natural parting) have been de-

<pb n="110" />

posited upon the granite in the order in which they have been mentioned; then, the strata may be said to be mantle-shaped round the granitic nucleus; only interrupted in its continuity by the anomalous rocks of Carrock: but if it be assumed that the stratification follows the slaty cleavage; then it may be said to have its bearing tending towards the north-east and south-west; dipping generally at a high angle to the south-east, and presenting the edges of its lamina to the surface of the granite, from the proximity of which the nature and appearance of the rock must be presumed to be altered. </p>

<p>The rocks belonging to this division do not effervesce with acids; they contain no calcareous spar, except a little in some of the veins. They are intersected in places by dykes of a harder kind of rock, apparently of the nature of trap or greenstone. Veins of lead ore occur in several places; and have been worked betweeen Skiddaw and Saddleback, in Thornthwaite, Newlands, and Buttermere, but one in the parish of Loweswater, and another about two miles below Ennerdale Bridge, are the most productive at present in this district. A copper vein has formerly been worked to a great depth in a hill called Gold Scalp, in Newlands, and is said to have produced a very rich ore, which appears to have been the yellow sulphuret or copper pyrites. A little cobalt ore

<pb n="111" />

has been got in Newlands, and small quantities of manganese in various places. A salt spring near the Grange in Borrowdale, has anciently been of some repute for its medicinal qualities; another has been more recently discovered in working a lead mine near Derwent lake. They both issue from veins in this rock, but their source remains unknown. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>The SECOND division comprehends the mountains of Eskdale, Wasdale, Ennerdale, Borrowdale, Langdale, Grasmere, Patterdale, Martindale, Mardale, and some adjacent places; including the two highest mountains of the district, Scawfell and Helvellyn, as well as the Old Man at Coniston. All our fine towering crags belong to it; and most of the cascades among the lakes fall over it. There are indeed some lofty precipices in the first division; but owing to the shivery and crumbling nature of the rock, they present none of the bold colossal features which are exhibited in this. </p>

<p>It comprises a great variety of rocks, many of them shewing some appearance of stratification; the general direction being towards the north-east and south-west, and the dip (but not without some exceptions) to the south-east. The nomenclature of these rocks is still very imperfect; some 

<pb n="112" />

of them may perhaps belong to the family of the greenstones, some are of a porphyritic, others of a slaty structure; differing however from the slates of the last division, inasmuch as these exhibit no distinct partings by which they are to be separated. A reddish aggregated rock of a coarse slaty structure, is to be seen on entering the common on the road from Keswick towards Borrowdale. It appears to form one of the lower beds of the division, and may be traced each way to some distance. It is succeeded by the more compact, dark-coloured rock of Wallow Cragg, in which quartz, calcareous spar, chlorite, and epidote, are found in veins. Garnets are found imbedded in some of the rocks on Castlerigg Fell and Great Gable. An amygdaloid rock, containing nodules of calcareous spar, and sometimes of agate, or calcedony, is met with in several places; as near Honister Crag -- between Bowder Stone and Rosthwaite -- on Castlerigg Fell, near Keswick -- and in Wolf Crag on the road to Matterdale; and a curious porphyritic and amygdaloidal rock near Berrier. No organic remains have yet been discovered, either in this or the preceding division. </p>

<p>Most of these rocks are of a pale bluish-grey colour. The fine pale-blue roofing slate occurs in beds (called by the workmen veins:) the most natural position of the lamina or cleavage of the slate appears to be vertical; but it is to be found in 

<pb n="113" />

various degrees of inclination, both with respect to the horizon, and the planes of stratification. The direction the slaty cleavage bears most commonly towards the north-east and south-west; while the dip or inclination varies. The former may be ascribed to some general operation of nature; the latter being influenced by local circumstances -- one of which may be the weight of a mountain pressing upon one side, while the other side is void of a support. The direction and inclination of the strata are more distinguishable by stripes and alternations in the colour and texture, than by any natural partings or strata seams; and the slates are split of various thickness, according to their fineness of grain, and the discretion and skill of the workman, without any previous indication of the place where they may be so divided. They do not separate into thin flakes, like those of the former division; but some of them, when long in use, are subject to a peculiar species of decay, which operates most powerfully on parts least exposed to the weather. </p>

<p>Most of the rocks of this division effervesce in some degree with acids, but more especially those possessing the slaty structure. They are not very productive of metallic ores, although they afford a considerable variety. Lead ore has been got in Patterdale; copper at Dalehead in Newlands, which is near the northern boundary of the divi-

<pb n="114" />

sion -- it consists of grey and purple copper, with specimens of malachite. A mine at Coniston, near the southern boundary, produces the yellow sulphuret; and a vein of the same has lately been opened at Wythburn. Small veins of iron ore are frequently met with, but scarcely thought worth notice. The famous plumbago or black-lead mine of Borrowdale is also situated in this division. </p>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p>The THIRD division, forming only inferior elevations, commences with a bed of dark-blue or blackish transition limestone, containing here and there a few shells and madrepores, and alternating with a slaty rock of the same colour; the several layers of each being in some places several feet, in others only a few inches in thickness. This limestone crosses the river Duddon near Broughton; passing Broughton Mills it runs in a north-east direction through Torver, by the foot of the Old Man mountain, and appears near a place called Yew Tree. It is then seen near the Tarns upon the hills above Borwick Ground; and stretching through Skelwith, it crosses the head of Windermere near Low Wood inn. Then passing above Dovenest, and Skelgill, it traverses the vales of Troutbeck, Kentmere, and Long-Sleddale; crossing the two intervening mountains in the direction of the roads which lead over 

<pb n="115" />

 them; so that no relation can be discovered between the direction of the vallies and that of the stratification. It dips to the south-east, while the cleavage of the slate with which it is associated, frequently inclines in an opposite direction. </p>

<p>Towards the south-east succeeds a series of rocks of the same dark-blue colour, and principally of a slaty structure: but associated in places with a rock which breaks alike in all directions. This has supplied a great portion of the rounded stones found in the beds of the rivers Kent and Lune; and furnishes materials for paving the streets and repairing the roads in the neighbourhood. </p>

<p>A rock of fine-grained sienite is observed near the foot of Coniston Lake; and one containing a large portion of mica appears in Crosthwaite. The strata seams are more distinct in this than in the preceding division; but, like that, it is not marked by any natural partings in the plane of cleavage. A quarry one mile from Brathay on the road towards Hawkshead, yields excellent flags for flooring; and they are manufactured into tombstones with good effect, by Mr. Webster of Kendal, and by Mr. Bromley of Keswick. This quarry affords a good example of the stratification (or, as some will have it, the rhomboidal crystallization) of these rocks. The cleavage is here nearly perpendicular; and the strata, being from one foot to five in thickness, dip to the south-

<pb n="116" />

east at an angle of about thirty degrees. In some districts the layers are so much diminished in thickness, that slates and tables are formed in the plane of the stratification, instead of that of the cleavage; and this has probably given rise to the notion of two distinct cleavages crossing each other under a certain angle. Large quantities of roofing-slate (called black slate, to distinguish it from the pale-blue of the second division) is manufactured in the district between Ulverston and Broughton; which is well situated for shipping either by the river Duddon or by canal from Ulverston. This division seems to correspond most nearly with the greywack&#233; formation of some geognosts; but advocates for the term will find greywack&#233; and greywack&#233;-slate interspersed through the whole of the series. </p>

<p>Although little difference has hitherto been made by authors between the roofing slates of these three divisions, yet a workman of moderate experience will readily distinguish them: and I have endeavoured to describe the peculiarities of each, that those who are hereafter engaged in examining similar districts may be better enabled to compare them. </p>


<p>The preference given to the slates from certain quarries as requiring less weight for the covering of a roof of given dimensions, depends not so much upon the specific gravity (which varies 

<pb n="117" />

at most from 2750 to 2800, or one part in 55) as upon the fineness of grain, which enables it to bear splitting thinner. All these rocks effervesce more or less with acids; they contain some calcareous spar and pyrites; but little metallic ore, except a small quantity of galena, with green and yellow phosphate of lead, which has been got near Stavely. </p>

<p>A conglomerate composed of rounded stones of various sizes, from the smallest gravel, to the weight of several pounds, held together by an iron-shot, calcareous cement, forms a hill of parabolic shape, about 1000 feet in height, called Mell Fell; and some lesser elevations extending to the foot of Ullswater. These pebbles are apparently fragments of older rocks, rounded by attrition, and must have been transported from some distance, as the majority do not correspond with those of the immediate neighbourhood. This has been taken by some to belong to the old red sandstone formation; but whether it passes under or only abuts against the adjacent limestone has not yet, I believe, been clearly ascertained. </p>

<p>A superincumbent bed of limestone mantles round these mountains, in a position unconformable to the strata of the slaty and other rocks upon which it reposes. It bassets out near Egremont, Lamplugh, Pardshaw, Papcastle, Bothel, Ireby, Caldbeck, Hesket, Berrier, Dacre, Lowther and Shap; it appears again near Kendal, Witherslack,

<pb n="118" />

Cartmel, Dalton and Millum, from whence for some distance its place is occupied by the sea, and in the neighbourhood of Gosforth and Calder Bridge, a red sandstone intervenes, so that the limestone is either wanting or buried under more recent formations. It dips from the mountains on every side, but with different degrees of elevation; the declivity being generally least on the southern side. In the neighbourhood of Witherslack it forms lofty isolated ridges, while the subjacent slaty rock appears in the lower ground: and it may be seen upon the surface as far as Warton and Farleton Crags, and even as far as Kellet, before it is covered by the sandstone of the coal measures. A remarkable exception, however, occurs in Holker Park, where the mountain rock is succeeded by limestone, and that by sandstone and shale, resembling that which accompanies coal -- all within a very short distance. On the north and west of the mountains, the inclination of the newer rocks appears to be greater and the strata thinner; so that the clay-slate of the first division is succeeded by limestone, sandstone, and coal, all in the distance of two or three miles. The principal mineral production of this limestone, is iron ore, which is raised in great quantities near Dalton; and the mines near Egremont, which have lain dormant for some time, are about to be re-opened. </p>

<pb n="119" />

<p>On external parts of this circle various sandstones and coal succeed each other, and a thin seam of coal may be sometimes found interstratified with the limestone, as at Hesket Newmarket; but it is easily understood, that it would be in vain to search for coal within this limestone circle; consequently it cannot be found in the neighbourhood of the lakes. </p>

<p>Bowlder stones are often met with, far removed from their native rock, but do not appear to have been carried over high mountain ridges. The granite blocks from Shap Fells are scattered over a great part of Westmorland; but are not found in the neighbourhood of the lakes. Bowlders from the sienite of Buttermere and Ennerdale are found on the west coast of Cumberland; but not in the vales of Keswick and Windermere. The granite of Caldew and sienite of Carrock can be recognized in bowlders in the neighbourhood of Carlisle; but are not seen to the south of Keswick. The famous Bowder Stone of Borrowdale does not come within the present description; but a large block near Skelwith Bridge on the road to Grasmere -- one near Coniston Waterhead, and another near Gosforth, as well as many others of smaller dimensions -- are far more interesting to the geologist, yielding sufficient scope for conjecture as to the place of their origin, and the mode of their removal. </p>

</chap>

<pb n="120" />

 <chap title="ON METEOROLOGY.">

<head level="2" align="center">ON METEOROLOGY.</head>

<p>Besides the permanent beauties of a country diversified by hills and dales, mountains and lakes, there are transient subjects capable of arresting the attention of the contemplative observer; -- amongst which are -- the mists or fogs -- forming over the surface of lakes -- floating along the sides of hills -- or collected into clouds, hovering upon the summits of mountains. </p>

<p>Mountains have been supposed to attract the clouds with which their summits are so frequently enveloped; but it is more to their agency in forming them, that the accumulation of clouds in mountainous countries may be attributed. Clouds are formed of aqueous particles floating in the atmosphere; and they serve as an awning, to shield the earth from the violence of the sun's rays in hot weather; and to protect it from the rigour of a cold winter's night, by obstructing the radiation of heat from its surface. In the clearest weather a portion of water always exists in the atmosphere in the state of an invisible vapour; and the higher the temperature of the air, the greater quantity of vapour it is able to sustain: therefore, when air, fully saturated with vapour, suffers a diminution of its heat, the water is exhibited in the form 

<pb n="121" />

of mists, clouds, dew, or rain. It has been stated by the late Dr. Hutton of Edinburgh, and more fully exemplified by Mr. Dalton, that the quantity of vapour capable of entering into air, increases in a greater ratio than the temperature; of course, whenever two volumes of air, of different temperatures, are mixed together, (each being previously saturated with vapour,) the mean temperature is not able to support the mean quantity of vapour; and consequently the precipitation of vapour in the form of clouds and rain, is occasioned, not by mere cold, but by a mixture of comparatively cold and warm air. And on this principle, may be explained, most of the phenomena of mist or fog, clouds, dews, and rain. </p>

<p>Different portions of the earth's surface, and consequently the contiguous portions of air, are differently heated by the sun's rays impinging upon them in different degrees of obliquity; and this difference is naturally much greater in a mountainous than in a champaign country; and on two portions of air thus unequally heated, being intermixed one with the other, either by the ascent of the warmer and consequently lighter part, or by the ordinary current of the wind, the vapour assumes a visible form. </p>

<p>The temperature of the earth, from a few yards below the surface, to the greatest depth hitherto 

<pb n="122" />

explored, suffers little variation between summer and winter. It corresponds nearly with the mean temperature of the atmosphere; being here, about 48 degrees of Fahrenheit's thermometer. A body of water, such as a lake of considerable depth, forms a kind of mean, between the subjacent earth and the superincumbent air: its surface is influenced by the temperature of the atmosphere, while its lower parts admit of little variation; consequently, the surface will in summer be the warmest, and in winter the coldest part. So long as the surface of the water retains its fluidity, the adjacent air never suffers so great an extreme of cold, as may be experienced at a distance; and the surface being frozen, the water contiguous to the ice will always be nearly 32&#176;; at the same time in the deeper parts, the temperature towards the bottom will be several degrees higher. </p>


<p>In clear weather, the surface both of the earth and of water, is warmed in the day and cooled during the night; but in very different proportions -- the water retaining its heat much longer than the land. It will sometimes happen in an autumnal evening, that the temperature of the air and that of the water of a lake, will be equal; and yet before sunrise there may be a difference of twenty degrees or upwards: in this case, the air above the water being warmer, will contain more 

<pb n="123" />

vapour than that above the land, and on their intermixture a mist or fog will be formed; which will continue to float in the atmosphere till it be either dissolved by an increase of heat, or being moved into a colder region, be deposited in the form of dew or hoar frost. Sir Humphry Davy has observed, that upon some rivers on the continent, a mist or fog began to appear as soon as the temperature of the air was diminished from 3 to 6 degrees below that of the water. This will depend upon the previous moisture or dryness of the air, and partly upon the current of the wind; but little of fog is to be seen on these lakes, until the difference of the temperature is more than 12 degrees. </p>

<p> On the disappearance of the sun in a clear evening, a mist is sometimes observed over a piece of moist ground; where it seems to be formed, and for some time kept afloat, by a kind of contention between the heated surface of the earth below it, and the colder atmosphere above; but the earth not continuing to afford the necessary supply of heat, the conflict ceases; and the vapour settles upon the grass in the shape of dew. </p>

<p>It has been a matter of surprise to some, that a cloud should seem to remain stationary upon the summit of a high mountain, while the air was moving at a brisk rate. The warm air of a valley

<pb n="124" />

being impelled up the inclined plane of a mountain side, into a colder region, is not able to support the same quantity of vapour; and a cloud is formed in consequence: and although the individual particles of which it is composed, are continually moving forward with the wind; yet by a perpetual accession of vapour on one side, and dispersion on the other, the cloud may continue to occupy the same place, and appear to a distant observer as stationary; although its component parts are successively changed. And in this manner may the materials of a cloud be transported invisibly from the summit of one mountain to that of another. </p>

<p>When a dense cloud settles upon a mountain, the wind frequently blows from it on one side with an increased momentum, while on the opposite side its motion is retarded: and a shower commencing on the hills, is generally preceded in its course by a squall; the air displaced by the falling rain, making its escape along the vallies where it meets with the least resistance. </p>

<p>A covering of snow makes a kind of barrier, between the internal heat of the earth, and that of the atmosphere: being a bad conductor, it preserves the surface of the earth from the severity of cold in winter; but in spring, excludes it from the genial effects of the solar rays. In the meantime the contiguous atmosphere suffers more ex-

<pb n="125" />

tensive variations; the greatest extreme of cold being experienced when the earth is covered with snow. Patches of snow are frequently remaining on Scawfell and Helvellyn, near the middle of July; and in 1816, a small speck was observed on the former mountain, on the 30th of that month, but it generally vanishes before that time, and there is no authentic account of its continuing the whole year upon any of these mountains. </p>

<gap desc="Two horizontal lines, the bottom line being thicker than the top one." />

</chap>

<chap title="THE FLOATING ISLAND IN DERWENT LAKE.">

<head level="2" align="center">THE FLOATING ISLAND IN DERWENT LAKE.</head>

<p>The existence of this phenomenon has been doubted by some persons, while others admitting the fact, have contended that the term Floating Island was incorrectly given; as it never changes its situation, being attached by its sides to the adjacent earth under water. Its occasional appearance, however, is ascertained beyond a doubt; and as the Floating Island is the name by which it has always been known, there can be no manifest impropriety in retaining the appellation. </p>

<p>It is situated in the south-east corner of the lake, not far from Lowdore, about 150 yards from the shore, where the depth of the water does not exceed six feet in a mean state of the lake. It 

<pb n="126" />

has been said to make its appearance once in seven years, but that is quite uncertain; it happens generally after an interval of a few years, and towards the conclusion of a warm summer. Its figure and dimensions are also variable; it has sometimes contained about half an acre of ground, at other times only a few perches: but as it extends in a gradual slope under water, a much greater portion is raised from the bottom, than reaches the surface of the lake. When at rest in the bottom of the lake, it cannot be distinguished from the neighbouring parts, being covered with the same kind of vegetation; namely, <i>Isoetes lacustris</i>, <i>Lobelia dortmanna</i>, <i>Littorella lacustris</i>, and other plants, found growing in the bottom of this and all the neighbouring lakes. Its surface to the depth of a few inches, is composed of a clayey or earthy matter, apparently deposited by the water; and in which the roots of the plants principally vegetate: the rest is a congeries of decayed vegetable matter, forming a stratum of loose peat earth about six feet in thickness; which rises from a bed of very fine soft clay, and is found to contain a considerable quantity of air; which may be dislodged by probing the earth with a pole. </p>

<p>After an absence of eight years, it emerged on the 20th of July 1808, and increased in size till 

<pb n="127" />

it might be about 80 yards in length, its height above water being about a foot; and although the depth of water in the lake was variable, yet for some weeks the island preserved nearly the same dimensions. It appeared to sink gradually till the beginning of October, when it became wholly covered with water. Its next appearance was on the 7th of September, 1813: but it was then of smaller dimensions; being only about 12 yards in length: yet, when in consequence of rain the surface of the lake rose above three feet in height, the island was buoyed up along with it, and was not entirely submerged before the end of October. It emerged again on the 6th of August, 1815; and on the 21st of that month it measured 88 yards in length, and in some places 25 in breadth; part of it remained above water, from that time till the first of September. And again in 1819 it appeared above water from the 14th of August to the end of that month. In 1824, after a fit of warm, dry weather, a small portion of it appeared on the 1st of June, being the earliest ever remembered; yet it never attained its full size, although it remained in part above water till the end of September. </p>

<p>Various solutions have been offered for this phenomenon: some assuming water, and others air, as the principal agent in its production; but 

<pb n="128" />

many of those attempts to account for its appearance, have been founded upon an incorrect description of the premises. In a Survey of the lakes, published by James Clarke in 1789, he says, it never appears but when the lake is swelled with rain; and then describes a mountain torrent called Cat Gill, which pours down a rock opposite the island, and before it reaches the lake disappears among the stones and gravel at the foot of the hill. This water he supposes to run to some distance under the lake, and that by its action upwards "it raises the turf into a convex form, and during the continuance of the torrent, gives it the appearance of an island." But even supposing that this water could be conveyed so far underneath the lake, the surface of the earth in this part always presents cracks and openings sufficient to admit of its being discharged without difficulty; besides that, on referring to a journal of the weather, it will be found, that every instance of its rising within the last twenty years, has happened when the lake was low, and not swelled with rain -- as Mr. Clarke had premised. </p>

<p>In the year 1808, during the time the island remained above water, various theories were presented to the public through the medium of the Carlisle Journal. When not concurring in any of those previously advanced, I offered my opinion

<pb n="129" />

thus: "Perhaps the carburetted hydrogen gas usually found at the bottom of stagnant water, may be produced here in greater quantity than in other parts of the lake; and probably this production may be increased by heat. Probably too by reason of springs underneath, the upper stratum of earth may not be so firmly attached to its bed; and the surface of the earth in the bottom of the lake, being closely interwoven with the roots of aquatic plants, prevents the escape of the gas, till the uppermost stratum of earth, being charged therewith, is raised from its bed: and the water gradually gaining admission underneath, easily bears it up, so long as the earth contains air enough to make its specific gravity less than that of water -- but when by exposure to the sun and wind, the earth becomes discharged of its gas, it gradually sinks to its old bed, to remain till a sufficient quantity is again accumulated." </p>


<p>It would be tedious to enumerate all the different theories, which have been from time to time proposed to account for this phenomenon, with the arguments for and against each. It may be sufficient to notice the following. </p>

<p>Some have ascribed its origin to those internal commotions by which earthquakes and volcanoes are produced. Some suppose, with Mr. Clarke, that the subterranean passage of the stream before 

<pb n="130" />

alluded to, may be continued to the place where the island appears, and that its usual aperture being in a dry season choked up, the increased pressure on the swelling of the brook by rain, may elevate the island. Others say, that the water in its fall down the rock being beat into a foam, a quantity of air, thus mechanically mixed with the water, may be conveyed underneath, and that this air on its disengagement may force up the earth along with it. Others again suppose, that the alluvia of vegetable matter may in this manner be carried underneath, and by its decomposition a quantity of hydrogen gas capable of producing this effect, may be evolved. And while one imagines that carburetted hydrogen, sufficient to elevate this mass of earth, may be produced by the decomposition of pyrites, supposed to be placed underneath it; another, not caring to enter so deeply into the subject, thinks the air contained in the cellular leaves of the plants growing upon the island, may be sufficient to give it buoyancy. </p>

<p>One material circumstance has however generally escaped observation: namely, that the air to which the rising of this island has been attributed, is not collected in a body underneath it; but interspersed through the whole mass: not causing it to float "as a reversed saucer would in a bowl of water;" but by enlarging its bulk, and thereby 

<pb n="131" />

diminishing its specific gravity. And the most rational conclusion seems to be, that air or gas is generated in the body of the island by decomposition of the vegetable matter of which it is formed; and this gas being produced most copiously, as well as being more rarefied in hot weather, the earth at length becomes so much distended therewith, as to render the mass of less weight than an equal bulk of water. The water then insinuating itself between the substratum of clay and the peat earth forming the island, bears it to the surface, where it continues for a time, till partly by escape of the gas, partly by its absorption by water, and partly by its condensation consequent on a decrease of heat, the volume is reduced; and the earth gradually sinks to its former level, where it rests till successive increments of gas again render it buoyant. </p>

<p>But as the vegetable matter of which the island is principally composed, appears to have been amassed at a remote period, when the lake has been of less depth than at the present; and very little addition recently made by the plants now growing upon the spot; it is reasonable to suppose that the process furnishing the gas cannot from the same materials be continued <i>ad infinitum</i>: but that there must be a time when it shall have arrived at its maximum; after which the eruptions will become less extensive or less frequent. </p>

<pb n="132" />

<p>In a note subjoined by Mr. Dalton to a paper of mine on this subject, (published in the Memoirs of the Literary and Philosophical Society of Manchester, vol. 3, new series,) he says, "a quantity of the inflammable gas collected from the Floating Island in 1815, I found to consist of equal parts of carburetted hydrogen and azotic gasses, with about 6 per cent of carbonic acid. The carburetted hydrogen was such that one part required two of oxygen for its complete combustion by electricity. It seems most probable that this gas is generated by the decomposition of vegetable matter in contact with water; two atoms of carbon decompose two of water, and form at the same instant an atom of carburetted hydrogen and one of carbonic acid. The carbonic acid, being absorbable by water, is mostly dispersed, and the other gas collects in small bubbles in the spongy texture of the soil till it is disturbed, when the bubbles unite and ascend in a body. The azotic gas is probably from the atmosphere, by means of the water. The almost total absence of oxygen from such mixtures is remarkable." </p>

<gap desc="Two horizontal lines, the top line being thicker than the bottom one."/>

</chap>

<pb n="133"/>

<chap title="THE BLACK-LEAD MINE IN BORROWDALE.">

<head level="2" align="center">THE BLACK-LEAD MINE IN BORROWDALE.</head>

<p>The mineral substance from which black-lead pencils are manufactured has successively been known by the several names of <i>wad</i>, <i>black-cawke</i>, <i>black-lead</i>, <i>plumbago</i>, and <i>graphite</i>. In the progress of chemistry and its application to mineralogy, the original term <i>wad</i>, was abandoned, probably in consequence of the same name being given by the Germans, to a substance somewhat resembling this in appearance but of a different nature, viz, an oxide of manganese: the term <i>black-cawke</i> might be subject to a similar objection, the word <i>cawke</i> being applied by miners to a sulphate of barytes: the names of <i>plumbago</i> and <i>black-lead</i>, although still retained in common use, tend to convey an erroneous idea of the subject, as lead forms no part of its composition, which is found to be principally carbon combined with a small portion of iron: and <i>graphite</i>, perhaps the least objectionable term, has scarcely yet obtained currency. </p>

<p>This mineral occurs in various parts of the world, and in rocks of different formation. In this island it has been discovered in Invernesshire, in gneiss, which is considered as one of the primitive rocks; there it appears to be intermixed

<pb n="134" />

with a micaceous substance and other hard mineral bodies which render it unfit for pencils. In the borders of Ayrshire, it is found in the neighbourhood of coal, to which it seems too nearly allied: but in no place has it been met with equal in purity to that produced from Borrowdale, in Cumberland, where it lies in a rock of intermediate formation. </p>

<p>We have no account of the first discovery, or opening of this mine, but from a conveyance made in the beginning of the seventeenth century, it appears to have been known before that time. The manor of Borrowdale is said to have belonged to the Abbey of Furness, and having at the dissolution of that monastery, in the reign of Henry the Eighth, fallen to the Crown, it was granted by James the First to William Whitmore, and Jonas Verdon, including and particularizing among other things, "the <i>wad-holes</i>, and <i>wad</i>, commonly called <i>black-cawke</i>, within the commons of Seatollar, or elsewhere within any of the wastes, or commons of the said manor, now, or late in the tenure or occupation of Roger Robinson, or his assigns, by the particulars thereof mentioned, to be of the yearly rent, or value of <i>fifteen shillings and fourpence</i>." By a deed bearing date the twenty-eighth day of November, 1614, the said William Whitmore, and Jonas Verdon, 

<pb n="135" />

sold and conveyed unto Sir Wilfred Lawson, of Isel, Knight, and several others therein named, to the number of thirty-six, chiefly inhabitants of Borrowdale, "all the said manor of Borrowdale, with the appurtenances of what nature or kind soever, <i>excepted</i> and <i>reserved</i> unto the said William Whitmore, and Jonas Verdon, their heirs and assigns, all those wadholes, and wad, commonly called black-cawke, within the commons of Seatollar, or elsewhere within the commons and wastes of the manor of Borrowdale aforesaid, with liberty to dig, work, and carry the same, and other their appurtenances whatsoever." In consequence of which reservation the wad, or black-lead mine has been ever since held distinct from other royalties of the said manor, one moiety thereof now belonging to Henry Banks, Esq. M.P. the other half being subdivided into several shares. </p>

<p>This mine is situated about nine miles from Keswick, near the head of the valley of Borrowdale, in the steep side of a mountain, facing towards the south-east, and has been opened at different places where the wad had probably appeared on the surface; the rock in which it occurs is called by Mr. Bakewell, a grey felspar porphyry; near the mine it becomes of a darker colour, as containing more iron, the joints being lined with a ferruginous clayey matter; it is intersected in 

<pb n="136" />

various directions by strings, or small rake veins, containing in some places a little calcareous spar, and other vein stuff, and sometimes a superficial glazing of black-lead without the substance; but the wad is only found in sops, or bellies, which appear generally to be formed by the intersection, or crossing of the veins, and are often at considerable distances from each other, and found with difficulty. </p>

<p>Formerly this mine was worked only at intervals, and when a sufficient quantity had been procured to supply the demand for a few years, it was strongly closed up until the stock was reduced; but of late, it has been obtained less plentifully, and the demand being greater, the working has been continued for several years successively. </p>

<p>Bishop Nicholson, who visited this mine in 1710, says, in a letter to Dr. Woodward, that "on opening the old level in that year, great discouragements appeared, for no search having been made in thirty-two years, they found that some pilfering interlopers had carried it on till they had lost it in the rocks; but after a few days' trial a new belly was happily discovered before the forehead of the Old Man, which proved so rich, that in less than twenty-four hours they had filled several sacks with fine and clean washed-mineral." An old level, which was re-opened in 1769, was 


<pb n="137" />

found to have been cut through this very hard rock, without the help of gunpowder; and a kind of pipe vein which had produced a great quantity of wad, having been pursued to the depth of one hundred yards and upwards, much inconvenience was experienced in working it: to obviate which, in 1798, an adit, or level was begun in the side of the hill, which at the length of 220 yards communicates with the bottom of the former sinking; since which time the works have been carried on internally through various ramifications; a survey of which has lately been made by Mr. Farey. Through this principal level the water now passes off, and the produce and rubbish are brought out upon a rail-way in a small waggon; and over its mouth a house is built, where, when the mine is open, the overseers dwell, and the workmen are undressed and examined as they pass through it on leaving their work. </p>

<p>Owing to the great value of this mineral, and the facilities afforded for disposing of it in an unmanufactured state, the greatest precaution has sometimes been scarcely sufficient to keep the workmen from pilfering, and even those appointed to overlook them have not always escaped suspicion; yet, it is but justice to the present manager, Mr. William Dixon, to state, that for upwards of fifty years that he has been employed, he has always sustained an unimpeachable character. </p>

<pb n="138" />

<p>To prevent the depredations of intruders, it has sometimes been necessary to keep a strong guard upon the place; and for its better protection, an Act of Parliament was passed 25th Geo. 2d. cap. 10th, by which an unlawful entering of any mine or wadhole of wad, or black-cawke, commonly called black-lead, or unlawfully taking, or carrying away any wad, &#38;c. therefrom, as also the buying, or receiving the same, knowing it to be unlawfully taken, is made felony. In the preamble to this Act, it is stated to be "necessary for divers useful purposes, and more particularly in the casting of bomb-shells, round shot, and cannon balls;" however, its use in cleaning and glossing cast iron work, such as stoves, grates, &#38;c. is now well known to every housemaid. </p>

<p>Being capable of enduring a great heat without fusing, or cracking, it is used in the manufacture of crucibles; and its excellence in diminishing friction in wooden screws, and other machinery, makes it become an ingredient in several anti-attrition compositions; but effects have been formerly attributed to it in dying, and medicine, which were perhaps only imaginary. Yet its principal use is in pencils, for which Keswick has long been famed; and in their manufactory great improvements have lately been made; but though in the vicinity of the mine, the pencil-makers are 

<pb n="139" />

obliged to purchase all their black-lead in London, as the proprietors will not permit any to be sold until it has first been lodged in their own warehouse. It has generally been used without any previous preparation, being only cut with a saw to the scantlings required, and thus enclosed in a suitable casing of cedar wood; but as it varies greatly in quality, both as to purity and hardness, considerable skill is requisite in the choosing and sorting it, according to the different purposes for which the pencil is intended. Being generally too soft for some purposes, a method of hardening it had long been a desideratum; and a process has at length been discovered, by which it may be rendered capable of bearing a finer and more durable point, but its colour will be somewhat deteriorated. </p>

<p>Great quantities of pencils are now made of a composition, formed of the saw-dust and small pieces of black-lead, which being ground to an impalpable powder, is mixed with some cohesive medium: for this purpose different substances are employed, some of which make a very inferior pencil; but others being united at a proper degree of heat, and consolidated by a strong pressure, make a pencil to answer for many purposes, (especially where the writing is intended to be permanent,) full as well as the genuine black-lead. </p>

<pb n="140" />

<p>The specific gravity of the best wad, or black lead, is, to that of water, as two to one nearly: the coarser kind is heavier in proportion, as it contains more stony matter. It comes from the mine in pieces of irregular shape, and of various sizes, requiring no process to prepare it for the market, further than freeing the pieces from any stony or extraneous matter, which may adhere to them. It is then assorted according to the different degrees of purity and size, and thus packed in casks to be sent off to the warehouse in London, where it is exposed to sale only on the first Monday in every month. </p>

<p>In the year 1803, after a tedious search, one of the largest bellies was fallen in with, which produced five hundred casks, weighing about one hundred and a quarter each, and worth thirty shillings a pound and upwards; besides a greater quantity of inferior sorts; and since that time several smaller sops have been met with; but for the last seven years the quantity raised has been comparatively trifling. </p>

<p>By an account published in 1804 the stock then on hand was valued at &#163;54,000, and the annual consumption stated to be about &#163;3,500. This afforded a clue to the assessors of the property tax which soon after came into operation; and this mine -- which 200 years ago had been 

<pb n="141" />

valued at fifteen shillings and four-pence -- was accordingly rated at &#163;2,700 a year. The consumption appears to be constantly increasing; but how far a permanency of supply can be calculated upon, is questionable. The most prolific part of the mountain may be already explored, and the principal body or trunk of the mine excavated, so that posterity must be contented with gleaning from the branches. </p>

</chap>

<gap desc="A blank space." />

<p align="center">THE END. </p>

<gap desc="The last six pages are empty and have not been digitised." />

</text>
