<text id="1833_a">
<pb n="title"/>
<head level="1">VIEWS OF THE LAKES IN THE NORTH OF ENGLAND,</head>
<head level="2">FROM ORIGINAL PAINTINGS BY THE MOST EMINENT ARTISTS;</head>
<head level="2">WITH HISTORICAL AND DESCRIPTIVE ILLUSTRATIONS,</head>
<head level="2">BY JOHN ROBINSON, D.D.</head>
<head level="1"></head>
<p align="center">ON THE SCOPE EVEN OF SUBLIMITY, THE SUPERIORITY OF THE ALPS IS BY NO MEANS SO GREAT AS MIGHT HASTILY BE INFERRED * * * * AS MY OBJECT IS TO RECONCILE A BRITON TO THE SCENERY OF HIS OWN COUNTRY, THOUGH NOT AT THE EXPENCE OF TRUTH, I AM NOT AFRAID OF ASSERTING, THAT IN MANY POINT OF VIEW OUR LAKES, ALSO, ARE MUCH MORE INTERESTING THAN THOSE OF THE ALPS." -- WORDSWORTH.</p>
<head level="2" align="center">LONDON: C TILT, FLEET STREET; LONGMAN AND CO. PATERNOSTER ROW; WHITAKER AND CO., AVE MARIA LANE; J. BROWN, PENRITH; AND J. COCKBURN, CARLISLE.</head>
<head level="2" align="center">1833.</head>
<gap desc="front matter, not digitised"/>
<pb n="1"/>
<head level ="1" align="center"> THE LAKES, &amp;c. </head>
<head level="2" align="center"> ULSWATER. </head>
<p> Elg, Hel, Ul, Hul, Wel, and Elv or Elf, are all of the same origin, and all signify <i> water</i>.  Hence Ulswater is a pleonastic name, in the same manner as Elesmere in Shropshire. </p>
<p> Ulswater is distant about five miles and a quarter from Penrith, whence it may be approached by either of two roads, one on the left, and the other on the right bank of the river Eamonth.  The road on the left or north side passes by Penrith Castle, which is supposed to have been built by the Nevils, earls of Westmorland, and enlarged and repaired by the duke of Gloucester, afterwards Richard the Third.  On the left of this road is Skirsgill, the seat of Hugh Parkin, Esq.; and further on, to the right, is Dalemain, the sweetly secluded 
<pb n="2"/>
mansion of Edward Williams Hasell, Esq. In the reign of Henry the Second, Dalemain, <i> Dominium in Valle </i>, belonged to John de Morville; and it was possessed successively by his immediate descendants, Nigel de Morville, Walter de Morville, John de Morville, and Richard de Morville.  In the 38th of Henry the Third, Sir Richard Layton was lord of the manor and of Auldby.  In the time of Edward the second, it belonged to Thomas Layton; in that of Edward the Third, to William Layton; and in that of Henry the Sixth, to William Layton.  It continued in the male line of this family till after the time of William Layton, Esq. who was sheriff of Cumberland in the 20th of Charles the Second.  At his death, having five daughters and no son, he devised the same by will to trustees with directions that they should sell it for the benefit of his daughters.  Accordingly, Dalemain was purchased by Sir Edward Hasell, ancestor of the present proprietor. </p>
<p> The other road from Penrith to Ulswater, on the right or south side of the Eamont, after passing through the village of Eamont-bridge, turns to the west.  It then conducts through the village of Yanwath, where is Yanwath-hall, once a seat of the Threlkelds, and afterwards of the Dudleys.  Sir Lancelot Threlkeld, who lived in the latter part of queen Elizabeth's reign, was the last of the name who inhabited this hall.  This Sir Lancelot was wont to observe, that ˈhe had three noble houses: one for pleasure at Crosby in Westmorland, where he had a park full of deer; one for profit and warmth, in which to reside in winter, namely, at Yanwith, nigh Penrith; and the third well stocked with tenants and men to go with him to the wars, at Threlkeld, near Keswick.ˈ He had three daughters, co-heiresses, the eldest of whom married Thomas Dudley, of a younger branch of the Dudleys of the south, and possessed Yanwath; the other two married two brothers, younger sons of Sir James Pickering of Killington, and had one Threlkeld, and the other Crosby-ravensworth.  Christopher Dudley, the descendant of Thomas Dudley, was the last of that name that inhabited Yanwath-hall.  As he had no issue living, he sold the manor of Yanwath and Eamont-bridge to Sir John Lowther, baronet, about the year 1654, reserving in it both his own and his wife's estate for life.  He died in London, 12th of Charles the Second (1661); and his wife died at Yanwath-hall, October 5, 1671, and was buried in Barton church, October 7, 1671.  </p>
<pb n="3"/>
<p> About a mile south of Yanwath-hall, and at the end of Yanwath-wood, near the New Gardens-bridge, is an ancient circular fortification, called Castle Steads.  The entrance to this fortification, which is on the east, has a ridge of stones on each side like a foundation.  The first bulwark, from the rise of the plane to the crest, is seven yards, and from the crest to the bottom of the first trench or ditch, five yards.  The second bulwark, from the bottom of the trench or ditch to the crest, is seven yards.  The third bulwark has a ring of stones like a foundation.  The area of the innermost circle is twenty-two yards in diameter; and of the whole fortification, fifty-four yards.  The antiquity of this fortification appears from the oaks, elms, and other wood which grow on the rampires, and which, upwards of one hundred and forty years ago, nearly covered it from sight. </p>
<p> Ulswater is surrounded on all sides, except by the east, by ranges of mountains, which, in the neighbourhood of Pooley, are of no great height, but are chiefly cultivated, and divided into farms.  Father to the west, these mountains gradually assume a greater height, approach nearer to the water, and on the right bank of the lake seem to impede all farther passage in that direction.  In this manner they appear to the extremity of the lake in Patterdale, where they rear their rocky heads to the clouds, surround Ulswater, and produce, with other objects, the most magnificent scenery. </p>
<p> Ulswater is eight miles and three quarters in length by land, and eight miles and a quarter by water, from the foot to the end of the lake.  When low, it contains 2563 acres of water; and this gives the mean breadth at nearly half a mile; but when the water is high, the breadth may be reckoned at half a mile, without any sensible error.  It has the greatest average depth of all the lakes, being in some parts thirty-five fathoms, and in most not less than nine or ten. </p>
<p> The fisheries in this lake belong to different persons, and pay a high quit rent to the lord of the adjacent soil. Henry Howard Esq. of Greystoke Castle possesses the largest share of these fisheries.  This gentleman's right of fishing extends over one half of Ulswater, from Stybarrow-crag to Rampsbeck, near to Colonel Salmon's Lodge, on the northern side of the lake.  He possesses also another fishery called Crosdermond or Trostermont, on the Westmorland or southern side. </p>
<p> The fish in Ulswater are trout, perch, eels, char, skellies, and a fish which is peculiar to this lake and to that of Buttermere, and is called a grey trout. The grey trouts resemble other trouts in form, but are much larger.  They sometimes weigh thirty or forty pounds; and Mr. Clarke mentions one which weighed fifty-six pounds; but their ordinary weight is from seven to twenty 
<pb n="4"/>
pounds each.  They are found chiefly in the deepest part of the lake, below the island of House-holme; but they are sometimes, though seldom, taken in other parts, except in the month of October, which is their spawning season.  During that month, nets are set across the foot of Goldril-beck, which they attempt to ascend for the purpose of spawning; a few make a similar attempt to ascend Glenridding-beck; but it is not known that any enter the other streams which flow into the lake.  Some of these trouts escape the nets, and succeed in getting into the river; but in that case, they are generally killed by the farmers, who, during the darkness of the night, strike them with a spear by the light of a torch.  ˈThis lordly creature,ˈ observes Mr. Wordsworth, ˈseems to know that ˈˈretiredness is a piece of majesty,ˈˈ for it is scarcely ever caught, or ever seen, except when it quits the depths of the lake in the spawning season, and runs up into the streams, where it is too often destroyed in disregard of the law of the land and nature.ˈ Mr. Clarke, however, mentions that he killed with the rod one which weighed upwards of seven pounds; and in the summer of 1831, a grey trout, which weighed twelve pounds, was taken with the net in the lower part of the lake.  It is said to be a very excellent fish when caught in season; and even those which are killed in the streams are much relished by some. </p>
<p> The char are smaller than those of other lakes, and of inferior quality.  The skelly is said to be peculiar to Ulswater, and not to be found in any other of these lakes.  This fish will take no bait, and seems to be a sort of fresh-water herring.  Like the herring, which it resembles both in size and shape, it assembles in shoals during the harvest months, and may be seen dimpling or rippling the surface of the lake in calm weather.  When shoals of this fish lie in water which is not too deep, immense numbers are sometimes taken at one draught.  Mr. Wordsworth seems inclined to think that the chevin or chub frequents Ulswater, as he has seen a large shoal passing into the lake from the river Eamont.  Yet, it is not well ascertained that the chevin is an inhabitant of this lake, though it is sometimes found in the lower part, whither it probably comes from the Eamont; certain it is, that in the higher parts of Ulswater, this fish is never seen. </p>
<p> The water which supplies this lake at its highest source is said to be upon Kirkstone-fell, in the manor of Hartsop.  This water runs on the east side of Hartsop-hall into Brotherswater, whence it descends till it joins first Hayswater, and afterwards Deepdale-beck.  Others say, that the highest spring is at Jack-brig, where the parishes of Barton, Kendal, and Windermere, all meet.
<gap desc="image of Ulswater"/>
<pb n="5"/>
these rivulets have been joined by Deepdale-beck, the water is called Deepdale-beck till it arrives at Goldril-bridge, where it assumes the name of Goldril-beck, which it retains till it empties itself into the lake.  It is observable that six streams enter Ulswater on the western side of the vale, and that these six streams issue from six glens or vallies.  The opposite side has only two streams of any importance, one of which would lead up from the point where it crosses the Kirkstone-road, near the foot of Brotherswater, to the decaying hamlet of Hartsop, and thence to Hayswater.  The other, coming down Martindale, enters Ulswater at Sandwyke, opposite to Gowbarrow-park. </p>
<head level="2" align="center"> ULSWATER, </head>
<head level="3" align="center"> FROM YEW CRAG. </head>
<p> This view is taken about half way between the head and foot of Ulswater, and exhibits the greatest part of what is called the second or middle reach of the lake, with the mountains and surrounding scenery on the east, south, and south-west.  At this place, the road from Pooley to Patterdale closely approaches the water, and is imperceptible in the view.  Yew Crag, from which it is taken, is a magnificent and towering mass of shattered rock on the western side of the lake. </p>
<p> The mountain to the left, on the eastern side of the water, is Birk-fell, which rises steep from the edge of the lake, and presents a bold wall of mountain really glorious.  Next to Birk-fell is Place-fell, whose giant bulk appears in his enormous elevation.  These mountains are craggy, broken, and irregular in shape.  Their surfaces are generally naked and barren.  They project boldly 
<pb n="6"/> 
to the very lake; and the outlet or winding of the water is by them excluded from the sight: it seems enclosed by a shore of steep hills and crags.  Yet, at the base of Birk-fell, and ˈalong the craggy side of Place-fell, richly adorned with juniper, and sprinkled over with birches,ˈ a narrow track conducts from Martindale to Patterdale, by the way of Sandwyke. </p>
<p> At the north end of Birk-fell are Sandwyke and Sandwyke-force.  The former consists of a few straggling houses, with cultivated inclosures.  The fields are of the finest verdure, and the picturesque appearance of the whole is most exquisitely pleasing.  It is indeed a most delicious spot, bounded by an amphitheatre of rugged hills. This beautiful place forms part of the vale of Martindale.  </p>
<p> About the year 1689, the Rev. Richard Birket was curate of the chapel of Martindale.  He was usually styled Sir Richard, and was perhaps the last of those clergy who in these parts was dignified with the title of Sir.  Mr. Clarke says, that he was designated Sir Richard, ˈon account of his transacting most of the law affairs of his parishioners.ˈ This, however, seems a mistake.  The title of Sir was anciently given to many clergymen, and in particular to all readers in chapels.  It was a designation by which the poorer clergy were generally distinguished till the time of the Reformation.  Even after that period, it was a title frequently bestowed on persons of that description.  Bishop Nicolson, who held the see of Carlisle at the beginning of the eighteenth century, says ˈSince I can remember, there was not a reader in any chapel who was not called Sir.ˈ In Shakespeare's ˈMerry Wives of Windsor, ˈ the tutor, Hugh Evans, is designated by the title of Sir Hugh; and in the registers of institution, in the different dioceses, this designation is frequently given.  Mr. Machel says, that within his own memory, ˈall readers in chapels were called Sirs, and were anciently so designated in writing;ˈ and hence he is of opinion, that such of the laity as received the order of knighthood, had, for the sake of distinction, the word 'knight,' written after their names, otherwise this would have been superfluous.  ˈBut now,ˈ he says, ˈthis Sir Richard Birket is the only <i> knight templar </i> (if I may so call him) who retains the ancient title, which has now become obsolete.ˈ </p>
<p> Martindale is one of the few places in England where red deer are now kept.  Those in Martindale are the property of Edward Williams Hasell, Esq. of Dalemain, who is lord of the manor.  Mr. Clarke says, that ˈwhenever the lord goes to hunt the stag, the bailiff summons all the tenants, before sun-set the preceding night, to attend their <i> strones </i> or stations: these stations are at two places, namely, Rampskin and Bannerdale, where the deer chiefly life, and where the tenants stand with their dogs to prevent the deer from escaping to the mountains.  This service, which they are to render once a year, is called a <i> boon </i> day, and for this every tenant has his dinner and a quart of ale.ˈ Mr. Hasell has a room furnished for the accommodation of his friends at the annual chase of red deer in these forests.  ˈThis room is fitted up in the sportsman's style, with a cupboard for bottles and glasses, with strong chairs, and a dining-table; and ornamented with the horns of the stags caught at these hunts for a succession of years, the length of the last race each had run being recorded under his spreading antlers.ˈ There is a place in the Middle Bannerdale called <i> lord's seat, </i> which is a chair of stone upon the top of a hill, about two miles south-west from the chapel.  Here, it is said, the lords were formerly accustomed to sit, and see their greyhounds course the red deer. </p> 
<p> In the south-west of the view, and above the termination of this reach of the lake, ˈthe mighty Helvellynˈ rears its lofty head.  This mountain is environed by others which rise one above another in height, and the bases of which extend to the margin of the lake.  The highest hills by which, in this mass, Helvellyn is more immediately surrounded, are Striding-edge, Swirril-edge, and Catchedicam, though of late years they have all begun to be considered only as continuous parts of this stupendous mountain.  Helvellyn signifies <i> the waterfall; </i> and about three hundred yards from the summit, and on the western side of the mountain, is Brownrigg's Well, from which the water issues at all seasons in a copious stream.  This mountain, of astonishing grandeur, is, according to the trigonometrical survey, 3055 feet above the level of the sea, exceeding Skiddaw in height by 33 feet. </p>
<p> In the south of the view is Stybarrow-crag, where the bases of the mountains which surround Helvellyn, extend to the lake, and leave a very narrow space for the road which lies between the crag and the water.  This space seems to have been much narrower formerly than at present.  Machel says, that in his time it was not more than two yards in width, and had been less. ˈStybarrow,ˈ he observes, ˈis a huge rock on the west side of Ulswater, in the way to Barton and Penrith
<pb n="8"/>
Here is a strait passage about two yards broad, having on one side a high hanging rock, which threatens to fall on passengers, and on the other a steep precipice into Ulswater, which, near this crag, is said to be about forty-eight yards in depth.  A few men might defend this passage against a great army; and this actually took place in 1648, during the civil wars, when the Scottish army attempted to force their way into Patterdale.  A few shepherds posted themselves in this strait, and boring a hole in an oak tree, which stood upon the brink of the lake, they drove a bar through it into the rock on the other side.  In this situation, they so conducted themselves, that they diverted the Scottish army from their purpose, and obliged them to retire into the parish of Bampton.  This account seems to corroborate the tradition, that the ancestors of Mr. Mounsey were distinguished by the name of kings of Patterdale, in consequence of a gallant action performed by one of the family; who, at the head of a few trusty shepherds, defeated at the pass of Stybarrow-crag a numerous band of Scottish marauders.  This person, in all probability, was John Mounsey, Esq. who, in the year 1689, was of the age of sixty years. </p>
<p> If Ulswater be substituted for ˈVennachar,ˈ and Helvellyn for ˈBenledi,ˈ the following description will portray, with great accuracy, the pass at Stybarrow-crag: </p>
 <poem>
<stanza> 
<line>ˈAt length they came where stern and steep,</line>
<line> The hills sink down upon the deep; </line>
<line> Here Vennachar in silver flows, </line>
<line> There ridge on ridge Benledi rose; </line>
<line> Ever the hollow path twined on, </line>
<line> Beneath steep bank and threatening stone; </line>
<line> An hundred men might hold the post. </line> 
<line> With hardihood against a host.ˈ </line>   
</stanza>
</poem>
<p> Mr. Machel mentions two accidents which happened at Stybarrow-crag, neither of which was attended with serious consequences.  In the summer of 1681, a Scottish pedlar was resting himself at this place, with his pack upon his shoulders; and as he sat looking at the fish which were sporting in the water below, the weight for his pack threw him into the lake; however, he contrived to get out.  The other was in the severe winter of 1688, when John Dobson, son of James Dobson, of Watermillock, fell into the water here on horseback, and narrowly escaped with his life.  After this last accident, the road between the crag and the lake was widened, and rendered less dangerous for passengers. </p>
<pb n="9"/> 
<head level="2" align="center"> DERWENT LAKE, </head>
<head level="3" align="center"> OR </head>
<head level="2" align="center"> DERWENT WATER </head>
<p> Keswick is distant from Penrith eighteen miles.  Upon Castlerigg, about a mile and a half from Keswick, is a Druid Temple.  This venerable relic of British antiquity is situated upon the summit of a smooth hill, and surrounded by grand mountain scenery.  It consists of an arrangement of rude stones, of which some stand upright, but many have fallen, and others are leaning obliquely.  The whole number of these stones is fifty-eight, of which forty-eight are disposed in an oval form, in an area of one hundred and eight feet from north to south, and of one hundred feet from east to west.  The other ten stones constitute a rectangular recess or oblong square, on the eastern side of the oval figure; and this recess, which is seven yards by three, is supposed to have been the sacred place appropriated exclusively to the Druids.  The largest of these stones is upwards of seven feet in height, and may weigh about eight tons; but the greater number are only three or four feet high.  The situation of this ancient place of worship is the central point of three vallies, whose mountains form part of an amphitheatre, which is completed by those of Derwent Water on the west, and by Skiddaw and Saddleback on the north. Such seclusion and sublimity were admired suited to the deep and wild mysteries of the Druids, who celebrated their midnight festival </p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line> By rites of such strange potency, </line>
<line> As, done in open day, would dim the sun, </line>
<line> Though enthroned in noontide brightness. </line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line> He cross'd his brow beside the stone, </line>
<line> Where Druids erst heard victims groan; </line>
<line> And at the cairns upon the wild, </line>
<line> O'er many a heathen hero piled, </line>
<line> He breath'd a timid prayer for those </line>
<line> Who died ere Shiloh's sun arose.ˈ </line> 
</stanza>
</poem>
<pb n="10"/>
<p> Nearly in the same direction, and about the distance of a mile farther from Keswick, is the vale of Wanthwaite, in the chapelry of St. John.  In this vale is the appearance of an ancient ruined castle, which amidst an amphitheatre of mountains, seems to rise from the summit of a small eminence.  This massive bulwark shows a front of various towers, and with its lofty turrets and ragged battlements, forms an awful, rude, and Gothic appearance.  This whole figure of a fortress of great strength, in which the semblance of galleries, of bending arches and buttresses, may be traced, is no other than a shaken massive pile of rocks, which stand in the midst of this little vale, and are disunited from the surrounding mountains.  They have so much of the real form and appearance of a castle, that they are known by the name of the Castle Rocks of St. John's.  By the power of fiction, this ideal fortress has been converted into a real castle, and constitutes the principal scene in the romance entitled ˈThe Bridal of Triermain:ˈ —  </p>
<poem> 
<stanza>
<line> Midmost of the vale, a mound </line>
<line> Arose, with airy turrets crown'd, </line>
<line> Buttress, and rampire's circling bound, </line>
<line> And mighty keep and tower; </line>
<line> Seem'd some primeval giant's hand </line>
<line> The castle's massive walls had plann'd </line>
<line> A ponderous bulwark to withstand </line>
<line> Ambitious Nimrod's power. </line>
<line> Above the moated entrance slung </line>
<line> The balanc'd drawbridge trembling hung, </line>
<line> As jealous of a foe; </line>
<line> Wicket of oak, as iron hard, </line>
<line> With iron studded, clench'd, and barr'd, </line>
<line> And prong'd portcullis join'd to guard </line>
<line> The gloomy pass below. </line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p> Between Crosthwaite church and the town of Keswick, on the left, is the Villa Lucretilis of the Poet Laureate, by whom it is beautifully apostrophized: </p> 
<poem>
<stanza>
<line> ˈHeaven hath with goodly increase blest me here, </line>
<line> Where childless and opprest with grief I came; </line>
<line> With voice of fervent thankfulness sincere, </line>
<line> Let me the blessings which are mine proclaim: </line>
<line> Here I possess, – what more should I desire? </line>
<line> Books, children, leisure, – all my heart's desire.ˈ </line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<pb n="11"/>
<p> The beautiful lake of Derwent Water is of an oblong form, being rather more than three miles in length, and nearly a mile and a half in breadth.  It contains at low water, twelve hundred and ninety-five acres, including the islands; and deducting thirteen acres for the islands, the area of the lake consists of twelve hundred and eighty-two acres of water.  It does not in any part exceed fourteen fathoms in depth, and in several places is not more than three.  It derives its principal supplies of water from the rivers Lowdore and Derwent, the latter of which flows through it, and has given name to the lake. </p>
<p> By some this has been considered as the finest lake in the north of England; but in the opinion of others, Ulswater may claim the pre-eminence for beauty and grandeur.  Fantastic wildness, and romantic beauty, form the leading characteristics of Derwent Water, which has this decided advantage over all the other lakes, that it immediately appears to be what it really is.  The breadth of the lake bears an inconsiderable proportion to its length.  This renders its arm nearly the same from whatever point it may be viewed, and constitutes a distinction which is peculiar to itself.  The dark frowning Skiddaw forms its northern boundary, and though distant at least a mile and a half, seems to rise immediately behind it.  One long mountain, part of Derwent Fells, along with the road forms a fine terrace, reaches nearly the whole of its western border; but the pride of this lake is the head, where the mountains of Borrowdale bound the prospect in a manner singularly grand. ˈDerwent, ˈ observes Mr. Wordsworth, ˈis distinguished from all the other lakes by being surrounded with sublimity: the fantastic mountains of Borrowdale to the south, the solitary majesty of Skiddaw to the north, the bold steeps of Wallow-crag and Lowdore to the east, and to the west the clustering mountains of Newlands.ˈ </p>
<p> The whole of Derwent Lake is seen at one glance.  It expands within an amphitheatre of mountains, which are rocky but not vast, and are broken into many fantastic shapes.  Some are peaked, splintered, impending, and some pyramidal, opening by narrow valleys to the view of rocks which rise immediately beyond, and are again overlooked by others.  The precipices seldom overhang the water, but are arranged at some distance; and the shores swell with woody eminences, or sink into green pastoral margins.  Among the cliffs also frequently appear masses of wood, which feather them to their summits; and at their skirts sometimes peeps out a white cottage, which, seated on the smooth knoll of a pasture projecting to the water, looks so exquisitely picturesque, as to have the appearance of having been placed there for the purpose of adorning the scene. 
<pb n="12"/>
The lake in return faithfully reflects the whole picture; and so even brilliantly translucent is the surface of the water, that it rather brightens than obscures the colouring. </p>
<p> Skiddaw constitutes such a distinguished part of the Alpine scenery which environs the lake and vale of Keswick, that it is necessary to give some description of this celebrated mountain. </p>
<poem>
<stanza> 
<line> ˈWhat was the great Parnassus' self to thee, </line>
<line>  Mount Skiddaw? In his natural sovereignty, </line>
<line> Our British hill is fairer far! he shrouds </line> 
<line> His double-fronted head in higher clouds, </line>
<line> And pours forth streams more sweet than Castaly.ˈ </line> 
</stanza>
</poem>
<p> This mountain is three thousand and twenty-two feet above the level of the sea, according to the trigonometrical survey of Colonel Mudge.  It extends into several parishes and townships; and that part which is in the parish of Crosthwaite, has been inclosed under an act of parliament passed in 1810. </p>
<p> The view from the summit of Skiddaw is grand and extensive.  Derwent Lake and the vale of Keswick are hidden from the sight; but more distant objects arrest the attention and delight the spectator.  To the north lies the vast tract of low country which extends between Bassenthwaite Lake and the Irish Channel.  The town of Whitehaven is not visible but its white coast is distinctly seen; and beyond it appears the Isle of Man.  Cockermouth, with its church and castle, seems almost under the eye.  Workington, and its shipping, may be seen due west; and further to the north, appear Maryport and the fashionable bathing place of Allonby.  Bounding the low country to the north, is seen the wide Solway Frith, with its indented shores; and the double range of Scottish mountains is also visible.  Carlisle, with its cathedral, and other prominent buildings, forms a central object in the intervening space. Beyond the Solway Frith appears the mountain Criffel in Kirkcudbrightshire, the loftiest of the southern highlands.  The Beacon at Penrith may be seen; and beyond it the lofty Crossfell, ˈthe British Appennines,ˈ bordering on the counties of Northumberland, Durham, and Yorkshire.  The hills which surround Ulswater are in view; and Ingleborough appears beyond the end of High Street.  Southward and westward is a ˈturbulent chaos of dark mountains.ˈ All individual dignity seems now lost in the immensity of the whole; and every variety of character is overpowered by that of astonishing and gloomy grandeur.  The circumference of this sublime panoramic view is probably not less than three hundred miles. </p>
<p> ˈIt is not likely that a mountain will be ascended without disappointment, 
<gap desc="Image of Derwent Water"/>
<pb n="13"/>
if a wide range of prospect be the object, unless either the summit be reached before sunrise, or the visitant remain there until the time of sunset, and afterwards.  The precipitous side of the mountain, and the neighbouring summits, may be seen with effect under any atmosphere which allows them to be seen at all; but <i>he </i> is the most fortunate adventurer, who chances to be involved in vapours which open and let in an extent of country partially, or, dispersing suddenly, reveal the whole region from centre to circumference.ˈ</p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line> ˈOnce more I see the, Skiddaw! Once again </line>
<line> Behold thee in thy majesty serene, </line>
<line> Where, like the bulwark of this favoured plain, </line>
<line> Alone thou standest, monarch of the scene. – </line>
<line> Thou glorious Mountain, on whose ample breast </line>
<line> The sunbeams love to play, the vapours love to rest!ˈ </line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<head level="2" align="center"> DERWENT LAKE, </head>
<head level="3" align="center"> FROM THE FOOT OF CASTLE-HILL. </head>
<p> LORD'S ISLAND, which is situated near the eastern shore of the lake, is said to have been once a peninsula; but after it became the residence of the Radcliffes, it was severed from the main land by a ditch, and rendered accessible only by a drawbridge.  This island contains about six acres and a half, and is now entirely covered with wood.  Its situation near the shore was probably the cause of its being selected for the residence of the family of Derwentwater.  The mansion of this unfortunate family, on the island, has long been in ruins, and nothing remains by the foundation. </p>
<p> Mr. Clarke relates, that in the year 1749, the wood upon Lord's Island and at Crow Park was sold by the governors of Greenwich Hospital to a person of the name of Marthas or Mathews, for seven thousand pounds.  It was advertised to be sold publicly in London; but the governors contrived to exclude every other purchaser, and the wood was almost literally given to Mathews.  The purchaser was allowed to ten years in which to cut down the timber.  The person whom he employed to cut it down commenced his undertaking in May, 1749, and before the end of that year, returned to Mathews eighteen hundred pounds clear 
<pb n="14"/>
money.  The next year he paid his employer nearly the same sum.  Mathews then sold the remainder of the wood to some merchants at Whitehaven; but the sum for which this part was sold has not been made known. </p>
<p>The Derwentwater family took their name from the place where they were seated at Castlerigg, on the lake of Derwent.  This family was of great antiquity, and resided here in the reign of Edward the First.  In the reign of Henry the Sixth, Sir Nicholas Radcliffe, of Dilston, in the county of Northumberland, knight, married the heiress of Sir John de Derwentwater, knight.  In 1688, his descendant, Sir Francis Radcliffe, baronet, was created, by king of James the Second, baron of Dilston, viscount Langley and Radcliffe, and earl of Derwentwater.  All these titles, with his estate and life, were forfeited by his son James, the second ear, of Derwentwater, who was beheaded on Tower-hill in 1716, for being concerned in the rebellion the preceding year.  The estate amounting, it is said to twenty thousand pounds a year, including the mines, was vested in trustees for the support of Greenwich Hospital.  All the property in this neighbourhood which had belonged to that unfortunate nobleman, was sold by government in the year 1832, to John Marshall, Esq. of Halsteads, on the banks of Ulswater.</p>
<p> Vicar's Island belongs to General Peachy, and consists of about six acres.  It is beautifully laid out in pleasure-grounds, interspersed with a variety of trees, and crowned with a house in the centre.  ˈFor some years it was called Pocklington's Island, as it then belonged to a gentleman of that name; and it is sometimes by way of pre-eminence, called Derwent Isle; but its proper denomination seems to be Vicar's Island, as it apparently received this name from its having formerly belonged to Fountain Abbey, in Yorkshire.  Deprecating the bad taste which sometimes prevails among new proprietors in this part of the country, Mr. Wordsworth has the following observations on the changes made upon this island some years ago: —ˈThe Hind's Cottage upon Vicar's Island, with its embowering sycamores and cattle-shed, disappeared at the bidding of an alien improver, from the corner where they had stood; and right in the middle, and upon the precise point of the island's highest elevation, rose a tall square habitation, with four sides exposed, like an observatory, or a warren-house reared upon an eminence for the detection of depredators, or like the temple of &#338;olus, where all the winds pay him obeisance.  Round this novel structure, but at a respectful distance platoons of firs were stationed, as if to protect their commander when weather and time should somewhat have shattered his strength. 
<pb n="15"/>
Within the narrow limits of this island were typified also the state and strength of a kingdom, and its religion as it had been and was – for neither was the druidical circle uncreated, nor the church of present establishment; nor the stately pier, emblem of commerce and navigation; nor the fort, to deal out thunder upon the approaching invader.  The taste of a succeeding proprietor rectified the mistakes as far as was practicable, and has ridded the spot of all its puerilities.ˈ </p>
<p> St. Herbert's Island contains about four acres of land, and is situated nearer the centre of the lake.  It obtained its name from St. Herbert, a priest and confessor, who, about the middle of the seventh century, made it his lonely abode.  Some remains of what is said to have been his hermitage are still visible among the trees with which the island is covered.  Near these hallowed ruins, the late Sir Wilfrid Lawson erected, about thirty years ago, a grotto called the New Hermitage.  The island is the property of the present Sir Wilfrid Lawson, baronet.  That St. Herbert had his hermitage upon this island is evident from the Venerable Bede, who says that he lived ˈa solitary life in the isle of that great and extended lake, from whence proceeds the river Derwent.ˈ St. Herbert was particularly distinguished for his friendship to St. Cuthbert of Farn Isle, whom he was accustomed to visit every year, for the purpose of receiving ˈfrom his lips the doctrine of eternal life.ˈ It is said, that at the intercession of St. Herbert, they both expired on the same day, and in the same hour. </p>
<poem>
<stanza> 
<line> ˈSt. Herbert hither came, </line>
<line> And here, from many seasons, from the world </line>
<line> Remov'd, and the affections of the world, </line>
<line> He dwelt in solitude.  He living here, </line>
<line> This island's sole inhabitant, had left </line>
<line> A fellow-labourer, whom the good man lov'd </line>
<line> As his own soul; and when within his cave </line>
<line> Alone he knelt before the crucifix, </line>
<line> While o'er the lake the cataract of Lowdore </line>
<line> Peal'd to his orisons, and when he paced </line>
<line> Along the beach of this small isle, and thought </line>
<line> Of his companion, he would pray that both </line>
<line> (Now that their earthly duties were fulfilled) </line>
<line> Might die in the same moment.  Nor in vain </line>
<line> So pray'd he: — as our Chronicles report, </line>
<line> Though here the hermit number'd his last days, </line>
<line> Far from St. Cuthbert, his beloved friend, </line>
<line> Those holy men both died in the same hour.ˈ </line> 
</stanza>
</poem>
<pb n="16"/>
<p> It is probable that the hermit's little oratory or chapel might be kept in repair after his death, as a particular veneration appears to have been paid by the religious of succeeding ages to this retreat, and to the memory of the saint.  Bede says, that St. Herbert died A.D. 687.  In the year 1374, at the distance of nearly seven centuries, the register of bishop Appleby contains an indulgence of forty days to every inhabitant of the parish of Crosthwaite, who should attend the vicar to St. Herbert's Island on the 13th day of April yearly, and there celebrate mass in memory of St. Herbert. </p>
<head level="2" align="center"> DERWENT LAKE, </head>
<head level="3" align="center"> FROM THE FOOT OF BARROW. </head>
<p> This view of the lake is taken from the foot of Barrow.  The Floating, or more properly, as Mr. Wordsworth thinks, the Buoyant Island is not visible in the plate.  This island, which appears only occasionally, is situated in the south-east corner of the lake, about one hundred and fifty yards from the shore, and not far from Lowdore.  It is sometimes visible for several weeks successively, and sometimes does not appear for several years.  Usually, however, it is seen after an interval of a few years, and towards the conclusion of a warm summer.  Being attached by its sides to the adjacent earth under water, it never changes its situation, but always makes its appearance in the same place.  In extent it is sometimes half an acre, and sometimes only a few perches.  It has risen seven times during the last twenty-five years, and appeared in the summers of 1824, 1825, and 1826.  The uncommon circumstance of its appearing in three consecutive years, has been attributed to the extraordinary warmth of the summers.  Various hypotheses have been offered, to account for the alternate rising and sinking of this island.  The most probable opinion seems to be, that the vegetable matter of which the island is composed, produces by decomposition a quantity of gas.  This gas being generated most copiously, as well as being more rarefied in hot weather, at length distends the earth so much as to render the mass of less weight than the same bulk of water.  The island then rises to
<gap desc="image of unclear"/>  
<pb n="17"/>
the surface where it continues till the gas is reduced, partly by absorption, and partly by condensation, consequent on a decrease of heat.  In the body of the island a considerable quantity of air is contained, and this air, when dislodged, has been found to consist of equal parts of carburetted hydrogen and azotic gases, with a little carbonic acid.  We are told that artificial islets, with dwelling huts upon them, float on the lakes of Mexico and China; and, however philosophy may solve the problem in nature, poetry, less scrupulous of her authorities, has wrought the artificial image with peculiar felicity to the hands of the voyager: </p>
<poem> 
<stanza>
<line> ˈWe reach'd the shore: </line>
<line> A floating islet waited for me there, </line>
<line> The beautiful work of man.  I set my foot </line>
<line> Upon green-growing herbs and flowers, and sate </line>
<line> Embower'd in odorous shrubs: four long light boats, </line>
<line> Yoked to the garden, with accordant song, </line>
<line> And dip and dash of oar in harmony, </line>
<line> Bore me across the lake.ˈ</line> 
</stanza>
</poem>
<p> The waterfall of Lowdore, which is seen in the place, is three miles distant from Keswick, and presents a singular harmonious assemblage of the sublime and beautiful.  It is the Niagara of Derwent Water, and is situated near the head of the lake.  The stupendous crags, between which the torrent precipitates itself, are broken into the boldest forms, and covered with birch, ash, and other trees, which hang in the most fantastic shapes from the fissures of the rock.  The character of this deservedly celebrated cataract varies with the season.  In dry weather the fall is inconsiderable, and its grandeur consequently diminished; but when charged with a thousand streams, which a torrent of rain pours from the mountains, the bubbling cascade becomes a stupendous cataract, which, rushing down an enormous pile of protruding rocks, roll along with uninterrupted volume and impetuous velocity, and shakes the hills with its rebound. At such times the scene is truly magnificent.  The tremendous roar of the rushing waters, which is said to be distinctly heard, in a serene evening, at the distance of ten or twelve miles, is perfectly in unison with its rocky accompaniments.  The descent of the waterfall is not less than one hundred and fifty feet and after a heavy rain, in a full torrent, it exhibits a scene of grandeur of which no verbal description can give an adequate idea. </p>
<pb n="18"/>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line>ˈSmooth to the shelving brink, a copious flood </line>
<line> Rolls fair and placid; where, collected all </line>
<line> In one impetuous torrent, down the steep </line>
<line> It thundering shoots, and shakes the country round. </line>
<line> At first, an azure sheet, it rushes broad; </line> 
<line> Then whitening by degrees as prone it falls, </line>
<line> And from the loud resounding rocks below, </line>
<line> Dash'd in a cloud of foam, it sends aloft </line>
<line> A hoary mist, and forms a ceaseless shower. </line>
<line> Nor can the tortured wave here find repose: </line>
<line> But, raging still amid the shaggy rocks, </line>
<line> Now flashes o'er the scatter'd fragments, now </line>
<line> Aslant the hollow'd channel rapid darts; </line> 
<line> And falling fast from gradual slope to slope, </line>
<line> With wild infracted course, and lessen'd roar, </line>
<line> It gains a safer bed, and steals, at last, </line>
<line> Along the mazes of the quiet vale.ˈ </line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p> Castle Crag is a detached mountain, which appears between others more lofty than itself, as if it were a centinel, placed to protect the entrance into Borrowdale.  It is said to have obtained its name from a fortress supposed of Roman origin, which once frowned upon its summit, and guarded this tremendous pass.  After this fortress had been relinquished by the Romans, it was occupied by the Saxons; and it was subsequently given, with all the lands about Borrowdale, by one of the lords of Derwentwater, to the monks of Furness.  By these religious it was still continued in its military capacity, to defend their valuable possessions in the vale of Borrowdale, against the predatory incursions of the Scots, who, in those days, frequently made irruptions even thus far into the country.  This would seem to account for the manor of Borrowdale being in the possession of the crown; as, on the dissolution of the monasteries, in the reign of the state.  It appears, indeed, that in the reign of James the First, the whole of this manor was granted by that king to William Whitmore and Jonas Verdon.  These last-mentioned persons, by a deed bearing date the twenty-eighty day of November 1614, sold and conveyed ˈall the said manor of Borrowdaleˈ, with the exception of the wad holes and wad, within the said manor, to Sir Wilfrid Lawson, of Isel, knight, and thirty-six others, chiefly inhabitants of Borrowdale. </p>
<pb n="19"/>
<p> At the head of Borrowdale, on the side of a steep mountain called Seatoller, is the celebrated Wad Mine.  This mineral substance, from which black lead pencils are manufactured, has been designated by the several names of wad, black cawke, black lead, plumbago, and graphite.  The exact time when this mine was discovered has not been ascertained.  Certain, however, it is, that the mine has been occasionally worked since the reign of queen Elizabeth.  It is private property; one moiety of which belongs to Henry Banks, Esq. M.P. and the other half is subdivided into several shares.  On account of the great value of this mineral, various precautions have been adopted to prevent the workmen and others from committing depredations.  The mine is accessible only through a house, which is built over the entrance.  More than eighty years ago, a person who possessed a part of the mountain contiguous to the mine, determined to obtain a share of this rich mineral.  Here with great labour, he sank a shaft, which he carried diagonally till he entered the mine; and, with secret joy, he continued his depredations for some time undiscovered.  At length, his fraud was detected, and he was tried at Carlisle.  The peculiarity of the case saved his life; but in the year 1752, an act of parliament was passed to secure this valuable property.  By this act, both the stealer and the receiver are subjected to the same punishment as for felony.  In the preamble to the act, this mineral is described as necessary to the casting of bomb-shells, round shot and cannon-balls.  At present, it is used in cleansing and giving lustre to iron, and in the composition of crucibles and other vessels; but its principal consumption consists in what are called black-lead pencils, which have acquired so much reputation abroad under the title of <i> crayons d'Angleterre </i>.</p> 
<p> This mineral is not found in regular veins, but in lumps or nodules, which vary both in size and quality.  Some of these pieces are hard and gritty, and of less value; others are soft and of a fine texture, and worth thirty-five shillings a pound.  It is described as lying in the mine sometimes in the form of a tree, with a body or root, from which proceed veins or branches in all directions.  The body consists of the finest wad; and the branches are of an inferior quality.  It is, however, sometimes found in <i> sops </i> or floats, in a body without branches. </p>
<p> Dr. Merret and some others, have supposed that these are the only mines of wad in the world; but this is not the case.  This mineral is found in various parts – in Scotland, Spain, Germany, and the East Indies; but in no place has it been discovered equal in purity to that which is produced in Borrowdale. 
<pb n="20"/>
Mr. Otley observes, that is found in the shire of Inverness, in gneiss, which is considered as one of the primitive rocks; in the borders of the shire of Ayr, in the neighbourhood of coal, to which it seems too nearly allied; and in Borrowdale, in a rock of intermediate formation. </p>
<p> Such was formerly the abundance of this mineral, that the mine was opened occasionally to meet the requisite demand; and when the mine was worked, a sufficient quantity of wad was easily procured to supply the demand for a few years.  When this had been obtained, the mine was strongly closed up till the stock became reduced.  Of late, however, this mineral has been procured less plentifully, and the demand for it having increased, the working has been continued for several years successively.  It appears that in the year 1803, the workmen met with a large belly, which filled five hundred casks.  Each of these casks weighed about one hundred and twenty-five pounds; and the wad was worth at least thirty shillings a pound.  In the year 1829, a sop was obtained which produced about six casks; and the best part of the wad was eagerly bought at thirty-five shillings a pound.  Since that time the quantity raised has been trifling. </p>    
<gap desc="image"/>
<pb n="21"/>
<head level="2" align="center"> ULSWATER, </head>
<head level="3" align="center"> FROM THE MATTERDALE ROAD. </head>
<p> ˈUlswaterˈ, observes Mr. Wordsworth, ˈis finely approached from Keswick by Matterdale and Lyulph's Tower into Gowbarrow Park.  A magnificent view is unfolded of the two higher reaches of the lake.ˈ From the place at which this view of Ulswater has been taken, as delineated in the plate, the lake was seen by Mr. Gilpin, who thus expresses the feelings which the sight produced:  – ˈThe whole scene of the lake opened before us, and such a scene as almost drew from us the apostrophe of the enraptured bard:</p> 
<poem>
<line>'Visions of glory, spare my aching sight!'</line>
</poem>
<p>Among all the visions of this enchanting country, we had seen nothing so beautiful sublime, so correctly picturesque as this.ˈ </p>
<p> At the southern point of the lake, under impending mountains, lies Patterdale, of which, as it forms a prominent object in this view, some account shall be given. </p>
<p> Patterdale, anciently written Patrikdale, and Patrickdale, is apparently a corruption of Patrick's Dale.  The church is dedicated to St. Patrick, from which circumstance Patterdale probably received its name.  Adjoining to the road, below Patterdale Hall, is a fine spring called St. Patrick's Well. </p>  
<p> Patterdale Hall is a handsome modern mansion, built by the late John Mounsey, Esq. who died in 1821; and it has been improved since his death, by its present possessor William Marshall, Esq.  It stands north-west of the church, and fronts the lake.  This mansion is surrounded by thriving plantations, which, together with the lofty mountains behind it, completely shelter it from the stormy blast.  The pleasure-grounds are laid out with much taste. </p>
<pb n="22"/>
<p> The mansion is erected on the site of the former hall, a great part of which was built by John Mounsey, Esq. in 1677.  The former hall was a good building, and had a court and orchard, with a small terrace-walk at the door.  The ascent to the house was by ten or twelve steps.  In the floor of the hall was a curious pavement, formed of the shreds and fragments of slates placed on edge. </p>
<p> It appears that Patterdale Hall demesne, and the manor of Glenridding, were purchased by Joan, the widow of Mr. George Mounsey, who had been agent to the countess of Arundel, at Greystoke, and who left much property at his decease.  They were bought by Mr. George Mounsey's widow for her son John, then in his minority, who must, therefore, be considered as the first of the name of Mounsey that possessed Patterdale Hall.  The demesne of Patterdale Hall and the manor of Glenridding, were purchased by her of Richard Threlkeld, of Newbiggin, in the parish of Dacre, gentleman; Thomas Threlkeld, of Patterdale, his son; and Christopher Threlkeld, his grandson, of Threadneedle-street, London, mercer.  Mr. Machel says, that this lordship had been the property, and continued in the name and family, of the Threlkelds, for several hundred years; but that he found no coats of arms relating to them, either at the hall, or in Patterdale church. </p>
<p> The church in Patterdale is an ancient white structure, furnished with oaken benches.  In the church, and at the north-east end, is a small quire which belongs to the hall, and which shows that if the ancient proprietors of Patterdale Hall were not the founders of this church, they had been at least its chief benefactors.  In the church-yard is a venerable old yew-tree of amazing circumference, with embers of life still remaining.  It is completely hollow in the trunk; but its branches are still long and vigorous, though they do not cover so large a space of ground as formerly.  No ˈstoried urns or animated bustsˈ are here; and with one solitary exception, this church-yard does not contain a single stone in commemoration of the dead.  The peaceful inhabitants of this quiet and delightful vale are content to rest with one green sod to cover them, which may be in perfection when tomb-stones and other mementos of those whom the grave conceals shall be no more.</p> 
<poem>
<stanza>
<line> – ˈIn our church-yard, </line>
<line> Is neither epitaph nor monument, </line> 
<line> Tombstone nor name – only the turf we tread, </line>
<line> And a few natural graves.ˈ</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>Mr. Machel mentions, that in this church-yard were the fragments of an ancient 
<pb n="23"/>
cross curiously carved; but these have, since his time, entirely disappeared, and no living inhabitant now remembers any thing of the kind. </p>
<p> In 1689, to this church belonged a parcel of glebe lands, and also one-third of the tithes of wool and lamb, and Easter-book, in Patterdale only; and these amounted at that time to about 18<i>l.</i> a year.  Of this sum, the incumbent paid, as an acknowledgment and indemnification to the mother church 4<i>l.</i> per annum to the vicar of Barton.  The same sum is still paid to the vicar of Barton; but the living of Patterdale has since that time has been much augmented by several donations from queen Ann's bounty, and by an increase in the value of the tithes.  The present incumbent, the Reverend John Thompson, has built a neat and comfortable parsonage house, with part of the augmentations furnished by the governors of queen Ann's bounty. </p>
<p> A portion of the head of Ulswater, with two of its islands, surrounds the river Goldrill, which empties itself into the lake about half way across the fields at its head.  These fields are succeeded by sweet undulations of ground, over which woods, approaching almost to redundancy, dilate with great beauty.  Mr. Askew's house, at nearly the head of the lake, is well situated for a view of the surrounding scenery, as well as for the enjoyment of those excursions which the proximity of the water, or of the surrounding mountains may invite.  It stands on the western border of the lake, at the foot of the rocky and wooded valley of Glenridding. </p>
<p> From Patterdale, the stupendous Helvellyn is sometimes ascended by those who visit the lakes.  The road to this ˈmightyˈ mountain, leads from the inn at Patterdale over the bridge at Grisedale-beck, where it turns immediately to the left, near Patterdale Hall.  It then leads by Upper Grassenthwaite, usually called Grassat How, which has been in the possession of the late Mr. John Dobson's family for upwards of three hundred years. </p>          
<p> The passage of Striding-edge, however, is attended with some danger.  In the spring of 1805, Mr. Charles Gough, a young gentleman of talents, and of a most amiable disposition, was making a solitary tour in this part of the country.  He left Patterdale with the hopes of reaching Wythburn; but unhappily trusting too much to his own local knowledge, he lost his way, and perished beneath ˈthe dark brow of the mighty Helvellyn.ˈ  It appeared, that at Patterdale Mr. Gough had inquired for a guide to Wythburn; but there being a review of the volunteers in the neighbourhood, no person could be procured to direct him.  Snow also fell on that day.  He was, therefore, advised to remain at Patterdale till the 
<pb n="24"/>
following day; but unhappily, he did not comply with the advice.  The remains of this unfortunate gentleman were not discovered till three months afterwards, when they were found guarded by a faithful female terrier, his constant attendant during his rambles through the wilds of Westmorland and Cumberland.  This affecting incident gave rise to the following pathetic lines by Mr. Wordsworth, commemorative of the ˈfidelityˈ of the dog to its master. After noticing the manner by which the body of the unfortunate gentleman had been discovered by a shepherd, the poet thus observes: </p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line> ˈFrom those abrupt and perilous rocks </line>
<line> The man had fallen, that place of fear! </line>
<line> At length upon the shepherd's mind </line>
<line> It breaks, and all is clear: </line>
<line> He instantly recalled the name, </line>
<line> And who he was, and whence he came; </line>
<line> Remembered, too, the very day </line>
<line> On which the traveller pass'd this way. </line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line> But hear a wonder, for whose sake </line>
<line> This lamentable tale I tell! </line>
<line> A lasting monument of words </line>
<line> This wonder merits well. </line>
<line> The dog, which still was hovering nigh, </line>
<line> Repeating the same timid cry, </line>
<line> This dog had been, through three months' space, </line>
<line> A dweller in that savage place. </line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line> Yes, proof was plain, that since the day </line>
<line> When this ill-fated traveller died, </line>
<line> The dog had watch'd about the spot, </line> 
<line> Or by his master's side: </line>
<line> How nourish'd here, through such long time, </line>
<line> He knows, who gave that love sublime; </line>
<line> And gave that strength of feeling, great </line>
<line> Above all human estimate.ˈ</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p> The mountain on the left of the view is Birk-fell, and beyond it is Place-fell.  The road leads into Gowbarrow Park, the property of Henry Howard, Esq. of Greystoke Castle.  This park is said to contain eight hundred acres of land, and to pasture four hundred head of deer, of which some are red deer.  In this park stands Lyulph's Tower, which is a square gray edifice, with four towers, battlements, and gothic windows, and which was erected by the late duke of Norfolk,
<pb n="25"/>
Partly as an object to the surrounding scenery.  It is used as a hunting-seat.  It was named Lyulph's Tower, from Lyulph, the first baron of Greystoke, who, it was said, was the proprietor of Ulswater; but, as Mr. Hutchinson justly observes, there is no historical foundation for any such assertion. </p>
<p> Airey Force thunders down the gill on the left of the Matterdale Road, and at the distance of about half a mile from the lake.  This cascade is the entire work of nature, and the water rushes from the summit of a wooded cliff through a rocky chink, about eighty feet in perpendicular height, and sixteen in width.  ˈHere,ˈ says Mr. Green, ˈrocks in perpendicular and a&#235;rial perspective, recede from the eye to a vast height; but this appearance, in some instances terrific, is in others transformed into a solemnity of beauty by trees, which impending from the fissures of the rocks, almost exclude the light of heaven.ˈ Mr. Wordsworth justly observes, that ˈIt is generally supposed that waterfalls are scarcely worth being looked at, except after much rain, and that the more swoln the stream the more fortunate the spectator.  But this, however, is true only of large cataracts with sublime accompaniments; and not even of these without some drawbacks.ˈ </p>
<p> At Goldril Bridge is a road which leads to Martindale.  Angle-tarn, which 
<pb n="26"/>
is situated upon the summit of the south end of Place-fell, contains trouts of the most exquisite taste and flavour.  The water of this tarn is of a dark colour, resembling the water of a peat-moss.  A person fond of angling may here enjoy excellent sport; but Hayswater, a tarn about a mile and a half east of Hartsop, is said to afford the angler still better diversion. </p>
<p> Beyond Hartsop, which is on the left in proceeding towards Kirkstone, is Brotherswater, a small lake named in old maps ˈBroaderwater;ˈ but the change in the appellation of this small lake or pool (if it be a corruption) may have been assisted by some melancholy accident similar to what happened in 1785, when two brothers were drowned there, having gone out to take their holiday pleasure upon the ice on new-year's Day. </p>
<p> The road from Brotherswater to Ambleside is truly an alpine pass, winding in a contracted vale, with a high and naked mountain on the left.  A steep and rugged path ascends to the heights of Kirkstone, meeting the noisy waters of a raging torrent tumbling over its rocky channel. </p>
<head level="2" align="center"> HEAD OF BUTTERMERE, </head>
<p> HONISTER CRAG, which is seen in the left of the view, raises to an immense height.  If viewed from the road which leads from Borrowdale-hawe to Buttermere, this mountain seems to elevate itself in horrible grandeur to the skies; and disdaining to be encumbered with a blade of grass, assumes a most dreary and inhospitable aspect.  Viewing the dark gray sides of this frightful mountain, it is beheld with terror, and the dreadful summit is observed, by the spectator below, with much the same feelings as the pale mariner, on an unknown shore, observes the dark clouds which bear the tempest in their bosom, and bring ruin and destruction.  The scenery around exhibits a view of sterility, as wild and frightful, probably, as can be met with in any part of the United Kingdom. </p>
<p> Honister Crag is said to rise to the height of seventeen-hundred feet above the vale.  From the rugged front of this stupendous mountain, is procured a slate which is as smooth and valuable as any in the island.  Here may be observed one of those tracks on which the slaters ascend to their daily labour. 
<gap desc="image of Buttermere"/>
<pb n="27"/>
From many quarries, the descent of which is not particularly steep, the slate is conveyed in carts to the lower grounds.  From Honister it was formerly brought by men on hurdles, and down a descent so precipitous as to appear incredible to those who had not witnessed the act. </p>
<p> As the slate lies generally near the summit of Honister Crag, it has, for many years, been lowered in carts, on the winding traverses which have been made for that purpose in the mountain. From Yew Crag, however, which is on the opposite side of the road, the hurdle is still employed.  The average weight of the slate which a man brings down each time, is eight hundred and ninety-six pounds; besides the weight of the hurdle which is five stones, or eighty pounds.  The ascent from the road to the Yew Crag quarry is steep, and half a mile in length.  The usual number of journies which are daily performed to. And from the quarry are nine, or fifty-four in the week, and hence a man brings down 8064 pounds weight of slate in one day, or 48, 384 pounds in a week. </p>
<p> ˈOur guideˈ, observes a writer on the subject, ˈpointed out to us tracks down the declivity opposite to Honister, which are made by a man bringing slate from the top of the mountain into the vale below.  This hardy and industrious creature, having attained the summit of a mountain hundreds of feet high, fastens together a large quantity of the slate, and placing it behind him, to preserve it from being shattered to pieces by an unprotected descent, he slides down to the precipice with his burthen pressing him forward, and thus, like Sisyphus, incurs the daily risk of being crushed to death, with the additional honour of a yawning abyss before his eyes.ˈ </p>
<p> The road to the south, between Honister and Yew Crag, leads to Borrowdale-hawse, and thence into Borrowdale.  It has been already observed that all Borrowdale was formerly possessed by the monks of Furness Abbey.  It appears that this property was given to them by Alice, who was the third daughter of William Fitz Duncan, Earl of Murray, and of Alice de Romley, lady of Egremont and Skipton in Craven, and who took her mother's surname of de Romley.  She married first Gilbert Pipard, and secondly Robert Courtney, but had no issue.  When she granted the whole of Borrowdale to God and the monastery of St. Mary of Furness, her latter husband was dead; she declares, that she grants it ˈby her own powerˈ and in her free widowhood, for the health of her lord, John king of England, that of her own soul, and of the souls of her ancestors and successors
<pb n="28"/>
and of her husbands of good memory, Gilbert Pipard and Robert de Cortenay.ˈ This grant is confirmed by king John. </p>
<p> It was afterwards confirmed by William, the son of William de Fortibus, earl of Albemarle, who married Hawise, the daughter of William le Gross, and niece of Alice de Romley.  This William le  Gross, who married Cecily, the eldest daughter of William Fitz Duncan, was earl of Albemarle and Holderness, and was descended from the daughter of William the Conqueror.  Lastly, this grant is confirmed by Alan de Multon and Alice his wife, of all Borrowdale to St. Mary and the Abbey of Furness.  This confirmation is dated in the month of March, ˈanno grati&#230; 1240.ˈ </p>
<p> There would seem to be an error in the assertion, that the rectory of Crosthwaite was appropriated to the abbot and convent of the monastery of the blessed Virgin Mary of Fountains, in the diocese of York.  The truth appears to be, that the parish of Crosthwaite was parcel of the great lordship or barony of Allerdale, above Derwent, which at the time of the conquest was given to William de Meschiens, and descended to his three great grand-daughters, Cecily, Alice, and Amabil.  It was this Alice who granted all Borrowdale to the abbey of Furness; and Amabil was the wife of Reginald de Lucy, lord of Egremont, and ancestor of the Lucies, Multons, and Percies, lords of Egremont.  In corroboration of the opinion which has been brought forward, it appears that Isabella, countess of Albemarle, and widow of William de Fortibus, the third earl, was summoned in the time of Edward the First, to show on what ground she claimed to have a market at ˈCrosthweyt'?ˈ  The answer was, that she had no such claim; but that the people of the neighbourhood on holydays met there at the church, and sold flesh, fish, &amp;c. but that she took no toll or stallage of them.  In the tenth of Edward the Third, the abbot of Furness had a grant of free warren in numerous manors in Lancashire and Yorkshire; and in ˈBoroudale,ˈ Brothernelkle, Meles, and Salthouse, in Cumberland.  Thomas Percy, as heir of the Meschiens family, had a trial with queen Elizabeth respecting the mines in Derwent-fells.  There can, therefore, be no doubt that Borrowdale, with rectory of Crosthwaite, was given by the descendants of Meschiens to Furness Abbey.  Hence, ˈDe Fourness;ˈ the abbey of which place was founded by king Stephen, 
<pb n="29"/> 
then earl of Mortaign, in the year 1127, and contemporary with William le Gross, early of Albemarle, and lord of Allerdale above Derwent. </p>
<p> Down Fleetwith, which is bordered on the west by Green Crags, runs a precipitate stream, which in full water is a beautiful object from the lower grounds.  Gatesgarth-dale, into which the road descends from Honister Crag, is a tremendous scene, and has a character peculiar to itself.  The sides of this valley, which are almost perpendicular, are composed of a kind of broken craggy rock, and give to the scene the image of still greater desolation.  The river also, which runs through the vale, and is the principal supply of the lake, is as wild as the valley itself. </p>
<p>  The beautiful vale of Buttermere contains the lake called by the same name. This lake is small, being only about a mile and a half in length, and a quarter of a mile in breadth.  It is of an oblong form, and at one end sweeps around a woody promontory.  The scenery about it is grand and beautiful.  On the western side of a long range of mountainous declivity stretches from end to end, and appears at a distance to fall every where precipitately into the water; though, when the spectator is on the spot, a margin of meadow probably extends from the bottom of the mountain.  The eastern side of the lake is woody, and happily contrasts with the western.  Near the bottom of this vale is a cascade, which appears at a distance like a white ribband bisecting the mountain from which it descends.  The people of this country, in reference to its foam, call it Sour Milk Gill, or Sour Milk Force.  Those who wish to study rocks and precipitous waters, will find them in great variety in this cascade, which after falling down the steep mountain, reposes in the lake of Buttermere.  The water of this fall comes from Burtness-tarn, which is situated between Red-pike and High-stile. </p> 
<p> The lake of Buttermere contains trouts and char of an excellent quality.  Here also are the fish called grey trouts, which are found in no other lake than in this and Ulswater.  The right of fishery is said to belong entirely to the earl of Egremont, who is lord of the manor.  </p>
<p> The chapel of Buttermere is a very small edifice, yet capable of containing the number of inhabitants within the chapelry.  Mr. Green mentions a native poet, as well as painter, of the name of Edward Tyson, who thus feelingly expresses his religious sentiments on the worship paid here to the great Creator:</p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line>  ˈYou'll see old men, with tottering limbs </line>
<line> And heads as white as snow, </line>
<line> Ascend this rock, to meet their God, </line>
<line> From whom all blessings flow.ˈ</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<pb n="30"/>
<p> ˈA manˈ, says Mr. Wordsworth, ˈmust be very insensible who would not be touched with pleasure at the sight of the chapel of Buttermere, so strikingly expressing, by its diminutive size, how small must be the congregation there assembled, as it were, like one family; and proclaiming, at the same time, to the passenger, in connexion with the surrounding mountains, the depth of that seclusion in which the people live, that has rendered necessary the building of a separate place of worship for so few.  A patriot, calling to mind the images of the stately fabrics of Canterbury, York, or Westminster, will find a heartfelt satisfaction in presence of this lowly pile, as a monument of the wise institutions of our country, and as evidence of the all-pervading and paternal care of that venerable establishment, of which it is, perhaps, the humblest daughter.  The edifice is scarcely larger than many of the single stones of fragments of rock which are scattered near it.ˈ </p>
<head level="2" align="center"> HAWESWATER, </head>
<p> The approach to Haweswater is between two high ridges of mountains.  This sweet, but rather unfrequented lake, ˈa lesser Ulswater,ˈ is about three miles in length, and half a mile in some places, and a quarter of a mile in others, in breadth.  It is almost divided in the middle by a promontory of inclosures, and is joined only by a narrow strait, the water of which is said to be fifty fathoms deep.  Hence the lake consists of two sheets of water.  The upper part is sublime, with bold, steep, craggy rocks and mountains; and in the centre of the end, a few little inclosures at their feet, waving upwards in a very beautiful manner.  The south side of the lake is a noble ridge of mountains, very bold and prominent to the edge of the water.  The opposite shore consists of inclosures, which rise one above another, and are crowned with craggy rocks. </p>
<gap desc="Image of Haweswater"/>
<pb n="31"/>
<p> This lake is distinguished by the solemn grandeur of its rocks and mountains, which rise in bold characters.  In the first expanse of the lake, the southern shore rises in a tremendous ridge of rocks, darkened with wood to the summit, and appears to terminate in Wallow Crag, a promontory of great height, beyond which the lake recedes from sight.  The finely broken mountains on the north are covered with heath, and the summits impend in crags and precipices; but their ascent from the water is more gradual than that of the opposite rocks; and they are skirted by a narrow margin of vivid green, with tufted shrubs and little groves, which overhang the lake, and are reflected on its surface.  Above, a very few white cottages among wood appear, and the narrow perspective is closed by the summit of the hills. </p>
<p> The second expanse of the lake discloses a scenery still more sublime.  This perspective seems to be terminated by the huge mountain called Castle Crag; but further appears Harter-fell, which rears its awful front, impending over the water, and confines the scene. Here amidst rocks, and at the entrance of a glen almost choked with fragments from the heights, stands the chapel of Mardale.  Above the chapel is all hopeless waste and desolation. The little vale contracts into a deep glen, strewed with the precipitated ruins of mouldering mountains and the destruction of perpetual waterfalls. </p>
<p> Among the mountains of this dark prospect are Lathale, Whelter Crag, Castle Crag, and Riggendale, whose bold lines appear beyond each other.  Kidstey Pike is pre-eminent among the crowding summits beyond the southern shore of the lake.  On the west is High-street, which overlooks the head of Ulswater, and which has probably received its name from an ancient road over this mountain.  This road is supposed by some to have been a Roman road; but whether or not of so great antiquity, it is probably the highest road every formed in England, being 2700 feet above the level of the sea.  On account of its central situation between the vales of Patterdale, Martindale, Mardale, Kentmere, and Troutbeck, an annual meeting was formerly held upon High-street, on the 10th day of July.  To this meeting the shepherds of these vales brought with them such sheep as had strayed beyond their regular boundaries, in order that each person might claim and receive his own.  The meeting for this general restitution of property was attended with the happiest effects, and prevented all animosity, contention, and legal proceedings.  To enliven the meeting, races, wrestling, and other rural diversion were instituted; and the only expense incurred was a hearty feast. Meetings of 
<pb n="32"/>
the same kind, for the restoration of property, are, it is believed, still annually held in this neighbourhood. </p>
<p> Dr. Dalton says, that Haweswater is two hundred and thirty-eight yards about the level of the sea.  This lake is the property of the earl of Lonsdale.  Char, perch, trout, eels, skellies, and chub or chevin, are all inhabitants of Haweswater. </p>
<p> The few houses near this lake are chiefly built without mortar, with the exception of that of Mr. Bowstead, at Measand-beck, a neat and excellent edifice; and that of Mr. Richard Holme at Chapel Hill.  An ancestor of Mr. Holme settled in Mardale, in the reign of king John; and the family of Holme has continued to reside here ever since that time. </p>
<p> Haweswater is seven miles from the foot of Ulswater, and eleven from Penrith.  The road to it from Penrith is by Eamont-bridge, Clifton, and Askham.  The last is delightfully situated upon the western bank of the river Lowther.  The church of Askham is a very neat modern edifice, and was re-built in the year 1832, at the expense of the earl of Lonsdale, who is patron of the church, and lord of the manor. </p>
<p> When the church was taken down, in 1832, there was discovered, in the foundation, a stone with an inscription in Saxon characters.  This stone is noticed by Mr. Machel, who says, ˈUnder the south window of the church is an arch, over a grave-stone, with this inscription:</p> 
<p align="center"> ˈWILS: DE SANTONEˈ</p>
<p> At the east end of the church was a place called Holy well, the descent to which was by steps.  From this well, which was undoubtedly formed in the times of popery, water was brought to the church for consecration and baptizing.  At this place the parishioners of Askham were wont to assemble in the afternoon of Easter-day, for the purpose of singing hymns; and the parishioners of Lowther also assembled on the other side of the river, and joined the former in their praises to God. </p>
<p> Upon the cross at Askham, which is situated in the middle of the village, were formerly two escutcheons, one containing three boars' heads, supposed to be the arms of the Swinburnes, of Askham; the other, six annulets, 3, 2, and 1, those of the Musgraves.  The same coats were also in the wall over the east window of the chapel in Askham Hall.  In the glass of that window was a representation of the Trinity in one part, and of the Virgin Mary of our Saviour in the other.  Mr. Machel says, that the arms of the Musgraves, empaled with those of the Sandfords, were in one of the windows of the same chapel.  It appears that the families of Swinburne and Musgrave intermarried, and this may account for their arms being placed together. </p>
<p> At Helton, in the parish of Askham, at the end of the tithe barn, was formerly a stone seat, where the inhabitants met for the purpose of transacting their parochial affairs. He who came first waited till he was joined by the rest; and it was considered a mark of great rudeness for any one to absent himself from the meeting.  After conferring on such matters as related to the parish, they separated, and each returned home. </p>
<p> At the distance of two miles from the foot of Haweswater stand the church and school of Bampton.  In a house, on the north side of the church, was born Mr. Richard Jackson, who was a very eminent teacher in this county, and became successively master of the schools of Bampton, Kendal, and Appleby.  To the last situation he was appointed in the year 1671, by the provost and fellows of Queen's College, Oxford, and was the first person nominated by them to Appleby school, after the appointment of a master had been vested in them by the governors of that school.  Whilst Mr. Jackson presided over the school at Bampton, he had the honour of educating Dr. Mill, the eminent Biblical scholar.  Mr. Jackson died March 23, 1685.  He is said to have been of a mild and gentle disposition, wholly free from pride and pedantry, and a person of great worth and learning.  Dr. Burn observes, that, ˈhe was one of the most eminent teachers of his time.ˈ </p>
<p> There seems, indeed, to have been almost a constant succession of able and learned masters at Bampton school, which, by their means, has been rendered both eminent and highly useful to the community.  The name of the Rev. William Langhorne, who died in 1775, is still remembered with great respect.  The late master, the Rev. John Bowstead, B.D., who presided over this school for more than half a century, retired from the situation a short time ago, on being 
<pb n="34"/> 
collated to the rectory of Musgrave, by the present bishop of Carlisle.  Independently of those who, after being instructed at this school, have entered the universities, very many who possessed not the means of obtaining a college education, have acquired here such a knowledge of the learned languages, as enabled them to fill situations of some distinction, with credit to themselves, and honour to those from whom they received their instruction.  If it were not invidious, and unjust to those who are not mentioned, many names of living men who were educated at this school, and who are an honour to their profession, and highly useful to the community, might easily be  adduced.  Very many who were brought up at Bampton school, entered into the church, in which some of them continued in the humble situation of curates – a situation certainly of great respectability and usefulness, but comparatively of little advantage to themselves.  Others of them, indeed, rose to a degree of eminence in their profession.  But they were all the sons of yeomen, or of those who had little to spare for giving them a university education.  Add to this, that not only those sons who were intended for some of the learned professions, but even those who were designed to manage the farm, and to succeed to the property of their ancestors, were all instructed alike, and alike received such an education as this school could bestow.  By this means, knowledge was diffused through the whole family – nearly through the whole community; and it was no uncommon thing to find the son who tilled the ground, and him who was destined for a profession, equally learned and well informed.  It was no uncommon thing to find yeoman who could read the New Testament in Greek, and who was acquainted with the best writers of the Augustine age. </p>
<p> The era succeeding the Reformation gave birth to those institutions which have been the means of diffusing happiness and knowledge among the people of this country, and especially among the inhabitants of Westmorland and Cumberland.  ˈMuch of the useful learning which has so remarkably enlightened the middle ranks of the English nation, and rendered us a moral and an understanding people, has proceeded from our numerous public schools.  It is in these truly respectable nurseries of literature, that education has effected its most generous and valuable purposes.  The mind, which might otherwise have been confined by sordid habits, has been called forth to the honour of human nature; and the general manners, from rudeness and vulgarity, have been rendered easy, courteous, and polite.ˈ</p>
<p> Such has been the effect produced by the numerous endowed schools in this
<pb n="35"/>
and the sister county.  But what is the case at the present time? Why, the young men who cannot obtain a university education are precluded, by certain regulations which have been adopted, from entering into the church.  The consequence is, that much of the learning, – such learning as was formerly taught at the endowed schools in the counties of Westmorland and Cumberland – is now entirely neglected.  All, or chiefly all, which is now taught, is confined to English and writing.  This is a state of things which cannot be too much lamented.  The effects of such an education may easily be foreseen.  Besides preventing some of benefiting either themselves or their country, the probable effects will be to render the yeomanry and peasantry of these counties, in a short time, as ignorant as their brethren in the south.  Hitherto Westmorland and Cumberland have been famed for the superior intelligence of their sons; but the time seems fast approaching when the may no longer boast of that superiority.</p>
</text>
