<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE text [
<!ENTITY eacute "&#xE9;">
]>

<!-- Added DOCTYPE declaration for convenience because of missing entity
definition. This doesn't make it right. It just makes it work. CJR 190113 -->

<text id="1795_a">
  <chap title="front matter">
    <p align="center"> THREE SUCCESSIVE </p>
    <p align="center"> TOURS </p>
    <p align="center"> IN THE </p>
    <p align="center"> NORTH OF ENGLAND, </p>
    <p align="center"> AND GREAT PART OF </p>
    <p align="center"> SCOTLAND. </p>
    <p align="center"> INTERSPERSED WITH </p>
    <p align="center"> DESCRIPTIONS OF THE SCENES THEY PRESENTED, </p>
    <p align="center"> AND OCCASIONAL OBSERVATIONS" </p>
    <p align="center"> ON THE STATE OF SOCIETY, AND THE MANNERS AND </p>
    <p align="center"> CUSTOMS OF THE PEOPLE. </p>
    <p align="center"> BY HENRY SKRINE, ESQ. </p>
    <p align="center"> OF WARLEY IN SOMERSETSHIRE </p>
    <p align="center"> LONDON </p>
    <p align="center"> PRINTED BY W. BULMER AND CO. </p>
    <p align="center"> AND SOLD BY P. ELMSLY, STRAND. </p>
    <p align="center"> 1795.</p>
  </chap>
  <chap title="Preface">
    <pb n="3"/>
    <p align="center"> PREFACE. </p>
    <p> THE following Travels, written at different periods of the Author's life, were not originally designed to be printed; nor has he any apology to offer for submittingso trifling a work to the public eye, except the solicitations of some few partial friends. </p>
    <p> The first of these Tours was made many years ago, and covers those central parts of the North of England, whic hare too well known to require much minute description;it has therefore been compressed into a single chapter, and is prefixed as introductory to the others, and including too much material a potion of the general outline tobe entirely omitted. </p>
    <p> The second Tour was taken in the year 1787; and commencing with the vale of the Trent in Staffordshire, approached the beautiful region of the lakes of Cumberland,Westmoreland, and Lancashire, by Liverpool, Preston, and Lancaster. Though<pb n="4"/>frequently the subject of description, this district possesses too many charms to be passed over in silence; and has been dwelt upon with much pleasure. The ruder scenes of the Western Highlands of Scotland, though scarcely less known, presented yet superior attractions, as we approached them by the great commercial city of Glasgow; norcould Inveraray, Taymouth, or the Blair of Athol, be traversed without a due tribute of admiration. Perth, Sterling, and the proud display of Edinburgh, with its ornamentedenvirons, terminated this travel in Scotland, which we left by Berwick; and passing through Northumberland and Durham, crossed the upper part of Yorkshire, by Richmond,and through Wensley dale to Craven; descending again into the plains of Lancashire, and approaching Chester by Manchester. Shrewsbury, Ludlow, and a small district ofSouth Wales, concluded the whole. </p>
    <p> The last remaining Travel took place in the summer of 1793, and directed its course from Edinburgh to the eastern coast, by St. Andrew's, Dundee, and Aberdeen, from whence it crossed the eastern penin-<pb n="5"/>sula, and pursued the grand display of the northern bay, to Fort George and Inverness. The sublime scenery attending Loch-Ness, and surrounding the forts Augustus and William, with the tremendous pass of the Coriaraich mountain, could not fail to create a superior interest; and had the advantage of being less known to, and describedby former travellers. A second visit to the Blair of Athol restored us to an inhabited country: the ornamental territory of Drummond castle combined its external beautieswith the interior charms of its society; and by Sterling, Glasgow, and Hamilton, we return to Edinburgh, taking our farewell of Scotland by Melross abbey, and the pleasingvales of the Tweed, the Tiviot, and the Eske. </p>
    <p> Such were the objects severally pursued in these Travels, which will amply answer the end proposed, if they serve to mark out some fine points of view which have not yet been fully explored or described, to those whose pens or pencils may do them more justice. The additional illustration which might be obtained by the latter, has but toofrequently sug-<pb n="6"/>gested itself in the course of the Author's numerous travels; and caused him to lament that, in recording some of the most animated scenes nature has produced in differentparts of Europe, he was only qualified to substitute cold description to the happier effects of drawing, and the imagery of real landscape. </p>
    <p> In his observation on the state of society, and the manners which prevail in the remoter parts of our island, the Author has found less difficulty; and deems it noinconsiderable advantage, that six years intervened between his second and third Tours, so that he had a fuller opportunity of observing the particular traits and customs,and estimating the progress of improvement. In oding this, he had been studious to be impartial and unprejudiced, in his remarks on a nation, for which collectively, aswell as for many individuals to whom he has the honour of being known, he entertains a very high degree of respect and admiration. </p>
    <p> It should be added, in apology for the style of this work, that its irregularity is occasioned by the different times and seasons in which it was written, and <pb n="7"/>the various descriptions of country it comprehends. The person also is frequently changed, to give more animation to some particular scene, and to avoid the prolixity ofuniform narrative. In matters of opinion and observation, the Author frequently speaks in the singular number; but in description he generally uses the plural, except inthose parts of his Travels which he performed alone, a circumstance which occasionally happened. <ptr target="n1"/> </p>
    <p> It may not be improper to add, that the author, in each of his two last Travels, found much information, as well as entertainment, in Gray's and West's Tours of theLakess, Ainslie's new Map, and general Account of Scotland, Dr. Johnson's Tour, and above all, in Mr. Pennant's very accurate and valuable work.-These books he stronglyrecommends to all future travellers in the North of England and Scotland. </p>
    <note id="n1"> For the accidental inaccuracy also ofa few repetitions of epithets, or other words, in the same sentence, he has to apologize to the reader, never having been before accustomed to correct his manuscriptsfor the press. </note>
    <pb n="i"/>
    <head level="3" align="center">ERRATA</head>
    <p>Page 42, line 4 from the bottom, omit the word "boldly."</p>
    <p>Page 116, line 8 from the bottom, for "Earls of Marshall" <i>read</i> "Earls Marischall."</p>
  </chap>
  <chap title="Travels in Derbyshire">
    <pb n="ii"/>
    <p align="center"> TRAVELS </p>
    <p align="center"> IN </p>
    <p align="center"> DERBYSHIRE, YORKSHIRE, </p>
    <p align="center"> AND </p>
    <p align="center"> NOTTINGHAMSHIRE. </p>
    <pb n="iii"/>
    <p align="center"> TRAVELS IN DERBYSHIRE, &#38;c. </p>
    <p>
      <i> Derby-Keddleston Park-Matlock-Chatsworth-Buxton-Castleton-Sheffield-Wentworth House-Wentworth Castle-Nostall Park-Wakefield-Leeds-Moravian Settlement at Pudsey-Kirkstall Abbey-Harewood House-Ormus Cliff in Wharfe-Dale-Harrogate-Knaresborough-Rippon-Studley Garden, and Fountains Abbey-Castle-Howard-Malton-Scarborough-BurlingtonTown and Quay-Beverley-Hull-Weighton-York-Brahaman Park-Ferry-Bridge-Doncaster-Roche Abbey, and Sandbeck Terrace-Worksop Manor-Welbeck Abbey-Clumber House and Grounds-Thoresby Park.Newark-Southwell Cathedral-Bolsover Castle-Hardwick House-Mansfield-Nottingham Town and Castle. </i>
    </p>
    <p> THIS short preliminary Tour is meant to comprehend most of the objects worthy of observation in that interior part of the north of England, which is not covered bythe two ensuing travels;-it includes therefore much of the three counties of Derby, York, and Nottingham. </p>
    <p> The town of Derby is pleasantly situated in a rich, vale, watered by the fine river Derwent, and surrounded by a variety <pb n="iv"/>of wooded and cultivated hills, beyond which the bolder eminences of the Peak mark a rude but grander outline. </p>
    <p> In our approach to these magnificent boundaries we visited Keddleston, the noble seat of Lord Scarsdale, where a modern house, almost unexampled in the correct grandeur and beauty of his architecture, is happily placed in the midst of a park distinguished by groves of the finest tree, well grouped, and divided by a broad sheetof water. </p>
    <p> A succession of rude hills, after we had passed the pleasant village of Duffield, conducted us to the romantic spot on which the baths of Matlock are situated; wherethe rapid river Der-went, winding between two vast chains of rocks, forms a narrow valley, clothed with a profusion of fine wood, and enriched with a medicinal spring, which, together with the extraordinary beauty of the surrounding stripe of scenery, attracts a large por-tion of the public every summer. </p>
    <p> Emerging from this tract, after passing under the huge rock called its High Torr, we entered into a more spacious vale; and followed the banks of the Derwent, winding sweetly through a mixture of villages, meadows, and cultivation, till we reached the groves of Chatsworth. This noble seat of the Devonshire family will yield to few inEngland, either in grandeur, extent, or the peculiarity of its design and position.-Surrounded by the rudest moors, its plantations flourish with all the luxuriance ofa milder climate; and it bursts upon the eye of a traveller, descending from the hills, like a paradise formed in the midst of a desert. The traces of ancient magnificence, imitating, and in<pb n="v"/>points exceeding the dignity of Versailles, distinguish both the house and its environs; while the park, modernized in Brown's best style, encircles the Derwent with a velvet lawn, and covers all the nearer eminences with its plantations, contrasting the rough hills of the Peak which overhang it. </p>
    <p> At the village of Middleton we approached these boundaries; and through a long hollow, strangely guarded by barriers of rocks, imitating the works of art, and frowningover us like the battlements of an ancient fortification, we emerged into a dreary wild, intersected with stone walls in every direction, and marked with a few melancholyvillages. Near the centre of this gloomy district, we found the gay resort of Buxton, on a spot in which nature has lavished none but her medicinal charms. A more dismalsituation can hardly be imagined; liable to incessant rains from the height of the surrounding hills, which are yet deficient in grandeur, and exposed to all the inclemencyof its cliate, with hardly a leaf to shelter it. Under all these advantages Buxton, from the efficacy of its springs, or the caprice of the fashionable world, annually attracts an immense number of visitors, who enrich both the place and its neighbourhood; in consequence of which, it has swelled from a paltry village to a handsome town;and now boasts a crescent, almost rivalling that of Bath. </p>
    <p> It must be confessed that a stranger, whose object is to ex-plore a curious country, may here find ample materials, as all the celebrated wonders of the Peak are within his reach; and the almost transcendent beauties of Dove-Dale are not far <pb n="vi"/>distant. The charming vale of Ashborne, the gradens of Ilam, and the paintings of Okeover, may also be visted from hence with ease; neither is the cavern of Castleton aninconsiderable object. We pursued the mazes of this cave under the auspicies of a guide grown grey in his office; and our return to the blaze of day, after the temporarynight we had experienced, was attended with its customary degree of surprise and admiration. </p>
    <p> Passing the village of Hope, in the midst of its rich valley, we mounted a dreary range of moors, from whence we descended to Sheffield, a dirty, unpleasant town, butrich in its manufac-tures. </p>
    <p> Here the country began to improve; and after we had passed the town of Rotherham, famous for its iron works, we reached the ancient mansion of Thrybergh park, situatedon a fine emi-nence above the river Don, and commanding all the vale from Sheffield to the hills near Doncaster, bounded towards the north bu the groves and buildings ofWentworth. </p>
    <p> Having passed some pleasant days with our friends at this place, we sat out with them to visit most of the fine objects with which the county of York abounds; and beganwith the splendid display of Wentworth house and its environs. </p>
    <p> Entering the park through a neat modern gateway, the lawn, wood, and water, opened upon us with the happiest effect, and the approach to the house was attended withsufficient grandeur. The front is truly magnificent, being nearly a copy of Lord Tylney's celebrated seat on Epping forest; but the wings, which are very extensive, seeminadequate to the structure, and defi-<pb n="vii"/>cient in taste. The whole also, both without and within, appears unfinished; and perhaps it ought to be lamented, that too great an outline has been taken to be completedwithin the life, or by the taste of any one possessor. An attempt was made by its late noble owner to remove a hill in front, which excludes great part of the distantprospect; but this, though partlly ef-fected, seems to have stagnated from the difficulty of the undertaking, and will probably never get accomplished. The views, however,of the park and its extensive plantations, with two lofty pillars which mark its boundaries, are sufficiently striking; and well diversified with all the ornaments of wood, water, and fine swells of ground. </p>
    <p> About half a mile from Wentworth house, we passed through the village of Wentworth, and soon afterwards reached an obelisk, directing our way, through a well clumped avenue, across a heath, to the groves which encompass Wentworth castle, the fine seat of the Earl of Strafford. Much beauty as well as grandeur is exhibited in the approach,which partakes of the rural and forest-like species of scenery, but somewhat ornamented, till it terminates in a spacious park, where a profusion of wood and water appearsmost judiciously disposed, and the two grand fronts of the house burst on the sight with almost unequalled magnificence. This great pile of building exhibits a happy spe-cimen of the architecture prevailing in two different ages, which yet sufficiently correspond with each other to please the eye when united. The old front is a very extensive,bold, plain building, containing several good apartments, together with the <pb n="vii"/>hall, and a magnificient gallery, extending through the house, and supported at each end by two pillars of foreign marble. The view from the windows of this noble room isenchantingly striking, commanding the whole vale wth its opposite hills, abundantly clothed with wood and villages, and decorated with several ornamental buildings, while the verdant lawn of the park sloping gradually to a great sheet of water, so dispersed as to assume the form of a serpentine river, and surrounded by noble groves of oaks,descending in each side of the house, strongly contrasts the wilder features of the distant prospect. The new front, forming an angle with the other, exhibits a beautifulspecimen of the Greacian taste, in its chaste decoration, and its highly finished portico, resting on fluited Corinthian pillars.-If I could mark a defect, it should consist in the frames of the windows being burnished with gold, which, though admissible in such a house as Chatsworth, is not compatible with the tast of a more modern building.The new apartments also, which are yet in an unfinished state, are too uniform in point of size to equal the grandeur of the exterior. The gardens of this place, risingabove the house, are well laid out, and are crowned with a high building imitating a castle, which contains a handsome room, and commands an unbounded prospect over a finecountry; to embellish which, the beauty of the park and its adjacent woods contribute not a little. </p>
    <p>Crossing the vale, to which Wentworth castle gives so great an ornament, we ascended the opposite hill to the pleasantly situated inn of Bank-Top, and soon reached the gloomy town of <pb n="ix"/>Barnsley, covering a steep descent with its dirty streets, and blackened with the tinge of its manufactures. </p>
    <p> Here we deserted the great road, and pursued a wretched lane, for the purpose of visiting Nostall Park, the seat of Sir Rowland Wynne, which ill repaid our curiosity.-Anovergrown, and yet unfinished modern house, in the midst of a bare and flat park, without features or keeping, could indeed interest a stranger but little; and the surrounding country, crowded with collieries, did not enliven the scene. We regained our road with difficulty; and soon reached the handsome town of Wakefield, rich inits flourishing manufactures, and displaying the opulence they have introduced in the width of its principal street, and the many considerable housess wiith which it isembellished. The establishment of the cllothing trade in this part of the country, has made the whole way from Wakefield to Leeds appear like a town, except where a smallportion of heath diversifies the scene. But Leeds, through of much greater extent, seems to want the neatness and regularity which prevail at Wakefield. we had an opportunityof visiting its cloth hall during the market, which fills three sides of a spacious quadrangle, forming two long galleries, which communicate in several places with eachother, and join at the end so as to encompass the whole building. Here an innumerable quantity of cloths are ranged on each side, on a row of tables, by which the manufacturers stand, with little rods or brushes in their hands, ready to deal with the chapmen, who are diligent in examining the goods, and transact every thing in awhisper. The novelty <pb n="x"/>of the scene both suprised and interested us; and the size of the building, though much inferior to that of Halifax, which we afterwards visited, far exceeded our expectation.</p>
    <p> From Leeds i made an excursion of about six miles, to view the singular establishment of the Moravian college, at the village of Pudsey, charmingly situated on theslope of a fine hill towards the south, and adorned with a range of buildings which equal many of the colleges in our universities. With their religious tenets I did notconcern myself; but I was pleased to see a large Christian establishment well conducted, preserving the utmost order and decorum within its walls, and promoting industryin the midst of a popolous country with great success. In my return I passed the magnificent remains of Kirkstall abbey, charmingly situated on the banks of the river Aire,about three miles from Leeds; and exhibiting a rich specimen of the Gothic order of the architecture. </p>
    <p> Tacking the north road from Leeds, we soon reached the magnificent seat of Lord Harewood, close to the village from which his title is derived. This house is a trulynoble edifice, built of a brown stone produced in the neighbourhood; and the interior range of apartments are finely disposed, and enriched with every ornament that artor expence can produce. Its situation also is happily chosen; and when the plantations are sufficiently grown, the grand outline of the park, and its piece of water, willhave their due effect. </p>
    <p> Immediately on leaving Harewood, we descended into Wharfe-Dale, a fine view of which the upper walks of its gardens com- <pb n="xi"/>mand, and which altogether forms the stronger feature of the place. This is one of the great valleys peculiar to the north of Yorkshire, where a rapid river, descendingfrom a great ridge of moors, divides the country, and a chain of towns and villages, with a cultivated district, following its banks, beautifully distinguish it from thewildness of the adjacent scenery. In the midst of this vale rises the extraordinary hill of Ormus Cliff, almost swelling to the dignity of a mountain, and commanding aprospect hardly capable of description, from the summit of the bold rock which crowns this insulated eminence. </p>
    <p> Passing the Wharfe by a handsome bridge, we soon found the country decline in beauty; and though of late much improved in cultivation, it presented little better thana dreary moor as we approached the great public resort of Harrogate. Here, however, the adjacent country, as at Buxton, produces a variety of objects; and the ornamented scenes of Harewood, Plumpton, Studley, Hackfall, and Newby, form perceptual sources of amusement to the strangers who visit Harrogate. Still nearer are the romantic beautieswhich encircle Knaresborough, a town proudly situated beneath the swelling groves of Scriven Park; and with the bold ruin of its castle overhanging a deep hollow, intermixedwith wood and rock, through which the river Nid tears its course, and receives in its passage a tributary stream from the Dropping Well, famous in ancient legend. </p>
    <p> Three large houses of public resort now flourish on the heath of Harrogate, and in the high season contain an astonishing concourse of company with their walls. At the Dragon in <pb n="xii"/>particular, where I have repeatedly made a long sojourn, in pursuit of health from the water, every species of accommodation is provided with the utmost care, and accompaniedwith the most unvaried attention. There houses, together with a few shops, a chapel, and the mansion of its very respectable minister, form almost all the buildings onthe heath; but at the distance of about a mile, at Lower Harrogate, near the sulphureous well, there are various other houses of public resort. </p>
    <p>In a few miles after we had left Harrogate we reached an inclosed country, and passing a handsome seat of Sir John Ingleby at Ripley, we visited Mr. Weddel's admirablecollection of statues at Newby, in our way to Rippon. This neat borough town covers an eminence above the river Ure, forming a spacious and well built square in its centre;from the middle of which a fine obelisk of stone rises to a great height, with a gilt buglehorn on its summit. Here we found an excellent inn, and passed several days very agreeably in visiting the many places worthy of observation in the adjacent country. </p>
    <p> Of these the neighbouring seat and gardens of Studley claim a manifest pre-eminence, being scarcely equalled in grandeur or extent by any place in the kingdom. Theapproach is nobly formed; and enetering the park under a lofty arch, we proceeded through a spacious avenue terminated by an obelisk, to a terrace on which the house issituated, commanding a most extensive prospect over the great vale of Yorkshire, terminated at a vast distance towards the east of the Hambledon moors, with the town,pillar, and great collegiate church of Rippon in full view<pb n="xiii"/>below. The house, though by no means equal to the splendour of the place, is ample and convenient; but the garden have long been justly celebrated, and though some partsof them are not exactly in the modern taste, the profusion of ornament and beauty which distinguishes them cannot be too much admired. </p>
    <p> In some places, formal slopes and regular pieces of water ex-hibit the species of gardening which decorates most of the palaces on the Continent; but their uniformityonly causes a pleasing variety in the midst of the wild scenery of the park, and the wonderful display of evergreens which flourish abundantly in this favoured spot. Themost magnificent buildings are happily dispersed over the whole territory, and every effort of art to delight and astonish is exhausted with the best effect. After a succession of there objects, ascending a high hill, and penetrating through a thick wood, we reached arustic building, the folding doors of which being thrown open, displayeda scene far surpassing in grandeur all that the most favoured painter could design. Immediately below us lay the whole extent of the great lake, unconfined by formalboundaries, but encompassed by groves of towering shrubs, and hills fringed with every species of wood, which insensibly grew rougher and less adorned as the valley beforeus became narrower, till the whole was closed by the stupendous ruin of Fountains abbey, proudly occupying a gentle eminence, from whence the rivulet rolls in a successionof falls till it loses itself in the lake. </p>
    <p> This noble abbey is more perfect in its preservation, and happier in its situation, than any ruin I have seen in the king- <pb n="xiv"/>dom. The remains of the library, and the east window of the church, which is in high preservation, front this part of the garden; and these are mostly Gothic, togetherwith the tower, which is entire, with all its ornaments for four stories. It rises to a great height, rather narrowing towards the pinnacles on the top, with niches forstatues finely carved between each story; and the grandeur of its appearance is rather aided than diminished by the upper parts of the building being somewhat broken. Weentered at a door close to the east window, and from thence had an uninterrupted view through the whole body of the church, 600 feet in length, to the western door andwindow at the extremity of the great aile, which being finely pre-served, together with the two rows of Saxon pillars which descend from the choir, give an astonishingair of grandeur to the whole. To the left of the church is a large court surrounded with monastic buildings; among which we admired the architecture of the chapter-house,the refectory, and the kitchen, to-gether with a spacious clouister 160 feet in length, supported by four rows of arches on light pillars, and unlike any other build-ingof the kind in the kingdom. A wild tract of ground over-hung with wood and rock closes the scene judiciously behind the abbey; and some scattered fragments of the abbot'shouse are visible at a small distance. Through this opening the path wound pleasantly till it reached the water; and all the scenery grew gradually less rude and unequalas we returned to the more polished parts of the garden, in which we found a splen-did banqueting house on an eminence, well decorated with<pb n="xv"/>shrubberies and parterres of flowers, and commanding most of the buildings in the grounds. Here we eat our cold coalition with great pleasure; after which we returned inthe evening to Rippon. </p>
    <p> A second excursion from thence brought us to Hackfall, which though an appendage to Studley, at the distance of about seven miles, contrasts its grandeur and regularitywith a profusion of romantic beauty, and does equal credit to the taste which formed both these places. A neat cottage supplies a residence for the gardener; and a simplewicket introduces a stranger to the grounds, through which a winding path conducts him down a steep descent covered with wood, by the side of a rivulet tum-bling insuccessive falls to a rustic building impending over the river Ure, which dashes with immense rapidity over a rocky bed beneath a hill finely fringed with wood. The samepath afterwards winds along a terrace above the river, crossing several little lawns, some of which are ornamented with suitable build-ings, commanding the principleobjects of the garden; among which a cascade of a very considerable height is most conspicuous. An ardeous ascent follows, which, however, is frequently relieved by seatsjudiciously placed, so as to command various points of view through vistas to advantage, till the whole bursts upon the sight with great majesty from an eminence calledMowbray Point. All the objects of the garded are here visible almost perpendicularly below; while opposite, a magnificent column of wood spreads its base into a vastamphi-theatre, round which the foaming river Ure tears its way with<pb n="xvi"/>an impetuous torrent, fronted by a high cliff crowned with the fictitious ruons of a castle. Beyond this bold and striking fore-ground, a distant scene opens over a broadlevel, extending to the Hambledon hills and Rosemary Topping in Cleveland, and finely distinguished by towns, villages, and the frequent windings of the river. The buildingwhich commands this view represents the rough walls of a ruined temple, but contains a handsome room within, where strangers are permitted to dine, if they prefer thisspot to the cottage, from which it is not far distant. </p>
    <p> Turning to the east of Rippon, we crossed the vale, and soon reached Thirsk, a decent town, with a spacious market-place, near the extremity of the great plain ofYorkshire, towards the Hambledon hills. The ascent of this high barrier was uncommonly precipitous, and the view from the summit hardly repaid us for the labour we underwent. Before us a dreary and uninteresting heath extended far in sight, crossed by more distant hills, bearing as wild an aspect, and enlivened by no one pleasingobject till we reached the fine territory of Duncombe park, close to the wretched town of Helmsley. This noble seat of the Duncombe family, is a heavy but magnificent building, in Sir John Vanbrugh's best style, and contains a valuable collection of pictures, tapestry, and statues; among which latter we could not but notice the dogof Alcibiades, said to be the work of the celebrated Myron of Athens. This mansion overlooks one of the great terraces peculiar to Duncombe park, being near half a milein length, with an Ionic <pb n="xvii"/>rotunda at one hand, and a circular temple, on Doric pillars, at the other: it commands a great extent of prospect over a romantic vale, to thedistant Wolds of Yorkshire, where they close in with the sea coast; and abounds in a profusion of fine wild scenery. At the distance of about two miles, the second terraceextends itself in a bold curve of near a mile, from a circular Tuscan temple to a noble banqueting-house, fronted by a portico on Ionic pillars. The perpetual variation of the view, as we passed from one of these buildings to the other, can hardly be described; suffice it therefore to say, that a high range of hills, projecting in theboldest forms, and covered with the richest wood, encircle a beautiful valley, where a picturesque river winds round the three entire ailes of Rivaulx abbey, a ruin in-ferior only to that of Fountains in magnificence, and boasting some peculiar traits of beauty. </p>
    <p> We took the Malton road from Duncombe park, and soon reached the seat of Lord Carlisle at Castle Howard. The grand approach to this place is from the York road, andleads through an ornamented territory to a large building, with a high pyramid in its centre, which being a lodge to the park, is likewise an inn forthe accommodation ofthose whom curiosity brings to visit Castle Howard. The outline of this place is very consider-able, but its execution has been so varied and retarded, that the whole appearsa shapeless mass. The great front of the house, built by Sir John Vanbrugh, is 320 feet in length; but, like most of that architect's works, it is heavy, and crowded withornament; neither does it contain a single good room except the <pb n="nviii"/>hall. The opposite extreme is pursured in a new wing, erected from a design of Sir Thomas Robinson; in which immense apartments, and the lightness of the Grecian architecture,assort but ill with the clumsy weight of the mansion. These however are yet unfurnished; but the house contains a mine of treasure in paintings, statues, and marbles, which can hardly be paralleled. The gardens are rather in the formal taste, but the park is extensive, on an eminence in the centre of which is built a grand mausoleum,containing a chapel, with a perfect labyrinth of catacombs below, for the interment of the family. </p>
    <p> Soon after we left Castle Howard, we reached the handsome borough town of Malton; and passing a seat of Sir William St. Quintin, on a dead flat, we mounted the Woldsof Yorkshire; and then traversing several wild hills, descended to Scarborough. The first view of the sea, and Scarborough castle covering the summit of a bold rock, isstriking, where the town encircles a fine semicircular bay of considerable extent. It contains however few good streets, except the High-street, and that in which thepublic rooms are situated; but the new buildings on the Cliff occupy the pleasantest situation. At the distance of about half a mile across the sands is the mineral spa,which, together with the advantageous position of Scarborough for sca-bathing, has annually attracted a great influx of company. The church, though a sea mark, has littleto recommend it; but the castle is a noble object, notwithstanding its ruinous condition, and within it forms a barrack for soldiers. </p>
    <p> We ascended the Wolds again on leaving Scarborough; and<pb n="xix"/>passing through the neat village of Humnanby, adorned with a handsome seat of Mr. Osbaldiston, arrived at Bridlington, and soon afterwards at its quay, which being originallyonly constructed for naval purposes, hasacquired both extent and splen-dour from its annual importation of company. Those who dislike the public display of Scarborough,resort to this place, where they are well accommodated, and have the advantage of a much more pleasant country, with as good as sea beach. </p>
    <p> We mounted the Wolds again, in the way from hence to Driffield, an irregular town, situated nearly in the centre of this ridge of wild country, which presents a species of downs greatly inferior to those in the southern and western parts of England. </p>
    <p> Soon afterwards we descended into a fertile plain, in the midst of which we found the large and handsome town of Beverley, admirably built and paved, and adorned witha cathedral, inferior to few in the kingdom for the peculiar lightness and ele-gance of its Gothic architecture. The road from hence to Hull extends across an uninterestinglevel, which makes a part of the Fens of Yorkshire; and the churches of the two respective towns form almost theo nly visible objects in the ride between them. That ofHull, though inferior to Beverley, is a noble structure; but the town itself, though the central opening of its market-place is spacious, cannot boast the neatness orregularity of its neighbour. It derives, however, no inconsiderable advantage from its fine situation on the river Humber, and the abundant trade it has produced; everyconsequence of opulence having followed in the splendour of its merchants' houses, and the good<pb n="xx"/>arrangement of its new quay, which for beauty and regularity, will vie with most in Europe. </p>
    <p> Returning to Beverley, we once more crossed a corner of the Wolds, and descended to the neat town of Market-Weighton, where we entered the immense flat in which the city of York is situated, advancing towards that capital, without any object in view, except its lofty cathedral in front, and the fine old building of Howden church, inthe Fens, on our left. </p>
    <p> Thus can York boast little in its situation; neither is its interior distribution more pleasing, a great outline being divides and subdivided into a number of narrowand crooked streets intersected by the muddy and uninteresting river Ouse. This river being navigable for large vessels, York is situated well for trade; but it seems never to have pursued its advantages with spirit; a singular air of languor and inaction pervades the whole city. It has also, in past times, been the metropolis of thenorth of England, forming the winter residence of several families of distinction, till the superior grandeur and accommodations of Edinburgh gained a just preference; since which York appears to languish in a state of desertion and neglect. Many remnants of antiquity yet exist in this city, and the pre-cinct of its walls is almost entire,with several respectable old gateways. Its castle also forms the most spacious and best con-trived county gaol I have seen, containing within its walls two beautifulmodern buildings, which form the new county hall, and a range of opposite apartments for the females who are in confinement. The assembly-room of York also ought not tobe<pb n="xxi"/>left unmentioned, being a spacious Egyptian hall, designed by the late Lord Burlington, and decorated with a profusion of or-nament, in projecting pillars, and other incumbrances; yet with all its advantages, it must be called a heavy and gloomy building, better calculated for a church than a place of public entertainment. One object,however, in York, remains yet undescribed; and bold indeed must be the pen which attempts to do justice to the beauties of the finest cathedral in England, which risesfar above the level of all other churches. The whole building, when viewed from a distance, across the great level which surrounds it, appears like a large ship at sea;and it loses nothing in dignity as you approach it. The west front, with a noble tower on each side of entrance, is surprisingly grand, both in the richness of its ornaments, and the uncommon state of their preservation, hardly an arch being broken, or a statue defaced. The burst of view, on the entrance from the Western gate, iswonderfully great, extending through the whole of the church, finely paved, richly decorated with painted glass, and unincumbered with monuments. The screen of the choiris highly ornamented; and the Gothic arched stalls, ending on one side in the archbishop's throne, and on the other in the pulpit, together with the light elegance ofthe pillars and arches over the altar-piece, almost exceed all description. The blaze of the cast window also should not pass unnoticed; and the chapter-house is highlyworthy of admiration, being an octagon, sixty-three feet in diameter, without a single pillar to support<pb n="xxii"/>it, surrounded with marble stalls, and basso-relievos, finely exe-cuted in alabaster. </p>
    <p> Having exhausted all that was interesting in York, we passed over its fine race course, leaving the palace of Bishopthorpe on our left; and visiting the grand butformal display of Bramham park, descended into a rich vale, crossed by the river Aire at Ferrybridge, where we found an incomparable inn, delightfully situated on thenorth side of the river. From hence we deviated a little, to visit the ancient town of Pomfret; and then pursuing the great road, with an extensive view over the Fens of Yorkshire on the left, crossed a deep valley, and ascending a considerable hill, gained a prospect of the rich and beautiful vale in which Doncaster is situated. We approached this handsome town by an avenue of trees, fronting the Gothic tower of its church; and crossing the Don by a noble bridge, entered ne of the finest streets in England, well formed, admirably paved, and adorned with many noble structures. Here we left the great road, following the fine vale of the Don, and passing by thepicturesque ruin of Connisburgh castle, in our return to the hospitable mansion of Thrybergh park. </p>
    <p> After a long and very pleasant stay with our friends at that place, we turned towards the south, and soon reached the orna-mented tract of Roche abbey, belonging to the Earl of Scar-borough. The entrance to this ruin is finely contrived, through a Gothic gateway, so turned as to let in the light only by degrees, and progressivelyopen the view of a beautiful lawn,<pb n="xxiii"/>divided by a broad sheet of water; the rough fragments of rock, wood, and broken pillars, that surround the abbey, and the ivy mantled arches of the ruin. The vast amphitheatre of wood in front of the abbey forms a noble outline to the scene, and the whole round of the pleasure ground is executed in Brown's best style. At a smalldistance is Lord Scarborough's seat of Sand-beck, consisting of a large modern house, surrounded by an extensive park, and an ornamented pleasure ground; but the finestfeature of the place is the grand terrace by which it is approach-ed from the south, winding through clumps of evergreens, and parterres of flowers, well disposed, andcommanding frequent views of the surrounding country in a drive of above to miles. </p>
    <p> At length we quitted this highly adorned territory by a light Grecian gateway built of Portland stone, which in the elegance and beauty of its design surpasses mostin the kingdom, and soon after reached the town of Worksop in Nottingham shire, close to the Duke of Norfolk's noble seat of Worksop Manor. The original design of this house was intended to form a quadrangle of four fronts, similar to the one now exectured, which is 2.10 feet in length, and terminated at each end by a light turrect onIonic columns, rising one story above the attic;- within it contains two great ranges of apartments, with a grand staircase, superbly ornamented with compartments of basso-relievo; and its collection of Vandyke painings is very valuable. Its ssituation, on a low and sandy flat, is far from pleasant, but the upper parts of its spaciouspark are more strongly marked; through which we approached Welbeck abbey, the seat of the<pb n="xiv"/>Duke of Portland. This house also can boast little of its si-tuation, and the structure itself is not pleasing, though it contains several good rooms; a magnificent oldriding-house, which was the hall of the ancient abbey, is the only object worthy of much observation here, except an excellent kitchen garden. </p>
    <p> Crossing a part of Sherwood forest, we entered the Duke of Newcastle's extensive plantations, surrounding Clumber park, which we found better kept, and more highlyornamented than any of the places in this district of country. Two winding hills gently sloping towards each other, and well planted, form a pleas-ing valley, intersectedby a large and well disposed piece of water, crossed by a fine bridge of Portland stone. The house is judi-ciously situated on one of these slopes, and covers a great tractof ground, containing an immense number of fine apartments, richly furnished, and adorned with some valuable paintings. </p>
    <p> We crossed the bridge on leaving this place, and ascending the opposite hill, entered the adjoining park of Thoresby through a grand avenue. This place is very extensive,and its ground is more varied than the nature of a flat and sandy country and its accompaniment of wood and water is well disposed. </p>
    <p> almost surfeited with the display of so many fine places, in a small compass of country, we once more advanced into the forest, and through the neat village of Ollertonapproached an inclosed country, which varied little in form till we descended into the extensive flat on which the handsome town of Newark <pb n="xxv"/>is situated. The Trend here rolls its silver stream through a spacious level, bounded on one side by the hill on which Lincoln cathedral rises proudly to view, and on theother by the Leicestershire Wolds, before which the noble edifice of Belvoir castle projects boldly on an insulated rock, overhung by the hills of its park, finely clothedwith wood. The rich spire of Newark presented a handsome obhect on our left, as we bent our course to the collegiate church of Southwell, which may be called one of the finest remnants of the Saxon architecture in England. </p>
    <p> We then crossed another part of Sherwood forest to Mansfield, and made a short excursion to visit the Durk of Portland's splendid ruin of Bolsover castle, overhangingthe rich vale in which Chesterfield is situated, and the fine old seat of Hardwick, belonging to the Duke of Devonshire. This magnificent man-sion stands in the midst ofa wild and spacious park, and commands all the undulations of he Derbyshire hills on one side, together with most part of the forest of Sherwood on the other. The architecture is of that bold kind which distinguished many of those buildings in which the ancient orders were re-intro-duced, and its ornamental parts are grandly disposed. The apartments are very considerable, and, with great judgement, not at all modernized, neither is the furniture of many room changed since the date of thebuilding: many relicks of the unfortunate Mary of Scotland are left here, as she resided at this place for some time after her flight to England. Hardwick upon the wholeforms a fine contrast to Chatsworth, from which it is about sixteen miles distant, and is often visited by its<pb n="xxvi"/>noble owners, who are making great improvements in the ground, and the whole surrounding territory. </p>
    <p> Returning through Mansfield, we pursued a good new made road through the dreary forest of Sherwood, leaving a deserted place of Lord Byron on our right, till wereached the large and flourishing county town of Nottingham. This place is abundantly populous, to which its manufactures contribute in a great degree; the buildingsi ingeneral are of brick, and there are many good houses, but the streets are mostly narrow and steep; there inconveniences might be alleviated, but could hardly be altogetheravoided, yet there are circumstances in which Not-tingham might be improved without difficulty, its pavement being wretched almost beyond comparison, and the entranceson every side very arduous. One grand opening exists around the market-place, where the houses are built on piazzas, which form a commodious shelter to those on foot,and make rather a singular appearance. </p>
    <p> The situation of this town is very remarkable, spreading over a hill, which slopes towards the south; and forming a spacious amphitheatre, which terminates on eachside in a high rock, crwned with the Gothic building of the great church on the east and the castle on the west. The latter presents a proud object of the adjacent country,on the summit of an almost per-pendicular cliff, and insulated by a narrow valley from the town. It forms a grand but neglected seat of the Newcastle family; and exhibitsfour highly ornamented fronts, in the species of architecture which prevailed about the end of the last century. </p>
    <pb n="xxvii"/>
    <p> The apartments are large, but ill kept; and the whole presents the display of a magnificent palace, languishing in a premature state of decay and desertion. The viewfrom the windows, and the terrace which surrounds the castle, is astonishingly fine, commanding the whole town below it, the rich vale intersected by the Trent, the oppositeseats of Wollaton and Clifton, and the distant hills of Derbyshire and Leicestershire, marked with a variety of objects. A noble park rises on the north-west; and thewhole is finely interspersed with that species of sandy rock on which all the town of Nottingham is built. This rock, being easily perforated, produces many caverns, someof which are nature, and others the works of art: the cellars at the White Lion Inn are of the latter description; and descend in a succession of galleries, curiouslyarranged, to the level of the river. </p>
    <p> Winding through a variety of steep and inconvenient streets, we reache da long and ill formed causeway, which brought us to the banks of the Trent, and crossed thatriver by an awkward old bridge. Very little now remained to occupy our attention, as we soon descended into the rich plains of Leicestershire; and found nothing materialafterwards, in our way to London, to engage our observation. </p>
    <gap desc="Text omitted as not of interest for this project"/>
    <p> We proceeded through an indifferent falt country to Gar-stang, near which we saw the small remains of Greenough casle under an eminence on the right. The ground nowbeganto grow somewhat unequal, and in consequence thereof we gained occasional views of the sea on the left, while the hills closed in upon us on the right. At lengthwe mounted one of them, and had a delightful descent to Lancaster, with a full view of its noble church and castle, on a high hill above the sea. I was not long beforeI visited the celebrated scene of Lancas-ter churchyard, which amply deserves the reputation it has acquired. The ascent is under the walls of the castle, and the pathleads you round the church; a neat Gothic fabric, with a high tower, the upper part of which is modern. As soon as you have passed the body of the church, the sea opensto the left, and you trace the river Lune through several meanders to its mouth; further on the left, the flat country through which we had passed is extended; and on theright, Peel castle appears just raised above the level of the water, from which the hills of Furness gradually ascend. The whole view changes on passing round the church, and entering the contiguous field. All the hills of Furness appear in front, beyond which the lofty mountains of Westmoreland and Cumberland, in two distinct and craggytracts, seem to contend with the very skies for pre-emi-nence. Turning to the right, you see a very elegant bridge of five elliptic arches crossing the Lune, which passeswith a bold<pb n="8"/>sweep under the hill on which you stand; and further to the right, the whole town descends into the vale in a great curve from the castle, while several high barren hillsrise grandly in front. I passed from hence, over an old bridge of four arches, to the new bridge, which now presents a grand access to the town from the north. </p>
    <p> Nothing can be more striking than the river and the noble warehouses on the quay, when viewed from this approach; and as you come nearer to the town, the lofty turretsof the castle overhang it with a royal grandeur, almost rivalling those of Windsor. The town is extensive, and as handsome as the in-equality of its situation will admitof; the streets are many of them steep, and not very wide; the modern houses, which are built of a fine brown stone, with roofs of blue slate, are elegant. The castle isa noble fabric, on the highest point of the hill, and contains the county-hall and prison, the latter of which is admirably contrived. From the highest tower I had a view nearly similar to that from the churchyard; and I was much struck with the grandeur of the great gate, with two lofty turrets rising from it, which was erected byJohn of Gaunt, whose statue sood in a nich yet remaining over it. </p>
    <p>We staid two days at this place, and the second was favour-able for our seeing the view from the third mile-stone on the Hornby road, which has been so deservedly commended by Mr. Gray. The whole ride is charming, on an elevation above the banks of the river, with high hills rising on each side. Soon after we had passed the mile-stone,the great scene of<pb n="9"/>Lonsdale opened, and we pursued the Lune winding in a variety of folds, under a steep cliff entirely covered with wood, and encircled by the richest meadows. A pine-cladhill rose on the right, and descended to a village, whose whitened houses terminated the fore ground. Beyond it the vale became more extensive, and the river was yet tobe traced at a distance, under Hornby church and castle, while the outline grew more wild and mountainous, till the whole scene was closed by the lofty barried on Ingleborough,projecting his rocky head and furrowed sides with unequalled magnificence. All that could please and delight the eye was contained in this beautiful landscape; and enoughof the sublime was added to give it im-portance without inspiring terror. On our return to Lancaster, we could not but be struck with the noble appearance of the castleand church, which impended over the town and river with infinite majesty, while the elegant structure of the new bridge divided the stream below in the happiest position.The following day was less prepitious, but we had sun shine enough between the storms to enjouy the frequent views of the sands ex-tending into the great bay of Morecambe, which every ascent in the first part of our ride presented. The country soon grew more mountainous as we receded from the coast, and the lofty eminence of Warton craggon the left, was finely opposed by the bold and rugged cliff of Farlton Knot on the right. After we left the little town of Burton, we passed immediately under the almost perpendicular height of the latter mountain, from whence a lovely succession of hills and vallies, ornamented with<pb n="10"/>the most picturesque inclosures, and covered with thick woods, conducted us imperceptibly to the top of a hill, which com-manded the large town of Kendale, spread overthe summit of a knowl, gently rising in the midst of the vale from which it takes its name, and almost surrounded by the river Kent. A great variety of wild and unequalhills closed in upon it at a small distance on every side; and far behind, the indented summits of the Westmorland and Cumberland mountains extended in a long irregularchain high above them all. kendale consists principally of one street near a mile long, ascending on each side to the market-place, which breaks in upon the center in-conveniently. The river flows all along beneath, and is crossed by two old bridges, on of which bears the name of Stramon gate; and near it a round hill rises on the right,crowned with the ruins of Kendale castle. Little more than a circular row of unequal fragments remains; but the situation is bold, and must have commanded the town completely. This place is famous for a branch of the woolen manufacture; though I could not find that the green colour which Falstaff so happily descried in the dark,is still predominant. The town is abundantly po-pulous, and it happening to be market day when we were there, the concourse of the country people from the hills wasprodigious, and gave it the appearance of a fair. Most of them drove a small light cart, which came filled with turf or peat, to be disposed of, and returned loaded with the produce of the market. We made an excursion from hence to see the falls of the Kent, and passed by the old hall of Sizergh on the Mil-<pb n="11"/>thorpe turnpike, to Leven's bridge, close to a very ancient seat of Lord Suffolk, which formerly belonged to the Bellingham family. Being provided with a key at Kendale,we passed through the park, a beautiful tract of ground, full of charming inequalities, and decorated with a profusion of the finest trees scattered about in large clumps.Among these, the beech, and a grand avenue of oaks, were most eminent; several large haw-thorns distinguished every swell, and thick groves of birch hung over the steepmargin of the river, which rolled in a mountain torrent, and wound delightfully through the middle of the grounds. As soon as we left this enchanting scene, the road ledus through a romantic glen, almost on the edge of a precipice above the river, till we came to a point, where a bold and rough arch connects the impending rocks on eachside, through which the stream rushes in a dark and gloomy current, and soon falls in a foaming cataract over several high ledges of the rock, after which it is embosomedin the wood of Leven's park. A forge lately erected somewhat lower on the opposite bank, has a little diminished the beauty of this scene, by baying up the water, andmaking the torrent less full than nature had left it; but still there is enough to please the eye, and delight the mind sufficiently. </p>
    <p> As we proceeded on the bank of the river, we passed a pretty new-built mansion, which looked down upon one of the finest reaches of the stream, just where it is ruffledby a shallow. The Gothic fabric of Sizergh hall rises out of the opposite wood, and <pb n="12"/>lofty hills encompass it at no great distance; while a neighbour-ing mill adds to the concurrence of rural beauties, with its wheel perpetually turning in view. </p>
    <p> A narrow lane conducted us back to Kendale, through the villages of Sedgewick and Natland; and the view of Kendale castle and town, backed by a rough ridge of mountains,opened finely as we descended to Watercrook. </p>
    <p> From Kendale we pursued an excellent road towards Amble-side, and passing a considerable hill, descended through a fine wild country again to the river Kent, nowbecome a mere rivu-let, and the romantic village of Stavely on its banks. we soon gained the summit of another hill; and while we took a parting view of the wild androcky vale we left behind us, from Orest head, one of the great boundaries of Kendale, a new scene opened suddenly in front, almost surpassing all that the most fertileimagination could picture. A broad sheet of water, like a great arm of the sea filled the whole of an extensive valley, and reflected a variety of tints from its glassysurface, as the surrounding objects changed in the long course of our descent. This was the great lake of Windermere. A rude unequal chain of hills rose immediately fromits borders, and increased in magnitude as it receded from the south, till a huge mass of rocky summits, piled on each other in the most fantastic forms, surrounded innorthern curve, and the still mightier mountains of Cumberland erected their majestic heads above all. We dwelt with rapture on this scene, in a descent of six miles tothe <pb n="13"/>lake, which varied its form perpetually as we seemed to approach each separate part of it, while several wooded hills rose to sight beneath us on its banks, and the manybeautiful islands it abounds with, became distinguished objects. At length we reached the margin of the lake itself, and took up our quarters at a very pleasant inn atLow-wood, on its banks. </p>
    <pb n="14"/>
    <p align="center"> CHAP. II. </p>
    <p>
      <i> Lake of Windermere-Bowness-Great Island-fine View from the Lancashire Shore-Newby Bridge-Ulverstone-Furness Abbey-Dalton-Connished Priory-Connistonmere-Hawks-head-Esthmere-Low-wood House on Windermere-Amble-side-Rydal Hall and Cascades-Rydal Water-Grassmere-Dunmail Raise-Leathes Water-Helvellyn-Vale of Leger-thwayte-granddisplay from Castle Rigg, of Skiddaw, Bassen-thwayte Lake, and the Lake of Derwentwater-Pleasing view from the Vicarage House of Keswick. </i>
    </p>
    <p> THE following morning was fine, but before we set out the day become overcast, yet the showers, though violent, gave us at invervals a tolerable opportunity of enjoying the incomparable scenes we met with in the descent of Windermere. </p>
    <p> It would be impracticable to describe minutey the infinity variety of beauties, which presented themselves as we traversed the eastern shore of this noble sheet ofwater, for twelve miles, to Newby bridge. Every turn of the road opened a new assem-blage of objects, decorating the sides and surface of the lake, the transparency ofwhose waters reflected the impending woods and mountains, and varied its appearance with every occasional gleam of sunshine. Our course lay directly southward; and everyeminence, as we turned back, displayed the vast tract of <pb n="15"/>mountains that encircle the northern end of the lake in the highest perfection. We descended through a beautiful wood to the village of Bowness, and crossed the lake ina boat, taking a slant direction of about three miles, in the course of which we passed by the great island, where Mr. Christian has built a handsome house, which commandseach extremity of the lake. We landed on the Furness shore, under a lofty rock, which I as-cended, and was astonished with the scene it displayed. The towering heght of Rydal head, among a number of inferior mountains, blocked up the northern bay, which appeared fringed with abundance of wood, feathering down to its banks in the boldestprojections, and studded with a great variety of islands of different shapes and sizes. The opposite shore advanced far into the water, and shewed the church and villageof Bowness, with several whitened houses, in the most pleasing positions, be-neath a rugged chain of cliffs; and the promontory on which I stood advancing to meet it, contractedand seemed to divide the lake. Turning to the south, a far different view met my eyes: the shores receded on each side, and formed a prodigious bason, beyond which theyadvanced again in less bold projections; and a farther expanse appeared, till a waving and wooded range of hills bounded the landscape. Every thing here bore a milderaspect; and the unruffled sheet of water seemed a noble river, passing its transparent stream through mountains mellowing down into moderate hills, while several bold projections of rock started forth from the wood cloathing their sides. </p>
    <p> I have enlarged upon this glorious scene, as it is one of the <pb n="16"/>most justly admired stations of the lake. Opposite to it is another, which Mr. Young's description tempted me to seek; but I was prevented visiting it by the weather,which drove me from the spot I have described by a thunder storm. Having regained the Westmoreland coast, we proceeded by a steep un-even track, through a rocky sort ofwide forest above the lake, as we turned to Newby bridge, where we crossed its outlet, and re-entered Lancashire. A neat little inn accommodated us with a homely, butwelcome dinner; and we crossed over some wooded hills and fine vales as we descended into a salt marsh, which led us to Ulverston in the evening. This is a tolerabletown, the capital of that tract of Lancashire called Furness, which covers the opposite extremity to Lancaster, in the great bay of Morecambe. In a retired vale, one sideof which is over-hung with wood in the most romantic form, I approached the venerable ruins of Furness abbey, once the palace of this whole territory, but now hasteningto the oblivion in which its former possessors are obscured. Still however the ivied walls and lofty arches denote somewhat its former splendour, and discover amidst therich follage from which they emerge, that others than the husbandmen and peasants, to whome they are now abandoned, have once possessed them. </p>
    <p> This abbey was founded by King Stephen before he attained the regal dignity, and flourished till the general dissolution of monasteries in the time of Henry the Eighth.The remains<pb n="17"/>shew it to have been very extensive, and the arches forming the east window, together with those of the tower, one of which is entire, are extremely lofty: most part ofanother tower at the west end is also standing, which seems of the heavy Saxon architecture, but the rest is pure Gothic. The four walls of the chapter-house are perfect,and the arches on their sides are con-structed in the most ornamented taste; when complete, it must have been a superb and very elegant piece of architecture; at presentit forms a considerable addition to one of the finest ruins in the kingdom. </p>
    <p> Like most other great peninsulas, Furness exhibits but a bleak and barren country, and its principal views are those of the sea; for its hills, though considerable, are comparatively deficient in its grandeur. After passing through Dalton, where the abbot of Furness held his court in an old building yet remaining, I visited one ofthe iron mines with which this country abounds; it seemed worked with great spirit and success, and the roads in the country are all tinged with the ore. In the eveningwe visited Connished priory the elegant seat of Mr. Bradyll, who has fitted up his house and laid out his grounds with much taste. It stands on an elevated spot above the coast under a pyramidical hill of wood, and commands an uninterrupted view over Cartmel, the sands, and the whole coast of Lancashire, in which Lancaster church andcastle are distinguished objects at a considerable distance. Conniston mere was our next object; and we continued to traverse a bleak unplea-<pb n="18"/>sant country from Ulverston, till that beautiful lake became visible at the foot of a vast range of rocky mountains. it is about six miles in legth and a mile in breadth,of nearly an oval form, and includes in its circumference all that can be deemed picturesque, in great perfection. After crossing Lowick bridge over the river Crake,which flows from it, we descended through the miserable village of Nibthwayte to its bank, and all traces of cultivation immediately vanished. A rugged forest of underwoodclothed each of its shores, through which an un-equal and dangerous track led us on a shelf immediately above the chrystal level. A lofty range of mountains, towering into one prodigious summit rose directly in front, and descended abruptly into a chain of mishapen rocks, which extended along the head of the water. All the horrors ofan inhabited world seems here collected; but the chrystal surface of the lake smiled sweetly in the midst of them, and seemed to contrast the asperity of the country. Atlength we discovered near its head two beautiful round hills, one of which glowed with the most luxuriant cultivation, while the other was covered with a coat of thethickest wood, gently undulating in several swells till it rose above our sight. Between these hills we descried the vil-lage of Conniston, whose church and cottages were charmingly dispersed about the hollow; a white house of a superior kind adorned the margin of the lake, and the ivied walls of Conniston hall peeped forth amidst a grove of tall trees. Above all, the mountains rose in all their native sublimity; a craggy pile<pb n="19"/>of rocks bounded the view abruptly, and the aspiring summit of the highest rising in a conic form, seemed the crater of some great volcano. </p>
    <p> We dwelt long upon this view, which united so happily the beautiful and sublime, and asccending a steep hill on the right, soon lost sight of Conniston lake, andregained the view of win-dermere at a considerable distance. A precipitate decent led us to Hawkshead, a village above the little lake of Esthmere, which seemed a nakedand uninteresting pool, from whence we traversed a forest of underwood, intermixed with rock, extending to the foot of the Westmoreland and Cumberland moun-tains forseveral miles, till we descended suddenly to Ambleside, and once more reached the shore of Windermere. We found ourselves here, as it were by magic, transported into a habitable country, which contrasted the desert we had left, most agreeably; and an excellent road on the banks ofthis beautiful lake, brought us back through severalcharming groves to our pleasant inn at Low-wood. A wet day confined us there altogether to the house, and I regretted not being able to get an hour or two to reviewsome part of the lake towards Bowness. </p>
    <p> On the following morning we took our leave of this enchant-ing scene, and passing through the old irregular town of Ambleside, where the mountains closed round the rapid river Rothsay, we soon reached Rydal Hall, the seat of Sir Michael le Fleming. This venerable mansion stands on a proud eminence, overhung by the lofty of Rydal,amidst the thick woods which clothe its spreading base. A great variety of rich plan-<pb n="20"/>tations encompass a swelling lawn descending into the wooded vale of Ambleside, and the whole lake of Windermere appears beautifully foreshortened in front, through agrand vista of rocks and mountains. </p>
    <p> This place is celebrated for its cascades, which deservedly attract the attention of the curious; they are formed by a moun-tain river rushing down one side of the cove into Sir Michael's ground, and were so much increased by the late wet weather that I was tempted to walk through a hard rain to visit them. The first is visiblethrough the window of an old summer-house below the mansion, and exhibis a small but picturesque water-fall, with a rough bridge on onearch most happily crossing the stream above, which rushes precipitately through a thick wood towards it The other is of a grander nature; and Sir Michael has made an excellent walk up the woodedascent that approaches it, while the torrent rattles all the way on the left below. There are two stations for the view, from the first of which you see the river tumbling violently over a prodigious ledge of rocks into the valley, and catch a distant and partial view of the higher fall above. The upper station is immediatelyunder the great fall, where it has worn a hollow between two vast cliffs, and rushes in a perpendicular yet finely broken stream of at least forty feet, into a ruggedbasing of craggy rocks, which dashes back the spray in a thick mist on the astonished specta-tor, and almost deafens him with the roar it creates. </p>
    <p> The road from hence soon began to grow mountainous, and abounded with all the spectacles peculiar to that kind of country, among which a prodigious variety of torrents,tearing their way in every direction down the hills on each side, were not the least admirable. The first ascent from the small pool of Rydal-water brought us in view ofGrassmere, a charming oval lake, with a village and church well placed on its opposite shore, behind which an almost perpendicular pyramid of rock rose to a vast height. All below was mild and tranquil, and even the surround-ing mountains participated in the placid beauty of the vale. a long ascent through a verdant hollow, formed by twoof the highest hills, brought us to the barrow of stones called Dunmail Raise, supposed to be the monument of the last kind of Cumberland. </p>
    <p> Here we entered that county; and scarcely had we lost sight of Grassmere, when the larger lake of Thirlmere, or Leathes-water appeared in front at a considerabledistance. A naked pile of grey cliffs extended on the left to its banks, while on the right the mighty Helvellyn descended in a tremendous precipice of black rocks,overhanging the road for several miles. We were too near to this prodigious mountain to discern its summit, but its base greatly overtopped the neighbouring hills; and rock piled upon rock as far as the eye could stretch, threatened destruction to the traveller below. Many of these huge fragments had al-ready escaped from the pile,and were strawed in wild disorder over the whole side of the mountain, while some had actually reached the lake, sweeping every thing before them in their course. The lake formed an irregular kind of crescent below, and a projecting rock obstrcted our view of it just where it <pb n="21"/>becomes narrow enough to be crossed by three wooden bridges; beyond which it extends again to a considerable width. an extreme point of Skiddaw closed the scene at a remote distance, and added to the dignity of the whole. We soon turned into the romantic vale of Legerthwayte, whose narrow tract of culti-vated ground, sweetly interspersedwith cottages, is hemmed in by lofty mountains, and closed in front by the high grassy hill of St. John. The small river which issues from Leatherswater, rolls throughthis pleasing valley, and we crossed it as we emerged from the inclosing hills into a spacious plain, from which we gradually mounted the eminence of Castle-rigg. A suddensweep of the road to the left brought us at once in sight of the most enchanting and astonishing landscape that ever struck upon the senses of an admiring traveller. </p>
    <p> Skiddaw, the lordly master of this extensive scene, erected high his pointed summits on the right; and sunk with many smooth and broad undulations into a plain enrichedwith the highest cultivation, and adorned with a great luxuriance of wood. Beneath his further base the broad and tranquil lake of Bassen-thwayte extended, and on theleft the glorious scenes of Der-wentwater burst upon our enraptured sight. Imagine a basin of the most transparent water, three miles in length, and near two miles wide,dotted with two circular islands covered with wood, and a third on which a large house has been lately con-structed, surround this beautiful expanse with the richestwood; behind all erect the wildest range of mountains, with <pb n="22"/>the boldest rocks the painter's imagination can furnish, and you will still fall short of the beauties which encompass the lake of Derwent. </p>
    <p> Full of wonder at this matchless scene, which continued long spread before our eyes, we descended to the neat town of Keswick, which lies between the lake and Skiddaw.Before the even-ing closed I walkedto see Mr Gray's favourite view from the vicarage house, and I found it amply deserving of the praise he has bestowed on it. On a gentleelevation at the foot of Skiddaw, it raises its simple and whitened front amidst a range of pleasing inclosures. The view from it is both grand and cheer-ful, for itlooks over the town to a full view of the lake and its islands, and fronts directly the grand opening of Borrodale, which the intervening distance, with several pleasingobjects strewed between, dismantles of ts surrounding horrors. </p>
    <pb n="24"/>
    <p align="center"> Chap. III. </p>
    <p>
      <i> Excursion to visit the Lake of Derwent-Lowdore Cascade-Bor-rodale-View from Swinside of Bassanthwayte Lake, Derwent-Water, and Foe Park-Building son the Shore andIslands-Grand Prospect from the Top of Skiddaw-Penrith-Vale of Emont-Ullswater Lake-Lynulph's Tower-return to Pen-rith-Carlisle-its Cathedral and Castle.</i>
    </p>
    <p> WE took advantage of the first fine day for our excursion to Borrodale, and from the base of Castle hill, a rock entirely covered with wood, we gained a charmingprospect of the lake. every object we had before admired at a distance, became still more beautiful as it grew distinct; the surrounding mountains increased in grandeur,and the lake itself in figure and transparency. The beautifully wooded island of St. Herbert marked its centre, and the well planted oval of Lords island, once the seatof the unhappy Derwentwater family, closed almost in with the shore under Castle hill, which was included in the park. </p>
    <p> We soon descended through a fine wood of young oaks to a high terrace above the lake, which lay like a polished mirror be-low us, and reflected the rocks that beganto project over it from the crags of Borrowside. In a steep wood, behind a small house which Mr. Pocklington has built on a beautiful eminence at Ashness, we visited aconsiderable cascade in two broken <pb n="25"/>sheets of water, to which he is making a walk in imitation of that at Rydal, but we soon approached a greater object in the famousfall of Lowdore. </p>
    <p> The Watenlath river turmbles here in a sloping and disjointed cataract of near two hundred feet, filling a prodigious aperture between two tall cliffs, finely distinguishedwith wood, and dashing its wild spray in an impetuous torrent over innumerable fragments which had been severed from the rocks above, and strewed to the margin of the lake. This cascade labours under a temporary want of water during the summer months, but the rains that had lately fallen amply supplied that deficiency. We had now reached the head of the lake, and pursued the Derwent gliding through some bbeautiful inclosures, while the mountains closed in upon us, and the scenery grew gradually wilder.The first ascent from the little village of Grange brought us sin sight of the grand pass of Borrodale, the centre of which seemed choked up by a huge rocky pyramid, withwhich two craggy mountains projecting from each side appeared almost incorporated.-It looked like an entrance to the infernal regions, and the daemon of desolation mightfix his empire here unrivalled to amidst the wreck of an universe. A vast black rock ascending to the skies frowned over us in silent horror on the right, and a lofty barrier of impending cliffs lifted high their embattled heads on the left, sharpened into a thousand points, and whit-ened with perpetual storms. Immense fragments fromthis mighty rampar had fallen to the vale, and numberless signs of the devastation they had occasioned were still apparent. One<pb n="26"/> of them, which bears the name of the Bowdar stone, of an enormous size and weight, rather a mountain itself than a rock, lay like a huge ship upon its keel, andseemed every moment threat-ening to overwhelm the river, and fill the vale below. Beneath us the Derwent rolled his silver stream, and rattled over the rocky beach as hecircled round the woods which filled the hollow. </p>
    <p> A far different scene opened as soon as we had gained the highest ascent. In front the mighty mountain of Glenamara, with various others, as uncouth and horrible intheir figures as their names, formed a grand amphitheatre, beneath which the small but highly cultivated vale of Rothwayte was visible, and a range of the most smilingwoods and pastures, divided by the meander-ing Derwent, shewed us a second Eden in the midst of the sur-rounding chaos. We passed, through the little village which givesits name to the valley, to the spot where the road divides in front of the chapel at the foot of Glenamara, which is ge-nerally the utmost extent of the traveller's progress. The right hand way ascends to some lead mines on the hills, and the left pursues a dangerous and almost impervious track beneath the lofty rock called the Eaglecrag, and over a mountain named the Stake of Borrodale, into Westmorland. We followed it no further, but satisfied with the wonders he had seen, repassed them withpleasure in our return. The prospect on our coming forth from this gloomy region was beyond measure striking. In front of the lake, which glowed like burnished gold, Skid-daw displayed his verdant head and sides, finely illuminated by<pb n="27"/>the evening sun marking each furrow distinctly, and all before us was light, cheerful, and habitable, as if we had emerged from the regions of eternal night into day.Nothing can be stronger than this contrast, and West, in his Tour of the Lakes, happily resembles Skiddaw to "a gentle generous lord smiling over the "land he governs,while the Fells of Borrodale frown on it like "a hardened tyrant." The opposite shore of this charming lake, though rather inferior to that which I had traversed, is byno means deficient in its peculiar beauties. The road being too rugged for a carriage, I was obliged to mount my horse, and after crossing the Derwent, ascended theheathy hill of Swin-side, where I was recompensed for my arduous ascent by a noble prospect. </p>
    <p>This view stretched on one side over the whole oblong ex-panse of Bassenthwayte water, as it lay extended along the base of Skiddaw, calm and unruffled, with a longtract of cultivation along its banks, and several ahndsome houses near its head. The more animated scene of Derwent lay in front, adn behind it, in a broad gap betweenthe mountains, the placid vale of Newlands opened a truly pastoral landscape, full of small inclo-sures and corn-fields, and enlivened with many whitened cot-tages. Thewoods of Foe park, covering an eminence before us, concealed the town of Keswick, through a part of which I passed to a whimsical house, or rather a chain of single rooms,which Lord William Gordon has built on the bank of the lake. The architecture indeed, both of this house and Mr. Pocklington's numerous buildings, is not much to be approved, and in the<pb n="28"/>latter the pert appearance of a tall house, full of small Venetian windows, suit but ill with the grandeur and simplicity of the surrounding country, and seems bettercalculated for the meri-dian of five miles round the metropolis. Both these gentlemen, however, deserv&eacute; ample praise for the spirit of improvement they have introducedinto the country, and Lord william Gor-don in particular is now employed about a noble road, carried for a considerable extent on a raised terrace above the lake, which views with the magnificence of a Roman work; and when finished, will present a scene almost rivalling the beauties of the opposite shore. I traced it for some distanceas far as it was opposite shore. I traced it for some distance as far as it was passable, and had a more complete view than I could before gain of the whole lake withits islands immediately below me, while the close-impending cliffs of Barrowside made a bold finish to the opposite view, and Skiddaw on the left closed up the am-phitheatre. I could not leave Keswick without making an at-tempt to scale the top of that mighty hill; but though I gained the summit, after a long and laboriousascent of five miles, the clouds collecting all around, prevented my enjoying the ample prospect it affords, and soon enveloped the whole in obscurity. The two lakes,however, were still distinct and beautiful ob-jects, and the chaos of mountains around Borrodale hung their diminished heads far below, while the craggy top of Helvellynalone presumed to equal the height on which I stood. In a clear day, I am told the Isle of Man is visible from hence, and the coast of Scotland with the Galloway mountainsmay be ob-served towards Port Patrick, where the Irish shore advances to<pb n="29"/>meet it; while on the right the Northumbrian hills of Cheviot rise boldly in view. For my part I could only discern the Sol-way Frith, dividing England and Scotland, andsome blue hills on the Scotch side, when the advancing storm drove me from my position, and I was gad to avoid its fury by a precipitate descent. </p>
    <p> At length we left Keswick, highly satisfied with the wonders and beauties that nature has embellished it with, and passing through the fertile vale of Saint John,soon reached an open country, over which we proceeded to Penrith. The opposite hills of Westmorlands were finely llluminated by the evening sun as we descended to thetown, and the bold ruin of Brough-am castle directly fronted us. Penrith is a handsome well-built town, and has an air of opulence and gentility which dif-fers much fromthe places we had left. We entered the town by the walls of its castle, which stands directly above it, and would be a handsome ruin, were it not for the red stone where-with all the buildings in this part of the country are construct-ed, which gives it the appearance of a coarse brick. It stands in a pleasant and well-wooded country, watered by the river Emont, which takes its course hither from Ullswater. </p>
    <p> To this last remaining lake we now bent our course through the pleasant and shady vale of Emont, and almost on the banks of the river, passing by Dalmain, a large oldseat of Mr. Hazell, and winding round the singular conic hill of Dunmallet, which is covered with its plantations, and projects into the head of the lake. Ullswater, being nine miles in length, is next in size to<pb n="30"/>Windermere, and units in some measure the cultivated beau-ties of that lake with the sublimity of Derwentwater; though I think it falls short of the peculiar characterof each. Its most striking distinction is in the boldness of its two great turns, where the protruding mountains seem to have altered its natural course, and divided itinto three grand reaches. The first of these is somewhat more than three miles in length, and near a mile wide; at the extremity of which the bold projection of PlaceFell presents itself, nearly opposite to some pleasing in-closures about Watermillock, and old seat of Mr. Robinson. </p>
    <p> Hitherto the country appeared rather tame in comparison with that we had left, and the hills seems deficient in grandeur; but the inclosures crept sweetly up the sidesof them, where they were interspersed agreeably with farm houses and wood, and the broad bosom of the lake entirely filled the vally. It turned al-most in a right anglefrom Place Fell, and for a time grew somewhat narrower; but as soon as we entered the fine wild tract of Gowborow park it expanded again, and after another long reachmade a second curve to the left, at the foot of the ridge of moun-tains which forms the base of Helvellyn. Just at this turn the Duke of Norfolk has erected a Gothic building, to which he has given the name of Lynulph's Tower. It stands considerably above the lake, in the midst of the wild romantic scenery of Goborow park, and withinis parcelled out into a vast number of indifferent and ill-furnished apartments. The prospect it commands, however, is beyond measure striking. A circular hill of heathmixed with rock, rises on the opposite shore, which grows<pb n="31"/>apparently bolder, till it ends in a high promontory of grey cliffs at the turn of the lake; the mountains press forward on the other side, with their hollows charmingly variegated with wood and rock; and a cltivated tract still decorates the level that ex-tends below them towards Paterdale, where a few whitened cot-tages just shew their heads at the extremity of the view. The bold and waving sweep of the lake itself forms the finest feature in the landscape, while two rocky islands distinguish the levelwhere it begins to contract, and the mishapen heads of the great cluster of mountains behind, give a grand finish to the whole. I cannot do justice to this scene, orindeed to the particular beau-ties of llswater, as we were favoured with but few gleams of sunshine in our view of it, and the showers gae but little in-termission. Theygrew incessant before we quitted Lynulph's tower; so we proceeded no further, but turning back, took refuge at a little inn at Pooley bridge, beneath the foot of Dun-mallet,from whence we returned to Penrith. </p>
    <p> We had now entirely left the regions of romance; and hav-ing passed the view which Penrith beacon commands, we tra-versed a range of dreary and heathy downs till wecame within sight of Carlisle. Beyond it we discovered the blue hills of Scotland; and the Solway Frith appeared as if raised above the fenny tract of its moss whichsurrounds it. One bold hill to-wards the sea distinguished itself in the midst of the level, which scemed to extend from the water to the very foot of Skiddaw, whosepointed head now began to exalt itself in sight, and appear as the last link of a prodigious chain of mountains. The <pb n="32"/>road grew very indifferent as we approached Carlisle, the south gate of which led us into a handsome street; it has also two others nearly as good, leading to the Irishand Scotch gates. Were the passes to each of these, where they meet in the centre of the town, enlarged, and an area formed there, with a new county hall, which is muchwanted, few cities would make a neater appearance. It is walled entirely round; and its castle fronts the north, on an eminence above the river Eden, to defend the cityagainst any attack from its restless neighbours, the Scotch. Being now useless, little remains except the gate-way, and a ruined tower, in which Mary Queen of Scots was confined; yet the idle parade of a warden, and a few cannon mounted on the walls, is still kept up. Of the cathedral, the choir alone remains entire, which has been latelyvery well fitted up; and the old oak stalls, after the manner of those of York, are judiciously preserved. It is all built of a mouldering red stone; the choir and theeast window being of light Gothic, and just enough remaining of the great aile to show it was of very heavy Saxon. It formerly extended to a great length, and was oulleddown by Cromwell, at the time of the rebellion, to make a barrack. This being the frontier town of England, it has be-come the resort of several genteel families, whose houses make a respectable appearance. </p>
  </chap>
</text>
