<text id="1822_a">
<gap desc="Map of Westmorland, Cumbria, Lancashire"/>
<gap desc="folded map, Lancaster"/>
<gap desc="Map of Westmorland, Cumbria, Lancashire"/>
<gap desc="front matter, not digitised"/>
<chap title="Contents">
<pb n="iii"/>
<head level="1" align="center">CONTENTS.</head>
<gap desc="double line"/>
<head level="2" align="center">SECTION FIRST.</head>
<head level="3" align="center">VIEW OF THE COUNTRY AS FORMED BY NATURE.</head>
<p>Vales running up to a common Centre. --Effect of light and Shadow as dependant upon the Position of the Vales. --Mountains, --their Substance, --Surfaces, --and Colours. --Winter Colouring. --The Vales, --Lakes, --Islands, --Tarns, --Woods, --Rivers, --Climate.</p>
<p align="right"><i>Page</i> 1</p>
<head level="2" align="center">SECTION SECOND.</head>
<head level="3" align="center">FACE OF THE COUNTRY AS AFFECTED BY ITS SUCCESSIVE INHABITANTS.</head>
<p>Retrospect. --Primitive Aspect. --Roman and British Antiquities. --Feudal Tenantry, --their Habitations and Enclosures. --Tenantry reduced in Number by the Union of the Two Crowns. --State of Society after that Event. --Cottages, --Bridges, --Places of Worship, --Parks and Mansions, --General Picture of Society.</p>
<p align="right">37</p>
<pb n="iv"/>
<head level="2" align="center">SECTION THIRD.</head>
<head level="3" align="center">CHANGES, AND RULES OF TASTE FOR PREVENTING THEIR BAD EFFECTS.</head>
<p>Tourists. --New Settlers. --The Country disfigured. --Cause of false Taste in Grounds and Buildings. --Ancient Models recommended. --Houses. --Colouring of Buildings. --Grounds and Plantations. --The Larch. --Planting. --Further Changes probable. --Conclusion.</p>
<p align="right"><i>Page</i> 65</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="2" align="center">MISCELLANEOUS OBSERVATIONS.</head>
<p>Time for visiting the Country. --Order in which Objects should be approached. --Views from the Heights. --Comparisons, how injurious. --Alpine Scenes compared with Cumbrian, &#38;c. --Phenomena. --Ascent to the Top of Scawfell.</p>
<p align="right">102</p>
<gap desc="line"/>
<head level="3" align="center">DIRECTIONS AND INFORMATION TO THE TOURIST</head>
<p>Windermere. --Coniston. --Donnerdale. --Eskdale. --Wastdale. --Ennerdale. --The Vale of Keswick. --Buttermere. --Ullswater, with its tributary Streams. --Haweswater.</p>
<p align="right">137</p>
</chap>
<chap title="SECTION FIRST">
<head level="2" align="center">DESCRIPTION</head>
<head level="3" align="center">OF THE</head>
<head level="1" align="center">SCENERY OF THE LAKES.</head>
<gap desc="double line"/>
<head level="2" align="center">SECTION FIRST.</head>
<head level="3" align="center">VIEW OF THE COUNTRY AS FORMED BY NATURE.</head>
<p>At Lucerne, in Switzerland, is shewn a Model of the Alpine country which encompasses the Lake of the four Cantons. The spectator ascends a little platform, and sees mountains, lakes, glaciers, rivers, woods, waterfalls, and vallies, with their cottages, and every other object contained in them, lying at his feet; all things being represented in their appropriate colours. It may be easily conceived that this exhibition affords an exquisite delight to the imagination, tempting it to wander at will from valley to valley, from mountain to mountain, through the deepest recesses of the Alps. But it supplies <pb n="2"/> also a more substantial pleasure: for the sublime and beautiful region, with all its hidden treasures, and their bearings and relations to each other, is thereby comprehended and understood at once.</p>
<p>Something of this kind, without touching upon minute details and individualities which would only confuse and embarrass, will here be attempted, in respect to the Lakes in the north of England, and the vales and mountains enclosing and surrounding them. The delineation, if tolerably executed, will, in some instances, communicate to the traveller, who has already seen the objects, new information; and will assist in giving to his recollections a more orderly arrangement than this own opportunities may have permitted him to make; while it will be still more useful to the future traveller, by directing his attention at once to distinctions in things which, without such previous aid, a length of time only could enable him to discover. It is hoped, also, that this Essay might become generally serviceable, by leading to habits of more exact and considerate observation than, as far as the writer <pb n="3"/> knows, have hitherto been applied to local scenery.</p>
<p>To begin, then, with the main outlines of the country; --I know not how to give the reader a distinct image of these more readily, than by requesting him to place himself with me, in imagination, upon some given point; let it be the top of either the mountains, Great Gavel, or Scawfell; or, rather, let us suppose our station to be a cloud hanging midway between those two mountains, at not more than half a mile's distance from the summit of each, and not many yards above their highest elevation; we shall then see stretched at our feet a number of vallies, not fewer than eight, diverging from the point, on which we are supposed to stand, like spokes from the nave of a wheel. First, we note, lying to the south-east, the vale of Langdale<ptr target="n1"/>, which will conduct the eye to the eye to the long lake of Winandermeres stretched nearly to the sea; or rather to the sands of the vast bay <pb n="4"/>  of Morcamb, serving here for the rim of this imaginary wheel; --let us trace it in a direction from the south-east towards the south, and we shall next fix our eyes upon the vale of Coniston, running up likewise from the sea, but not (as all the other vallies do) to the nave of the wheel, and therefore it may be not inaptly represented as a broken spoke sticking in the rim. Looking forth again, with an inclination towards the west, immediately at our feet lies the vale of Duddon, in which is no lake, but a copious stream winding among fields, rocks, and mountains, and terminating its course in the sands of Duddon. The fourth vale, next to be observed, viz. that of the Esk, is of the same general character as the last, yet beautifully discriminated from it by peculiar features. Its stream passes under the woody steep upon which stands Muncaster Castle, the ancient seat of the Penningtons, and after forming a short and narrow &#230;stuary enters the sea below the little town of Ravenglass. Next, almost due west, look down into, and along the deep valley of Wastdale, with its little chapel and half a dozen neat dwellings scattered upon a plain of <pb n="5"/> meadow and corn-ground intersected with stone walls apparently innumerable, like a large piece of lawless patch-work, or an array of mathematical figures, such as in the ancient schools of geometry might have been sportivley and fantastically traved out upon sand. Beyond this little fertile plain lies, within its bed of steep mountains, the long, narrow, stern, and desolate Lake of Wastdale; and, beyond this, a dusky tract of level ground conducts the eye to the Irish Sea. The stream that issues from Wast-water is named the Irt, and falls into the &#230;stuary of the river Esk. Next comes in view Ennerdale, with its lake of bold and somewhat savage shores. Its stream, the Ehen or Enna, flowing through a soft and fertile country, passes the town of Egremont --and the ruins of the castle, then, seeming, like the other rivers, to break through the barrier of sand thrown up by the winds on this tempestuous coast, enters the Irish Sea. The vale of Buttermere, with the lake and village of that name, and Crummock-water, beyond, next present themselves. We will follow the main stream, the Cocker, through the fertile and beautiful vale of Lorton, till it is lost in the <pb n="6"/> Derwent, below the noble ruins of Cockermouth Castle. Lastly, Borrowdale, of which the vale of Keswick is only a continuation, stretching due north, brings us to a point nearly opposite to the vale of Winandermere with which we began. From this it will appear, that the image of a wheel, thus far exact, is little more than one half complete; but the deficiency on the eastern side may be supplied by the vales of Wytheburn, Ulswater, Hawswater, and the vale of Grasmere and Rydal; none of these, however, run up to the central point between Great Gavel and Scawfell. From this, hitherto our central point, take a flight of not more than three or four miles eastward to the ridge of Hellvellyn, and you will look down upon Wytheburn and St. John's Vale, which are a branch of the vale of Keswick; upon Ulswater, stretching due east, and not far beyond to the south-east, (though from this point not visible,) lie the vale and lake of Hawswater; and lastly, the vale of Grasmere, Rydal, and Ambleside, brings you back to Winandermere, thus completing, though on the eastern side in a somewhat irregular manner, the representative figure of the wheel.</p>
<note id="n1">Anciently spelt Langden, and so called by the old inhabitants to this day -- <i>dead</i>, from which the latter part of the word is derived, being in many parts of England a name for a valley.</note><!-- this note crosses a page break -->
<pb n="7"/>
<p>Such, concisely given, is the general topographical view of the country of the Lakes in the north of England; and it may be observed, that, from the circumference to the centre, that is, from the sea or plain country to the mountain stations specified, there is --in the several ridges that enclose these vales and divide them from each other, I mean in the forms and surfaces, first of the swelling grounds, next of the hills and rocks, and lastly of the mountains --an ascent of almost regular gradation from elegance and richness to the highest point of grandeur and sublimity. It follows therefore from this, first, that these rocks, hills, and mountains, must present themselves to view in stages rising above each other, the mountains clustering together towards the central point; and, next, that an observer familiar with the several vales, must from their various position in relation to sub, have had before his eys every possible embelishment of beauty, dignity, and splendour, which light and shadow can bestow on objects so diversified. For example, in the vale of Winandermere, if the spectator looks for gentle and lovely scenes, his eye is turned towards the <pb n="8"/> south; if for the grand, towards the north; in the vale of Keswick, which (as hath been said) lies almost due north of this, it is directly the reverse. Hence, when the sun is setting in summar far to the north-west, it is seen by the spectator from the shores or breast of Winandermere, resting among the summits of the loftiest mountains, some of which will perhaps be half or wholly hidden by clouds, or by the blaze of light which will perhaps be half or wholly hidden by clouds, or by the blaze of light which the orb diffuses around it; and the surface of the lake will reflect before the eye the correspondent colours through every variety of beauty, and through all degrees of splendour. In the vale of Keswick, at the same period, the sun sets over the humbler regions of the landscape, and showers down upon <i>them</i> the radiance which at once veils and glorifies, --sending forth, meanwhile, broad streams of rosy, crimson, purple, or golden light, towards the grand mountains in the south and south-east, which, thus illuminated, with all their projections and cavities, and with an intermixture of solemn shadows, are seen distinctly through a cool and clear atmosphere. Of course, there is as marked a difference between the <i>noontide</i> appearance of these two <pb n="9"/> opposite vales. The bedimming haze that overspreads the south, and the clear atmosphere and determined shadows of the clouds in the north, at the same time of the day, are each seen in these several vales, with a contrast as striking. The reader will easily conceive in what degree the intermediate vales partake of the same variety.</p>
<p>I do not indeed know any tract of country in which, within so narrow a compass, may be found an equal variety in the influences of light and shadow upon the sublime or beautiful features of landscape; and it is owing to the combined circumstances to which I have directed the readers attention. From a point between Great Gavel and Scawfell, a shepherd would not require more than an hour to descend into any one of eight of the principal vales by which he would be surrounded; and all the others lie (with the exception of Hawswater) at but a small distance. Yet, though clustered together, every valley has its distinct and separate character; in some instances, as if they had been formed in studied contrast to each other, and in others with the united pleasing differences and resemblances <pb n="10"/> of a sisterly rivalship. This concentration of interest gives to the country a decided superiority over the most attractive districts of Scotland and Wales, especially for the pedestrian traveller.  In Scotland and Wales are found, undoubtedly, individual scenes, which, in there several kinds, cannot be excelled. But, in Scotland, particularly, what long tracts of desolate country intervene! so that the traveller, when he reaches a spot deservedly of great celebrity, would find it difficult to determine how much of his pleasure is owing to excellence inherent in the landscape itself; and how much to an instantaneous recovery from an oppression left upon his spirits by the barrenness and desolation through which he has passed.</p>
<p>But, to proceed with our survey; --and, first, of the MOUNTAINS. Their <i>forms</i> are endlessly diversified, sweeping easily or boldly in simple majesty, abrupt and precipitous, or soft and elegant. In magnitude and grandeur they are individually inferior to the most celebrated of those in some other parts of the island; but, in the combinations which they make, towering above each other, or lifting themselves in ridges <pb n="11"/> like waves of a tumultuous sea, and in the beauty and variety of their surfaces and colours, they are surpassed by none.</p>
<p>The general <i>surface</i> of the mountains is turf, rendered rich and green by the moisture of the climate. Sometimes the turf, as in the neighbourhood of Newlands, is little broken, the whole covering being soft and downy pasturage. In other places rocks predominate; the soil is laid bare by torrents and burstings of water from the sides of the mountains in heavy rains; and not unfrequently their perpendicular sides are seamed by ravines (formed also by rains and torrents) which, meeting in angular points, entrench and scar the surface with numerous figures like the letters W and Y.</p>
<p>The MOUNTAINS are composed of the stone by mineralogists termed schist, which, as you approach the plain country, gives places to limestone and free-stone; but schist being the substance of the mountains, the predominant <i>colour</i> of their <i>rocky</i> parts is bluish, or hoary gray --the general tint of the lichens with which the bare stone is encrusted. With this blue or grey <pb n="12"/> colour is frequently intermixed a red tinge, proceeding from the iron that interveins the stone, and impregnates the soil. The iron is the principle of decomposition in these rocks; and hence, when they become pulverized, the elementary particles crumbling down overspread in many places the steep and almost precipitous sides of the mountains with an intermixture of colours, like the compound hues of a dove's neck. When, in the heat of advancing summer, the fresh green tint of herbage has somewhat faded, it is again revived by the appearance of the fern profusely spread over the same ground; and, upon this plant, more than upon any thing else, do the changes which the seasons make in the colouring of the mountains depend. About the first week in October, the rich green, which prevailed through the whole summer, is usually passed away. The brilliant and various colours of the fern are then in harmony with the autumnal woods; bright yellow or lemon colour, at the base of the mountains, melting gradually, through orange, to a dark russet brown towards the summits, where the plant, being more exposed to the <pb n="13"/> weather, is in a more advanced state of decay. Neither heath nor furze are <i>generally</i> found upon the <i>sides</i> of these mountains, though in some places they are richly adorned by them. We may add, that the mountains are of height sufficient to have the surface towards the summits softened by distance, and to imbibe the finest a&#235;rial hues. In common also with other mountains, their apparent forms and colours are perpetually changed by the clouds and vapours which float around them: the effect indeed of mist or haze, in a country of this character, is like that of magic. I have seen six or seven ridges rising above each other, all created in a moment by the vapours upon the side of a mountain, which, in its ordinary appearance, showed not a projecting point to furnish even a hint for such an operation.</p>
<p>I will take this opportunity of observing, that they, who have studies the appearances of nature, feel that the superiority, in point of visual interest, of mountainous over other countries --is more strikingly displayed in winter than in summer. This, as must be obvious, is partly owning to the <i>forms</i> of the <pb n="14"/> mountains, which, of course, are not affected by the seasons; but also, in no small degree, to the greater variety that exists in their winter than in their summer <i>colouring.</i> This variety is such, and so harmoniously preserved, that is leaves little cause of regret when the splendour of autumn is passed away. The oak-coppices, upon the sides of the mountains, retain russet leaves; the birch stands conspicuous with its silver stem and puce-coloured twigs; the hollies, with green leaves and scarlet berries, have come forth to view from among the deciduous trees, whose summer foliage had concealed them; the ivy is now plentifully apparent upon the stems and boughs of the trees, and upon the steep rocks. In place of the deep summer-green of the herbage and fern, many rich colours play into each other over the surface of the mountains; turf (the tints of which are interchangeably tawny-green, olive, and brown,) beds of withered fern, and grey rocks, being harmoniously blended together. The mosses and lichens are never so fresh and flourishing as in winter, if it be not a season of frost; and their minute beauties <pb n="15"/> prodigally adorn the fore-ground. Wherever we turn, we find these productions of nature, to which winter is rather favourable than unkindly, scattered over the walls, banks of earth, rocks, and stones, and upon the trunks of trees, with the intermixture of several species of small fern, now green and fresh; and, to the observing passenger, their forms and colours are a source of inexhaustible admiration. Add to this the hoar-frost and snow, with all the varieties they create, and which volumes would not be sufficient to describe. I will content myself with one instance of the colouring produced by snow, which may not be uninteresting to painters. It is extracted from the memorandum-book of a friend; and for its accuracy I can speak, having been an eye-witness of the appearance. "I observed," says he, "the beautiful effect of the drifted snow upon the mountains, and the perfect <i>tone</i> of colour. From the top of the mountains downwards a rich olive was produced by the powdery snow and the grass, which olive was warmed with a little brown, and in this way harmoniously combined, by insensible goodness, with the white. <pb n="16"/> The drifting took away the monotony of snow; and the whole of Grasmere, seen from the terrace walk in Easedale, was as varied, perhaps more so, than even in the pomp of autumn. In the distance was Loughrigg-Fell, the basin-wall of the lake: this, from the summit downward, was a rich orange-olive; then the lake of a bright olive-green, nearly the same tint as the snow-powdered mountain tops and high slopes in Easedale; and lastly, the church with its firs forming the centre of the view. Next to the church came nine distinguishable hills, six of them with woody sides turned towards us, all of them oak-copses with their bright red leaves and snow-powdered twigs; these hills --so variously situated in relation to each other, and to the view in general, so variously powdered, some only enough to give the herbage a rich brown tint, one intensely white and lighting up all the others --were yet so placed, as in the most inobtrusive manner to harmonise by contrast with a perfect naked, snowless bleak summit in the far distance."</p>
<p>Having spoken of the forms, surface, and colour of the mountains, let us descend into the <pb n="17"/> VALES. Though these have been represented under the general image of the spokes of a wheel, they are, for the most part, winding; the windings of many being abrupt and intricate. And, it may be observed, that in one circumstance, the general shape of them all has been determined by that primitive conformation through which so many became receptacles of lakes. For they are not formed, as are most of the celebrated Welsh vallies, by an approximation of the sloping bases of the opposite mountains towards each other, leaving little more between than a channel for the passage of a hasty river; but the bottom of these vallies is, for the most part, a spacious and gently declining area, apparently level as the floor of a temple, or the surface of a lake, and beautifully broken, in many cases, by rocks and hills, which rise up like islands from the plain. In such of the vallies as make many windings, these level areas open upon the traveller in succession, divided from each other sometimes by a mutual approximation of the hills, leaving only passage for a river, sometimes by correspondent windings, without such approximation; and sometimes <pb n="18"/> by a bold advance of one mountain toward that which is opposite to it. It may here be observed with propriety, that the several rocks and hills, which have been described as rising up like islands from the level area of the vale, have regulated the choice of the inhabitants in the situation of their dwellings. Where none of these are found, and the inclination of the ground is not sufficiently rapid easily to carry off the waters, (as in the higher part of Langdale, for instance,) the houses are not sprinkled over the middle part of the vales, but confined to their sides, being placed merely so far up the mountain as to be protected from the floods. But where these rocks and hills have been scattered over the plain of the vale, (as in Grasmere, Donnerdale, Eskdale, &#38;c.) the beauty which they give to the scene is much heightened by a single cottage, or cluster of cottages, that will be almost always found under them, or upon their sides; dryness and shelter having tempted the Dalesmen to fix their inhabitations there.</p>
<p>I shall now speak of the LAKES of this country. The form of the lake is most perfect when, like Derwent-water and some of the <pb n="19"/> smaller lakes, it least resembles that of a river; --I mean, when being looked at from any given point where the whole may be seen at once, the width of it bears such proportion to the length, that, however the outline may be diversified by far-receding bays, it never assumes the shape of a river, and is contemplated with that placid and quiet feeling which belongs peculiarly to the lake --as a body of still water udner the influence of no current; reflecting therefore the clouds, the light, and all the imagery of the sky and surrounding hills; expressing also and making visible changes of the atmosphere, and motions of the lightest breeze, and subject to agitation only from the winds --</p>
<poem>
<line>--The visible scene</line>
<line>Would enter unawares into his mind</line>
<line>With all its solemn imagery, its rocks,</line>
<line>Its woods, and that uncertain heaven received</line>
<line>Into the bosom of the <i>steady</i> lake!</line>
</poem>
<p>It must be noticed, as a favourable characteristic of the lakes of this country, that, though several of the largest, such as Winandermere, Ulswater, Hawswater, do, when the whole lenght of them is commanded from an elevated <pb n="20"/> point, lose somewhat of the peculiar form fo the lake, and assume the resemblance of a magnificent river; yet, as their shape is winding, (particularly that of Ulswater and Hawswater) when the view of the whole is obstructed by those barriers which determine the windings, and the spectator is confined to one reach, the appropriate feeling is revived; and one lake may thus in succession present to the eye the essential characteristic of many. But, though the forms of the large lakes have this advantage, it is nevertheless a circumstance favourable to the beauty of the country, that the largest of them are comparatively small; and that the same valley generally furnishes a succession of lakes, instead of being filled with one. The vallies in North Wales, as hath been observed, are not formed for the reception of lakes; those of Switzerland, Scotland, and this part of the North of England, are so formed; but, in Switzerland and Scotland, the proportion of diffused water is often too great, as at the lake of Geneva for instance, and in most of the Scotch lakes. No doubt it sounds magnificent and flatters the imagination, to hear at distance of expanses of <pb n="21"/> water so many leagues in length and miles in width; and such ample room may be delightful to the fresh-water sailor, scudding with a lively breeze amid the rapidly-shifting scenery. But, who ever travelled along the banks of Loch-Lomond, variegated as the lower part is by islands, without feeling that a speedier termination of the long vista of blank water would be acceptable; and without wishing for an interposition of green meadows, tress, and cottages, and a sparkling stream to run by his side? In fact, a notion of grandeur, as connected with magnitude, has seduced persons of taste into a general mistake upon this subject. It is much more desirable, for the purposes of pleasure, that lakes should be numerous, and small or middle-sized, than large, not only for commmunication by walks and rides, but for variety, and for recurrence of similar appearances. To illustrate this by one instance: --how pleasing is it to have a ready and frequent opportunity of watching, at the outlet of a lake, the stream pushing its way among the rocks in lively contrast with the stillness from which it has escaped; and how amusing to compare its <pb n="22"/> noisy and turbulent motions with the gentle playfulness of the breezes, that may be starting up or wandered here and there over the faintly-rippled surface of the broad water! I may add, as a general remark, that, in lakes of great width, the shores cannot be distinctly seen at the same time, and therefore contribute little to mutual illustration and ornament; and, if the opposite shores are out of sight of each other, like those of the American and Asiatic lakes, then unfortunately the traveller is reminded of a nobler object; he has the blankness of a sea-prospect without the grandeur and accompanying sense of power.</p>
<p>As the comparatively small size of the lakes in the North of England is favourable to the production of variegated landscape, their <i>boundary-line</i> also is for the most part gracefully or boldly indented. That uniformity, which prevails in the primitive frame of the lower grounds among all chains or clusters of mountains where large bodies of still water are bedded, is broken by the <i>secondary</i> agents of nature, ever at work to supply the deficiencies of the mould in which things were originally cast. Using the word <pb n="23"/> <i>deficiencies</i>, I do not speak with reference to those stronger emotions which a region of mountains is peculiarly fitted to excite. The bases of those huge barriers may run for a long space in straight lines, and these parallel to each other; the opposite sides of a profound vale may ascend as exact counter-parts or in mutual reflection like the billows of a troubled sea; and the impression be, from its very simplicity, more awful and sublime. Sublimity is the result of Nature's first great dealings with the superficies of the earth; but the general tendency of her subsequent operations is towards the production of beauty, by a multiplicity of symmetrical parts uniting in a consistent whole. This is every where exemplified along the margin of these lakes. Masses of rock, that have been precipitated from the heights into the area of waters, lie frequently like stranded ships; or have acquired the compact structure of jutting piers; or project in little peninsulas crested with native wood. The smallest rivulet --one whoe silent influx is scarcely noticeable in a season of dry weather --so faint is the dimple made by it on the surface of the smooth lake -- <pb n="24"/> will be found to have been not useless in the shaping, by its deposits of gravel and soil in time of flood, a curve that would not otherwise have existed. But the more powerful brooks, encroaching upon the level of the lake, have, in course of time, given birth to ample promontories of sweeping outline that constracts boldly with the longitudinal base of the steeps on the opposite shore; while their flat or gently-sloping surfaces never fail to introduce, into the midst of desolation and barrenness, the elements of fertility, even where the habitations of men may not have been raised. These alluvial promontories, however, threathen, in some places, to bisect the waters which the have long adorned; and, in course of ages, they will cause some of the lakes to dwindle into numerous and insignificant pools; which, in their turn, will finally be filled up. But, checking these intrusive calculations, let us rather be content with appearances as they are, and pursue in imagination the meandering shores, whether rugged steeps, admitting no cultivation, descend into the water; or gently-sloping lawns and rich woods, or flat and fertile meadows stretch between the margin <pb n="25"/> of the lake and the mountains. Among minuter recommendations will be noted with pleasure the curved rim of fine blue gravel thrown up by the waves, especially in bays exposed to the setting-in of strong winds; and, bordering the lake, groves, if I may so call them, of reeds and bulrushes; or plots of water-lilies lifting their large target-shaped leaves to the breeze, while the white flower is heaving upon the wave.</p>
<p>The ISLANDS are neither so numerous nor so beautiful as might be expected from the account that has been given of the manner in which the level areas of the vales are so frequently diversified by rocks, hills, and hillocks, scattered over them; nor are they ornamented, as are several islands by the lakes in Scotland and Ireland, by the remains of old castles or other places of defence, or of monastic edifices. Those upon Derwent-water are neither fortunately placed nor of pleasing shape; but if the wood upon them were managed with more taste, they might become interesting features in the landscape. There is a beautiful cluster of islands on Winandermere; a pair pleasingly contrasted <pb n="26"/> upon Rydal; nor must the solitary green island in Grasmere be forgotten. In the bosom of each of the lakes of Ennerdale and Devock-water is a single rock which, owing to its neighbourhood to the sea, is -- </p>
<p align="center">"The haunt of cormorants and sea-mews' clang,"</p>
<p>a music well suited to the stern and wild character of the several scenes!</p>
<p>This part of the subject may be concluded with observing --that, from the multitude of brooks and torrents that fall into these lakes, and of internal springs by which they are fed, and which circulate through them like veins, they are truly living lakes, "<i>vivi lacus;</i>" and are thus discriminated from the stagnant and sullen pools frequent among mountains that have been formed by volcanoes, and from the shallow meres found in flat and fenny countries. The water is also pure and crystalline; so that, if it were not for the reflections of the incumbent mountains by which it is darkened, a delusion might be felt, by a person resting quietly in a boat on the bosom of Winandermere or Derwent-water similar to that which <pb n="27"/> Carver so beautifully describes when he was floating alone in the middle of the lake Erie or Ontario, and could almost have imagined that his boat was suspended in an element as pure as air, or rather that the air and water were one.</p>
<p>Having spoken of Lakes I must not omit to mention, as a kindred feature of this country, those bodies of still water called TARNS. These are found in some of the vallies, and are numerous upon the mountains. A Tarn, in a <i>Vale,</i> implies, for the most part, that the bed of the vale is not happily formed; that the water of the brooks can neither wholly escape, nor diffuse itself over a large area. Accordingly, in such situations, Tarns are often surrounded by an unsightly tract of boggy ground; but this is not always the case, and in the cultivated parts of the country, when the shores of the Tarn are determined, it differs only from the Lake in being smaller, and in belonging mostly to a smaller valley, or circular recess. Of this class of miniature lakes Loughrigg Tarn, near Grasmere, is the most beautiful example. It has a margin of green firm meadows, of rocks, and <pb n="28"/> rocky woods, a few reeds here, a little company of water-lilies there, with beds of gravel or stone beyond; a tiny stream issuing neither briskly nor sluggishly out of it; but its feeding rills, from the shortness of their course, so small as to be scarcely visible. Five or six cottages are reflected in its peaceful bosom; rocky and barren steeps rise up above the hanging enclosures; and the solemn pikes of Langdale overlook, from a distance, the low cultivated ridge of land that forms the northern boundary of this small, quiet, and fertile domain. The <i>mountain</i> Tarns can only be recommended to the notice of the inquisitive traveller who has time to spare. They are difficult to access and naked; yet some of them are, in their permanent forms, very grand; and there are accidents of things which would make the meanest of them interesting. At all events, one of these pools is an acceptable sight to the mountain wanderer, not merely as an incident that diversifies the prospect, but as forming in his mind a center or conspicuous point to which objects, otherwise disconnected or unsubordinated, may be referred. Some few have a varied outline, with bold heath-clad promontories; <pb n="29"/> and, as they mostly lie at the foot of a steep precipice, the water, where the sun is not shining upon it, appears black and sullen; and, round the margin, huge stones and masses of rock are scattered; some defying conjecture as to the means by which they came thither, and others obviously fallen from on high --the contribution of ages! A not unpleasing sadness is induced by this perplexity, and these images of decay; while the prospect of a body of pure water unattended with groves and other cheerful rural images by which fresh water is usually accompanied, and unable to give any furtherance to the meagre vegetation around it --excites a sense of some repulsive power strongly put forth, and thus deepens the melancholy natural to such scenes. Nor is the feeling of solitude often more forcibly or more solemnly impressed than by the side of one of these mountain pools: though desolate and forbidding, it seems a distinct place to repair to; yet where the visitants must be rare, and there can be no disturbance. Water-fowl flock hither; and the lonely Angler may oftentimes here be seen; but the imagination, not content <pb n="30"/> with this scanty allowance of society, is tempted to attribute a voluntary power to every change which takes place in such a spot, whether it be the breeze that wanders over the surface of the water, or the splendid lights of evening resting upon it in the midst of awful precipices.</p>
<poem>
<line>"There, sometimes does a leaping fish</line>
<line>Send through the tarn a lonely cheer;</line>
<line>The crags repeat the raven's croak</line>
<line>In symphony austere:</line>
<line>Thither the rainbow comes, the cloud</line>
<line>And mists that spread the flying shroud,</line>
<line>And sunbeams, and the sounding blast." --</line>
</poem>
<p>It will be observed that this country is bounded on the south and east by the sea, which combines beautifully, from many elevated points, with the inland scenery; and, from the bay of Morcamb, the sloping shores and back-ground of distant mountains are seen composing pictures equally distinguished for grandeur and amenity. But the &#230;stuaries on this coast are in a great measure bare at low water, and there is no instance of the sea running far up among the mountains, and mingling with the Lakes, which are such in the strict and <pb n="31"/> usual sense of the word, being of fresh water. Nor have the streams, from the shortness of their course, time to acquire that body of water necessary to confer upon them much majesty. In fact, the most considerable of them, while they continue in the mountain and lake-country, are rather large brooks than rivers. The water is perfectly pellucid, through which in many places are seen to a great depth their beds of rock or of blue gravel, which give to the water itself an exquisitely cerulean colour: this is particularly striking in the rivers, Derwent and Duddon, which may be compared, such and so various are theirs beauties, to any two rivers of equal length of course in any country. The number of the torrents and smaller brooks is infinite, with their water-falls and water-breaks; and they need not here be described. I will not only observe that, as many, even of the smallest of these rills, have either found, or made for themselves, recesses in the sides of the mountains or in the vales, they have tempted the primitive inhabitants to settle near them for shelter; and hence, cottages so placed, by seeming to withdraw from the eye, are the more endeared to the feelings.</p>
<pb n="32"/>
<p>The WOODS consist chiefly of oak, ash, and birch, and here and there a species of elm, with underwood of hazel, the white and black thorn, and hollies; in moist places aldwers and willows abound; and yews among the rocks. Formerly the whole country must have been covered with wood to a great height up the mountains; where native Scotch firs (as in the northern part of Scotland to this day) must have grown inn great profusion. But not one of these old inhabitants has existed, perhaps, for some hundreds of years; beautiful traces, however, of the universal sylvan appearance of the country formerly had, yet survive in the native coppice-woods that have been protected by inclosures, and also in the forest-trees and hollies, which, though disappearing fast, are yet scattered both over the inclosed and uninclosed parts of the mountains. The same is expressed by the beauty and intricacy with which the fields and coppice-woods are often intermingled: the plough of the first settlers having followed naturally the veins of richer, dryer, or less stony soil; and thus it has shaped out an intermixture of wood and lawn, with a grace and wildness which it would have <pb n="33"/> been impossible for the hand of studied art to produce. Other trees have been introduced within these last fifty years, such as beeches, larches, limes, &#38;c. and plantations of Scotch firs, seldom with advantage, and often with great injury to the appearance of the country; but the sycamore (which I believe was brought into this island from Germany, not more than two hundred years ago) has long been the favourite of the cottagers; and with the Scotch fir, has been chosen to screen their dwellings; and is sometimes found in the fields whither the winds or waters may have carried its seeds.</p>
<p>The want most felt, however, is that of timber trees. There are few magnificent ones to be found near any of the lakes; and, unless greater care be taken, there will, in a short time, scarcely be left an ancient oak that would repay the cost of felling. The neighbourhood of Rydal, notwithstanding the havoc which has been made, is yet notably distinguished. In the woods of Lowther, also, is found an almost matchless store of ancient trees, and all the majesty of wildness of the native forest.</p>
<p>Among the smaller vegetable ornaments must <pb n="34"/> be reckoned the bilberry, a ground plant, never so beautiful as in early spring, when it is seen under bare or budding trees, that imperfectly intercept the sun-shine, covering the rocky knolls with a pure mantle of fresh verdure, more lively than the herbage of the open fields; the broom that spread luxuriantly along rough pastures, and in the month of June intervenes the steep copses with its golden blossoms; and the juniper, a rich evergreen, that thrives in spite of cattle, upon the uninclosed parts of the mountains: --the Dutch myrtle diffuses fragrance in moist places, and there is an endless variety of brilliant flowers in the fields and meadows, which, if the agriculture of the country were more carefully attended to, would disappear. Nor can I omit again to notice the lichens and mosses: their profusion, beauty, and variety, exceed those of any other country I have seen.</p>
<p>It may be proper to say a few words respecting climate, and "skiey influences," in which this region, as far as the character of its landscapes is affected by them, may, upon the whole, be considered fortunate. The country <pb n="35"/> is, indeed, subject to much bad weather, and it has been ascertained that twice as much rain falls here as in many parts of the island; but the number of black drizzling days, that blot out the face of things, is by no means <i>proportionally</i> great. Nor is a continuance of thick, flagging, damp air, so common as in the West of England and Ireland. The rain here comes down heartily, and is frequently succeeded by clear, bright weather, when every brook is vocal, and every torrent sonorous; brooks and torrents, which are never muddy, even in the heaviest floods, except after a drought they happen to defiled for a short time by waters that have swept along dusty roads, or broken out into ploughed fields. Days of unsettled weather, with partial showers, are very frequent; but the showers, darkening or brightening as they fly from hill to hill, are not less grateful to the eye than finely interwoven passages of gay and sad music are touching to the ear. Vapours exhaling from the lakes and meadows after sun-rise, in a hot season, or, in moist weather, brooding upon the heights, or descending towards the vallies with inaudible motion, give <pb n="36"/> a visionary character to every thing around them; and are in themselves so beautiful, as to dispose us to enter into the feelings of those simple nations (such as the Laplanders of this day) by whom they are taken for guardian deities of the mountains; or to sympathise with others who have fancied these delicate apparitions to be the spirits of their deceased ancestors. Akin to these are fleecy clouds resting upon the hill tops; they are not easily managed in picture, with their accompaniments of blue sky; but how glorious are they in nature! how pregnant with imagination for the poet! and the height of the Cumbrian mountains is sufficient to exhibit daily and hourly instances of those mysterious attachments. Such clouds, cleaving to their stations, or lifting up suddenly their glittering heads from behind rocky barriers, or hurrying out of sight with speed of the sharpest edge, will often tempt an inhabitant to congratualte himself on belonging to a country of mists, and clouds, and storms, and make him think of the blank sky of Egypt, and of the cerulean vacancy of Italy, as an unanimated and even sad spectacle. The atmosphere <pb n="37"/>, however, as in every other country subject to much rain, is frequently unfavourable to landscape, especially when keen winds succeed the rain, which are apt to produce coldness, spottiness, and an unmeaning or repulsive detail in the distance; --a sunless frost, under a canopy of leaden and shapeless clouds, is, as far as it allows things to be seen, equally disagreeable.</p>
</chap>
<gap desc="double line"/>
<chap title="SECTION SECOND">
<head level="2" align="center">SECTION SECOND.</head>
<head level="3" align="center">ASPECT OF THE COUNTRY AS AFFECTED BY ITS INHABITANTS.</head>
<p>THUS far I have chiefly spoken of the features by which nature has discriminated this country from others. I will now describe, in general terms, in what manner it is indebted to the hand of man. What I have to notice on this subject will emanate most easily and perspicuously from a description of the ancient and present inhabitants, their occupations, their condition of life, the distribution of landed property among them, and the tenure by which it is holden.</p>
<pb n="38"/>
<p>The reader will suffer me here to recall to his mind the shapes of the vallies, and their position with respect to each other, and the forms and substances of the intervening mountains. He will people the vallies with lakes and rivers; the coves and sides of the mountains with pools and torrents; and will bound half of the circle which we have contemplated by the sands of the sea, or by the sea itself. He will conceive that, from the point upon which he stood, he looks down upon this scene before the country had been penetrated by inhabitants; --to vary his sensations, and to break in upon their stillness, he will form to himself an image of the tides visiting and re-visiting the Friths, the main Sea dashing against the bolder shore, the rivers pursuing their course to be lost in the mighty mass of waters. He may see or hear in fancy the winds sweeping over the lakes, or piping with a loud voice among the mountain peaks; and, lastly, may think of the primeval woods shedding and renewing their leaves with no human eye to notice, or human heart to regret or welcome, the change. "When the first settlers entered this region (say an animated <pb n="39"/> writer) they found it overspread with wood: forest trees, the fir, the oak, the ash, and the birch, had skirted the fells, tufted the hills, and shaded the vallies, through centuries of silent solitude; the birds and beasts of prey reigned over the meeker species; and the <i>bellum inter omnia</i> maintained the balance of nature in the empire of beasts."</p>
<p>Such was the state and appearance of this region when the aboriginal colonists of the Celtic tribes were first driven or drawn towards it, and became joint tenants with the wolf, the boar, the wild bull, the red deer, and the leigh, a gigantic species of deer which has been long extinct; while the inaccessible crags were occupied by the falcon, the raven, and the eagle. The inner parts were too secluded, and of too little value to participate much of the benefit of Roman manners; and though these conquerors encouraged the Britons to the improvement of their lands in the plain country of Furness and Cumberland, they seem to have had little connection with the mountains, except for military purposes, or in subservience to the profit they drew from the mines.</p>
<pb n="40"/>
<!-- the following note begins on pg 40, but covers the next several pages. I have placed it here to avoid moving it too far from its origin -->
<note id="n2"><p>It is not improbable that these circles were once numerons, and that many of them may yet endure in a perfect state, under no very deep covering of soil. A friend of the Author, while making a trench in a level piece of ground, not far from the banks of the Emont, but in no connection with that river, met with some stones which seemed to him formally arranged; this excited his curiosity, and proceeding, he uncovered a perfect circle of stones, from two, to three or four feet high, with a <i>sanctum sanctorum,</i> --the whole of a complete place of Druidical worship of small dimensions, having the sort of relation to the STONES OF SHAP, or LONG MEG and her DAUGHTERS, near the banks of the Eden, that a rural chapel bears to our noble cathedrals. This interesting little monument having passed, with the field in which it was found, into other hands, has been destroyed. It is much to be regretted, that the striking relic of antiquity at Shap has been in a great measure destroyed also. It is thus described in the History of Westmorland: --</p>
<p>"Towards the south end of the village of Shap, near the turnpike road, on the east side thereof, there is a remarkable monument of antiquity; which is an area upwards of half a mile in length, and between twenty and thirty yards broad, encompassed with large stones (with which that country abounds), many of them three or four yards in diameter, at eight, ten, or twelve yards distance, which are of such immense weight that no carriage now in use could support them. Undoubtedly this hath been a place of Druid worship, which they always performed in the open air, within this kind of enclosure, shaded with wood, as this place of old time appears to have been, although there is now scarce a tree to be seen, (<i>Shapthorn</i> only excepted, planted on the top of the hill for the direction of travellers). At the high end of this place of worship there is a circle of the like stones about eighteen feet in diameter, which was their <i>sanctum sanctorum,</i> (as it were), and place of sacrifice. The stone is a kind of granite, and when broken appears beautifully variegated with bright shining spots, like spar. The country people have blasted and carried away some of these stones, for the foundation-stones of buildings. In other places some have cut these stones (but with difficulty) for mill-stones. When polished they would make some beautiful pieces." Some contend that this is a Danish monument.</p>
<p>The DAUGHTERS of LONG MEG are placed not in an oblong, as the STONES OF SHAP, but in a perfect circle, eighty yards in diameter, and seventy-two in number, and from above three yards high, to less than so many feet: a little way out of the circle stands LONG MEG herself --a single stone eighteen feet high.</p>
<p>When the Author first saw this monument he came upon it by surprize, therefore might over-rate its importance as an object; but he must say, that though it is not to be compared with Stonehenge, he has not seen any other remains of those dark ages, which can pretend to rival it in singularity  and dignity of appearance.</p>
<poem>
<line>A weight of awe not easy to be borne</line>
<line>Fell suddenly upon my spirit, cast</line>
<line>From the dread bosom of unknown past,</line>
<line>When first I saw that sisterhood forlorn; --</line>
<line>And her, whose strength and stature seems to scorn</line>
<line>The power of years --pre-eminent, and placed</line>
<line>Apart, to overlook the circle vast.</line>
<line>Speak, Giant-mother! tell it to the Morn,</line>
<line>While she dispels the cumbrous shades of night;</line>
<line>Let the Moon hear, emerging from a cloud,</line>
<line>When, how, and wherefore, rose on British ground</line>
<line>That wond'rous Monument, whose mystic round</line>
<line>Forth shadows, some have deem'd, to mortal sight</line>
<line>The inviolable God that tames the proud.</line>
</poem>
</note>
<p>When the Romans retired from Great Britain, it is well known that these mountain-fastnesses furnished a protection to some unsubdued Britons, long after the more accessible and more fertile districts had been seized by the Saxon or Danish invader. A few, though distinct traces of Roman forts or camps, as at Ambleside, and upon Dunmallet, and few circles of rude stones attributed to the Druids,<ptr target="n2"/> are the only vestiges <pb n="41"/> that remain upon the surface of the country, of these ancient occupants; and, as the Saxons <pb n="42"/> and Danes, who succeeded to the possession of the villages and hamlets which had been established by the Britons, seem at first to have confined themselves to the open country, --we may descend at once to times long posterior to the conquest by the Normans, when their feudal polity was regularly established. We may easily conceive that these narrow dales and mountain <pb n="43"/> sides, choaked up as they must have been with wood, lying out of the way of communication with other parts of the Island, and upon the edge of a hostile kingdom, could have little attraction for the high-born and powerful; especially as the more open parts of the country furnished positions for castles and houses of defence, sufficient to repel any of those sudden attacks, which, in the then rude state of military knowledge, could be made upon them. Accordingly, the more retired regions (and to such I am now confining myself) must have been neglected or shunned even by the persons whose baronial or signioral rights extended over them, and left, doubtless, partly as a place of refuge for outlaws and robbers, and partly granted out for the more settled habitation of a few vassals following the employment of shepherds or woodlanders. Hence these lakes and inner vallies are unadorned by any remains of ancient grandeur, castles, or monastic edifices, which are only found upon the skirts of the country, as Furness Abbey, Calder Abbey, the Priory of Lannercost, Gleaston Castle, --long ago a residence of the Flemings, --and the numerous <pb n="44"/> ancient castles of the Cliffords, the Lucys, and the Dacres. On the southern side of these mountains, (especially in that part known by the name of Furness Fells, which is more remote from the borders,) the state of society would necessarily be more settled; though it also was fashioned, not a little, by its neighbourhood to a hostile kingdom. We will, therefore, give a sketch of the economy of the Abbots in the distribution of lands among their tenants, as similar plans were doubtless adopted by other Lords, and as the consequences have affected the face of the country materially to the present day, being, in fact, one of the principle causes which give it such a striking superiority, in beauty and interest, over all other parts of the island.</p>
<p>"When the Abbots of Furness," says an author before cited, "enfranchised their villains, and raised them to the dignity of customary tenants, the lands, which they had cultivated for their lord, were divided into whole tenements; each of which, besides the customary annual rent, was charged with the obligation of having in readiness a man completely armed for <pb n="45"/> the king's service on the borders, or elsewhere: each of these whole tenements was again subdivided into four equal parts; each villain had one; and the party tenant contributed his share to the support of the man at arms, and of other burdens. These divisions were not properly distinguished; the land remained mixed; each tenant had a share through all the arable and meadow-land, and common of pasture over all the wastes. These sub-tenements were judged sufficient for the support of so many families; and no further division was permitted. These divisions and sub-divisions were convenient at the time for which they were calculated; the land, so parcelled out, was, of necessity, more attended to; and the industry greater, when more persons were to be supported by the produce of it. The frontier of the kingdom, within which Furness was considered, was in a constant state of attack and defence; more hands, therefore, were necessary to guard the coast, to repel an invasion from Scotland, or make reprisals on the hostile neighbour. The dividing the lands in such manner as has been shown, increased the number of inhabitants, and kept <pb n="46"/> them at home till called for; and, the land being mixed, and the several tenants united in equipping the plough, the absence of the fourth man was no prejudice to the cultivation of his land, which was committed to the care of three.</p>
<p>While the villains of Low Furness were thus distributed over the land, and employed in agriculture; those of High Furness were charged with the care of flocks and herds, to protect them from the wolves which lurked in the thickets, and in winter to browse them with tender sprouts of hollies and ash. This custom was not till lately discontinued in High Furness; and holly-trees were carefully preserved for that purpose when all other wood was cleared off; large tracts of common being so covered with these trees, as to have the appearance of a forest of hollies. At the Shepherd's call, the flocks surrounded the holly-bush, and received croppings at his hand, which they greedily nibbled up, bleating for more. The Abbots of Furness enfranchised these pastoral vassals, and permitted them to enclose <i>quillets</i> to their houses, for which they paid encroachment rent." --West's <i>Antiquities of Furness.</i></p>
<pb n="47"/>
<p>However desirable, for the purpose of defence, a numerous population might be, it was not possible to make at once the same numerous allotments among the untilled vallies, and upon the sides of the mountains, as had been made in the cultivated plains. The enfranchised shepherd, or woodlander, having chosen there his place of residence, builds it of sods, or of the mountain stone, and, with the permission of his lord, encloses, like Robinson Crusoe, a small croft or two immediately at his door for such animals as he wishes to protect. Others are happy to imitate his example, and avail themselves of the same privileges; and thus a population, mainly of Danish or Norse origin, as the dialect indicates, crept on towards the more secluded parts of the vallies. Chapels, daughters of some distant mother church, are first erected in the more open and fertile vales, as those of Bowness and Grasmere, offsets of Kendal; which again, after a period, as the settled population increases, become mother-churches to smaller edifices, planted, at length, in almost every dale throughout the country. The enclosures, formed by the tenantry, are<pb n="48"/> for a long time confined to the home-steads; and the arable and meadow land of the vales is possessed in common field; the several portions being marked out by stones, bushes, or trees; which portions, where the custom has survived, to this day are called <i>dales</i> from the word <i>deylen</i>, to distribute; but, while the valley was thus lying open, enclosures seem to have taken place upon the sides of the mountains; because the land there was not intermixed, and was of little comparative value; and, therefore, small opposition would be made to its being appropriated by those to whose habitations it was contiguous. Hence, the singular appearance which the sides of many of these mountains exhibit, intersected, as they are, almost to the summit, with stone walls, of which the fences are always formed. When first erected, they must have little disfigured the face of the country; as part of the lines would every where be hidden by the quantity of native wood then remaining; and the lines would also be broken (as they still are) by the rocks which interrupt and vary their course. In the meadows, and in those parts of the lower grounds where the soil <pb n="49"/> has not been sufficiently drained, and could not afford a stable foundation, there, when the increasing value of land, and the inconvenience suffered from intermixed plots of ground in common field, had induced each inhabitant to inclose his own, they were compelled to make the fences of alders, willows, and other trees. These, where the native wood had disappeared, have frequently enriched the vallies with a sylan appearance; while the intricate intermixture of property has given to the fences a graceful irregularity, which, where large properties are prevalent, and large capitals employed in agri-culture, is unknown. This sylvan appearance is still further heightened by the number of ash-trees planted in rows along the quick fences, and along the walls, for the purpose of browzing cattle at the approach of winter. The branches are lopped off and strewn upon the pastures; and, when the cattle have stripped them of the leaves, they are used for repairing hedges, or for fuel.</p>
<p>We have thus seen a numerous body of Dalesmen creeping into possession of their home-steads, their little crofts, their mountain-enclosures <pb n="50"/>; and, finally, the whole vale is visibly divided; except, perhaps, here and there some marshy ground, which, till fully drained, would not repay the trouble of enclosing. But these last partitions do not seem to have been general, till long after the pacification of the Borders, by the union of the two crowns; when the cause, which had first determined the distribution of the land in such small parcels, had not only ceased, --but likewise a general improvement had taken place in the country, with a correspondent rise in the value of its produce. From the time of the union, it is certain that this species of feudal population must rapidly have diminished. That it was formerly much more numerous than it is at present, is evident from the multitude of tenements (I do not mean houses, but small divisions of land) which belonged formerly each to a several proprietor, and for which separate fines are paid to the manorial lord at this day. These are often in the proportion of four to one, of the present occupants. "Sir Lancelot Threlkeld, who lived in the reign of Henry VII. was wont to say, he had three nobles houses, one for <pb n="51"/> pleasure, Crosby, in Westmoreland, where he had a park full of deer; one for profit and warmth, wherein to reside in winter, namely, Yanwith, nigh Penrith; and the third, Threlkeld (on the edge of the vale of Keswick) well stocked with tenants to go with him to the wars." But, as I have said, from the union of the two crowns, this numerous vassalage (their services not being wanted) would rapidly diminish; various tenements would be united in one possessor; and the aboriginal houses, probably little better than hovels, like the kraels of savages, or the huts of the Highlanders of Scotland, would fall into decay, and the places of many be supplied by substantial and comfortable buildings, a majority of which remain to this day scattered over the vallies, and are often the only dwellings found in them.</p>
<p>From the time of the erection of these houses, till within the last sixty years, the state of society, though no doubt slowly and gradually improving, underwent no material change. Corn was grown in these vales (through which no carriage road had ever been made) sufficient upon each estate <pb n="52"/>to furnish bread for each family, and no more: notwithstanding the union of several tenements, the possession of each inhabitant still being small, in the same field was seen an intermixture of different crops; and the plough was interrupted by little rocks, mostly overgrown with wood, or by spongy places, which the tillers of the soil had neither leisure nor capital to convert into firm land. The storms and moisture of the climate induced them to sprinkle their upland property with outhouses of native stone, as places of shelter for their sheep, where, in tempestuous weather, food was distributed to them. Every family spun from its own flock the wool with which it was clothed; a weaver was here and there found among them; and the rest of their wants was supplied by the produce of the yarn, which they carded and spun in their own houses and carried to market, either under their arms, or more frequently on pack-horses, a small train taking their way weekly down the valley or over the mountains to the most commodious town. They had, as I have said, their rural chapel, and of course their minister, in clothing or in manner of life, <pb n="53"/>in no respect differing from themselves, except on the Sabbath-day; this was the sole distinguished individual among them; every thing else, person and possession, exhibited a perfect equality, a community of shepherds and agriculturists, proprietors, for the most part, of the lands which they occupied and cultivated.</p>
<p>While the process above detailed was going on, the native forest must have been every where receding; but the trees were planted for the sustenance of the flocks in winter, --such was then the rude state of agriculture; and, for the same cause, it was necessary that care should be taken of some part of the growth of the native woods. Accordingly, in Queen Elizabeth's time, this was so strongly felt, that a petition was made to the Crown, praying "that the Blomaries in high Furness might be abolished, on account of the quantity of wood which was consumed in them for the use of the mines, to the great detriment of the cattle." But this same cause, about a hundred years later, produced effects directly contrary to those which have been deprecated. The re-establishment, at that period, of furnaces upon a large scale, <pb n="54"/> made it the interest of the people to convert the steeper and more stony of the inclosures, sprinkled over with remains of the native forest, into close woods, which, when cattle and sheep were excluded, rapidly sowed and thickened themselves. The reader's attention has been directed to the cause by which tufts of wood, pasturage, meadow, and arable land, with its various produce, are intricately intermingled in the same field, and he will now see, in like manner, how enclosures of wood, and those of cultivated ground, are blended over the country under a law of similar wildness.</p>
<p>An historic detail has thus been given of the manner in which the hand of man has acted upon the surface of the inner regions of this mountainous country, as incorporated with and subservient to the powers and processes of nature. We will now take a view of the same agency --acting, within narrower bounds, for the production of the few works of art and accomodations of life which, in so simple a state of society, could be necessary. These are merely habitations of man and converts for beasts, roads and bridges, and places of worship.</p>
<pb n="55"/>
<p>And to begin with the COTTAGES. They are scattered over the vallies, and under the hill sides, and on the rocks; and, even to this day, in the more retired dales, without any intrusion of more assuming buildings;</p>
<poem>
<line>Clustered like stars some few, but single most,</line>
<line>And lurking dimly in their shy retreats,</line>
<line>Or glancing on each other cheerful looks,</line>
<line>Like separated stars with clouds between.</line>
<author>S.</author>
</poem>
<p>The dwelling-houses, and contiguous outhouses, are, in many instances, of the colour of the native rock, out of which they have been built; but, frequently the dwelling-house has been distinguished from the barn and byer by rough-cast and white wash, which, as the inhabitants are not hasty in renewing it, in a few years acquires, by the influence of weather, a tint at once sober and variegated. As these houses have been from father to son inhabited by persons engaged in the same occupations, yet necessarily with changes in their circumstances, they have received additions and accomodations adapted to the needs of each successive occupant, who, being for the most part proprietor,<pb n="56"/> was at liberty to follow his own fancy; so that these humble dwellings remind the contemplative spectator of a production of nature, and may (using a strong expression) rather be said to have grown rather than to have been erected; --to have risen, by an instinct of their own, out of the native rock --so little is there in them of formality, such is their wildness and beauty! Among the numerous recesses and projections in the walls and in the different stages of their roofs, are seen bold and harmonious effects of contrasted sunshine and shadow. It is a favourable circumstance, that the strong winds, which sweep down the vallies, induced the inhabitants, at a time when the materials for buildings were easily procured, to furnish many of these dwellings with substantial porches; and such as have not this defence, are seldom unprovided with a projection of two large slates over their thresholds. Nor will the singular beauty of the chimneys escape the eye of the attentive traveller. Sometimes a low chimney, almost upon a level with the roof, is overlaid with a slate, supported upon four slender pillars, to prevent the wind from driving the smoke <pb n="57"/>down the chimney. Others are of a quadrangular shape, rising one or two feet above the roof; which low square is often surmounted by a top cylinder, giving to the cottage chimney the most beautiful shape in which it is ever seen. Nor will it be too fanciful or refined to remark, that there is a pleasing harmony between a tall chimney of this circular form, and the living column of smoke, through the still air ascending from it. These dwellings, mostly built, as has been said, of rough unhewn stone, are roofed with slates, which were rudely taken from the quarry before the present art of splitting them was understood, and are, therefore, rough and uneven in their surfaces, so that both the coverings and sides of the houses have furnished pieces of rest of the seeds of lichens, mosses, ferns, and flowers. Hence buildings, which, in their very form call to mind the processes of nature, do thus, clothed with this vegetable garb, appear to be received into the bosom of the living principle of things, as it acts and exists among the woods and fields; and, by their colour and their shape, affectingly direct the thoughts to that tranquil <pb n="58"/> course of nature and simplicity, along which the humbled-minded inhabitants have thruogh so many generations been led. Add the little garden with its shed for bee-hives, its small beds of pot-herbs, and its borders and patches of flowers for Sunday posies, with sometimes a choice few too much prized to be plucked; an orchard of proportioned size; a cheese-press, often supported by some tree near the door; a cluster of embowering sycamores for summer shade; with a tall Scotch fir, through which the winds sing when other trees are leafless; the little rill or household spout murmuring in all seasons; --combine these incidents and images together, and you have the representative idea of a mountain-cottage in this country so beautifully formed in itself, and so richly adorned by the hand of nature.</p>
<p>Till within the last sixty years there was no communication between any of these vales by carriage-roads; all bulky articles were transported on pack-horses. Owing, however, to the population not being concentrated in villages but scattered, the vallies themselves were intersected as now by innumerable lanes and pathways <pb n="59"/> leading from house to house and from field to field. These lanes, where they are fenced by stone walls, are mostly bordered with ashes, hazels, wild roses, and beds of tall fern, at their base; while the walls themselves, if old, are overspread with mosses, small ferns, wild strawberries, the geranium, and lichens; and if the wall happen to rest against a bank of earth, it is sometimes almost wholly concealed by a rich facing of stone-fern. It is a great advantage to a traveller or resident, that these numerous lanes and paths, if he be a zealous admirer of nature, will lead him on into all the recesses of the country, so that the hidden treasures of its landscapes may, by an ever-ready guide, be laid open to his eyes.</p>
<p>Likewise to the smallness of the several properties is owing the great number of bridges over the brooks and torrents, and the daring and graceful neglect of danger or accomodation with which so many of them are constructed, the rudeness of the forms of some, and their endless variety. But, when I speak of this rudeness, I must at the same time add, that many of these structures are in themselves models of elegance, <pb n="60"/>as if they had been formed upon principles of the most thoughtful architecture. It is to be regretted that these monuments of the skill of our ancestors, and of that happy instinct by which consummate beauty was produced, are disappearing fast; but sufficient specimens remain to give a high gratification to the man of genuine taste. Travellers who may not have been accustomed to pay attention to things so inobtrusive, will excuse me if I point out the proportion between the span and elevation of the arch, the lightness of the parapet, and the graceful manner in which its curve follows faithfully that of the arch.</p>
<note id="n3">In some places scholars were formerly taught in the church, and at others the school-house was a sort of anti-chapel to the place of worship, being under the same roof; and arrangement which was abandoned as irrelevent. It continues, however, to this day in Borrowdale. In the parish register of that chapelry is a notice, that a Youth who had quitted the valley, and died in one of the towns on the coast of Cumberland, had requested that his body should be brought and interred at the foot of the pillar by which he had been accustomed to sit while a schoolboy. One cannot but regret that parish registers so seldom contain any thing but bare names; in a few of this country, especially in that of Loweswater, I have found interesting notices of unusual natural occurrences-- characters of the deceased, and particulars of their lives. There is no good reason why such memorials should not be frequent; these short and simple annals would in future ages become precious.</note>
<p>Upon this subject I have nothing further to notice, except the PLAXES OF WORSHIP, which have mostly a little school-house ajoining.<ptr target="n3"/> The architecture of these churches and chapels,<pb n="61"/> where they have not been recently rebuilt or modernised, is of a style not less appropriate and admirable than that of the dwelling-houses and other structures. How sacred the spirit by which our forefathers were directed! The <i>religio loci</i> is no where violated by these unstinted, yet unpretending, works of human hands. They exhibit generally a well-proportioned oblong, with a suitable porch, in some instances a steeple tower, and in others nothing more than a small belfry, in which one or two bells hang visibly. But these objects, though pleasing in their forms, must necessarily, more than others in rural scenery, derive their interest from the sentiments of piety and reverence for the modest virtues and simple manners of humble life with <pb n="62"/>which they may be contemplated. A man must be very insensible who would not be touched with pleasure at the sight of the chapel of Buttermere, so strikingly expressing, by its diminutive size, how small must be the congregation there assembled, as it were, like one family; and proclaiming at the same time to the passenger, in connection with the surrounding mountains, the depth of that seclusion in which the people live, that has rendered necessary the building of a separate place of worship for so few. A patriot, calling to mind the images of the stately fabrics of Canterbury, York, or Westminster, will find a heart-felt satisfaction in presence of this lowly pile, as a monument of the wise institutions of our country, and as evidence of the all-pervading and paternal care of that venerable Establishment, of which it is, perhaps, the humblest daughter. The edifice is scarcely larger than many of the single stones or fragments of rock which are scattered near it.</p>
<p>We have thus far confined our observations on this division of the subject, to that part of these Dales which runs up far into the mountains. In addition to such objects as have been hitherto described, it may be mentioned that, as we descend towards the open part of the Vales, we meet with the remains of ancient Parks, and with old Mansions of more stately architecture; and it may be observed, that to these circumstances the country owes whatever ornament it retains of majestic and full-grown timber, as the remains of the park of the ancient family of the Ratcliffs at Derwent-water, Gowbray-park, and the venerable woods of Rydal. Through open parts of the vales are scattered, with more spacious domains attached to them, houses of a middle rank, between the pastoral cottage and the old hall-residence of the more wealthy <i>Estatesman.</i></p>
<p>Thus has been given a faithful description, the minuteness of which the reader will pardon, of the face of this country as it was, and had been through centuries, till within the last sixty years. Towards the head of these Dales was found a perfect Republic of Shepherds and Agriculturists, among whom the plough of each man was confined to the maintenance of his own family, or to the occasional accommodation of his neighbour.<ptr target="n4"/> Two or three cows furnished each family with milk and cheese. The Chapel was the only edifice that presided over these dwellings, the supreme head of this pure Commonwealth; the members of which existed in the midst of a powerful empire, like an ideal society or an organised community, whose constitution had been imposed and regulated by the mountains which protected it. Neither high-born Nobleman, Knight, nor Esquire, was here; but many of these humble sons of the hills had a consciousness that the land, which they walked <pb n="65"/>over and tilled, had for more than five hundred years been possessed by men of their name and blood; --and venerable was the transition, when a curious traveller, descending frmo the heart of the mountains, had come to some ancient manorial residence in the more open parts of the Vales, which, through the rights attached to its proprietor, connected the almost visionary mountain Republic he had been contemplating with the substantial frame of society as existing in the laws and constitutions of a mighty empire.</p>
<note id="n4">One of the most pleasing characteristics of manners in secluded and thinly-people districts, is a sense of the degree in which human happiness and comfort are dependent on the contingency of neighbourhood. This is implied by a rhyming adage common here, "<i>Friends are far, when neighbours are nar</i>" (near). This mutual helpfulness is not confined to out-of-doors work; but is ready upon all occasions. Formerly, if a person became sick, especially the mistress of a family, it was usual for those of the neighbours who were more particularly connected with the party by amicable offices, to visit the house, carrying a present; this practice, which is by no means obsolete, is called <i>owning</i> the family, and is regarded as a pledge of a disposition to be otherwise serviceable in a time of disability and distress.</note>
<gap desc="double line"/>
</chap>
<chap title="SECTION THIRD">
<head level="2" align="center">SECTION THIRD.</head>
<head level="3" align="center">CHANGES, AND RULES OF TASTE FOR PREVENTING THEIR BAD EFFECTS.</head>
<p>SUCH, as hath been said, was the appearance of things till within the last sixty years. A practice, by a strange abuse of terms, denominated Ornamental Gardening, was at that time becoming prevalent over England. In union with an admiration of this art, and in some instances in opposition to it, had been generated a <pb n="66"/> relish for select parts of natural scenery; and Travellers, instead of confining their observations to Towns, Manufactories, or Mines, began (a thing till then unheard of) to wander over the island in search of sequestered spots, distinguished, as they might accidentally have learned, for the sublimity or beauty of the forms of Nature there to be seen. --Dr. Brown, the celebrated Author of the Estimate of the Manners and Principles of the Times, published a letter to a Friend, in which the attractions of the Vale of Keswick were delineated with powerful pencil, and the feeling of a genuine Enthusiast. Gray, the Poet, followed; he died soon after his forlorn and melancholy pilgrimage to the Vale of Keswick, and the record left behind him of what he had seen and felt in this journey, excited that pensive interest with which the human mind is ever disposed to listen to the farewell words of a man of genius. The journal of Gray feelingly showed how the gloom of ill health and low spirits had been irradiated by objects, which the Author's power of mind enabled him to describe with distinctness and unaffected simplicity. Every reader of this <pb n="67"/> journal must have been impressed with the words which conclude his notice of the Vale of Grasmere: --"Not a single red tile, no flaring gentleman's house or garden-wall, breaks in upon the repose of this little unsuspected paradise; but all is peace, rusticity, and happy poverty, in its nearest and most becoming attire."</p>
<p>What is here so justly said of Grasmere applied almost equally to all its sister Vales. It was well for the undisturbed pleasure of the Poet that he had no forebodings of the change which was soon to take place; and it might have been hoped that these words, indicating how much the charm of what <i>was</i>, depended upon what was <i>not</i>, would of themselves have preserved the ancient franchises of this and other kindred mountain retirements from trespass; or (shall I dare to say?) would have secured scenes so consecrated from profanation. The lakes had now become celebrated; visitors flocked hither from all parts of England; the fancies of some were smitted so deeply, that they became settlers; and the Islands of Derwent-water and Winandermere, as they offered the <pb n="68"/>strongest temptation, were the first places seized upon, and were instantly defaced by the intrusion.</p>
<p>The venerable wood that had grown for centuries round the small house called St. Herbert's Hermitage, had indeed some years before been felled by its native proprietory, and the whole island planted anew with Scotch firs left the spindle up by each other's side -- a melancholy phalanx, defying the power of the winds, and disregarding the regret of the spectator, who might otherwise have cheated himself into a belief, that some of the decayed remains of those oaks, the place of which was in this manner usurped, had been planted by the Hermit's own hand. This sainted spot, however, suffered comparatively little injury. At the bidding of an alien improver, the Hind's Cottage, upon Vicar's island, in the same lake, with its embowering sycamores and cattle-shed, disappeared from the corner of where they stood; and right in the middle, and upon the precise point of the island's highest elevation, rose a tall square habitation, with four sides exposed, like an astronomer's observatory, or a warren-house <pb n="69"/>reared upon an eminence for the detection of depredators, or, like the temple of &#338;olus, where all the winds pay him obeisance. Round this novel structure, but at respectful distance, platoons of firs were stationed, as if to protect their commander when weather and time should somewhat have shattered his strength. Within the narrow limits of this island were typified also the state and strength of a kingdom, and its religion as it had been, and was, --for neither was the druidical circle uncreated, nor the church of the present establishment; nor the stately pier, emblem of commerce and navigation; nor the fort, to deal out thunder upon the approaching invader. The taste of a succeeding proprietor rectified the mistakes as far as was practicable, and has ridded the spot of all it puerilities. The church, after having been docked of its steeple, is applied, both ostensibly and really, to the purpose for which the body of the pile was actually erected, namely, a boat-house; the fort is demolished; and, without indignation on the part of the spirits of the ancient Druids who officiated at the circle upon the opposite hill, the mimic arrangement <pb n="70"/> of stones, with its <i>sanctum sanctorum</i>, has been swept away.</p>
<p>The present instance has been singled out, extravagant as it is, because, unquestionably, this beautiful country has, in numerous other places, suffered from the same spirit, though not clothed exactly in the same form, nor active in an equal degree. It will be sufficient here to utter a regret for the changes that have been made upon the principal Island at Winandermere, and in its neighbourhood. What could be more unfortunate than the taste that suggested the pairing of the shores, and surrounding with an embankment this spot of ground, the natural shape of which was so beautiful! An artificial appearance has thus been given to the whole, while infinite varieties of minute beauty have been destroyed. Could not the margin of this noble island be given back to nature? Winds and waves work with a careless and graceful hand: and, should they in some places carry away a portion of the soil, the trifling loss would be amply compensated by the additional spirit, dignity, and loveliness, which these agents and the other powers of <pb n="71"/>nature would soon communicate to what was left behind. As to the larch-plantations upon the main shore, --they who remember the original appearance of the rocky steeps scattered over with native hollies and ash-trees, will be prepared to agree with what I shall have to say hereafter upon plantations in general.</p>
<p>But, in truth, no one can now travel through the more frequented tracts, without being offended, at almost every turn, by an introduction of discordant objects, disturbing that peaceful harmony of form and colour which had been through a long lapse of ages most happily preserved.</p>
<p>All gross transgressions of this kind originate, doubtless, in a feeling natural and honourable to the human mind, viz. the pleasure which it receives from distinct ideas, and from the perception of order, regularity, and contrivance. Now, unpractised minds receive these impressions only from objects that are divided from each other by strong lines of demarcation; hence the delight with which such minds are smitted by formality and harsh contrast. But I would beg of those who are eager to create <pb n="72"/>the means of such gratification, first carefully to study what already exists; and they will find, in a country so lavishly gifted by nature, an abundant variety of forms marked out with a precision that will satisfy their desires. Moreover, a new habit of pleasure will be formed opposite to this, arising out of the perception of the fine gradations by which in nature one thing passes away into another, and the boundaries that constitute individuality, disappear in one instance only to be revived elsewhere in one instance only to be revived elsewhere under a more alluring form. The hill of Dunmallet, at the foot of Ulswater, was once divided into different portions, by avenues of fir-trees, with a green and almost perpendicular lane descending down the steep hill through each avenue; --contrast this quaint appearance with the image of the same hill overgrown with self-planted wood, --each tree springing up in the situation best suited to its kind, and with that shape which the situation constrained or suffered it to take. What endless melting and playing into each other of forms and colours does the one offer to a mind at once attentive and active; and how insipid and lifeless, compared with it, appear <pb n="73"/>those parts of the former exhibition with which a child, a peasant perhaps, or a citizen unfamiliar with natural imagery, would have been most delighted!</p>
<p>The disfigurement which this country has undergone, has not, however, proceeded wholly from the common feelings of human nature which have been referred to as the primary sources of bad taste in rural scenery; another cause must be added, that has chiefly shown itself in its effect upon buildings. I mean a warping of the natural mind occasioned by a consciousness that, this country being an object of general admiration, every new house would be looked at and commented upon either for approbation or censure. Hence all the deformity and ungracefulness that ever pursue the steps of constraint or affectation. Persons, who in Leicestershire or Northamptonshire would probably have built a modest dwelling like those of their sensible neighbours, have been turned out of their course; and, acting in part, no wonder if, having had little experience, they act it ill. The craving for prospect, also, which is immoderate, particularly in new settlers, has <pb n="74"/>rendered it impossible that buildings, whatever might have been their architecture, should in most instances be ornamental to the landscape; rising as they do from the summits of naked hills in staring contrast to the snugness and privacy of the ancient houses.</p>
<p>No man is to be condemned for a desire to decorate his residence and possessions; feeling a disposition to applaud such an endeavour, I would show how the end may be best attained. The rule is simple; with respect to grounds -- work, where you can, in the spirit of nature with an invisible hand of art. Planting, and a removal of wood, may thus, and thus only, be carried on with good effect; and the like may be said of building, if Antiquity, who may be styled the co-partner and sister of Nature, be not denied the respect to which she is entitled. I have already spoken of the beautiful forms of the ancient mansions of this country, and of the happy manner in which they harmonise with the forms of nature. Why cannot such be taken as a model, and modern internal convenience be confined within their external grace and dignity? Expense to be avoided, or difficulties to be overcome, <pb n="75"/>may prevent a close adherence to this model; still, however, it might be followed to a certain degree in the style of architecture and in the choice of situation, if the thirst for prospect were mitigated by those considerations of comfort, shelter, and convenience, which used to be chiefly sought after. But, should an aversion to old fashions unfortunately exist, accompanied with a desire to transplant into the cold and stormy North, the elegancies of a villa formed upon a model taken from countries with a milder climate, I will adduce a passage from an English poet, the divine Spenser, which will show in what manner such a plan may be realised without injury to the native beauty of these scenes.</p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line>"Into that forest farre they thence him led,</line>
<line>Where was their dwelling in a pleasant glade</line>
<line>With MOUNTAINS round about environed,</line>
<line>And MIGHTY WOODS which did the valley shade,</line>
<line>And like a stately theatre it made,</line>
<line>Spreading itself into a spacious plaine;</line>
<line>And in the midst a little river plaide</line>
<line>Emongst the pumy stones which seem'd to plaine</line>
<line>With gentle murmure that his course they did restraine.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Beside the same a dainty place there lay,</line>
<line>Planted with mirtle trees and laurels green,</line>
<pb n="76"/>
<line>In which the birds sang many a lovely lay</line>
<line>Of God's high praise, and of their sweet loves teene,</line>
<line>As it an earthly paradise had beene;</line>
<line>In whose <i>enclosed shadow</i> there was pight</line>
<line>A fair pavilion, <i>scarecely to be seen</i>,</line>
<line>The which was all within most richly dight,</line>
<line>That greatest princes living it mote well delight."</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>Houses or mansions suited to a mountainous region, should be "not obvious, not obtrusive, but retired;" and the reasons for this rule, though they have been little adverted to, are evident. Mountainous countries, more frequently and forcibly than others, remind us of the power of the elements, as manifested in winds, snows, and torrents, and accordingly make the notion of exposure very unpleasing; while shelter and comfort are in proportion necessary and acceptable. Far-winding valleys difficult of access, and the feelings of simplicity habitually connected with mountain retirements, prompt us to turn from ostentation as a thing there eminently unnatural and out of place. A mansion, amid such scenes, can never have sufficient dignity or interest to become principal in the landscape, and to render the mountains, lakes, or torrents, by which it may be surrounded,<pb n="77"/> a subordinate part of the view. It is, I grant, easy to conceive, that an ancient castellated building, hanging over a precipice or raised upon an island, or the peninsula of a lake, like that of Kilchurn Castle, upon Loch Awe, may not want, whether deserted or inhabited, sufficient majesty to preside for a moment in the spectator's thoughts over the high mountains among which it is embosomed; but its titles are from antiquity --a power readily submitted to upon occasion as the vicegerent of Nature: it is respected, as having owed its existence to the necessities of things, as a monument of security in times of disturbance and danger long passed away, --as a record of the pomp and violence of passion, and a symbol of the wisdom of law; it bears a countenance of authority, which is not impaired by decay.</p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line>"Child of loud-throated war, the mountain-stream</line>
<line>Roars in thy hearing; but thy hour of rest</line>
<line>Is come, and thou art silent in thy age!"</line>
</stanza>
<author><i>MS.</i></author>
</poem>
<p>To such honours a modern edifice can lay no claim; and the puny efforts of elegance appear contemptible, when, in such situations, they are <pb n="78"/>obtruded in rivalship with the sublimities of Nature. But, towards the verge of a district like this of which we are treating, where the mountains subside into hills of moderate elevation, or in an undulating or flat country, a gentleman's mansion may, with propriety, become a principal feature in the landscape; and, itself being a work of art, works and traces of artificial ornament may, without censure, be extended around it, as they will be referred to the common centre, the house; the right of which to impress within certain limits a character of obvious ornament will not be denied, where no commanding forms of nature dispute it, or set it aside. Now, to a want of the perception of this difference, and to the causes before assigned, may chiefly be attributed the disfigurement which the Country of the Lakes has undergone, from persons who may have built, demolished, and planted, with full confidence, that every change and addition was or would become an improvement.</p>
<p>The principle that ought to determine the position, apparent size, and architecture of a house, viz. that it should be so constructed, and <pb n="79"/> (if large) so much of it hidden, as to admit of its being gently incorporated into the scenery of nature --should also determine its colour. Sir Joshua Reynolds used to say, "if you would fix upon the best colour for your house, turn up a stone, or pluck up a handful of grass by the roots, and see what the colour of the soil where your house is to stand, and let that be your choice." Of course, this precept, given in conversation, could not have been meant to be taken literally. For example, in Low Furness, where the soil, from its strong impregnation with iron, is universally of a deep red, if this rule were strictly followed, the house also must be of a glaring red; in other places it must be of a sullen black; which would only be adding annoyance to annoyance. The rule, however, as a general guide, is good; and, in agricultural districts, where large tracts of soil are laid bare by the plough, particularly if (the face of the country being undulating) they are held up to view, this rule, though not to be implicitly adhered to, should never be lost sight of; --the colour of the house ought, if possible, to have a cast or shade of the colour of the soil. The principle is, that <pb n="80"/> the house must harmonise with the surrounding landscape: accordingly, in mountainous countries, with still more confidence may it be said, "look at the rocks and those parts of the mountains where the soil is visible, and they will furnish a safe direction." Nevertheless, it will often happen that the rocks may bear so large a proportion to the rest of the landscape, and may be of such a tone of colour, that the rule may not admit, even here, of being implicitly followed. For instance, the chief defect in the colouring of the Country of the Lakes (which is most strongly felt in the summer season) is an over-prevalence of a bluish tint, which the green of the herbage, the fern, and the woods, does not sufficiently counteract. If a house, therefore, should stand where this defect prevails, I have no hesitation in saying, that the colour of the neighbouring rocks would not be the best that could be chosen. A tint ought to be introduced approaching nearer to those which, in technical language of painters, are called <i>warm:</i> this, if happily selected, would not disturb but would animate the landscape. How often do we see this exemplified upon a small <pb n="81"/>scale by the native cottages, in cases where the glare of the white-wash has been subdued by time and enriched by weather-stains! No harshness is then seen; but one of these cottages, thus coloured, will often form a central point to a landscape by which the whole shall be connected, and an influence of pleasure diffused over all the objects that compose the picture. But where the cold blue tint of the rocks is enriched by the iron tinge, the colour cannot be too closely be imitated; and it will be produced of itself by the stones hewn from the adjoining quarry, and by the mortar, which may be tempered with the most gravelly part of the soil. The pure blue gravel, from the bed of the river, is, however, more suitable to the mason's purpose, who will probably insist also that the house must be covered with rough-cast, otherwise it cannot be kept dry; if this advice be taken, the builder of taste will set about contriving such means as may enable him to come the nearest to the effect aimed at.</p>
<p>The supposed necessity of rough-cast to keep out rain in houses not built of hewn stone or brick, has tended greatly to injure English landscape, <pb n="82"/>and the neighbourhood of these Lakes especially, by furnishing such apt occasion for whitening buildings. That white should be a favourite colour for rural residences is natural for many reasons. The mere aspect of cleanliness and neatness thus given, not only to an individual house, but, where the practice is general, to the whole face of the country, produces moral associations so powerful, that, in many minds, they take place of all others. But what has already been said upon the subject of cottages, must have convinced men of feeling and imagination, that a human habitation of the humblest class may be rendered more deeply interesting to the affections, and far more pleasing to the eye, by other influences than a sprightly tone of colour spread over its outside. I do not, however, mean to deny, that a small white building, embowered in trees, may, in some situations, be a delightful and animating object -- in no way injurious to the landscape; but this only, where it sparkles from the midst of a thick shade, and in rare and solitary instances; especially if the country be itself rich, and pleasing, and abound with <pb n="83"/>grand forms. On the sides of the bleak and desolate moors, we are indeed thankful for the site of white cottages and white houses plentifully scattered, where, without these, perhaps everything would be cheerless: this is said, however, with hesitation, and with a wilful sacrifice of some higher enjoyments. But I have certainly seen such buildings glittering at sunrise, and in wandering lights, with no common pleasure. The continental traveller also will remember, that the convents hanging from the rocks of the Rhine, the Rhone, the Danube, or among the Appenines or the mountains of Spain, are not looked at with less complacency when, as is often the case, they happen to be of a brilliant white. But this is perhaps owing, in no small degree, to the contrast of that lively colour with the gloom of monastic life, and to the general want of rural residences of smiling and attractive appearance, in those countries.</p>
<p>The objections to white, as a colour, in large spots or masses in landscapes, especially in mountainous country, are insurmountable. In nature, pure white is scarcely ever found but in small objects, such as flowers; or in those <pb n="84"/>which are transitory, as the clouds, foam of rivers, and snow. Mr Gilpin, who notices this, has also recorded the just remark of Mr. Locke, of N--, that white destroys the <i>gradations</i> of distance; and, therefore, an object of pure white can scarcely ever be managed with good effect in landscape-painting. Five or six white houses, scattered over a valley, by their obtrusiveness, dot the surface, and divide it into triangles, or other mathermatical figures, haunting the eye, and disturbing that repose which might otherwise be perfect. I have seen a single white house materially impair the majesty of a mountain; cutting away, by a harsh separation, the whole of its base, below the point on which the house stood. Thus was the apparent size of the mountain reduced, not by the interposition of another object in a manner to call forth the imagination, which will give more than the eye loses; but what had been abstracted in this case was left visible; and the mountain appeared to take its beginning, or to rise from the line of the house, instead of its own natural base. But, if I may express my own individual feeling, it is after sunset, at the <pb n="85"/>coming on of twilight, that white objects are most to be complained of. The solemnity and quietness of nature at that time are always marred, and often destroyed by them. When the ground is covered by snow, they are of course inoffensive; and in moonshine they are always pleasing --it is a tone of light with which they accord; and the dimness of the scene is enlivened by an object at once conspicuous and cheerful. I will conclude this subject with noticing, that the cold, slaty colour, which many persons, who have heard the white condemned, have adopted in its stead, must be disapproved of for the reason already given. The flaring yellow runs into the opposite extreme, and is still more censurable. Upon the whole, the safety colour, for general use, is something between a cream and a dust-colour, commonly called stone-colour; --there are, among the Lakes, examples of this that need not be pointed out.</p>
<p>The principle taken as our guide, viz. that the house should be so formed, and of such apparent size and colour, as to admit of its being gently incorporated with the scenery of nature, should also be applied to the management of the grounds and plantations, and is here more urgently needed; for it is from abuses in this department, far more even than from the introduction of exotics in architecture (if the phrase may be used) that this country has suffered. Larch and fir plantations have been spread, nor merely with a view to profit, but in many instances for the sake of ornament. To those who plant for profit, and are thrusting every other tree out of the way to make room for their favourite, the larch, I would utter first a regret that they should have selected these lovely vales for their vegetable manufactory, when there is so much barren and irreclaimable land in the neighbouring moors, and in other parts of the Island, which might have been had for this purpose at a far cheaper rate. And I will also beg leave to represent to them, that they ought not to be carried away by flattering promises from the speedy growth of this tree; because in rich soils and sheltered situations, the wood, though it thrives fast, is full of sap, and of little value; and is, likewise, very subject to ravage from the attacks of <pb n="87"/>insects, and from blight. Accordingly, in Scotland, where planting is much better understood, and carried on upon an imcomparably larger scale than among us, good soil and sheltered situations are appropriated to the oak, the ash, and other deciduous trees; and the larch is now generally confined to barren and exposed ground. There the plant, which is a hardy one, is of slower growth; much less liable to injury; and the timber is of better quality. But the circumstances of many permit, and their taste leads them, to plant with little regard to profit; and there are others, less wealthy, who have such a lively feeling of the native beauty of these scenes, that they are laudably not unwilling to make some sacrifices to heighten it. Both these classes of persons, I would entreat to enquire of themselves wherein that beauty which they admire consists. They would then se that, after the feeling has been gratified that prompts us to gather round our dwelling a few flowers and shrubs, which, from the circumstance of their not being native, may, by their very looks, remind us that they owe their existence to our <pb n="88"/>hands, and their prosperity to our care; they will see that, after this material desire has been provided for, the course of all beyond has been predetermined by the spirit of the place. Before I proceed, I will remind those who are not satisfied with the restraint thus laid upon them, that they are liable to a charge of inconsistency, when they are so eager to change the face of that country, whose native attractions, by the act of erecting their habitations in it, they have so emphatically acknowledged. And surely there is not a single spot that would not have, if well managed, sufficient dignity to support itself, unaided by the productions of other climates, or by elaborate decorations which might be becoming elsewhere.</p>
<p>Having adverted to the feelings that justify the introduction of a few exotic plants, provided they be confined almost to the doors of the house, we may add, that a transition should be contrived without abruptness, from these foreigners to the rest of the shrubs, which ought to be of the kinds scattered by Nature through the woods --holly, broom, wild-rose, elder, dogberry, white and black thorn, &#38;c. either <pb n="89"/>these only, or such as are carefully selected in consequence of their uniting in form, and harmonising in colour with them, especially with respect to colour, when the tints are most diversified, as in autumn and spring. The various sorts of fruit-and-blossom-bearing trees usually found in orchards, to which may be added those of the woods, --namely, the wilding, black cherry tree, and wild cluster-cherry (here called heck-berry) may be happily admitted as an intermediate link between the shrubs and the forest trees; which last ought almost entirely to be such as are natives of the country. Of the birch, one of the most beautiful of the native trees, it may be noticed, that, in dry and rocky situations, it outstrips even the larch, which many persons are tempted to plant merely on account of the speed of its growth. Sycamore, and the Scotch fir (which, when it has room to spread out it arms, is a noble tree) may be placed with advantage near the house; for, from their massiveness, they unite well with buildings, and in some situations with rocks also; having, in their forms and apparent substances, the effect of something <pb n="90"/>intermediate betwixt the immoveableness and solidity of stone, and the spray and foliage of the lighter trees. If these general rules be just, what shall we say to whole acres of artificial shrubbery and exotic trees among rocks and dashing torrents, with their own wild wood in sight --where we have the whole contents of the nurseryman's catalogue jumbled together --colour at war with colour, and form with form --among the most peaceful subjects of Nature's kingdom every where in discord, distraction, and bewilderment! But this deformity, bad as it is, is not so obtrusive as the small patches and large tracts of larch plantations that are over-running the hill-sides. To justify our condemnation of these, let us again recur to Nature. The process, by which she forms woods and forests, is as follows. Seeds are scattered indiscriminately by winds, brought by waters, and dropped by birds. They perish, or produce, according to the soil and situation upon which they fall are situated to them; and under the same dependence, the seedling or sucker, if not cropped by animals, thrives, and the tree grows, sometimes single, taking its <pb n="91"/>own shape without constraint, but for the most part compelled to conform itself to some law imposed upon it by its neighbours. From low and sheltered places, vegetation travels upwards to the more exposed; and the young plants are protected, and to a certain degree fashioned, by those that have preceded them. The continous mass of foliage which would be thus produced, is broken by rocks, or by glades or open places, where the browzing of animals has prevented the growth of the wood. As vegetation ascends, the wind begins also to bear their part in the moulding the forms of the trees; but, thus mutually protected, trees, though not of the hardiest kind, are enabled to climb high up the mountains. Gradually, however, by the quality of the ground, and by increasing exposure, a stop is put to their ascent; the hardy trees only are left; those also, by little and little, give way, -- and a wild and irregular boundary is established, graceful in its outline, and never contemplated without some feeling more or less distinct of the powers of nature by which it is imposed.</p>
<p>Contrast the liberty that encourages, and the law that limits, this joint work of nature and time, with the disheartening necessities, restrictions, and disadvantages, under which the artificial planter must proceed, even he whom long observation and fine feeling have best qualified for his task. In the first place his trees, however well chosen and adapted to their several situations, must generally all start at the same time; and this necessity would of itself prevent that fine connectipn of parts, that sympathy and organization, if I may so express myself, which pervades the whole of a natural wood, and appears to the eye in its single trees, its masses of foliage, and their various colours when they are held up to view on the side of a mountain; or when spread over a valley, they are looked down upon from an eminence. It is then impossible, under any circumstances, for the artificial planter to rival the beauty of nature. But a moment's thought will show that, if ten thousand of this spiky tree, the larch, are stuck in at once upon the side of a hill, they can grow up into nothing but deformity; that, while they are suffered to stand, we shall look in vain for <pb n="93"/>any of those appearances which are the chief sources of beauty in a natural wood.</p>
<p>It must be acknowledged that the larch, till it has outgrown the size of a shrub, shows, when looked at singly, some elegance in form and appearance, especially in spring, decorated, as it then is, by the pink tassels of its blossoms; but, as a tree, it is less than any other pleasing; its branches (for <i>boughs</i> it has none) have no variety in the youth of the tree, and little dignity even when it attains its full growth; <i>leaves</i> it cannot be said to have, consequently neither affords the shade or shelter. In spring the large becomes green long before the native trees; and its green long before the native trees; and its green is so peculiar and vivid that, finding nothing to harmonize with it, wherever it comes forth, a disagreeable speck is produced. In summer, when all other trees are in their pride, it is of a dingy lifeless hue; in autumn of a spiritless unvaried yellow, and in winter it is still more lamentably distinguished from every other deciduous tree of the forest, for they seem only to sleep, but the larch appears absolutely dead. If an attempt be made to mingle thickets, or a certain proportion of other forest-trees, <pb n="94"/>with the larch, its horizontal branches intolerably cut them down as a scythe, or force them to spindle up to keep pace with it. The terminating spike, renders it impossible, that the several trees, where planted in numbers, should ever blend together so as to form a mass or masses of wood. Add thousands to tens of thousands, and the appearance is still the same -- a collection of separate individual trees, obstinately presenting themselves as such; and which, from whatever point they are looked at, if but seen, may be counted upon fingers. Sunshine, or shadow, has little power to adorn the surface of such a wood; and the trees not carrying up their their heads, the wind raises among them no magical undulations. It is indeed true, that, in countries where the larch is a native, and where without interruption it may sweep from valley to valley, and from hill to hill, a sublime image may be produced such a forest, in the same manner as by one composec of any other single tree, to the spreading of which no limits can be assigned. For sublimity will never be wanting, where the sense of innumerable multitude is lost in, and alternates <pb n="95"/>with, that of intense unity; and to the ready perception of this effect, similarity and almost identity of individual form and monotony of colour contribute. But this feeling is confined to the native immeasurable forest; no artificial plantation can give it.</p>
<p>The forgoing observations will, I hope, (as nothing has been condemned or recommended without a substantial reason) have some influence upon those who plant for ornament merely. To such as plant for profit, I have already spoken. Let me then entreat that the native deciduous trees may be left in complete possession of the lower ground; and that plantations of larch, if introduced at all, may be confined to the highest and most barren tracts. Interposition of rocks would there break the dreary uniformity of which we have been complaining; and the winds would take hold of the trees, and imprint upon their shapes a wildness congenial to their situation.</p>
<p>Having determined what kinds of trees must be wholly rejected or at least very sparingly used, by those who are unwilling to disfigure <pb n="96"/>the country; and having shown what kinds ought to be chosen; I should have given, if my limits had not already been overstepped, a few pratical rules for the manner in which trees ought to be disposed in planting. But to this subject I should attach little importance, if I could succeed in banishing such trees as introduce deformity, and could prevail upon the proprietor to confine himself either to those found in then native woods, or to such as accord with them. This is, indeed, the main point; for, much as these scenes have been injured by what has been taken from them --buildings, trees, and woods, either through negligence, necessity, avarice, or caprice -- it is not the removals, but the harsh <i>additions</i> that have been made, which are the worst grievance -- a standing and unavoidable annoyance. Often have I felt this distinction with mingled satisfaction and regret; for, if no positive deformity or discordance be substituted or superinduced, such is the benignity of nature that, take away from her beauty after beauty, and ornament after ornament, her appearance cannot be marred --the scars, if any <pb n="97"/>be left, will gradually disappear before a healing spirit; and what remains will still be soothing and pleasing. --</p>
<poem>
<line>"Many hearts deplored</line>
<line>The fate of those old trees; and oft with pain</line>
<line>The traveller at this day will stop and gaze</line>
<line>On wrongs which nature scarcely seems to heed:</line>
<line>For sheltered places, bosoms, nooks and bays,</line>
<line>And the pure mountains, and the gentle Tweed,</line>
<line>And the green silent pastures, yet remain."</line>
</poem>
<p>There are few ancient woods left in this part of England upon which such indiscriminate ravage as is here "deplored," could now be committed. But, out of the numerous copses, fine woods might in time be raised, probably without sacrifice of profit, by leaving, at the periodical fellings, a due proportion of the healthiest trees to grow up into timber. --This plan has fortunately, in many instances, been adopted; and they, who have set the example, are entitled to the thanks of all persons of taste. As to the management of planting with reasonable attention to the ornament, let the images of nature be your guide, and the whole secret lurks in a few words; thickets or underwoods --single <pb n="98"/>trees -- trees clustered or in groups -- groves -- unbroken woods, but with varied masses of foliage -- glades -- invisible or winding boundaries -- in rocky districts, a seemly proportion of rock left wholly bare, and other parts half hidden -- disagreeable objects concealed, and formal lines broken -- trees climbing up to the horizon, and, in some places, ascending from its sharp edge, in which they are rooted, with the whole body of the tree appearing to stand in the the clear sky -- in other parts, woods surmounted by rocks utterly bare and naked, which add to the sense of height as if vegetation could not thither be carried, and impress a feeling of duration, power of resistance, and security from change!</p>
<p>I have been induced to speak thus at length by a wish to preserve the native beauty of this delightful district, because still farther changes in its appearance must inevitably follow, from the change of inhabitants and owners which is rapidly taking place. --About the same time that strangers began to be attracted to the country, and to feel a desire to settle in it, the difficulty, that would have stood in the way of their procuring situations, was lessened by an <pb n="99"/>unfortunate alteration in the circumstances of the native peasantry, proceeding from a cause which then began to operate, and is now from a cause which then began to operate, and is now felt in every house. The family of each man, whether <i>estatesman</i> or farmer, formerly had a twofold support; first, the produce of his lands and flocks; and secondly, the profit drawn from the employment of women and children, as manufacturers; spinning their own wool in their own houses (work chiefly done in the winter season) and carrying it to market for sale. Hence, however numerous the children, the income of the family kept pace with its increase. But, by the invention and universal application of machinery, this second resource has been cut off; the gains being so far reduced, as not to be sought after but by a few aged persons disabled from other employment. Doubtless, the invention of machinery has not been to these people a pure loss; for the profits  arising from home-manufacturers operated as a strong temptation to choose that mode of labour in neglect of husbandry. They also participate in the general benefit which the island has derived from the increased value of produce <pb n="100"/>of land, brought about by the establishment of manufactories, and in the consequent quickening of agricultural industry. But this is far from making them amends; and now that home-manufacturers are nearly done away, women and children might, at many seasons of the year, employ themselves with advantage in the fields beyond what they are accustomed to do, yet still all possible exertion in this way cannot be rationally expected from persons whose agricultural knowledge is so confined, and above all where there must necessarily be so small a capital. The consequence, then, is -- that proprietors and farmers being no longer able to maintain themselves upon small farms, several are united in one, and the buildings go to decay, or are destroyed; and that the lands of the <i>estatesmen</i> being mortgaged and the owners constrained to part with them, they fall into the hands of wealthy purchasers, who in like manner unite and consolidate; and, if they wish to become residents, erect new mansions out of the ruins of the ancient cottages, whose little enclosures, with all the wild graces that grew out of them, disappear. The <pb n="100"/>feudal tenure under which the estates are held has indeed done something towards checking this influx of new settlers; but so strong is the inclination that these galling restraints are endured; and it is probable that in a few years the country on the margin of the Lakes will fall almost entirely into the possession of Gentry, either strangers or natives. It is then much to be wished, that a better taste should prevent unnecessary deviations from that path of simplicity and beauty along which, without design and unconsciously, their humble predecessors have moved. In this wish the author will be joined by persons of pure taste throughout the whole Island, who, by their visits (often repeated) to the Lakes in the North of England, testify that they deem the district a sort of national property, in which every man has a right and interest who has an eye to perceive and a heart to enjoy.</p>
<gap desc="double line"/>
</chap>
<pb n="102"/>
<chap title="MISCELLANEOUS OBSERVATIONS">
<head level="3" align="center">MISCELLANEOUS</head>
<head level="2" align="center">OBSERVATIONS.</head>
<p>MR. WEST, in his well-known Guide to the Lakes, recommends, as the best season for visiting this country, the interval from the beginning of June to the end of August; and, the two latter months being a time of vacation and leisure, it is almost exclusively in these that strangers resort hither. But that season is by no means the best; the colouring of the mountains and woods, unless where they are diversified by rocks, is of too unvaried a green, as a large portion of the Vallies is allotted to hay-grass, some want of variety is found there also. The meadows, however, are sufficiently enlivened after hay-making begins, which is much later than in the southern part of the Island. <pb n="103"/>A stonger objection is rainy weather, setting in sometimes at this period with a vigour, and continuing with a perseverance, that may remind the disappointed and dejected traveller of those deluges of rain, which fall among the Abyssinian Mountains for the annual supply of the Nile. The months of September and October (particularly October) are generally attended with much finer weather; and the scenery is the, beyond comparison, more diversified, more splendid, and beautiful; but, on the other hand, short days prevent long excursions, and sharp and chill gales an unfavourable to parties of pleasure out of doors. Nevertheless, to the sincere admirer of Nature, who is in good health and spirits, and at liberty to make a choice, the six weeks following the 1st of September may be recommended in preference to July and August. For there is no inconveniece arising from the season which, to such a person, would not be amply recompensed by the <i>autumnal</i> appearance of any of the more retired Vallies, into which discordant plantation, and unsuitable buildings have not yet found entrance. --In such spots, at this <pb n="104"/>season, there is an admirable compass and proportion of natural harmony in colour, through the whole scale of objects; -- in the tender green of the after-grass upon the meadows interspersed with islands of grey or mossy rock, crowned by shrubs and trees; in the irregular inclosures of standing corn or stubble-fields in the manner broken; in the mountain sides glowing with fern of divers colours; in the calm blue Lakes and River-pools; and in the foliage of the trees, through all the tints of Autumn, from the pale and brilliant yellow of the birch and ash, to the deep greens of the unfaded oak and alder, and of the ivy upon the rocks, upon the trees, and the cottages. Yet, as most travellers are either stinted, or stine themselves, for time, I would recommend the space between the middle or last week in May and the middle or last week of June, as affording best combination of long days, fine weather, and variety of impressions. Few of the native trees are then in full leaf; but, for whatever may be wanting in depth of shade, more than an equivalent will be found in the diversity of foliage, in the blossoms of the fruit-and-berry-bearing <pb n="105"/>trees which abound in the woods, and in the golden flowers of the broom and other shrubs, with which many of the copses are interveined. In those woods, also, and on those mountain-sides which have a northern aspect, and in the deep dells, many of the spring-flowers still linger; while the open and sunny places are stocked with the flowers of approaching summer. And, besides, is not an exquisite pleasure still untasted by him who has not heard the choir of Linnets and Thrushes chaunting their love-songs in the copses, woods, and hedgerows, of a mountainous country; safe from the birds of prey, which build in the inaccessible crags, and are at all hours seen or heard wheeling about in the air? The number of those formidable creatures is probably the cause why, in the <i>narrow</i> vallies, there are no Sky-larks; as the Destroyer would be enabled to dart upon them from the near and surrounding crags, before they could descend to their ground-nests for protection. It is not often that Nightningales resort to these Vales; but almost all the other tribes of our English<pb n="106"/> warblers are numerous; and their notes, when listened to by the side of broad still waters, or when heard in unison with the murmuring of mountain-brooks, have the compass of their power enlarged accordingly. There is also an imaginative influence in the voice of the Cuckoo, when the voice has taken possession of a deep mountain valley, very different from any thing which can be excited by the same sound in a falat country. Nor must a circumstance be omitted which here renders the close of Spring especially interesting; I mean the practice of bringing down the ewes from the mountains to yean in the vallies and enclosed grounds. The herbage being thus cropped as it springs, <i>that</i> would otherwise have lasted little more than a fortnight, is prolonged in the pastures and meadows for many weeks; while they are farther enlivened by the multitude of lambs bleating and skipping about. These sportive creatures, as they gather strength, are turned out upon the open mountains, and with their slender limbs, their snow-white colour, and<pb n="107"/> their wild and light motions, beautifully accord or contrast with the rocks and lawns, upon which they must now begin to seek their food. And last, but not least, at this time the traveller will be sure of room and comfortable accommodation, even in the smaller inns. I am aware that few of those, who may be inclined to profit by this recommendation will be able to do so, as the time and manner of an excursion of this kind is mostly regulated by circumstances which prevent an entire freedom of choice. It will therefore be more pleasant to observe, that, though the months of July and August are liable to many objections, yet it often happens that the weather, at this time, is not more wet and stormy than they, who are really capable of enjoying the sublime forms of Nature of their utmost sublimity, would desire. For no Traveller, provided he be in good health and with any command of time, would have a just privilege to visit such scenes, if he could grudge the price of a little confinement among them or interruption of his journey for the sight or sound of a storm coming on or <pb n="108"/>clearing away. Insensible must be he who would not congratulate himself upon the bold bursts of sunshine, the descending vapours, wandering lights and shadows, and the invigorated torrents and water-falls, with which broken weather, in a mountainous region, is accompanied. At such time there is no cause to complain, either of the monotony of midsummer colouring or the glaring atmosphere of long, cloudless, and hot days.</p>
<p>Thus far respecting the most eligible season for visiting this country. As to the order in which objects are best seen -- a Lake being composed of water flowing from higher grounds, and expanding itself till its receptacle is filled to the brim, -- it follows, that it will appear to most advantage when approached from its outlet, especially if the Lake be in a mountainous country; for, by this way of approach, the traveller faces the grander features of the scene, and is gradually conducted into its most sublime recesses. Now, every one knows, that from amenity and beauty the transition to sublimith is easy and favourable; but the reverse <pb n="109"/>is not so; for, after the faculties have been elevated, they are indisposed to humbler excitement. <ptr target="n5"/></p>
<note id="n5">The only instances to which the foregoing observations do not apply, are Derwent-water and Loweswater. Derwent is distinguished from all the other Lakes by being <i>surrounded</i> with sublimity: the fantastic mountains of Borrowdale to the south, the solitary majesty of Skiddaw to the north, the bold Steeps of Wallow-crag and Lodore to the east, and to the west the cluttering mountains of Newlands. Loweswater is tame at the head, but towards its outlet has a magnificent assemblage of mountains. Yet as far as respects the formation of such receptacles, the general observation holds good, neither Derwent nor Loweswater derive any supplies from the streams of those mountains that dignify the landscape towards the outlets.</note>
<p>It is not likely that a mountain will be ascended without disappointment if a wide range of prospect be the object, unless either the summit be reached before sun-rise, of the visitant remain there until the time of sun-set, and afterwards. The precipitous sides of the mountain, and the neighbouring summits, may be seen with effect under any atmosphere with allows them to be seen at all; he <i>he</i> is the most fortunate adventure who chances to be involved in vapours which open and let in an extent of <pb n="110"/>country partially, or, dispersing suddenly, reveal the whole region from centre to circumference.</p>
<p>A stranger to a mountainous country may not be aware that his walk in the early morning, ought to be taken on the eastern side of the vale, otherwise he will lose the morning light, first touching the tops, and thence creeping down the sides of the opposite hills, as the sun ascends, or he may go to some central eminence, commanding both the shadows from the eastern, and the lights upon the western, mountains. But, if the horizon line in the east be low, the western side may be taken for the sake of the reflections, upon the water, of light from the rising sun. In the evening, for the reasons, the contrary course should be taken.</p>
<p>After all, it is upon the <i>mind</i> which a Traveller brings along with him that his acquisitions, whether of pleasure or profit, must principally depend. --May I be allowed a few words upon this subject?</p>
<p>Nothing is more injurious to genuine feeling than the practice of hastily and ungraciously depreciating the face of one country by comparing it with that of another. True it is, Qui <i>bene</i><pb n="111"/> distinguit bene <i>docet;</i> yet fastidiousness is a wretched travelling companion; and the best guide to which, in matters of taste, we can entrust ourselves, is a disposition to be pleased. For example, if a Traveller be among the Alps, let him surrender up his mind to the fury of the gigantic torrents, and take delight in the contemplation of their almost irresistable violence, without complaining of the monotony of their foaming course, or being disgusted with the muddiness of the water -- apparent even where it is violently agitated. In Cumberland and Westmorland, let not the comparative weakness of the streams prevent him from sypathising with such impetuosity as they possess; and, making the most of present objects, let him, as he justly may do, observe with admiration the unrivalled brilliancy of the water, and that variety of motion, mood, and character, that arises out of the want of those resources by which the power of the streams in the Alps is supported. -- Again, with respect to the mountains; though these are comparatively of diminutive size, though there is little of perpetual snow, and no voice of summer-avalanches is <pb n="112"/>heard among them; and though traces left by the ravage of the elements are here comparatively rare and unimpressive, yet out of this very deficiency proceeds a sense of stability and permanence that is, to many minds, more grateful --</p>
<poem>
<line>"While the coarse rushes to the sweeping breeze</line>
<line>Sigh forth their ancient melodies."</line>
</poem>
<p>Among the Alps are a few places that do not preclude this feeling of tranquil sublimity. Havoc, and ruin, and desolation, and encroachment, are every where more or less obtruded; and it is difficult, notwithstanding the naked loftiness of the <i>Pikes</i>, and the snow-capped summits of the <i>Mounts</i>, to escape from the depressing sensation that the whole are in a rapid process of dissolution, and, were it not that the destructive agency must abate as the heights diminish, would, in time to come, be levelled with the plains. Nevertheless I would relish to the utmost the demonstrations of every species of power at work to effect such changes.</p>
<p>From these general views let us descend a moment to detail. A stranger to mountain-scenery<pb n="113"/> naturally on his first arrival looks out of sublimity in every object that admits of it; and is almost always disappointed. For this disappointment there exists, I believe, no general preventive; nor is it desirable that there should. But, with regard to one class of objects, there is a point in which injurious expectations may be easily corrected. It is generally supposed that waterfalls are scarcely worth being looked at except after much rain, and that, the more swoln the stream, the more fortunate the spectator; but this is true only of large cataracts with sublime accompaniments; and not even of these without some drawbacks. The principal charm of the smaller waterfalls or cascades, consists in certain proportions of form and affinities of colour, among the component parts of the scene; and in the contrast maintained between the falling water and that which is apparently at rest, or rather settling gradually into quiet, in the pool below. The beauty of such a scene, where there is naturally so much agitation, is also heightened, in a peculiar manner, by the <i>glimmering</i>, and, towards the verge of the pool, by the <i>steady</i>, reflection of the surrounding images.<pb n="114"/> Now, all those delicate distinctions are destroyed by heavy floods, and the whole stream rushes along in foam and tumultuous confusion. A happy proportion of component parts is indeed noticeable among the landscapes of the North of England; and, in this characteristic essential to a perfect picture, they surpass the scenes of Scotland, and, in a still greater degree, those of Switzerland.</p>
<p>As a resident among the Lakes, I frequently hear the scenery of this country compared with that of the Alps; and therefore a few words shall be added to what has been incidentally said upon that subject.</p>
<p>If we could recall, to this region of lakes, the native pine-forests, with which many hundred years ago a large portion of the heights was covered, then, during spring and autumn, it might frequently, with much propriety, be compared to Switzerland, -- the elements of the landscape would be the same -- one country representing the other in miniature. Villages, chruches, rural seats, bridges and roads; green meadows and arable grounds, with their various produce, and deciduous woods of diversified <pb n="115"/>foliage which occupy the vales and lower regions of the mountains, would, as in Switzerland, be divided by dark forests from ridges and round-topped heights covered with snow, and from pikes and sharp declivities imperfectly arrayed in the same glittering mantle: and the resemblance would still be more perfect on those days when vapours resting upon, and floating around the summits, leave the elevation of the mountains less dependent upon the eye than on the imagination. But the pine-forests have wholly disappeared; and only during late Spring and early Autumn is realized here that assemblage of the imagery of different seasons, which is exhibited through the whole summer among the Alps -- winter in the distance, -- and warmth, leafy woods, verdure and fertility at hand, -- and widely diffused.</p>
<p>Striking, then, from among the permanent materials of the landscape, that stage of vegetation which is occupied by pine-forests, and, above that, the perennial snows, we have mountains, the highest of which little exceed 3000 feet, while some of the Alps do not fall short of 14,000 or 15,000, and 8,000 or 10,000 is not an uncommon <pb n="116"/>elevation. Our tracts of wood and water are almost as diminutive in comparison; therefore, as far as sublimity is dependent upon absolute bulk or height, and atmospherical influence in connection with these, it is obvious, that there can be no rivalship. But a short residence among the British Mountains will furnish abundant proof, that, after a certain point, the sense of sublimity depends more upon form and relation to objects to each other than upon their actual magnitude; and, that an elevation of 3000 feet is sufficient to call forth in the most impressive degree the creative and magnifying powers of the atmosphere; so that, on the score even of sublimity, the superiority of the Alps is be no means so great as might hastily be inferred; -- and, as to the <i>beauty</i> of the lower regions of the Swiss mountains, it is noticable -- that, as they are all regularly mown, their surface has nothing of the mellow tone and variety of hues by which mountain turf, that is never touched by the scythe, is distinguished. On the smooth and steep slopes of the Swiss hills, these plots of verdure do indeed make a lively contrast of colour, with the dark green pine-groves that <pb n="117"/>define them, and among which, they run in endless variety of shapes -- but this is most pleasing <i>at first sight;</i> the permanent gratification of the eye requires finer gradations of tone, and a more delicate blending of hues into each other. Besides, it is only in Spring and late Autumn that cattle animate by their presence the Swiss lawns; and, though the pastures of the higher regions where they feed during the Summer are left in their natural state of flowery herbage, those pastures are so remote, that their texture and colour are of no consequence in the composition of any picture in which a lake of the Vales is a feature. Yet in those lofty regions, how vegetation is invigorated by the genial climate of that country! Among the luxuriant flowers there met with, groves, or forests, if I may so call them, of Monks-hood are frequently seen; the plant of deep, rich blue, and as tall as in our gardens; and this at an elevation where, in Cumberland, Icelandic moss would only be found, or the stony summits be utterly bare.</p>
<p>We have, then, for the colouring of Switzerland, principally a vivid green herbage, black <pb n="118"/>woods, and dazzling snows, presented in masses with a grandeur to which no one can be insensible; but not often graduated by Nature into soothing harmony, and so ill suited to the pencil, that though abundance of good subjects may there be found, they are not such as can be deemed <i>characteristic</i> of the country; nor is this unfitness, though many of them in some points of view the noblest that can be conceived, are apt to run into spikes and needles, and present a jagged outline which has a mean effect, transferred to canvas. This must have been felt by the ancient masters; for, if I am not mistaken, they have not left a single landscape, the materials of which are taken from the <i>peculiar</i> features of the Alps; yet Titian passed his life almost in their neighbourhood; the Poussins and Claude must have been well acquainted with their aspects; and several admirable painters, as Tibaldi and Luino, were born among the Italian Alps. A few experiments have lately been made by English-men, but they only prove that courage, skill, <pb n="119"/>and judgment, may surmount any obstacles; and that it may be safely affirmed, that they who have done best in this bold adventure, will be the least likely to repeat the attempt. But, though our scenes are better suited to painting than those of the Alps, I should be sorry to contemplate either country in reference to that art, further than as its fitness or unfitness for the pencil renders it more or less pleasing to the eye of the spectator, who has learned to observer and feel, chiefly from Nature herself.</p>
<note id="n6">The greatest variety of trees is found in the Valais.</note>
<p>Deeming the points in which Alpine imagery is superior to British too obvious to be insisted upon, I will observe that the deciduous woods, though in many places unapproachable by the axe, and triumphing in the pomp and prodigality of Nature, have, in general<ptr target="n6"/>, neither the variety nor beauty which would exist in those of the Mountains of Britain, if left to themselves. Magnificent walnut-trees grow upon the plains of Switzerland; and fine trees, of that species, are found scattered over the hill-sides: birches also grow here and there, in luxuriant beauty; <pb n="120"/> but neither these, nor oaks, are ever a prevailing tree, nor can even be said to be common; and the oaks, as far as I had an opportunity of observing, are greatly inferior to those of Britain. Among the interior vallies, the proportion of beeches and pines is so great that oUther trees are scarcely noticeable; and surely such woods are at all seasons much less agreeable than that rich and harmonious distribution of oak, ash, elm, birch, and alder, that formerly clothed the sides of Snowdon and Helvellyn; and of which no mean remains still survive at the head of Ullswater. On the Italian side of the Alps, chestnut and walnut-trees grow to a considerable height on the mountains; but, even there, the foliage is not equal in beauty to the natural product of this climate.</p>
<p>As my object is to reconcile a Briton to the scenery of his own country, though not at the expence of truth, I am not afraid of asserting that in many points of view, our LAKES also are much more interesting than those of the Alps; first, as is implied above, from being more happily proportioned to the other features of the landscape, and next, both as being infinitely <pb n="121"/>more pellucid, and less subject to agitation from the winds. Como (which may perhaps be styled the King of Lakes, as Lugano is certainly the Queen) is disturbed by a periodical wind blowing <i>from</i> the head in the morning, and <i>towards</i> it in the afternoon. The magnificent Lake of the four Cantons, especially its noblest division, called the Lake of Uri, is not only much agitated by winds, but in the night time is disturbed from the bottom, as I was told, and indeed as I witnessed, without any apparent commotion in the air; and, when at rest, the water is not pure to the eye, but of a heavy green hue, --as is that of the other lakes apparently, according to the degree in which they are fed by melted snows. If the Lake of Geneva furnishes an exception, this is probably owing to its vast extent which allows the water to deposit its impurities. The water of the English Lakes, on the contrary, being of a crystalline clearness, the reflections of the surrounding hills are frequently so lively, that it is scarcely possible to distinguish the point where the real object terminates, and its unsubstantial duplicate begins. The lower part of the Lake of Geneva, (from its narrowness, <pb n="122"/>must be much less subject to agitation than the higher divisions, and, as the water is clearer than that of the other Swiss Lakes, it may exhibit this appearance, though it is not possible in an equal degree. During two comprehensive Tours among the Alps, I did not observe, except on one of the smaller Lakes, between Lugano and Ponte Tresa, a single instance of those beautiful repetitions of the surrounding scenery in the bosom of the water, which are so frequently seen here: not to speak of the fine, dazzling trembling net-work, breezy motions, and streaks and circles of intermingled smooth and rippled water, which make the surface of our Lakes a field of endless variety. But among the Alps where every thing tends to the grand and the sublime, in surfaces as well as in forms, if the Lakes do not court the placid reflections of land objects, those of first-rate magnitude make compensation, in some degree, by exhibiting those ever-changing fields of green, blue, and purple shadows or lights, (one scarcely knows which to name them) that call to mind a sea-prospect contemplated from a lofty cliff.</p>
<pb n="123"/>
<p>The subject of torrents and water falls has already been touched upon; but it may be added that the perpetual accompaniment of snow upon the higher regions, takes much from the effect of foaming white streams; while, from their frequency, they obstruct in some degree each other's influence upon the mind of the spectator; and, in all cases, the effect of an individual cataract, excepting the great Fall of the Rhine at Schaffhausen, is diminished by the general fury of the stream of which it is a part.</p>
<p>Recurring to the reflexions from still water, I will describe a similar phenomenon of this kind of which I was an eye-witness.</p>
<p>Walking by the side of Ullswater upon a calm September morning, I saw, deep within the bosom of the lake, a magnificent Castle, with towers and battlements; nothing could be more distinct than the whole edifice; --after gazing with delight upon it for some time, as upon a work of enchantment, I could not but regret that my previous knowledge of the place enabled me to account for the appearance. It was in fact the reflexion of a pleasure-house called Lyulph's Tower -- the towers and battlements <pb n="124"/>magnified and so much changed in shape as not to be immediately recognized. In the meanwhile, the pleasure-house itself was altogether hidden from my view by a body of vapour stretching over it and along the hill-side on which it stands, but not so as to have intercepted its communication with the lake; and hence this novel anf most impressive object, which if I had been a stranger to the spot, would, from its being inexplicable, have long detained my mind in a state of pleasing astonishment.</p>
<p>An appearance of this kind, acting upon the credulity of early ages, may have given birth to the stories of subaqueous palaces, gardens, and pleasure-grounds -- the brilliant ornaments of Romance.</p>
<p>With this <i>inverted</i> scene I will couple a much more extraordinary phenomenon, which may shew how other elegant fancies may have had their origin, less in invention than in the actual processes of Nature.</p>
<p>About eleven o'clock on the forenoon of a winter's day, coming suddenly, in company of a friend, into view of the Lake of Grasmere, we <pb n="125"/>were alarmed by the sight of a newly-created Island; the transitory thought of the moment was, that it had been produced by an earthquake or some other convulsion of nature. Recovering from the alarm, which was greater than the reader can possibly sympathize with, but which was shared to its full extent by my companion, we proceeded to examine the object before us. The elevation of this new island exceeded considerably that of the old one, its neighbour; it was likewise larger in circumference, comprehending a space of about five acres; its surface rocky, speckled with snow, and sprinkled over with birch-trees; it was divided towards the south from the other island by a narrow frith, and in like manner from the northern shore of the lake: on the east and west it was separated from the shore by a much larger space of smooth water.</p>
<p>Marvellous was the illusion! Comparing the new with the old Island, the surface of which is soft, green, and unvaried, I do not scruple to say that, as an object of sight, it was much the more distinct. "How little faith." we exclaimed, "is due to one sense, unless its evidence <pb n="126"/> be confirmed by some of its fellows! What Stranger could possibly be persuaded that this, which we know to be an unsubstantial mockery, is really so; and that there exists only a single Island on this beautiful Lake?" At length the appearance underwent a gradual transmutation; it lost its prominence and passes into a glimmering and dim <i>inversion</i>, and then totally disappeared; -- leaving behind it a clear open area of ice of the same dimensions. We now perceived that this bed of ice, which was thinly suffused with water, had produced the illusion, by reflecting and refracting (as persons skilled in optics would no doubt easily explain) a rocky and woody section of the opposite mountain named Silver How.</p>
<p>Having dwelt so much upon the beauty of pure and still water, and pointed out the advantage which the Lakes of the North of England have in this particular over those of the Alps, it would be injustice not to advert to the sublimity that must be given to Alpine scenes, by the agitations to which these vast bodies of diffused water are there subject. I have witnessed many tremendous thunder-storms among the Alps, and the most <pb n="127"/>glorious effects of light and shadow; but I have never happened to be present when any Lake was agitated by those hurricanes which I imagine must often torment them. If the commotions be at all proportionable to the expanse and depth of the waters and the height of the surrounding mountains, then, if I may judge from what is frequently seen here, the exhibition must be awful and astonishing. -- On this day, March 30. 1822, the winds have been acting upon the small Lake of Rydal, as if they had received command to carry its waters from their bed into the sky; the white billows in different quarters disappeared under clouds, or rather drifts, of spray, that were whirled along and up into the air by scouring winds, charging each other in squadrons in every direction, upon the Lake. The spray, having been hurried aloft till it lost is consistency and whiteness, was driven along the mountain-tops like flying showers that vanish in the distance. Frequently an eddying wind scooped the waters out of the basin, and forced them upwards in the very shape of an Icelandic Geyser, or boiling fountain, to the height of 800 or 900 feet.</p>
<pb n="128"/>
<p>This small Mere of Rydal, from its position, is subject in a peculiar degree to these commotions. The present season, however, is unusually stormy; -- great numbers of fish, two of them not less than 12 pounds weight, were a few days ago cast on the shores of Derwent-water by the force of the waves.</p>
<p>Lest, in the foregoing comparative estimate, I should be suspected of partiality to my native mountains, I will support my general opinion by the authority of Mr. West, whose Guide to the Lakes has been eminently servicable to the tourist for nearly 50 years. The Author, a Roman Catholic Clergyman, had passed much time abroad, and was well acquainted with the scenery of the Continent. He thus expresses himself: "They who intend to make the Continental tour should begin here; as it will give, in miniature, an idea of what they are to meet with there, in traversing the Alps and Appenines; to which our northern mountains are not inferior in beauty of line, or variety of summit, number of lakes, and transparency of water; not in colouring of rock, or softness of turf; but in height and extent only. The <pb n="129"/>mountains here are all accessible to the summit, and furnish prospects no less suprizing, and with more variety, than the Alps themselves. The tops of the highest Alps are inaccessible, being covered with everlasting snow, which commencing at regular heights above the cultivated tracts, or wooded and verdant sides, form indeed the highest contrast in nature. For there may be seen all the variety of climate in one view. To this, however, we oppose the sight of the ocean, from the summmits of all the higher mountains, as it appears intersected with promontories, decorated with islands, and animated with navigation." -- West's <i>Guide</i>, p.5.</p>
<p>It was my intention, several years ago, to describe a regular tour through this country. taking the different scenes in the most favourable order; but after some progress had been made in the work it was abandoned from a conviction, that, if well executed, it would lessen the pleasure of the Traveller by anticipation, and, if the contrary, it would only mislead him. The Reader may not however be displeased with the following extract from a letter to a Friend, giving an account of a visit to a summit of one <pb n="130"/>of the highest of these mountains; of which I am reminded by the observations of Mr. West, and by reviewing what has been said of this district in comparison with the Alps.</p>
<p>Having left Rossthwaite in Borrowdale, on a bright morning in the first week of October, we ascended from Seathwaite to the top of the ridge, called Ash-course, and thence beheld three distinct views. On one side, the continuous Vale of Borrowdale, Keswick, and Basenthwaite, -- with Skiddaw, Helvellyn, Saddleback, and numerous other mountains, -- and, in the distance, the Solway Frith and the Mountains of Scotland, On the other side, and below us, the Langdale Pikes -- their own vale  below <i>them;</i> -- Windermere, -- and, far beyond Windermere, Ingleborough in Yorkshire. But how shall I speak of the deliciousness of the third prospect! At this time, <i>that</i> was most favoured by sunshine and shade. The green Vale of Esk -- deep and green, with its glittering serpent stream, was below us; and, on we looked to the Mountains near the Sea -- Black Comb pre-eminent, -- and, still beyond, to the Sea itself in dazzling brightness. Turning round <pb n="131"/>we saw the Mountains of Wastdale in tumult; to our right, Great Gavel, the loftiest, a distinct and <i>huge</i> form, though the middle of the mountain was, to our eyes, as its base.</p>
<p>We had attained the object of this journey; but our ambition now mounted higher. We saw the summit of Scaw-fell, apparently very near to us; and we shaped our course towards it; but, discovering that it could not be reached without first making a considerable descent, we resolved, instead, to aim at another point of the same mountain, called the <i>Pikes</i>, which I have since found has been estimated as higher than the summit bearing the name of Scawfell Head, where the Stone Man is built.</p>
<p>The sun had never once been overshadowed by a cloud during the whole of our progress from the centre of Borrowdale: -- on the summit of the Pike, which we gained after much toil though without difficulty, there was not a breath of air to stir even the papers containing our refreshment, as they lay spread out upon a rock. The stillness seemed to not be of this world: -- we paused, and kept silence to listen; and no sound could be heard: the Scawfell <pb n="132"/>Cataracts were voiceless to us; and there was not an insect to hum in the air. The vales which we had seen from Ash-course lay yet in view; and, side by side with Eskdale, we now saw the sister Vale of Donnerdale terminated by the Duddon Sands. But the majesty of the mountains below, and close to us, is not to be conceived. We now beheld the whole mass of Great Gavel from its base, -- the Den of Wastdale at our feet -- a gulph immeasurable: Grasmire and the other mountains of Crummock -- Ennerdale and its mountains; and the Sea beyond! Gladly would we have tempered our beverage (for there was no spring or well near us) with such a supply of delicious water as we might have procured, had we been on the rival summit of Great Gavel; for on its highest point is a small triangular receptacle of water in the native rock, which, the shepherds say, is never dry. There, we might have slaked our thirst plenteously with a pure and celestial beverage, for the cup or basin, it appears, has no other feeder than the dews of heaven, the showers, the vapours, the hoar frost, and the spotless snow.</p>
<pb n="133"/>
<p>while we were gazing around, "Look," I exclaimed, "at yon ship upon the glittering sea!" "Is it a Ship?" replied our Shepherd-guide. "It can be nothing else," interposed my companion; "I cannot be mistaken, I am so accustomed to the appearance of Ships at sea." The Guide dropped the argument; but, before a minute was gone, he quietly said, "Now look at your Ship; it is changed into a Horse." So indeed it was, -- a horse with a gallant neck and head. We laughed heartily; and, I hope, when again inclined to be positive, I may remember the Ship and the Horse upon the glittering Sea; and the calm confidence, yet submissiveness, of our wise Man of the Mountains, who certainly had more knowledge of clouds than we, whatever might be our knowledge of ships.</p>
<p>I know not how long we might have remained on the summit of the Pike, without thought of moving, had not our guide warned us that we must not linger; for a storm was coming. We looked in vain to espy signs of it, Mountains, vales, and sea were touched with the clear light of the sun. "It is <pb n="134"/>there," he said, pointing to the sea beyond Whitehaven, and there we perceived a light vapour unnoticeable but by a Shepherd accustomed to watch all mountain bodings. We gazed around again, and yet again, unwilling to lose the remembrance of what lay before us in that lofty solitude; and then prepared to depart. Meanwhile the air changed to cold, and we saw that tiny vapour swelled into mighty masses of cloud which came boiling over the mountains. Great Gavel, Helvellyn, and Skiddaw, were wrapped in storm; yet Langdale, and the mountains in that quarter, remained all bright in sunshine. Soon the storm reached us; we sheltered under a crag; and almost as rapidly as it had come it passed away, and left us free to observe the struggles of gloom and sunshine in other quarters. Langdale now had its share, and the Pikes of Langdale were decorated by two splendid Rainbows. Before we again reached Ash-course every cloud had vanished from every summit.</p>
<p>I ought to have mentioned that round the top of Scawfell PIKE not a blade of grass is to <pb n="135"/>be seen. A few cushions or tufts of moss, parched and brown, appear between the huge blocks and stones that lie in heaps on all sides to a great distance, like skeletons or bones of the earth not needed at the creation, and there left to be covered with never-dying lichens, which the clouds and dews nourish; and adorn with colours of vivid and exquisite beauty. Flowers, the most brilliant feathers, and even gems, scarcely surpass in colouring some of those masses of stone, which no human eye beholds, except the Shepherd or Traveller be led thither by curiosity: and how seldom must this happen! For the other Eminence is the one visited by the adventurous Traveller; and the Shepherd has no inducement to ascend the PIKE in quest of his Sheep; for no food is <i>there</i> to tempt them.</p>
<p>We certainly were singularly favoured in the weather; for when we were seated on the summit, our Conductor, turning his eyes thoughtfully round, said, "I do not know that in my whole life, I was ever, at any season of the year, so high upon the mountains on so calm a day." (It was the 7th of October.) Afterwards we had the storm, which exhibited the grandeur of <pb n="136"/>the earth and heavens commingled; yet without terror. We knew that it would pass away; -- for so our prophetic Guide had assured us.</p>
<p>Before we reached Seathwaite in Borrowdale, a few stars had appeared, and we pursued our way down the Vale, to Rossthwaite, by moonlight.</p>
<pb n="137"/>
</chap>
<chap title="Directions and Information for the Tourist">
<head level="2" align="center">DIRECTIONS AND INFORMATION</head>
<head level="3" align="center">FOR</head>
<head level="2" align="center">THE TOURIST.</head>
<gap desc="double line"/>
<p>A BRIEF notice shall here be given of particulars in the several Vales of which the Country is composed. We will begin, as before, with</p>
<head level="3" align="center">WINDERMERE.</head>
<note id="n7">This Lake has seventeen Islands. Among those that lie near the largest, formerly called "Great Holm," may be noticed "Lady Holm," so called from the Virgin who had formerly a Chapel or Oratory there. On the road from Kendal to the Great-boat, might lately, and perhaps may still be seen, the ruins of the Holy Cross; a place where the Pilgrims to this beautifully situated shrine, must have been in the habit of offering up their devotions. -- Two other of these Islands are named from the lily of the valley, which grows there in profusion.</note>
<note id="n8">Mr. Green's Guide to the Lakes in two vols. contains a complete Magazine of minute and accurate information of this kind, with the names of mountains, streams, &#38;c.</note>
<p>This Lake is approached, by Travellers from the South, about the middle of its eastern side, at Bowness or by Orrest-head. The lower part is rarely visited, but as many interesting points of view, especially at Storr's Hall and at Fellfort, where the Coniston Mountains peer nobly over the western barrier, which is elsewhere along the whole Lake is comparatively tame. To one also who has ascended the hill from Grathwaite <pb n="138"/>on the western side, the promontory called Rawlinson's Nab, Storr's Hall, and the Troutbeck Mountains, about sunset, make a splendid landscape. The view from the Pleasure-house of the Station near the Ferry has suffered much from Larch plantations, and from other causes. Windermere ought to be seen both from its shores and from its surface. None of the other Lakes unfold so many fresh beauties to him who sails upon them. This is owing to its greater size, to the islands<ptr target="n7"/>, and its having <i>two</i> vales at the head, with their accompanying mountains of nearly equal dignity. Nor can the grandeur of these two terminations be seen at the same time from any one point, except from the bosom of the Lake. The Islands may be explored at any time of day; but one bright unruffled <pb n="139"/>evening, must, if possible, be set apart for the splendour, the stillness, and solemnity of a three hours' voyage upon the division of the Lake, not omitting, towards the end of the excursion, to quite the expanse of water, and peep into the close and calm River at the head; which, in its quiet character, at such a time, appears rather like an overflow of the peaceful Lake itself, than to have any more immediate connection with the rough mountains whence it has descended, or the turbulent torrents by which it is supplied. Many persons content themselves with what they see of Windermere during their progress in a boat from Bowness to the head of the Lake, walking thence to Ambleside. But the whole road of from Bowness is rich in diversity of pleasing or grand scenery; there is scarcely a field on the road side; there is scarcely a field on the road side, which, if entered, would not give to the landscape some additional charm. Low-wood Inn, a mile from the head of Windermere, is a pleasant halting-place; and the fields above it, and the lane that leads to Troutbeck, present beautiful views towards each extremity of the Lake. From this place and from Ambleside, rides may be taken in numerous <pb n="140"/>directions, and the interesting walks are inexhaustible<ptr target="n8"/>; a few out of the main road may be particularized; -- the lane that leads towards Skelgill; the ride, or walk by Rothay Bridge, and up the stream under Loughrigg Fell, continued on the western side of Rydal Lake, and thence round the church of Grasmere: or, turning round Loughrigg Fell by Loughrigg Tarn and the River Brathay, back to Ambleside. From Ambleside is a charming excursion, by Skelwith-fold an Colwith-force up Little Langdale, Blea Tarn, Dungeon-ghyll waterfall (if there be time) and down Great Langdale. Stockghyll-force and Rydal waterfalls, every one hears of. In addition to the two Streams at its head with their Vales, Windermere communicates with two lateral Vales, that of Troutbeck, distinguished by the mountains at its head, by picturesque remains of cottage architecture, and by fine fore-grounds formed by the steep and winding banks of the river. The other, the vale <pb n="141"/>Hawkshead, is seen to most advantage by the approach from the ferry over Windermere -- the Lake of Esthwaite. Hawkshead Church, and the cone of Langdale Pike in the distance. There are delightful walks in that part of Grasmere, called Easefale; and the Vale is advantageously seen from Butterlip How. As this point is four miles on the way to Keswick, it may here be mentioned, that, from the high road between Keswick and Ambleside, which passes along the eastern side of the several Lakes of Rydal, Grasmere, and part of Wythburn, these lakes are not seen to the best advantage, particularly Rydal, and Wythburn -- the lower half of which is entirely lost. If, therefore, the excursion from Ambleside has not been taken, a traveller on foot or or horseback would not be well recompensed by quitting the high road at Rydal over Pelter Bridge, -- proceeding on the western side of the two lakes to Grasmere Church; and, thence to Butterlip How. A second deviation may be made when he has advanced a little beyond the mile-stone, the sixth short of Keswick, whence there is a fine view of Legbertwhaite, with Blencathara (commonly called <pb n="142"/>Saddleback) in front. Having previously enquired, at the inn near Wythburn Chapel, the best way from his mile-stone to the bridge that divides the Lake, he must cross it, and proceed, with the Lake on the right, to the Hamlet near its termination, and rejoin the main road upon Shoulthwaite Moss, about four miles from Keswick. These two deviations lengthen the journey something less than three miles. Helvellyn may be ascended from Dunmail-raise by a foot Traveller, or from the Inn at Wythburn.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">CONISTON.</head>
<p>The next principal Vale, that of Coniston, is best seen by entering the Country over the Sands of Lancaster. The Stranger, from the moment he sets his foot on those Sands, seems to leave the turmoil and traffic of the world behind him; and, crossing the majestic plain whence the Sea has retired, he beholds, rising apparently from its base, the cluster of mountains among which he is going to wander, and towards whose recesses, by the Vale of Coniston he is gradually and peacefully led. From the Inn at the head of Coniston Lake, a leisurely Traveller might <pb n="143"/>have much pleasure in looking into Yewdale and Tilberthwaithe, returning to his Inn from the head of Yewdale by a mountain track which has the farm of Tarn Hows, a little on the right; --by this road is seen much the best view of Coniston be visited from the South. From Coniston it is best to pass by Hawkeshead to the Ferry of Windermere, instead of going direct to Ambleside, which would bring the Traveller upon the head of the Lake, and consequently with much injury to its effect. If the Lake of Coniston be visited from the upper end, it is scarcely worth while to proceed further than about a mile and a half down its eastern shore, for the sake of the views on returning.</p>
<p>DONNERDALE, or the Vale of the Duddon (<i>er</i> signifies <i>upon</i>) and the adjoining Vale of the Esk, are rarely visited by Travellers. -- Donnerdale is best approached by Coniston over Walna Scar, down to Seathwaite, New-field, and to the rocks where the river issues from a narrow pass into the broad Vale. The Stream is very interesting for the space of a mile above this point, and below, by Ulpha Kirk, till it enters the Sands, where it is overlooked by the solitary <pb n="144"/>Mountain Black Comb, the summit of which, as that experienced surveyor, the late Colonel Mudge, declare, commands a more extensive view than any point in Britain. Ireland he saw from it more than once, but not when the sun was above the horizon.</p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line>"Close by the Sea, lone sentinel,</line>
<line>Black-Comb his forward station keeps;</line>
<line>He breaks the sea's tumultuous swell, --</line>
<line>And ponders o'er the level deeps.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>He listens to the bugle horn,</line>
<line>Where Eskdale's lovely valley bends;</line>
<line>Eyes Walney's early fields of corn;</line>
<line>Sea birds to Holkner's woods he sends.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>Beneath his feet the sunk ship rests,</line>
<line>In Duddon Sands, its mast all bare:</line>
</stanza>
<gap desc="5 stars"/>
<author><i>The Minstrels of Windermere</i>, by Chas. Farish, B.D.</author>
</poem>
<p>Details of the Vale, are to be found in the Author's Poem "The River Dunnon."</p>
<p>In the Vale of Esk is an interesting Waterfall, called Birker Force, that lies apart; and, from the chasm, a fine mountain view of Scawfell. At the head of the Vale are conspicuous Remains of a Roman Fortress.</p>
<pb n="145"/>
<head level="3" align="center">ENNERDALE.</head>
<p>This Vale and Lake, though presenting some bold features, are only to be taken as leading to something else; -- the Vale may be approached by Pedestrians, at its head, from Wastdale; and also over the mountains from Buttermere; and, by an indifferent Carriage-road, either from Calder bridge, or Lowerswater.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">THE VALE OF BUTTERMERE, &#38;c.</head>
<p>We are again in the beaten track of the Lakes, I will therefore pass to<pb n="146"/></p>
<head level="3" align="center">THE VALE OF KESWICK,</head>
<p>Which place is the head-quaters of Tourists. The best views of Keswick Lake are from Crow Park; Frier's Crag; the Stable field, close by; the Vicarage, and by taking the circuit of the Lake. More distant views, and perhaps full as interesting, are from the side of Latrigg; from Ormathwaite, Applethwaite; and thence along the road at the foot of Skiddaw towards Bassenthwaite, for about a quarter of a mile. There are fine bird's-eye views from the Castle hill; from Ashness, on the road to Watenlath, and by following the Watenlath Stream downwards to the Cataract of Lodore. This Lake also, if the weather be fine, ought to be circumnavigated. There are good views along the western side of Bassenthwaite Lake, and from Armathwaite at its foot; but the eastern side from the high road has little to recommend it. The Traveller from Carlisle approaching by way of Ireby has, from the top of Bassenthwaite-hawse, much the most striking view of the Plain and Lake of Bassenthwaite, flanked by Skiddaw, and terminated by Wallow-crag <pb n="147"/>on the south-east of Derwent Lake; the same point commands an extensive view of Solway Frith and the Scotch Mountains. They who take circuit of Derwent Lake, may at the same time include BORROWDALE, going as far as Bowder-Stone, or Rossthwaite; Borrowdale is also conveniently seen on the way to Wastdale; or to Buttermere, by Seatoller and Honister-Crag; or, over the Stye to Langdale, and Ambleside. Buttermere may be visited by a shorter way, through Newlands, but the best approach is from Scale-hill: the Mountains of this vale are nowhere so impressive as from the bosom of Crummock Lake. Scale-force is a fine Waterfall.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">ULLSWATER</head>
<note id="n9">Pedestrians and Travellers on horseback cross the lower part of St. John's Vale, but a carriage must go a few miles along Hutton Moor before it turns off.</note>
<p>is finely approached from Keswick<ptr target="n9"/> by Matterdale and Lyulph's Tower into Gowbarrow Park; -- a magnificent view is unfolded of two higher reachers of the Lake. Airey Force thunders down the Ghyll on the left, at a small <pb n="148"/>distance from the road. If Ullswater be approached from Penrith, a mile and a half brings you to the winding vale of Emont, and the prospects increase in interest till you reach Patterdale; but the first four miles along Ullswater by this road are comparatively tame, and in order to see the lower part of the Lake to advantage, it is necessary to go round by Poolybridge, and to ride at least three miles along the Westmorland side of the water, towards Martindale. The views, especially if you ascend from the road into the fields, are magnificent; yet. this is only mentioned that the transient Visitant may know what exists; for it would be inconvenient to go in search of them. They who take this course of three or four miles <i>on foot</i>, should have a boat in readiness for the end of the walk, to carry the, across to the Cumberland side of the Lake, near Old Church, thence to pursue the road upwards to Patterdale. The Church-yard Yew-tree survives at Old Church, but there are no remains of a Place of Worship, a New Chapel having been erected in a more central situation, which Chapel was consecrated by the then Bishop of <pb n="149"/> Carlisle, when on his way to crown Queen Elizabeth, he being the only Prelate who would undertake the office. It may be here mentioned that Bassenthwaite Chapel, yet stands in a bay as sequestered, as the Site of Old Church; such situations having been chosen in disturbed times to elude marauders.</p>
<p>The Trunk, or Body of the Vale of Ullswater need not be further noticed, as its beauties shew themselves: but the curious Traveller may wish to know something of its tributary Streams.</p>
<p>At Dalemain. about three miles from Penrith, a Stream is crossed called the Dacre, or Dacor, which name it bore as early as the time of the Venerable Bede. This stream does not enter the Lake, but joins the Emont a mile below; it rises in the moorish Country about Penruddock, flows down a soft sequestered Valley, passing by the ancient mansions of Hutton John and Dacre Castle. The former is pleasantly situation, though of a character somewhat gloomy and monastic, and from some of the fields near Dalemain, Dacre Castle, backed by the jagged summit of Saddle Back, with the Valley and Stream in front, <pb n="150"/>forms a grand picture. There is no other stream that conducts to any glen or valley worthy of being mentioned, till we reach that which leads up to Airey Force, and thence into Matterdale, before spoken of. Matterdale, though a wild and interesting spot, has no peculiar features that would make it worth the Stranger's while to go in search of them; but in Gowbarrow Park, the lover of Nature might linger for hours. Here is a powerful Brook, which dashes among rocks through a deep glen, hung on every side with a rich and happy intermixture of native wood; here are beds of luxuriant fern, aged hawthorns, and hollies decked with honeysuckles; and fallow-deer glancing and bounding over the lawns and through the thickets. These are the attractions of the retired views, or constitute a foreground for ever-varying pictures of the majestic Lake, forced to take a winding course by bold promontories, and environed by mountains of sublime form, tower about each other. At the outlet of Gowbarrow Park, we reach a third stream, which flows through a little recess called Glencoin, where lurks a single house, <pb n="151"/>yet visible from the road. Let the Artist or leisurely Traveller turn aside to it, for the buildings and objects around them are romantic and picturesque. Having passed under the steeps of Styebarrow Crag, and the remains of its native woods, at Glenridding Bridge, a fourth stream is crossed.</p>
<p>The opening on the side of Ullswater Vale, down which the Stream flows, is adorned with fertile fields, cottages, and natural groves, that agreeably unite with the transverse views of the Lake; and the Stream, if followed up after the enclosures are left behind, will lead along bold water-breaks and waterfalls to a silent Tarn in the recesses of Helvellyn. This desolate spot was formerly haunted by eagles, that built in the precipice which forms its western barrier. These birds used to wheel and hover round the head of the solitary angler. It also derives a melancholy interest frmo the fate of a young man, a stranger, who perished some years ago, by falling down the rocks in his attempt to cross over to Grasmere. His remains were discovered by means of a faithful dog that had lingered here for the space of three months, <pb n="152"/>self-supported, and probably retaining to the last an attachment to the skeleton of its master. But to return to the road in the main Vale of Ullswater. -- At the head of the Lake (being now in Patterdale) we cross a fifth Stream, Grisdale Beck; this would conduct through a woody steep, where may be seen some unusually large ancient hollies, up to the level area of the Valley of Grisdale; hence there is a path for foot-travellers, and among which a horse may be led, to Grasmere. A sublime combination of mountain forms appears in front while ascending the bed of this valley, and the impression increases till the path leads almost immediately under the projecting masses of Helvellyn. Having retraced the banks of the Stream to Patterdale, and pursued the road up the main Dale, the next considerable Stream would, if ascended in the same manner, conduct to Deep-dale, the character of which Valley may be conjectured from its name. It is terminated by a cove, a craggy and gloomy abyss, with precipitous sides; a faithful receptacle of the snows that are driven into it, by the west wind, from the summit of Fairfield. Lastly, having gone along <pb n="153"/>the western side of Brother's-water and passed Hartsop Hall, a Stream soon after issues from a cove richly decorated with native wood. This spot is, I believe, never explored by Travellers; but, from these sylvan and rocky recesses whoever looks back on the gleaming surface of Brother's-water, or forward to the precipitous sides and lofty ridges of Dove Crag. &#38;c. will be equally pleased with the beauty, the grandeur, and the wildness of the scenery.</p>
<p>Seven Glens or Vallies have been noticed, which branch off from the Cumberland side of the Vale. The opposite side has only two Streams of any importance, one of which would lead up from the point where it crosses Kirkstone-road, near the foot of Brother's-water, to the decaying hamlet of Hartsop, remarkable for its cottage architecture, and thence to Hayswater, much frequented by anglers. The other, coming down Martindale, enters Ullswater at Sandwike, opposite to Gowbarrow Park. No persons but such as come to Patterdale, merely to pass through it, should fail to walk as far as Blowick, the only enclosed land which on this side borders the higher part <pb n="154"/>of the Lake. The axe has here indiscriminately levelled a rich wood of birches and oaks, that divided this favoured spot into a hundred pictures. It has yet its land-locked bays, and rocky promontories; but those beautiful woods are gone, which <i>perfected</i> its seclusion; and scenes, that might formerly have been compared to an inexhaustible volume, are now spread before the eye in a single sheet, magnificent indeed, but seemingly perused in a moment! From Blowick a narrow track conducts along the craggy side of Place-fell, richly adorned with juniper, and sprinkled over with birches, to the Village of Sandwyke; a few straggling houses, that with the small estates attached to them, occupy an opening opposite to Lyulph's Tower and Gowbarrow Park. This stream flows down Martindale, a valley deficient in richness, but interesting from its seclusion. In Vales of this character the general want of wood gives a peculiar interest to the scattered cottages, embowered in sycamores; and few of the Mountain Chapels are more striking than this of Martindale, standing as it does in the centre of the Valley, with one dark yew-tree, and enclosed by <pb n="155"/>"a bare ring of mossy wall." The name of Boardale, a deep, bare, and houseless Valley, which communicates with Martindale, shews that the wild Swine were once numerous in that nook; and Martindale Forest is yet one of the few spots in England ranged over by red deer. These are the descendents of the aboriginal herds. In Martindale, the road loses sight of the Lake, and leads over a steep hill, bringing you again into view of Ullswater. Its lowest reach, four miles in length, is before you; and the view terminated by the long ridge of Cross Fell in the distance. Immediately under the eye is a deep-indented bay, with a plot of fertile land, traversed by a small brook, and rendered chearful by two or three substantial houses of a more ornamented and showy appearance than usual in these wild spots.</p>
<p>From Poolly Bridge, at the foot of the Lake, Hawes-water may be conveniently visited. Hawes-water is a lesser Ullswater, with this advantage, that it remains undefiled by the intrusion of bad taste.</p>
<p>Lowther Castle is about four miles from Pooly Bridge, and, if during this Tour the <pb n="156"/>Stranger has complained, as he will have had reason to do so, of a want of majestic trees, he may be abundantly recompenced for his loss in the far-spreading woods which surround that mansion.</p>
<head level="3" align="center">THE END.</head>
</chap>
<gap desc="back matter, blank pages - not digitised"/>
</text>
