<text id="1899_b">
<pb n="cover"/>
<head level="1" align="center">WORDSWORTH</head>
<head level="3" align="center">AND</head>
<head level="1" align="center">THE COLERIDGES</head>
<head level="2" align="center">WITH OTHER MEMORIES</head>
<head level="2" align="center">LITERARY AND POLITICAL</head>
<head level="3" align="center">BY</head>
<head level="2" align="center">ELLIS YARNALL</head>
<head level="2" align="center">New York</head>
<head level="2" align="center">THE MACMILLAN COMPANY</head>
<head level="2" align="center">LONDON: MACMILLAN &amp; CO., LTD.</head>
<head level="2" align="center">1899</head>
<p align="center"><i>All rights reserved</i></p>
<gap desc="previous chapters not pertinent to project, not digitized"/>
<pb n="55"/>
<head level="2" align="center">WALKS AND VISITS IN WORDSWORTH'S COUNTRY</head>
<p><i>August</i> 11, 1855. &#8212; In company with my friend, the Rev. Derwent Coleridge, I called to-day at Rydal Mount. I had great interest in entering again the grounds and the house which six years ago I visited with such eager expectation. Everything remains as it was in the poet's lifetime &#8212; the books and the pictures and the furniture. Wordsworth's chair stands in its accustomed place by the drawing-room fireside. Mrs. Wordsworth seems also unchanged. Her manners are simple and unpretending, but she received me very cordially. As was natural, almost the first inquiries were after Mrs. Henry Reed and her children. She spoke with much feeling of Professor Reed and Miss Bronson, who scarcely a year ago perished in the <i>Arctic</i>. They left Rydal Mount for Liverpool to embark, and it was little more than a week after their parting from this dear venerable lady that the waves closed over them. Mrs. Wordsworth is almost eighty-five, and is as clear in mind as ever. You forget her great age in talking with her. And what tenderness there is in the tones of her voice, and what truthful simplicity in her
<pb n="56"/>
words! We did not remain very long. I accepted her invitation to drink tea the next evening in company with Mr. Coleridge. As we drove away, we passed the spot where Wordsworth gave me his hand in parting six years ago, and but six months before his death. Later in the day, Mr. Coleridge and I took a walk along the Brathay to Skelwith Force and back, a round of six miles. The valley through which we went was familiar ground to Mr. Coleridge, he and his brother Hartley, &#8212; "My poor brother Hartley!" as Mr. Coleridge says when he speaks of him, &#8212; having spent five or six years there in their schoolboy days. We went to the cottage where they had lived, and the well-remembered rooms brought up to my friend a crowd of recollections of forty years ago. He talked much of those early days as we walked together along that sweet valley. We reached the Force, which is a pretty waterfall, and returned on the other side of the valley. It rained occasionally, but one gets used to this in England.</p>
<p><i>August</i> 12, <i>Sunday</i>. &#8212; I went to the new Ambleside church this morning. It is one of Gilbert Scott's works, but not altogether pleasing. I sat with Dr. John Davy, brother of Sir Humphry. We were close to the memorial window for which Dr. Davy had applied, through Professor Reed, for American contributions. When the service was over, I remained to study this window. Its appropriate inscription is: &#8212;</p>
<pb n="57"/> 
	<poem>
	<line>"Gulielmi Wordsworth Amatores et Amici,</line>
	<line>partim Angli, partim Anglo-Americani."</line>
	</poem>
<p>Other smaller windows are near by, commemorating members of the Wordsworth family, so that the corner becomes a Wordsworth chapel. One window remains without inscription.</p>
<p>At two o'clock I started for my walk to Grasmere, five miles distant, where I had agreed to meet Mr. Coleridge. My way at first was along the Rothay by the lovely road at the base of Loughrigg, which mountain seems to embrace as with an encircling arm one side of the Ambleside valley. There was deep shade here and there, and for a part of the way there was the shadow of the mountain itself. I passed Fox How, where there are only servants at present. Other pretty houses, with lovely shade about them, I also passed, and the sweep of the road gave me a perpetually changing view. Then I crossed a bridge, and soon found myself in the Vale of Rydal. Skirting the small Rydalmere, I next entered the sweet Grasmere Vale. In the distance was the church which was my destination, the square tower being a striking object in the view. It was a day of wonderful brightness, and the green of the mountain sheep-pastures and the purple of the slate rock, which is seen here and there, made a lovely contrast in the sunlight.</p>
<p>The church, which I reached at length, is the one commemorated by Wordsworth in the "Excursion": &#8212; </p>
<poem>
	<line>"Not raised in nice proportions was the pile,</line>
	<line>But large and massy, for duration built,</line>
<pb n="58"/>
	<line>With pillars crowded, and the roof upheld</line>
	<line>By naked rafters intricately crossed,</line>
	<line>Like leafless under-boughs 'mid some thick grove."</line>
</poem>
<p>The interior is interesting. The pavement is of blue flagstones worn and uneven. The pillars support two rows of low stone arches, one above the other, and on these rest the beams and other framework, black with age, which uphold the roof. The pillars are square and are of separate stones, and all has the look of rude strength, the rough work of very ancient days. The congregation was large. Mr. Coleridge preached. When the service was over I waited a while to look at the tablet to Wordsworth, which is on the wall directly over the pew he occupied for many years. The inscription is a translation from the Latin of the dedication to him of Mr. Keble's "Lectures on Poetry," and is as follows: &#8212;</p>
<poem>
	<line>"To the memory of</line> 
	<line>WILLIAM WORDSWORTH</line>
	<line>A true philosopher and poet,</line>
	<line>Who by the special gift and calling of</line>
	<line>Almighty God,</line>
	<line>Whether he discoursed on man or Nature,</line>
	<line>Failed not to lift the heart</line>
	<line>to holy things,</line>
	<line>Tired not of maintaining the cause</line>
	<line>of the poor and simple,</line>
	<line>And so in perilous times was raised up</line>
	<line>to be a chief minister,</line>
	<line>Not only of noblest poesy,</line>
	<line>but of high and sacred truth."</line>
</poem>
<p>Mr. Coleridge and I now started for the walk we had arranged to take together. It was to be a vigorous
<pb n="59"/>
climb, and then a descent and a circuit of the vales of Rydal and Grasmere; and we had two hours for it. We took a narrow road leading up the mountain on the west side of Grasmere Lake: coming down a little, we ascended once more to look down on Rydal Water. The views were very lovely, and the mountain-air was exhilarating. These lakes, with their dark mountain settings, are like mirrors in their black transparency. Rydal Water is dotted with islands, each with its few trees, everything seeming in miniature. We went to a house which is the highest human habitation in England, save one on the top of Kirkstone Pass. The people occupying it knew Mr. Coleridge well: they showed me, at his request, the kitchen with its pavement of flagstones, and the opening between the rafters which served for the chimney &#8212; a curious specimen of Westmoreland cottage-life.</p>
<p>We reached at length Rydal Mount, which was our destination, and found there Miss Edith Coleridge, daughter of Sara Coleridge; William Wordsworth, a grandson of the poet; and Mr. Carter, Wordsworth's secretary for forty years. Young Wordsworth has his grandfather's face: he seems thoughtful, and, though silent, his manner is prepossessing. He is about twenty years of age, and is an undergraduate of Balliol College, Oxford.</p>
<p>Mr. Coleridge left us soon after tea, having to return to Grasmere. I walked out on the terrace with Mr. Carter, and enjoyed the fine view it commands of the valley of the Rothay, with Lake Windermere
<pb n="60"/>
in the distance. It is a double terrace, with flowerbeds interspersed, rich in bloom and fragrance. On either hand there is shrubbery of luxuriant growth, and one wall of the house is ivy-grown. All speaks of loving and tender care. Much of the work of raising the terraces was done, I believe, by Wordsworth's own hands. There are seats here and there on which one would be tempted to spend many an hour watching the changing lights on the distant hillsides and the fair valleys. Mr. Carter pointed out to me the valley down which "the Wanderer" and his party came to the "churchyard among the mountains" (the Grasmere church). He showed me also the stone with its inscription &#8212; </p>
<poem>
	<line>"In these fair vales hath many a tree</line>
	<line>At Wordsworth's suit been spared,</line>
	<line>And from the builder's hand this stone,</line>
	<line>For some rude beauty of its own,</line>
	<line>Was rescued by the bard:</line>
	<line>So let it rest, and time will come</line>
	<line>When here the tender-hearted</line>
	<line>May heave a gentle sigh for him</line>
	<line>As one of the departed."</line>
</poem>
<p>Mr. Carter was most helpful to the poet during the long years of his association with him. One could fancy that he appreciated from the first the dignity of the service he was thus rendering. Mrs. Wordsworth has only a lease of Rydal Mount: at her death it must pass to strangers, for neither of her sons will be able to live there. I have omitted
<pb n="61"/>
to say that she is rapidly losing her sight, but she has scarcely any other infirmity of age.</p>
<p><i>August</i> 13. &#8212; Early this morning I started for an excursion which had been planned for me by Mr. Coleridge. I went by coach from Ambleside, ascending the Kirkstone Pass. I was outside, and could enjoy at first, as I looked back, the sweet morning view of Lake Windermere with its islands and its fair green hillsides. But soon the sharp ascent of the road brought us between steep mountain-declivities, shutting out all view except their desolate grey slopes. There were but scanty patches of grass here and there: all else was stony and barren. I walked in advance of the coach, enjoying the silence and the solitude, and the grand slopes of the naked mountains on either hand. Up and up we went, until at last the summit of the pass is reached. There stands the old stone house said to be the highest inhabited house in England &#8212; a rude enough dwelling, and at present an alehouse. Beginning now our descent toward Patterdale, we had from the summit of the pass a view of the little lake of Brotherswater, and soon our road was along the margin of this fair high-lying tarn. The mountains stand quite around the lake, leaving only space for the road. From the foot of the pass a drive of a few miles brought us to Patterdale, and there my coach-journey ended. I climbed to a stone-quarry on the hillside opposite, and thence had a view of the valley through which I had just passed, and of the lake of Ullswater
<pb n="62"/>
stretching off to the right. Returning to the inn at Patterdale, I engaged a boat to take me to Lyulph's Tower, distant five or six miles. A young man with drawing-materials and pack slung over his shoulder was about to leave the inn. I asked him to take a seat with me, and we were soon side by side in the open boat on the beautiful lake. From the level of the water the mountains rising on either hand appeared in their full dignity. The lake is quite shut in by these steep and lofty hills. For a while the clouds where threatening, but we dreaded wind more than rain, for these lakes are often lashed by sudden storms. We landed and climbed to Lyulph's Tower, and there below, in its fair loveliness, lay the sweet Ullswater, this upper reach of it being of quite wonderful beauty. Thence we made our way to Aira Force, a mile distant &#8212; a dashing waterfall in a narrow gorge. Its height is about eighty feet. The "woody glen" and the "torrent hoarse," as Wordsworth describes it, are appropriate words.</p>
<p>A mile farther we found a road and a little inn. We asked for luncheon, but in the principal room, to which we were shown, two travelling tailors were at work. It seemed pleasanter to be in the open air, so we had our table under the trees outside. My companion proved to be a clergyman: he was fresh from Oxford, and had just taken orders. We had fallen at once into intimacy, but we had immediately to part company. My way was onward to Keswick, a walk of eleven miles. I ascended first a
<pb n="63"/>
long hill, and then my route wound along or around the side of a mountain. Above and below me was bare heath or mountain-moor: there were no trees whatever. For near two hours I saw no house or sign of cultivation, nor did I meet a human being. The wind blew strongly in my face, but my blood coursed through all my veins, and I had ever before me a wide sweeping view. I descended at length into the fair valley through which the Greta flows, and about two hours more of steady walking brought me to Keswick. My stopping-place, however, was at the inn at Portinscale on the banks of Derwentwater, a mile out of Keswick, where I had agreed to meet Mr. Coleridge. I dined, and was resting after my long walk, when I heard his voice in the hall inquiring for me. With him were three other gentlemen, one of them the friend with whom he was staying, who asked me to return with them and drink tea at his house. One of the four was Dr. Carlyle, a brother of the Chelsea philosopher, himself a man of letters, the prose translator of Dante. I soon found myself in a pretty drawing-room looking out on Derwentwater. Mr. Leitch was our host. We had a great deal of animated talk at the tea-table, and later in the long twilight Mr. Coleridge read to us the "Ancient Mariner" and "Genevieve," his father's matchless poems. He reads extremely well. We sat by one of the large windows, and the lake stretching before us and the mountains beyond seemed to put one in the mood for the poetry.</p>
<pb n="64"/>
<p><i>August</i> 14. &#8212; I went to Mr. Leitch's to breakfast this morning, meeting nearly the same party, and had another hour of pleasant talk. Then Dr. Carlyle, Mr. Coleridge, Mr. Leitch, and I rowed across the lake. Landing near the town, Mr. Coleridge and I took leave of the others and went up into Keswick, and so out to Greta Hall, the former residence of Southey, now occupied by strangers. It has a lovely situation on a knoll, Skiddaw looking down upon it, and other mountains standing around and in the distance, and the Greta flowing, or rather winding, by; for it is a stream which has many twists and turnings. We called at the house, and Mr. Coleridge sent in his name, telling the servant he had a friend with him, an American, to whom he would like to show some of the rooms, adding, "I was born here." There was a little delay, for the occupant of the house was a bachelor and his hours were late. So we looked first at the grounds, and my friend, as we walked slowly along under the trees and looked down on the Greta, seemed to be carried altogether back to his childhood. On that spot it was that his brother Hartley used to tell him and to their sister Sara, as well as to Southey's children, stories literally without end &#8212; one narration in particular in its ceaseless flow going on year after year. "Here, too," said my friend, pointing to a small house near by, "was the residence of the Bhow Begum." Need I add that this reference was to that strange book, "The Doctor"?</p>
<p>We were now summoned to the house, and though
<pb n="65"/>
we saw no one except the civil housekeeper who accompanied us, all was thrown open to us. My friend at every room had some explanation to make: "This was the dining-room;" "here was Mr. Southey's seat;" "here sat my mother." One room was called Paul, for some one had said its furniture was taken wrongly from another room &#8212; robbing Peter to pay Paul. Upstairs was the library, the room of all others sacred, for there had passed so much of the thirty years of Southey's life of unwearied labour. The very walls seemed to speak of that honourable industry. I looked from the windows on those glories of lake and mountain which had been the poet's solace and delight, and recalled his own description of the view in "The Vision of Judgment": &#8212;</p>
	<poem>
	<line>"Mountain and lake and vale; the hills that calm and majestic</line>
	<line>Lifted their heads in the silent sky."</line>
	</poem>
<p>Near the library was the room in which he died after years of mental darkness. In the same room Mrs. Southey had been released from life after a still longer period of mental decay.</p>
<p>Leaving Greta Hall with all its interesting associations, we returned to the road. Near the gateway were some cottages. "An old fiddler used to live here," said Mr. Coleridge. Then inquiring of some men at work near by, he learned to his surprise that he was still there. "But it is more than forty years since I knew him: he used to teach me to play on the violin." "He is still there," the men repeated; and
<pb n="66"/>
we entered the cottage. An old man rose from his seat near the fire as Mr. Coleridge asked for him by his name. "Do you remember me?" said my friend. "You gave me lessons on the violin more than forty years ago, until my uncle Southey interfered and said I should play no longer: he feared it would make me idle." "I remember you perfectly," said the old man. "You would have done very well if you had kept on." Then followed mutual inquiries. The wife of the old man sat by his side crippled with rheumatism, from which he himself also suffered. "But she bears it very patiently, sir," said he. There seemed Christian submission in the old people &#8212; a tranquil waiting for the end.</p>
<p>Our next visit was to Miss Katherine Southey, who lives in a beautiful cottage close at the foot of Skiddaw. Three little children, Robert, Edith, and Bertha Southey, grandchildren of the poet, came out to meet us. Miss Southey greeted her cousin warmly. She is of cheerful, agreeable manners. We talked of Greta Hall, and the cousins called up their old recollections. Mr. Coleridge went upstairs to see the aged Mrs. Lovell, his aunt, the last of her generation, so to say &#8212; sister of Mrs. Coleridge and Mrs. Southey. It was one of Southey's good deeds that he cared for this lady from the beginning of her early widowhood as long as his own life lasted. She was, I believe, one of his household and family for more than forty years; and since his death his children have continued the same dutiful offices. (As I copy
<pb n="67"/>
these notes, now long after the date of my visit, I may add that Mrs. Lovell died in 1862, aged ninety-one.)</p>
<p>Miss Southey showed me some of the manuscripts of her father &#8212; very minute, but exquisitely neat and clear. When the cousins took leave of each other, Miss Southey's eyes were filled with tears. We now took to our boat again, and started for the Falls of Lodore at the other end of Derwentwater. We stopped at Marshall's Island, so called from the owner, who has made it a summer residence of marvellous beauty, though the extent of it is but five acres. Trees of every variety adorn the grounds. The house is in the centre, of stately proportions: the drawing-room in the second story opens upon a balcony commanding a view which is beyond measure enchanting. Books in profusion lay upon the table, and pictures and drawings were upon the walls, all telling of refinement as well as of abundance of this world's goods. Returning to our boat, my friend and I took the oars. Our next stopping-place was at St. Herbert's Island &#8212; a hermitage a thousand or more years ago. A few remains of what may have been an oratory are still to be seen. St. Herbert was the friend of the good St. Cuthbert, whose especial shrine and memorial is Durham Cathedral. Once a year, according to Bede, he left his cell to visit St. Cuthbert and "receive from him the food of eternal life." And in Wordsworth's verse is embalmed the tradition that, pacing on the shore of this small island, St. Herbert prayed that he
<pb n="68"/>
and his friend might die in the same moment; "nor in vain so prayed he:" &#8212;</p>
	<poem><line>"Those holy men both died in the same hour."</line></poem>
<p>At length we reached Lodore. Here our real work was to begin. We climbed to the top of the hill down which the stream falls over rocks piled upon rocks, forming a succession of cascades. It was a ladder-like ascent of no little difficulty. After admiring the view of the rocky chasm and the falls, we turned to enjoy the prospect which opened before us from Ladderbrow, as it is called. Derwentwater lay stretched before us, and Skiddaw rose in its giant majesty in the distance. The view is a celebrated one. We then entered the wood, crossed a beck or small stream, losing our way once, and at length reached an upland valley &#8212; Watendlath &#8212; very retired and secluded, with its small hamlet, and near by a tarn &#8212; "A little lake, and yet uplifted high among the mountains." The day was cloudy, but there was not much mist. Climbing another ridge, we found ourselves looking down upon Borrowdale and the little village of Rosthwaite, one of the loveliest views I ever beheld. Sunlight was upon the vale while we stood in the shadow. We were looking up Borrowdale to the Sty-head Pass. As we descended into the valley we could enjoy the view of it every step of the way. At Rosthwaite we had luncheon. It was half past three. We had still a mountain to climb; and as there was something of danger, for we might lose our way should the mist
<pb n="69"/>
increase, we took a guide, a man well known to Mr. Coleridge &#8212; one of the dalesmen of Borrowdale. We started at a vigorous pace, and, following the course of a stony brook, ascended the steep mountain-side. It was very sharp work, for it was an absolutely continuous ascent, and there was no pathway whatever. There was no sign of human habitation. On either hand were only the stony mountain slopes. It seemed a long and weary way, but at the end of two hours of steady climbing we reached the summit. A cold mist here enveloped us. We hastened on, our guide accompanying us a short distance over the moor as we began our descent: he saw us clear of the mist and safely on our way. When we had reached an eminence from which we could look down into Far Easdale, our route was clear to us, and we turned and waved our adieus to our friendly guide. We were already a long way off from him, and he was resting where we had left him, waiting to see that we took the right course. Descending rapidly, we went on and on through the desolate and lonely valley of Far Easdale &#8212; a vale within a vale, for it opens into Easdale. Hereabouts it was that George and Sarah Green lost their way and perished on a winter's night, as the story is recorded in Wordsworth's verse and De Quincey's exquisite prose. So dreary is the solitude that scarcely a sheep-track is to be found in the valley. All around there is nothing but a bare and stony heath.</p>
<p>We hastened on, for Mr. Coleridge knew there would be anxiety in regard to us, as evening was
<pb n="70"/>
drawing on. Another ascent being accomplished, we looked down into Easdale, surrounded by its mountain-girdle. The sun was setting, and as we were drawing near our destination I almost forgot my fatigue. At length we reached Mr. Coleridge's cottage at the entrance to the Vale of Grasmere. Mrs. Coleridge came out to meet us, and expressed much relief at seeing us. She knew the perils of a long walk over these lonely mountains.</p>
<p>I found an invitation for me from Mrs. Fletcher, a venerable lady of eighty-five, who had been a friend of Jeffrey, and one of the literary circle of Edinburgh of sixty years and more ago. After refreshing ourselves, my friend and I sallied forth. Lancrigg is the name of Mrs. Fletcher's beautiful cottage. We found a brilliant company assembled. Mrs. Fletcher welcomed me with sweet but stately courtesy. "I am always glad to see Americans," she said; "my father used to drink General Washington's health every day of his life." Her look was radiant as she said this: there was light in her eyes and colour in her cheeks, and altogether her appearance was most striking. I never saw a more beautiful old age. I talked with her son, Mr. Angus Fletcher, a sculptor of some distinction. A bust of Wordsworth and one of Joanna Baillie, works of his, were in the drawing-room. He told me of his having lately been to see Tennyson, who is on Coniston Water in this neighbourhood, in a house lent him by Mr. Marshall of Marshall's Island. Mr. Fletcher said he asked Tennyson
<pb n="71"/>
to read some of his poetry to him. "No," was the reply; "I will do no such thing. You only want to take me off with the blue-stockings about here." But they got on well together in their after-talk, and Tennyson, softening a little, said he <i>would</i> read him something. "Nothing of my own, however; I will not give you that triumph. I will read you something from Milton." "Oh, very well," said Mr. Fletcher; "I consider that quite as good poetry."</p>
<p>The evening over, a drive of six miles brought me to the friends with whom I was staying at Rothay Bank, near Ambleside.</p> 
<p><i>August</i> 15. &#8212; Dined to-day at Rydal Mount &#8212; the one o'clock dinner which is always the hour there &#8212; with Mrs. Wordsworth, young William Wordsworth, and Mr. Carter. Six years almost to a day since I last sat in that quaint room in the familiar presence of the great poet himself. It is a low room without a ceiling &#8212; the rafters showing. A great number of small prints in black frames are on the walls, chiefly portraits. There are portraits of the royal family also, but these are in gilt frames; they were the gift of the Queen to Wordsworth. I was glad to see again the bust of Wordsworth by Chantry, and also the old oak cabinet or armoire with its interesting Latin inscription, both of which the great poet showed to me as among his choice possessions. James, who has lived there for thirty years, waited at the table. Mrs. Wordsworth asked me to take wine with her, &#8212; the courtesy of the old days, &#8212; the single glass of port
<pb n="72"/>
which she drinks daily. It was the last day of her eighty-fourth year.</p>
<p>The library, which adjoins the drawing-room, is smaller in size, and the collection of books is not large. I noticed that many were presentation copies: in one of them, a folio volume describing the Skerryvore Rock Lighthouse &#8212; was the following inscription (the author of the book was the architect of the lighthouse): "To William Wordsworth, a humble token of admiration for his character as a man and his genius as a poet, and in grateful remembrance of the peace and consolation derived from the companionship of his writings during the author's solitude on the Skerryvore Rock." <ptr target="n1"/></p>
<note id="n1">The architect was Alan Stevenson, uncle of Robert Louis Stevenson.</note>
<p>John, the loquacious but intelligent coachman of the friend at whose house I am staying, told me of his waiting at dinner at Rydal Mount a good many years ago: his then master was one of the guests. Miss Martineau, Hartley Coleridge, and F.W. Faber were present. Mr. Faber had then charge of the little church at Rydal. There was a rush and flow of talk, as one could well imagine &#8212; such a chatter, John said, as he had never heard &#8212; but the instant Wordsworth spoke all were attention. John himself was awed by the great man's talk, and described well its power. He told me also of a slight incident in regard to Wordsworth's last hours. Very shortly before his death it was thought he might be more
<pb n="73"/>
comfortable if he were shaved. Accordingly, he was raised in the bed, and his faithful servant was about to minister to him in this way when Wordsworth said in his serious, calm voice, "James, let me die easy." I may note here something which has been told me in regard to poor Hartley Coleridge's last days. During his illness a little child, the daughter of an artist who lived near him, quite an infant, used to be brought to him, and he would sit for hours holding it in his arms and looking down upon it with mournful tenderness.</p>
<p><i>Sunday</i>, <i>August</i> 19. &#8212; Walked to the Rydal church this morning. Just as I reached the porch, I saw Mrs. Wordsworth with her arm extended feeling for the door. I went forward to assist her; she turned her kind face toward me, not knowing who it was. I told my name. "Oh," said she, "I am glad to see you. You will take a seat with us, of course." William, her grandson, was now close behind us. We went to the pew, the nearest to the chancel on the left, and I sat in what had doubtless been Wordsworth's seat. The prayer-book I took up had on the fly-leaf, "Dorothy Wordsworth to William Wordsworth, Jr., 1819." The service over, Mrs. Wordsworth said to me, "You will dine with us, of course." She took my arm, and as we went out of the church I was struck with the looks of affectionate reverence in the faces of those we passed. As we walked along she said in her kind way, "I should have been glad if you taken up your
<pb n="74"/>
abode with us while here, but you expected to leave Ambleside immediately when I last saw you." The Misses Quillinan, the step-daughters of the late Dora Quillinan, who was Dora Wordsworth, were the guests beside myself to-day. In the drawing-room after dinner it was interesting to me to look at the portrait of the elder Miss Quillinan (Jemima), taken when a child six years old, and to recall the lines addressed to her, or rather suggested by the picture: &#8212;</p>
<poem>
	<line>"Beguiled into forgetfulness of care,</line>
	<line>Due to the day's unfinished task, of pen</line>
	<line>Or book regardless, and of that fair scene</line>
	<line>In Nature's prodigality displayed</line>
	<line>Before my window, oftentimes and long</line>
	<line>I gaze upon a portrait whose mild gleam</line>
	<line>Of beauty never ceases to enrich</line>
	<line>The common light."</line>
</poem>

<p>The sonnet, too, beginning &#8212;</p>
<poem>
	<line>"Rotha, my spiritual child! this head was grey</line>
	<line>When at the sacred font for thee I stood,</line>
	<line>Pledged till thou reach the verge of womanhood,</line>
	<line>And shalt become thy own sufficient stay" &#8212;</line>
</poem>
<p>came naturally to my mind as I talked with the younger sister. These ladies are intelligent and refined, and of very pleasing manners: their mother was a daughter of Sir Egerton Brydges. They live at a pretty cottage underneath Loughrigg, not far from Fox How.</p>
<p>We went to church again at half past three: I walked with Mrs. Wordsworth. She spoke of herself &#8212;
<pb n="75"/>
said she was rapidly growing blind: in the last week she had perceived a great change. One would get used to the deprivation, she supposed, however. Her life had been a happy one, she added: she had very much to be thankful for. Her manner in church, I may mention, is most reverent, her head bowed and her hands clasped. As I returned from church with her, a tourist accosted me: Could I tell him which was Mr. Wordsworth's house? I pointed it out to him. "We have many such inquiries," Mrs. Wordsworth said.</p>
<p>I had now to make my final adieus to the dear venerable lady. (I little thought I should ever see her again.) Her serene and tranquil old age, I said to myself, would be a remembrance to me for life. She wished me a good voyage and a safe return to my friends.</p>
<p>William Wordsworth kindly went with me for a mountain-climb. We ascended Loughrigg, from which we looked down on three lakes, Windermere, Rydal, and Grasmere &#8212; a last view of all this beauty. How lovely were the evening lights on mountain and valley!</p>
<p><i>Rothay Bank, Ambleside, August 7, 1857.</i>&#8212; Again, after a two years' absence, I find myself in this sweet region. With my kind host, Mr. C&#8212;&#8212;, I went this morning to call on Mrs. Arnold at Fox How. We found six or eight persons in the drawing-room. It was my first meeting with Mrs. Arnold: she came forward to receive us, welcomed me cordially, and<pb n="76"/> presented me to her three daughters, Mrs. Twining, Mrs. Cropper, and Miss Frances Arnold. I was fresh from Wharfeside, the home of her eldest daughter, Mrs. Foster. We talked about that home of such peculiar intellectual brightness, and I told of the happy days I had passed there. Mrs. Arnold's manners are gentle and winning. She asked me what evening I could spend with them, and Sunday was agreed upon. Fox How I was most glad to see with the stream of life flowing on in it: when I was last here the family were away. Mr. Penrose, a brother of Mrs. Arnold, a clergyman of Lincolnshire, Mrs. Penrose, and Dr. and Mrs. Perry of Bonn were the others in the room. Dr. Arnold's portrait was on the wall, also prints of Mr. Justice Coleridge, of Archbishop Whately, of Wordsworth, and of Julius Hare. The views from the windows had their own peculiar beauty, half hidden through the landscape was to-day in rolling mist.</p>
<p><i>August 8.</i>&#8212; Walked to-day along the beautiful road under Loughrigg, that huge winding mountain, past Fox How and many other lovely country homes. Went then into the Vale of Rydal and skirted this beautiful lake, watched the reflections in the water, and gazed on the noble hills which surround the vale. I continued on: Grasmere came in sight &#8212; a large lake with a view in the distance of the square white tower of the church under whose shadow Wordsworth lies. I passed the cottage in which Hartley Coleridge lived and in which he died. At <pb n="77"/>length I reached the head of the lake, and then the church which was my destination. Once more I stood at the grave of Wordsworth, that sacred spot which, as I believe, many generations will visit, and whence a voice, we may hope, will ever speak to men of the beauty of this fair earth and the higher glory of which it is the shadow. The great poet lies by the side of his daughter, Dora Quilliman; next to her lies Dorothy Wordsworth, his sister; then Edward Quillian and his first wife; and there is space left for Mrs. Wordsworth. Sarah Hutchinson, Mrs. Wordsworth's sister, also lies here: on the stone which marks her grave is the following:&#8212;</p>
<p align="center">"Near the graves of two young children, removed from a family to which through life she was devoted, Here lies the body of SARAH HUTCHINSON the beloved sister and faithful friend or mourners who have caused this stone to be erected with an earnest wish that their own remains may be laid by her side, and a humble hope that through Christ they may together be made partakers of the same Blessed Resurrection."</p>
<p>Here follow the dates of her birth and death, and then &#8212;</p>
<p align="center">"In fulfilment of the wish above expressed here repose the remains of WILLIAM WORDSWORTH, DOROTHY WORDSWORTH."</p>
<p>[Space being left for Mary Wordsworth.] A little farther on are the graves of the two young children<pb n="78"/> alluded to in the foregoing. On the tombstone of one is this inscription:&#8212;</p>
<poem>
<line>"Six months to six years added he remained</line>
<line>Upon this sinful earth, by sin unstained.</line>
<line>O Blessed Lord, whose mercy then removed</line>
<line>A child whom every eye that looked on loved!</line>
<line>Support us, make us calmly to resign</line>
<line>What we possessed, but now is wholly Thine."</line>
</poem>
<p>I lingered near an hour around these graves, and then retraced my steps along the water-side and beneath the shade of the solemn hills. I passed Town End, once the residence of Wordsworth, and halfwya between Grasmere and Rydal I climbed the old road to the Wishing Gate, from which there is a beautiful view of Grasmere. Looking down on this fair and peaceful scene, I did not wonder that what Wordsworth calls "the superstitions of the heart" had invested the place with a magic power. It seemed natural, too, to think that only what was best and purest in each soul would be touched by the spell.</p>
<poem>
<line>"The local Genius ne'er befriends</line>
<line>Desires whose course in folly ends,</line>
<line>Whose just reward is shame."</line>
</poem>
<p>Continuing my walk, I reached the Vale of Rydal, and then turned by the pretty shady ascending road leading to Rydal Mount. I entered by the small gateway the fair terraced garden so rich in bloom and fragrance. I saw once more the old greeting, <i>Salve!</i><pb n="79"/> as I stood on the threshold. James, the old servant, welcome me and conducted me to the drawing-room. I found Mrs. Wordsworth seated in her old place by the fireside. Her greeting was simple and cordial, but only by my voice could she know me, for I saw at once that she was quite blind. Her grandson William was with her. She was cheerful and bright, and talked of the events of the day in the sweet quiet manner peculiar to her, and with clear intelligence, and yet she was within a few days of being eighty-seven. She was mindful, too, of the duties of hospitality, for finding I had walked about eight miles she insisted on ordering some luncheon for me. I had a good deal of talk with young Wordsworth. His resemblance to his grandfather has become quite remarkable. He has the same dreamy eyes and the same forehead. But there seemed a benediction in the very presence of Mrs. Wordsworth, so much did her countenance express peace and purity, so gentle and so sweetly was her bearing.</p>
<p><i>August 9, Sunday.</i>&#8212; I went this aftertoon to the little Rydal church, and I sat in Mrs. Wordworth's pew. No one was there but young Wordsworth. Mrs. Arnold's pew is directly opposite, both being at the end of the church nearest to the chancel. Mrs. Arnold and her three daughters were present. The old clerk from his desk near the pulpit said at the end of the service, "Let us sing the praise and glory of God the 'undredth psalm &#8212; the 'undredth psalm," and then with the feeble step walked down the aisle to take his<pb n="80"/> place as leader of the choir. The preacher was a stranger, and the sermon was an appeal for missions. He seemed a good and earnest man, but his manner was odd, and some things he said were odd too. The woman of Samaria was the text: "You remember that when Dr. &#8212;&#8212; of the Scotch Church was in the Holy Land he visited the well, and as he sat there he took out his Bible to read the chapter, and he let it fall into the well, and it was not recovered for a long time afterward: the well was deep." But still stranger was what followed. Speaking of our Lord's humility: "We do not hear of His going about except on foot, never in any vehicle. Once only do we hear of His riding on an ass, and that was a borrowed one." There was a quaintness in this that was worthy of the old days, and certainly there was nothing of irreverence in the preacher's manner. John Mason Neale, I remember, quotes somewhere the following equally quaint utterance from a Middle-Age writer:&#8212;</p>
<poem>
<line>"Be Thou, O Lord, the Rider,</line>
<line>And we the little ass,</line>
<line>That to the Holy City</line>
<line>Together we may pass."</line>
</poem>
<p>After the service I walked up to Rydal Mount with Mrs. Arnold. Mrs. Wordsworth was in the drawing-room. It was an interesting sight to see the two ladies talking with each other &#8212; on the one side reverence and respect, on the other strong regard, and on both manifest affection. I thought, would the poet and teacher have been what they were to the<pb n="81"/> world but for the help and example which each had at hand in his household life?</p>
<p>At half past six I went to Fox How, where I was to drink tea. We were a large party at the table: we did not remain long, however, for we were to ascend Loughrigg to see the sun set. We had a lovely climb in the long summer twilight. We wandered on to a jutting rock, and from thence we saw the sun go down in glory behind the mountains, leaving a splendour of crimson in the light clouds for long afterward. Below us was Loughrigg Tarn, which Wordsworth has somewhere commemorated. Mrs Twining told us of a walk with the poet she recalled, though she was very younh at the time, which occasioned the poem: her father too was with them. A row of pines ascending a mountain on the opposite side of the valley was pointed out as "Fan's Funeral" &#8212; "A joke against me," said Miss Arnold. It seemed that in childhood she had somehow got the impression that it was a troop of mourners following a bier &#8212; perhaps some one had said, "How like a funeral!" &#8212; and many times afterward, in visiting the spot, the child still supposed it was a funeral, and wondered it should be so long stationary.</p>
<p>As we came down the mountain, Miss Arnold spoke of her recollection of the day of Wordsworth's death. She and one of her young friends were almost alone at Fox How. They knew that the end was at hand, and their minds were filled with the thought of it. They climbed one of the hills looking down on<pb n="82"/> Rydal Mount, their hearts bowed with a solemnity of feeling &#8212; burning, one might almost say, within them as they thought of the moment that approached. Suddenly as they looked they saw that the windows of the house were being closed, and they knew thus of the faring forth of the great soul. It was almost as if they themselves had witnessed his departure. I could well understand how the solemn Nature around would have a grave and awful look to them as they pondered in their young hearts that ending and that beginning. I spoke of Wordworth's own lines on hearing that "the dissolution of Mr. Fox was hourly expected": &#8212;</p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line>"A power is passing from the earth</line>
<line>To breathless Nature's dark abyss;</line>
<line>But when the great and good depart,</line>
<line>What is it more than this &#8212;</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>"That man, who is from God sent forth,</line>
<line>Doth yet again to God return?</line>
<line>Such ebb and flow must ever be:</line>
<line>Then wherefore should we mourn?"</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>At Fox How we assembled again in the pleasant drawing-room: books were brought out, and passages referred to which had been suggested in our walk. At length the bell was rung for prayers, and the servants came in: Mr. Penrose officiated. One could not but think how often Dr. Arnold's voice had been heard there saying the same office. Some refreshment was brought in. I remained but a few minutes longer. Mrs. Arnold asked me to dine with them on Wednesday.</p>
<pb n="83"/>
<p><i>August</i> 10. &#8212; My kind host has arranged an excursion of about three days, that I may see a part of this Lake District which is seldom visited. We started from his gate at ten o'clock by coach for Broughton, by way of Coniston Water &#8212; a beautiful drive, the weather delightful and all very promising. At Broughton we had a glimpse of the valley of the Duddon. Thence we went by rail along the sea-coast as far as Ravenglass, a lonely fishing village. Here we here a car for Strand's near Wast Water, a distance of seven or eight miles. We stopped, however, a mile from Ravenglass, at Muncaster Castle, "the seat of the ancient family of the Penningtons." The guidebooks say that Henry VI. was entertained here on his flight after the battle of Hexham, and that when he left Muncaster he gave to Sir John Pennington an enamelled glass vase. The glass has been carefully preserved in the castle, the tradition being that the family would never want a male heir while it remained unbroken. We drove through the park by a winding road, which brought us to the castle. The chief thing here is what is known as the terrace, cut on a hillside, and commanding a view which is said to be the finest in Cumberland. All around are noble trees and beautiful shrubbery and gay flowers, so that one could hardly think the great sea so near. Indeed, it had seemed like enchantment, the turning in from the bleak coast to all this rich foliage and summer beauty. Very lovely are the grounds, because so artificial. Nature has been the great beautifier.<pb n="84"/> After we left the terrace we came to a little church quite embosomed in the trees &#8212; as secluded a nook as one could imagine: it is in the castle grounds, but is the church of the neighbourhood.</p>
<p>We continued our drive. Alas! the promise of the morning was not fulfilled. Clouds had gathered, and at length the rain began. At Strands we found rooms in a very small inn, and concluded to stay there quietly for the night. So we had our tea-dinner, and composed ourselves to such indoor occupation as was possible. Books there were few of &#8212; some volumes of Swift's works, two volumes of poems &#8212; Liverpool poets of fifty years ago who had not achieved fame. However, with the aid of these notes, which had fallen in arrear, and with occasional talk, the hours were beguiled.</p>
<p><i>August</i> 11. &#8212; Still rainy and lowering. We breakfasted and waited, hoping for fair-weather signs. The rain did for a while ease, and I drove alone to Wast Water, two miles distant. This lake of black waters, with the bare mountains rising round it, showed well under the sombre sky. The mountains were capped with mist, so I could only imagine their height, but the whole length of the lake lay stretched out before me. In desolate savage beauty this surpasses all the other lakes of the region. It is said to look its best on gloomy days: its dark colour is perhaps due to the great depth of the water.</p>
<p>Returning to the inn, I found my friends all ready for our start for Seathwaite, eight miles distant. We <pb n="85"/>had still to keep to the one-horse car, the only vehicle to be had in these out-of-the-way places. At Seathwaite we obtained an open carriage for the rest of the journey, eighteen miles. We passed through Egremont, and saw the ruins of the castle &#8212; through Ennerdale, and stopped to look at the churchyard, the scene of Wordsworth's beautiful pastoral "The Brothers." At Scale Hill, which was our destination, we had again good weather, and it was a lovely view with which our journey for the day closed. My friends' carriage was awaiting us at the hotel, and the coachman had brought us our letters. He left Rothay Bank this morning, and came by way of Keswick, a drive of thirty miles. We dined, and then, as the clouds had broken away and the sun was about setting, we went out to enjoy the evening. We climbed the hill, from which a beautiful view of Crummock Water opened before us. John the coachman came up afterward, bringing his bugle, on which he plays very well. He soon set for us "the wild echoes flying," and all the vale below was filled with the sound. We then wandered away to the edge of the lake and watched the play of the evening light on the tranquil waters.</p>
<p><i>August</i> 12.&#8212; We started at half past six this morning to drive to Keswick to breakfast, twelve miles. The weather was beautiful, and all the fair vales and hills were in their full loveliness in the morning light. As we drew near Keswick we saw from a hill Derwentwater and Bassenthwaite Lake, and the <pb n="86"/>town in the centre of the valley, which lay below us. We passed the church where Southey lies, and then crossed the Greta and drove by Greta Hall, and so into Keswick. Here we breakfasted and our horses had a two hours' rest, and we then started again for Ambleside, seventeen miles. We ascended first the long hill from where there is the noble view of the Vale of Keswick and of its lakes, and of Skiddaw and the other mountains &#8212; a view which twice before I have had the happiness to see. When I last looked down on it, it was under a cloudy sky: now there was the full beauty of sunlight. But every foot of the way between Keswick and Ambleside had its charm: Southey calls it the most beautiful drive in the world. Why should I attempt to describe it? I may note the wonderful reflections in the lakes of Grasmere and Rydal, especially the latter. There was no ripple to disturb the glassy transparency. The islands, the sloping shores, the hedges, and the grazing sheep, all were doubled, and no water-line was to be seen. I suppose the mountains around protect the lake from currents of wind, and give a blackness to it which makes it so excellent a mirror.</p>
<p>At a little after one, my friends set me down at the entrance to Fox How. I was to dine there to meet Thomas Arnold and William Wordsworth, and we were to have a walk together in the afternoon. But Arnold had been suddenly called to Dublin, and had just started. Wordsworth, however, was <pb n="87"/>there, and with him Mr. Henry Crabb Robinson, who had just come to spend a few days at Rydal Mount &#8212; an old man of eighty-three, but fresh and gay and wonderfully fluent in discourse. He was a great friend of Wordsworth's, and was twice his companion in travelling on the Continent. Southey, Coleridge, and Lamb he knew well also. I was presented to him, and reminded him that five years ago I had the honour to breakfast with him in London &#8212; a fact which, I grieve to record, he seemed quite to have forgotten.</p>
<p>Dinner was soon announced, and the large table was again well filled. Mr. Robinson took the talk pretty much. He sat on Mrs. Arnold's right, and I was directly opposite. Perhaps it was having me in full view that led him to speak so much of the Americans he had known in the last forty years. He told us of his chance meeting with young Goddard of Boston in Switzerland in 1820, when he and Wordsworth were travelling together, and how that meeting had caused poor Goddard's death. Wishing to be in Wordsworth's company, he had asked Mr. Robinson's permission to join them in the ascent of the Rigi. He altered by so doing his course of travel, and a day or two afterward, in crossing the Lake of Zug in an open boat with a companion, a storm came on, the boat was upset, and he was drowned; his companion escaped by swimming to shore. We recalled Wordsworth's elegiac stanzas on the occasion, and I ventured to add, as a conclusion to the story, that when <pb n="88"/>Professor Reed was getting together the American contribution to the Wordsworth memorial window, a letter came from Mrs. Goddard, the mother of the young man who near forty years before had perished, desiring to take part in the commemoration, and referring to the imperishable monument to her son which the great poet had reared. She was then eighty-five, and had lived to give this token of her gratitude.</p>
<p>Mrs. Robinson had a great deal to say about the Rev. James Richmond, an American, a man of genius, but famous chiefly for his eccentricity. But I need make no further note of his discourse. He diverged perpetually, and sometimes did not come back to the main track of his story. I was half sorry that my presence should be the occasion of his talking so much about my countrymen. I should have preferred a subject which would have been of more interest to the others who were present. But it was idle to attempt to direct the current of his speech. Equally futile was Mrs. Arnold's effort to retain possession of the joint which was placed before her, and which she was about to carve. Mr. Robinson insisted with peremptory courtesy on relieving her, and as he brandished the great knife, continuing the while his animated talk, there was naturally a less skillful performance of the duty which was then of immediate urgency. Glances were exchanged by Mrs. Arnold with some of her guests, in part of apology and in part of amusement at the spectacle. And, sooth to <pb n="89"/>say, the fair tablecloth suffered from Mr. Robinson's double mind.</p>
<p>I remained most of the afternoon at Fox How, walking about the grounds or sitting under the shade of trees near the house, talking with one or other of the ladies. Seldom have I passed pleasanter hours. In the evening I was again with Mrs. Arnold and her daughters on a visit at one of the neighbouring houses. Nine o'clock came, and with it the <i>Times</i>, which was eagerly opened. The news from India is just now of absorbing interest. [It will be remembered that this was the year of the Sepoy Rebellion.] I should mention that Mrs. Arnold read us this afternoon letters from her son William, author of "Oakfield," from the Punjaub. Under date of February last he speaks of a Mohammedan secret organization, having its centre at Delhi, and ramifications everywhere, which he thinks means evil. He is the more of the opinion because his Persian secretary, whom he thinks very ill of, belongs to it. Writing under date of June 15, he says the Bengal Sepoy no longer exists, and that the civilisation of fifty years has gone in a day. The laying of the Atlantic cable is another matter of great interest just now. All England is watching its progress. Despatches from the ship come almost hourly as it steams westward.</p>
<p><i>August</i> 16. &#8212; My last Sunday in England. I went by the beautiful Fox How road to Rydal to church, and sat in Mrs. Wordsworth's pew. She and Mr. Crabb Robinson and William Wordsworth were there. <pb n="90"/>Mrs. Wordsworth to-day enters he eighty-eight year. I sat by her side as I did two years ago, in this same pew, the Sunday before I sailed. Her meek countenance, her reverent look, I saw once more &#8212; the face of one to whom the angels seemed already ministering. Service being over, I shook hands with her, and received a kind invitation to dine at Rydal Mount. Leaning on Mr. Robinson's arm, she went out, Wordsworth and I following. Mrs. Arnold and her daughters stopped to make their congratulations on her birthday, as others did, following her afterward with loving looks. We ascended the steep hill, Mr. Robinson talking, as usual, a great deal.</p>
<p>Once more I was at Rydal Mount; there were the books, the pictures, the old chairs. I went upstairs with Wordsworth to his room; it is the one that Dorothy Wordsworth, the poet's sister, occupied so long &#8212; the room in which she died. The house is very old, the passages narrow, the ceilings low, yet there is an air of comfort everywhere. At dinner Mr. Robinson was the talker, as he always is. He told us of his intercourse with Goethe. He said he never mentioned Wordsworth's name to Goethe, fearing that he would either say he had never read his poetry or that he did not like it. He said Southey was only a collector of other men's thoughts: Wordsworth gave forth his own. Wordsworth was like the spider, spinning his thread from his own substance; Southey the bee, gathering wherever he could. Mrs. Wordsworth did not join us at table till the dessert <pb n="91"/>came in. Then her one glass of port having been poured out for her, she took it in her hand and turning her face toward me, said, "I wish you your health, and a prosperous voyage and a safe return to your friends!"</p>
<p>The interval after dinner was short. I received, if I may so say, Mrs. Wordsworth's final blessing and went my way, thankful it had been given me to draw near to one so pure, to a nature so nobly simple. Not only her children, but all who have come in contact with her, will rise up to call her blessed. Surely, thrice blessed was the poet with such a wife; and indeed he himself with wonderful fulness has declared she was almost as the presence of God to him:&#8212;</p>
<poem>
<stanza>
<line>"That sigh of thine, not meant for human ear,</line>
<line>Tells that these words thy humbleness offend;</line>
<line>Yet bear me up&#8212; else faltering in the rear</line>
<line>Of a steep march: support me to the end.</line>
</stanza>
<stanza>
<line>"Peace settles where the intellect is meek,</line>
<line>And Love is dutiful in thought and deed;</line>
<line>Through thee communion with that love I seek;</line>
<line>The faith Heaven strengthens where <i>he</i> moulds the creed."</line>
</stanza>
</poem>
<p>My last evening in this sweet region was spent at Fox How. With Mr. Thomas Arnold and Miss Arnold I once more in the long twilight climbed Loughrigg Fell. There stretching out before us was range after range of grey mountains, with Skiddaw in the distance &#8212; a solemn and peaceful view, and to me a leave-taking of one of the loveliest regions of the earth.</p>
<p><i>Hotel, Windermere Station, July</i> 4, 1873. &#8212; Again, <pb n="92"/>after sixteen years' interval, I am on the threshold of this lovely region. I have been walking in the twilight hours through bowery lanes, hoping to reach the lake; but I took a wrong direction, and only when it was time to return did I get from a high part of the road a glimpse of the fair waters. I passed many gateways, with broad gravelled drives leading from them, doubtless to beautiful homes, for all this neighbourhood is occupied by lovely dwellings, more or less secluded and embowered in all luxuriant greenery. It was between nine and ten o'clock when I got back to the solitude of the hotel. There were people there, no one of whom I knew. I can stand being along with Nature; but the constrained silence of the coffee-room of an English inn is a trifle depressing.</p>
<p><i>July</i> 5. &#8212; I started early in a fly for the ferry at Bowness, then crossed the lake in almost a toy steamer to the Nab promontory, and thence took my way on foot by a quickly ascending road toward Hawkshead. From the summit of the ridge I looked back upon Lake Windermere, with its wooded promontories and its islands and its encircling mountains. The morning was beautiful, and the whole scene was in its rich summer loveliness. I had forgotten how fair and glorious were these Westmoreland lakes and mountains. Farther on I came to Esthwaite Water, a lake a mile and a half in length, and soon afterward I enterd the Vale of Hawkshead. The old church, on a rocky eminence, is the chief object as you approach the town. At the base of the hill on which <pb n="93"/>it stands is the grammar school at which Wordsworth received his first lessons, as he tells us in "The Prelude." I found carpenters at work in the old schoolroom, and one them told me he had himself been a scholar there, and he showed me at the desk at which Wordsworth sat. The schoolhouse, the church, and the streets of the town had all the quaint and antique look. I could fancy there had been little change since Wordsworth and his brother Christopher, afterward master of Trinity College, Cambridge, were scholars here, near a hundred years ago. It had been the chief object of my pilgrimage &#8212; the sight of this schoolhouse. Coniston was my further destination. A coach was standing at the door of an inn, which I found was just starting for this place, so I climbed to an outside seat, and found as my sole companion a good-natured man who at once entered into talk with me. He seemed a well-to-do man, and as he told me soon whence he had come and whither he was going, I naturally imparted to him what had been the object of my pilgrimage to Hawkshead. He seemed to find it hard to account to himself for my enthusiasm; still, the only inquiry he made of me in endeavouring to enlighten himself was a singular one. "Was he a rich man?" he asked me, referring to Wordsworth. I obliged to admit that he was not. Then we walked of the races at Newcastle, and on this subject my companion had greatly the advantage of me.</p>
<p>>We descended upon Coniston Water by a long<pb n="94"/>steep hill. The hotel known as the Waterhead Inn is beautiful as to architecture, and there were about it flower-beds with geraniums in glorious bloom &#8212; such splendour of colour as I never saw before. I went out in a boat on the lake, and enjoyed for a while the view of the hills around. Then rain came on, and I had to row quickly back, and my remaining hours were spent at the inn. But the spacious coffee-room commanded such a delightful view that there was little hardship in remaining indoors. At about five in the afternoon I started on the coach for Ambleside. I was on top, by the coachman, a civil fellow who knew every foot of the way. Three young ladies sat on the still higher seat behind. They were of severe propriety of manner, but they were refined, and talked with a careful modulation of voice which is peculiarly English. The afternoon was dull, but it did not rain. The road was perpetually either up hill or down, and the views every step of the way were lovely. We went through Yewdale, and stopped within a few minutes' walk of Skelwith Force, a waterfall reminding one of a single portion of Trenton Falls. Time was allowed us to see this, and then we climbed to our high seats again, the young ladies having the help of a ladder, and drove along the banks of the Brathay, passing as I drew near Ambleside the gateway of the pretty house which had been a home to me in two former visits. Alas! the dispensers of that gracious hospitality, my kind host and hostess, have both been removed by death. At the Salutation Inn,<pb n="95"/> Ambleside, I received the welcome answer that I coud have a room: the travelling season has begun, and as I had not written in advance, I had my fears.</p>
<p><i>July</i> 6. &#8212; It rained last night when I went to bed, but the day broke gloriously, and this wonderful, this enchanting region seemed to have a new and fresh charm. A young Canadian joined me in my walk to the Rydal church just under Rydal Mount. There was the little church hust as I had last seen it, only that it had been greatly improved as to the exterior architecture. Inside it was but little changed: the old high-backed pews remained. There in her accustomed place, in the large square pew near the chancel, sat Mrs. Arnold, and by her Miss Frances Arnold, both fronting the small congregation. I looked at the pew on the other side and missed the sweet an aged face of Mrs. Wordsworth. But the whole church seemed a memorial to her. My meeting with Mrs. Arnold and Miss Arnold was very pleasant and cordial when the service was over; they asked me to dine with them, and introduced me to the dean of Durham, who was with them. Mrs. Arnold and the dean drove. Miss Arnold said she would walk, so she and her nephew (a son of Thomas Arnold) and I Went by that most lovely road which winds underneath Loughrigg. The walk and the talk were delightful to me; the day was of rare splendour, and there was the unspeakable beauty of the valley and of the mountains around.</p>
<pb n="96"/>
<p>At Fox How, Mrs. Arnold and the dean were in the garden; the dear old lady (she is now eighty-two) came forward and made the kindest inquiries about those I had left at home, and was in every way most gentle and gracious. And then we walked into the house, and into the drawing-room, and it seemed like a bit of enchantment, the view from the window looking back over the way we had come &#8212; the solemn mountains shutting all the beauty in, as it were, giving a framework and a setting to it. We sat and talked, and there was such a sense of kindly feeling as to make the hospitality I was enjoying doubly grateful. The ladies went away for a moment, and I could look at the books and the pictures. Everything spoke of culture and of thought. Much seemed to have been added to the room since I last saw it. A fine drawing in water-colour, a portrait of Mrs. Arnold, hung over the fireplace &#8212; a recent picture. On the table I saw two thick volumes &#8212; the memoir and letters of Sara Coleridge. I had not known that the book was out: it seemed strange that I should see it for the first time at Fox How.</p>
<p>Our talk at dinner was very pleasant. The dean of Durham is Dr. Lake; he was, as Miss Arnold informed me, Dr. Arnold's favourite pupil. The fact of his being a dean was proof of his learning and high reputation; for in latter times these appointments are only given on the ground of distinguished merit. He said Emerson dined with him some<pb n="97"/> months ago when at Durham; that he spoke of having seen a good deal of Carlyle when in London; that he, Carlyle, was out of health and depressed. The loss of his wife preyed on him; he was unable to sleep, and the chief comfort he found in his sleepless hours was in saying over and over again the Lord's Prayer. Emerson's daughter was travelling with him, but being unwell, she could not go to dine at the dean's. At the table something from Keble was quoted, but neither Emerson nor the dean could get it right. "Oh, I'll ask my daughter," said Emerson. Emerson went with the dean to the cathedral service, and seemed greatly impressed by it. We talked of the Hare book, "Memorials of a Quiet Life." Miss Arnold had known well both Augustus and Maria Hare, as well as Julius and Esther Hare; indeed, it was probably at Fox How that the engagement of Julius Hare to Esther Maurice took place. The writer of the "Memorials" was well known to them at Fox How &#8212; a man of some eccentricity of character. Miss Arnold said she had within a few days talked about the book with Miss Martineau, who denounced it on some fantastic ground or other. Miss Arnold said it was not pleasant to her to hear this adverse criticism &#8212; "But you know one cannot tell a lady of great age, though a trumpet, that you utterly object to what she is saying." The dean spoke of Professor Jowett with admiration, though he could not wholly agree with him. Of Maurice the dean spoke with great respect; he said Hutton, the editor<pb n="98"/> of the <i>Spectator,</i> was the chief representative of his opinions. Mr. Forster, too, might be mentioned as a leading man on whom the teaching of Maurice had had a strong influence. Mrs. Arnold took part with much animation in all the talk; she seemed perfectly bright in mind. I was delighted to see her cheerfulness and serenity, and to feel that her closing days had so much of joy in them.</p>
<p>As I climbed Loughrigg late in the afternoon I thought of the long thirty years of Mrs. Arnold's widowhood, and of how much she had been given to cheer it loneliness, &#8212; the loving dutifulness of her children, her home in this beautiful region, around which must cling, for her, such vivid and tender associations, the ever recurring evidences of the fruitfulness of her husband's teaching. All this must have brought peace to her in the slowly passing years. I thought of Wordsworth, too, when, my view widening with each step, I at last reached a height from which I could look down on Rydal Water as well as Windermere. I wondered whether this grand Nature had made the man, or whether his genius had invested it with something of the charm which it has now for all beholders. I stood among grey mossy rocks; sheep were browsing on the grassy spaces between; below me lay the whole Ambleside Valley, with the church in the centre. A very Sabbath stillness seemed on all the hills and in the vale beneath. I said to myself, "Surely to any man such sights as these must give elevation of mind: how much more <pb n="99"/>to a poet!" I could understand the good that must have come to Wordsworth, wandering as he did over these hills, with the thought ever present to him that Nature was to be his teacher, and that it was to be his work to interpret her to men.</p>
<p>Late in the afternoon I called on the Misses Quillinan (Jemima and Rotha, commemorated by Wordsworth), and had a pleasant talk with them over the past. They told me that my friend of former visits, William Wordsworth, the poet's grandson, was now at home from India on a visit; he has been head of a college at Poonah for twelve years. I shall hope to see him when I reach Cockermouth. The ladies told me that the old Wishing Gate had been removed, and a new gate put in its place; they showed me a bar of the old gate, and I sought to make trial once more of its mystic power. The Misses Quillinan, as being the step-daughters of Dora Quillinan, are the nearest, and indeed the only, representatives of Wordsworth remaining here in the neighbourhood of Rydal Mount.</p>
<p><i>July</i> 7. &#8212; I left Ambleside to-day for Keswick. I was on the outside of the coach, and had a full view of the slopes of the hills, the green of the pastures, fretted here and there by crags; I saw the sweet lakes once more, Rydal and Grasmere, and farther on there were numerous flocks of sheep coming down the mountains, probably for the shearing. Dogs were guiding them and keeping them together with wonderful and unerring instinct. And then we passed Thirlmere, which is the highest of the English <pb n="100"/> lakes. Here the view had become wild and desolate, the hillsides bare and rocky. We descended from this high valley into a fair smiling country once more. The coach stopped at the entrance to St. John's Vale, and I determined to talk to Keswick by that route. It is a narrow, winding valley, shut in by deep hills, with a stream flowing through it. On either side of the water there is thick wood, but with open spaces here and there, and farmhouses. The rocks which overhang the vale at about centre have the look of a fortress. I entered the vale of the Greta, and then descended the long Saddelback, and made my way at length to the Portinscale Hotel; there I rested after my three hours' walk, and in the evening went on by rail to the neighbourhood of Cockermouth, where I was to spend a few days at the house of some friends.</p>
<p>Of this visit I need make but little record. I saw at Cockermouth the square and respectable mansion, quite the most considerable house in the town, in which Wordsworth was born April 7, 1770. The house has undergone but little change, it is said, since that date. I met William Wordsworth, too, as I had hoped I should. He and his wife were staying with his father, the Rev. John Wordsworth, vicar of Cockermouth. He was bearded and bronzed and otherwise changed, as a man well might be after twelve years in India. His wife showed more of the ill effect of the climate; her appearance was extremely delicate.</p>
<pb n="101"/>
<p>I may note one interesting incident which Mr. Wordsworth told me. He had been on a visit to Professor Jowett at Oxford, and was there on a Saturday, the day on which Jowett gathers about him people of distinction. "On this occasion," said Wordsworth, "I was to hand out to dinner a particular lady, but her name was not mentioned to me, or at least I did not catch it. She, however, was told that I was a grandson of Wordsworth. 'Oh,' she said, 'I began to read Wordsworth when I was fifteen, and have gone on ever since with continually increasing pleasure;' and then her talk flowed on with such strength and power, and showed such elevation of mind and such grasp and mastery of all learning, that I was certain she could be no other than Mrs. Lewes. So I asked her if she was not the author of "Middlemarch," and she said she was. In the drawing-room afterward she showed herself on the same level with Greek scholars and men of science, with whom she talked, filling with wonder all who listened."</p>
<p>Mr. Wordsworth spoke of his important position at Poonah, giving him direction of the education both of Hindoos and Europeans. I could not doubt his fitness for the work he had undertaken; but I remembered what I thought was the promise of sixteen years ago, and I fancied that whatever India might have gained, England had lost a man of letters &#8212; perhaps a poet. He was the last of my friends of the Lake District with whom I had intercourse <pb n="102"/> in that visit of 1873. It chanced that he accompanied me on my journey from Cockermouth to Carlisle, and there, on the threshold as it were of the region, we parted &#8212; he for the East when his brief furlough should be over, I for the West. I felt always that I had much in common with him; but now, with half the globe between us, and the changes which the flowing years might bring, the chance was small of our ever meeting again.</p>
</text>
