<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1857_b"><p><s id="s1">The English Lakes.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s2">Introduction.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s3">By the route which we have traced among the English Lakes in the following pages, we believe that the traveller may visit all the chief points of interest in the shortest space of time, while those who have their time more at command may extend their excursions to secondary points of interest by following the various diverging routes headed in italics. We have selected <enamex sw="w420" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> as the starting point, because Ulleswater, one of the finest of the lakes, is seen to greatest advantage by being approached from this direction, while it is as convenient a quarter as any of the others from which to set out on a tour through the district.</s></p>
<p><s id="s4">With the carefully prepared map attached to this guide, the tourist will experience no difficulty in tracing the main route and the diverging excursions here laid down; and a very little consideration, with the aid of occasional inquiry as to minutiae when on the spot, will enable him to vary his proceedings according to inclination.</s> <s id="s5">He will farther be very much aided in these investigations by observing the distinct markings on the map which include bridle-paths and carriage-roads.</s> <s id="s6">In a tour of this description we believe that minute detail in regard to every possible route is unnecessary, and would only prove perplexing.</s> <s id="s7">We conceive that the mere mention of all the places and objects of interest, with one good route to the most of them, and a slight indication of others, is all that is required.</s> <s id="s8">This we have attempted to give in these pages, and we trust that the traveller will find the volume sufficiently explicit, while the beautiful engravings with which it is embellished will enable him in some degree to anticipate the scenery he is about to visit.</s> <s id="s9">There is, perhaps, no part of <enamex  sw="w1786" name="Large admin unit">Great Britain</enamex> more beautiful and picturesque, more varied in its scenery, or more calculated to afford intense gratification to the tourist, - whether he travels as a man of science, as a painter, or simply as an admirer of the works of his Creator, - than the Lake District of <enamex  sw="w2064" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s> <s id="s10">It is rich in flowers, rare plants, and luxuriant undergrowth.</s> <s id="s11">Its numerous mountains present a tempting field of investigation to the geologist.</s> <s id="s12">Its ruins and several very curious Roman and Druidical remains furnish points of interest to the antiquarian, while its woods and streams are associated with the names of many of our greatest poets.</s> <s id="s13">Its scenery presents every variety of landscape, from the weather-beaten mountain crags and peaks, the brawling rivulets, and the wild ravines of the highlands, to the outspread lakes, the cottages, and level cultivated plains of the valleys - and in the picturesque effects of light and shade, caused by the changeful nature of its skies, the varied and happy combination of its parts, and the richness of its colouring, it is pre-eminently beautiful.</s> <s id="s14">Contained within an area of not more than fifty miles in diameter, the lakes, and all the points of interest in their vicinity, may be visited in a short space of time; and owing to the comparatively small scale of the scenery, the mind of the traveller is kept constantly on the qui vive by the multitude of ever-varying and lovely objects presented in his view.</s> <s id="s15">Amid the wild and magnificent scenery of the Scotch Highlands, and, much more, among the mountains and vales of <enamex  sw="w3347" name="Large admin unit">Switzerland</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w3363" name="Large admin unit">Norway</enamex>, the traveller, - albeit fulfilled with admiration at the majestic objects of nature around him, - is so completely lost in the immensity of space, and, in consequence of the magnitude of things, is frequently so long confined to one slowly shifting scene, that he entirely loses those softer feelings of placid delight which are aroused by the contemplation of equally wild and picturesque scenery on a reduced scale.</s> <s id="s16">The lakes, therefore, of the mountain regions of <enamex  sw="w3838" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, <enamex  sw="w3850" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, and <enamex  sw="w3868" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>, although not to be compared in magnitude or sublimity with the places before mentioned, are nevertheless possessed of charms to which the others cannot lay claim, besides having the additional advantage of being easy of access from almost any part of the kingdom.</s> <s id="s17">There are many routes by which the traveller may visit the lakes.</s> <s id="s18">That which we have selected as the groundwork of the present volume is one of the most central, and one by which all the principal lakes may be visited.</s> <s id="s19">It is also the best, perhaps, that can be followed by pedestrians.</s></p>
<p><s id="s20">At all seasons the scenery of the lake district is beautiful, and will amply reward the traveller who visits it; but the best time to do so is in August and September, particularly the latter month and in October, as the autumnal foliage at this time clothes the whole country in the most gorgeous hues, while the weather is usually steady and fine.</s> <s id="s21">Our starting point shall be</s></p>
<p><s id="s22"><enamex sw="w4808" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>.</s> <s id="s23">Inns - George And Crown.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s24">This is a clean-looking ancient town in the south of the county of <enamex  sw="w4910" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, lying near the junction of the Eamont and <enamex sw="w4964" long="-2.719930910627173" lat="54.6044092845645" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209204" name="Lowther" conf="2.6">Lowther</enamex>, and containing upwards of 6000 inhabitants.</s> <s id="s25">There are many objects of interest in and around the town, the chief of which are, the ruins of the castle - the church-yard, in which is a curious ancient monument called the <enamex sw="w5193" long="-2.2220644005054" lat="54.15693793522018" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11152078" name="Giant's Grave (Tumulus)" conf="1.122349364">Giant's Grave</enamex>; - the Beacon, from the top of which the view of some of the distant lakes is very fine and extensive; - the Giant's Caves, and a group of curious stones called <enamex sw="w5369" long="-2.660043139036953" lat="54.7305813607955" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11205581" name="Long Meg and her Daughters" conf="2.2">Long Meg and her Daughters</enamex>. At <enamex sw="w5401" long="-2.788960641" lat="54.73799996" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00106" name="Old Penrith" conf="99992">Old Penrith</enamex> are the remains of a Roman station, and the seats of the nobility and gentry in the neighbourhood are numerous.</s></p>
<p><s id="s26">From <enamex sw="w5530" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> two roads lead to <enamex sw="w5556" long="-2.817815867535586" lat="54.61151285171987" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36231" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley Bridge</enamex>, about six miles distant, which spans the Eamont just at its issue from Ulleswater.</s> <s id="s27">Either road may be taken, be we recommend that which follows the <enamex sw="w5719" long="-2.672303262975452" lat="54.53277861452185" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11281528" name="Shap" conf="2.6">Shap</enamex> road to <enamex sw="w5732" long="-2.736222945236761" lat="54.64925140783275" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11135204" name="Eamont Bridge" conf="2.6">Eamont Bridge</enamex>.</s> <s id="s28"><enamex sw="w5747" long="-3.408715821432785" lat="54.37363175225092" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11098453" name="Carleton Hall" conf="2.6">Carleton Hall</enamex> is near to it on the left.</s> <s id="s29">Cross the bridge, and take the first road to the right.</s> <s id="s30">At this point, on the left, are the druidical remains called King Arthur's <enamex sw="w5919" long="-2.177585627411565" lat="54.49856468880679" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11273455" name="Round Table or Roper Castle (Roman Signal Station)" conf="2.2">Round Table</enamex>, and Mayborough. Immediately after crossing <enamex sw="w5977" long="-2.817815867535586" lat="54.61151285171987" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36231" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley Bridge</enamex>, the road runs along the western shore of</s></p>
<p><s id="s31">Ulleswater</s> </p>
<p><s id="s32">To <enamex sw="w6048" long="-2.935009110358855" lat="54.53103319127506" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241197" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>, a distance of ten miles; but, before proceeding along it, the tourist would do well to take a walk of a few miles along the eastern shore, in the direction of <enamex sw="w6219" long="-2.8859" lat="54.5424" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_7300150" name="Martindale" conf="99991">Martindale</enamex>, from several points on which he will obtain a good view of the lake.</s> <s id="s33">Should this deviation be made, it will be necessary to return by the same road to <enamex sw="w6382" long="-2.817815867535586" lat="54.61151285171987" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36231" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley Bridge</enamex>, where there are two small inns, at which boats, for an excursion on the water, or for fishing, may be procured if desired.</s> <s id="s34">A fine view may be had from the top of <enamex sw="w6559" long="-2.8253" lat="54.6137" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY468246" name="Dunmallard Hill" conf="99992">Dunmallet</enamex>, on which are the vestiges of a Roman fort.</s> <s id="s35">There is some good fishing here in the lake and stream.</s> <s id="s36">Trout, perch, and eels, are numerous, and large lake-trout are sometimes, though seldom, taken.</s> <s id="s37"><enamex sw="w6765" long="-2.735411894879494" lat="54.60431623719995" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11209206" name="Lowther Castle" conf="2.2">Lowther Castle</enamex>, the seat of the Earl of Lonsdale, is distant from this bridge about four miles.</s> <s id="s38">Ulleswater is nine miles in length, by nearly a mile wide, at the broadest point; but, owing to its irregular form, it is divided into three reaches, the first of which is closed in by <enamex sw="w7046" long="-2.8785" lat="54.5704" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY43301982" name="Hallen Fell" conf="99992">Hallen Fell</enamex>, on the western shore.</s> <s id="s39">The second is ter - minated by <enamex sw="w7111" long="-2.950879265566048" lat="54.54888608843932" type="other" gazref="unlock:11295035" name="Stybarrow Crag" conf="2">Stybarrow Crag</enamex> on the east, with <enamex sw="w7144" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169753" name="Helvellyn" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex> towering in the distance behind it, and <enamex sw="w7194" long="-2.920163136188693" lat="54.55811187160969" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11077616" name="Birk Fell" conf="2.4">Birk Fell</enamex> on the west.</s> <s id="s40">The third reach is decidedly the most beautiful, being surrounded by towering mountains, and studded with little islands, which, combined with the woods and rich vegetation, present a magnificent scene.</s> <s id="s41">The view in our engraving is taken from <enamex sw="w7460" long="-2.920163136188693" lat="54.55811187160969" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11077616" name="Birk Fell" conf="2.4">Birk Fell</enamex>, having <enamex sw="w7478" long="-2.950879265566048" lat="54.54888608843932" type="other" gazref="unlock:11295035" name="Stybarrow Crag" conf="2">Stybarrow Crag</enamex> on the right.</s> <s id="s42">After leaving <enamex sw="w7521" long="-2.817815867535586" lat="54.61151285171987" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36231" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley Bridge</enamex>, the scenery, for the first three or four miles, is comparatively tame; but after passing the village of <enamex sw="w7640" long="-2.859266517427028" lat="54.5933169397067" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:39919" name="Watermillock" conf="2.6">Watermillock</enamex>, it improves rapidly.</s> <s id="s43">About a mile beyond <enamex sw="w7695" long="-2.482408319312641" lat="54.15617644890619" type="other" gazref="unlock:11164650" name="Halsteads" conf="2">Halsteads</enamex>, the road enters <enamex sw="w7722" long="-2.920770635497279" lat="54.58507196358554" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11157087" name="Gowbarrow Park" conf="2.2">Gowbarrow Park</enamex>, formerly the hunting seat of the Duke of Norfolk, now the property of Mr. Howards of Greystoke.</s> <s id="s44">It is of great size, and is filled with beautiful groups of trees, among which may be seen herds of fallow-deer, whose presence give the additional charm of wilderness to the scene.</s> <s id="s45"><enamex sw="w8016" long="-2.9206" lat="54.5761" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11210312" name="Lyulph's Tower" conf="99992">Lyulph</enamex>'s Tower, which stands on an eminence here, is a picturesque object; and there are many exquisite" bits" of minute scenery, clad with luxuriant verdure, that will delight the eye of a painter.</s> <s id="s46">From <enamex sw="w8220" long="-2.9206" lat="54.5761" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11210312" name="Lyulph's Tower" conf="99992">Lyulph</enamex>'s Tower, a delightful walk runs up a rocky vale to a waterfall called</s></p>
<p><s id="s47"><enamex sw="w8297" long="-2.936037483005751" lat="54.57596662121968" type="water" gazref="unlock:11057415" name="Aira Force" conf="2.4">Aira Force</enamex>.</s> </p>
<p> <s id="s48">Force is the general name for a waterfall.</s></p>
<p><s id="s49">This is a beautiful fall.</s> <s id="s50">It leaps from the top of a wooded cliff, through a narrow gorge, and descends a sheer perpendicular height of eighty feet.</s> <s id="s51">The roar of the falling waters, and the descending of spray, add to the feelings of romance created by the view of rugged rocks, thickly planted trees, and hanging verdure, which characterize the spot.</s> <s id="s52">At the upper end of <enamex sw="w8725" long="-81.47375" lat="28.58473" type="other" gazref="unlock:10792570" name="The Groves Mobile Home Park" conf="0.6546106913">the park</enamex> the last reach of the lake opens up the view, in a majestic sweep round the mountains on the opposite side.</s> <s id="s53">The shores are bold, covered partly with wood, and indented with bays.</s> <s id="s54">The road now passes under Sty - barrow Crag, which raises its broken and scarred front on the right, while a steep bank descends into the deep waters of the lake on the left, and, winding round the head of Ulleswater, it conducts to the village of</s></p>
<p><s id="s55"><enamex sw="w9160" long="-2.935009110358855" lat="54.53103319127506" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241197" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s56">Where there is a good inn, at which boats and guides may be procured.</s> <s id="s57">Some time ought to be spent here in visiting the beautiful scenes in the vicinity.</s> <s id="s58">Among these are, - the little islands at the head of the lake, in visiting which a day might be pleasantly whiled away.</s> <s id="s59">Some of the best views on the shores of Ulleswater are to be had from the lake itself, by rowing past the islands called Cherry <enamex sw="w9573" long="-2.75745233250588" lat="54.1983109600986" type="water" gazref="unlock:8787679" name="Holme Beck" conf="2.4">Holme</enamex> and House Holme, and approaching towards <enamex sw="w9620" long="-2.950879265566048" lat="54.54888608843932" type="other" gazref="unlock:11295035" name="Stybarrow Crag" conf="2">Stybarrow Crag</enamex>.</s> <s id="s60"><enamex sw="w9636" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169753" name="Helvellyn" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex> stand between four and five miles from the village.</s> <s id="s61">By ascending it, the visitor will be amply repaid for his toil by a magnificent, map-like view of the lake district.</s> <s id="s62">The mountain is 3055 feet above the sea-level, but is easy of ascent, and ponies can be taken to the top.</s> <s id="s63">There are two ways of approach from <enamex sw="w9957" long="-2.935009110358855" lat="54.53103319127506" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241197" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>; the best is by <enamex sw="w9984" long="-2.950879265566048" lat="54.54888608843932" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11155225" name="Glenridding" conf="2.6">Glenridding</enamex>.</s> <s id="s64">This valley is traversed by a stream, which ought to be followed to its source in the <enamex sw="w10083" long="-3.132896161282918" lat="54.42147870822834" type="water" gazref="unlock:11253836" name="Red Tarn" conf="2.4">Red Tarn</enamex>, lying a few hundred feet below the top of the mountain.</s> <s id="s65">The south-east boundary of <enamex sw="w10176" long="-3.421314275290081" lat="54.29258219417088" type="other" gazref="unlock:11297954" name="Tarn, The" conf="2">the Tarn</enamex> is a ridge of rock called <enamex sw="w10211" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="other" gazref="unlock:11294441" name="Striding Edge" conf="2">Striding Edge</enamex>, and the north-west is another ridge called <enamex sw="w10269" long="-3.0167" lat="54.5296" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY343154" name="Swirrel Edge" conf="99992">Swirrel</enamex> Edge.</s> <s id="s66">The latter must be followed, as striding edge is exceedingly dangerous.</s> <s id="s67">There is a spring, called <enamex sw="w10381" long="-3.027721484735965" lat="54.53028096399296" type="water" gazref="unlock:11090119" name="Brownrigg Well" conf="2.4">Brownrigg</enamex>'s Well, not more than 300 yards from the summit of the mountain, on the south-west side.</s> <s id="s68">For a short ramble, the <enamex sw="w10504" long="-2.9204" lat="54.5446" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7732640" name="Placefell" conf="99992">Place Fell Quarry</enamex>, half a mile from the inn, may be visited, as it affords a good view of Ulleswater: and the valley of <enamex sw="w10624" long="-2.8859" lat="54.5424" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_7300150" name="Martindale" conf="99991">Martindale</enamex> exhibits some beautiful scenery.</s> <s id="s69">There is a mountain called <enamex sw="w10695" long="-2.85" lat="54.48333" type="other" gazref="unlock:4571317" name="High Street" conf="2">High Street</enamex>, little more than four miles distant from the inn; but he who ascends <enamex sw="w10777" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169753" name="Helvellyn" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex> need not waste time in scaling this mountain, which is 2700 feet height, and de - rives its name from a road which the Romans constructed over it.</s> <s id="s70">Fro <enamex sw="w10937" long="-2.935009110358855" lat="54.53103319127506" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241197" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>, also, a detour may be made on foot across the <enamex sw="w10995" long="-2.8859" lat="54.5424" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_7300150" name="Martindale" conf="99991">Martindale</enamex> Fells to</s></p>
<p><s id="s71"><enamex sw="w11015" long="-2.804508842654697" lat="54.18142154182505" type="water" gazref="unlock:11167631" name="Hawes Water" conf="2.4">Hawes Water</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s72">Which lies between five and six miles east of the village.</s> <s id="s73">This sheet of water is usually visited from <enamex sw="w11132" long="-2.745809060481465" lat="54.32561646560368" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185036" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex> or <enamex sw="w11142" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, by way of <enamex sw="w11161" long="-2.672303262975452" lat="54.53277861452185" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11281528" name="Shap" conf="2.6">Shap</enamex>; but by the way we recommend, the distance is shortened very much, and the direct route to the principal lakes not interrupted.</s> <s id="s74"><enamex sw="w11294" long="-2.804508842654697" lat="54.18142154182505" type="water" gazref="unlock:11167631" name="Hawes Water" conf="2.4">Hawes Water</enamex> is three miles long, and about half a mile broad; it is embosomed in high mountains, and its eastern shores are clothed by the wood of <enamex sw="w11441" long="-2.780308223288561" lat="54.52314191177565" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11226102" name="Naddle Forest" conf="2.4">Naddle Forest</enamex>.</s> <s id="s75">The village of <enamex sw="w11471" long="-2.75135372969905" lat="54.55734083336002" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29535" name="Bampton" conf="2.6">Bampton</enamex> lies about two miles from the foot of the lake.</s> <s id="s76"><enamex sw="w11527" long="-2.85" lat="54.48333" type="other" gazref="unlock:4571317" name="High Street" conf="2">High Street</enamex> and <enamex sw="w11543" long="-2.857180862951445" lat="54.50464497850818" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11185815" name="Kidsty Pike" conf="2.4">Kidsty Pike</enamex> rear their summits above the head of it.</s> <s id="s77">Here there is a little village, or hamlet, called Mardale Green, where is a small inn.</s> <s id="s78">There is good fishing in <enamex sw="w11708" long="-2.804508842654697" lat="54.18142154182505" type="water" gazref="unlock:11167631" name="Hawes Water" conf="2.4">Hawes Water</enamex> and <enamex sw="w11724" long="-2.901154234742621" lat="54.52014480780301" type="water" gazref="unlock:8792626" name="Angle Tarn" conf="2.4">Angle Tarn</enamex>, both being within a short distance of <enamex sw="w11774" long="-2.935009110358855" lat="54.53103319127506" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241197" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s79">Returning to <enamex sw="w11799" long="-2.935009110358855" lat="54.53103319127506" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241197" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex> make an excursion to</s></p>
<p><s id="s80"><enamex sw="w11831" long="-2.918951147472433" lat="54.50419131247666" type="water" gazref="unlock:11089619" name="Brothers Water" conf="2.4">Brothers Water</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s81">Or, if time cannot be afforded to do so, the lake may be seen while travelling to <enamex sw="w11930" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>( which is ten miles from <enamex sw="w11965" long="-2.935009110358855" lat="54.53103319127506" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241197" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>), and especially from <enamex sw="w11998" long="-2.91667" lat="54.45" type="other" gazref="unlock:4569619" name="Kirkstone Pass" conf="2">Kirkstone Pass</enamex>, over which the road runs to <enamex sw="w12042" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>.</s> <s id="s82">The view here is exceedingly fine, and when lighted up by the slanting rays of the sun, and glowing in the garb and glory of an autumnal evening, it must be quite magnificent.</s> <s id="s83">From this point, however, the view of <enamex sw="w12267" long="-2.918951147472433" lat="54.50419131247666" type="water" gazref="unlock:11089619" name="Brothers Water" conf="2.4">Brothers Water</enamex> is somewhat distant.</s> <s id="s84">The lake is a large tarn, deriving its name from the circumstance of two brothers having been drowned there.</s> <s id="s85">Before leaving this scene, much enjoyment may be derived from a visit to the beautiful valley of <enamex sw="w12509" long="-2.423453431741072" lat="54.25369781174878" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785590" name="Deepdale Beck" conf="2.4">Deepdale</enamex>, which runs up into the mountains from <enamex sw="w12557" long="-2.972979752882944" lat="54.82734189561268" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11086791" name="Bridge End" conf="2.6">Bridge End</enamex>, two miles from <enamex sw="w12584" long="-2.935009110358855" lat="54.53103319127506" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241197" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s86">Just beyond this bridge is a splendid view of the surrounding country.</s> <s id="s87"><enamex sw="w12667" long="-2.82474894803935" lat="54.56225995962338" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785686" name="Dodd Beck" conf="2.4">Dodd</enamex>, with its sloping sides, <enamex sw="w12697" long="-2.857180862951445" lat="54.50464497850818" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11185815" name="Kidsty Pike" conf="2.4">Kidsty Pike</enamex>, <enamex sw="w12710" long="-2.779111006255583" lat="54.46023190225483" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11161005" name="Grey Crag" conf="2.4">Grey Crag</enamex>, part of <enamex sw="w12729" long="-2.9204" lat="54.5446" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7732640" name="Placefell" conf="99992">Placefell</enamex> and <enamex sw="w12743" long="-3.0878" lat="54.4697" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY296088" name="Coddale" conf="99992">Colddale</enamex> Crags are on the east of the road; and to the west are <enamex sw="w12807" long="-2.82474894803935" lat="54.56225995962338" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785686" name="Dodd Beck" conf="2.4">Dodd</enamex> <enamex sw="w12812" long="-3.055843425150577" lat="54.4221768039265" type="other" gazref="unlock:11076640" name="Bield, The" conf="2">Bield</enamex>, the <enamex sw="w12823" long="-3.214466500836419" lat="54.57349272667725" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11256013" name="Rigg Screes" conf="2.4">Screes</enamex>, <enamex sw="w12831" long="-3.000560623790019" lat="54.24386305141168" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16529" name="Low Wood" conf="2.6">Low Wood</enamex> on the borders of <enamex sw="w12858" long="-2.92425" lat="54.50643" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00058" name="Brothers Water" conf="99992">Bothers</enamex> Water,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s88"><enamex sw="w12877" long="-2.9033" lat="54.4953" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11166894" name="Hartshope" conf="99992">Hartsope</enamex> should also be visited for beautiful scenery.</s> <s id="s89"><enamex sw="w12932" long="-2.91667" lat="54.45" type="other" gazref="unlock:4569619" name="Kirkstone Pass" conf="2">Kirkstone Pass</enamex> derives its name from a large stone at the head of the pass, which bears a fancied resemblance to a church.</s> <s id="s90">There is a small inn here; and at this point the road to <enamex sw="w13112" long="-2.916539146877075" lat="54.39634869266406" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11306429" name="Troutbeck Bridge" conf="2.6">Troutbeck</enamex> turns to the left.</s> <s id="s91"><enamex sw="w13141" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex> is seen on descending the pass, and three miles beyond lies the village of</s></p>
<p><s id="s92"><enamex sw="w13227" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>.</s> <s id="s93">Inns - Commercial, Salutation, <enamex sw="w13269" long="-0.77061" lat="51.48793" type="other" gazref="unlock:13903231" name="White Waltham" conf="0.8180423747">White</enamex> Lion.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s94">This village ought to be made head-quarters, being a convenient central point, from which excursions may be made in all directions.</s> <s id="s95"><enamex sw="w13414" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> is a small market town, irregularly built, in the valley of Rothay, about a mile from the head of <enamex sw="w13522" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s96">It was once a Roman station, and several fragments of old pavement and other Roman relics have been dug up in the neighbourhood.</s> <s id="s97">Traces of a fortress have also been discovered.</s> <s id="s98">The town stands on a steep incline at the base of <enamex sw="w13761" long="-2.93275663555211" lat="54.43217842069659" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11313036" name="Wansfell Pike" conf="2.4">Wansfell</enamex>, and, excepting towards the south-west, is enclosed by mountains on all sides.</s> <s id="s99">It is a favourite resort of tourists.</s> <s id="s100">A few hundred yards behind the Salutation Inn is the <enamex sw="w13940" long="-2.9511" lat="54.4328" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY38400457" name="Stock Gill Force" conf="99992">Stock Gill River</enamex>, where is a fine fall called the</s></p>
<p><s id="s101"><enamex sw="w13990" long="-2.9511" lat="54.4328" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY38400457" name="Stock Gill Force" conf="99992">Stock Gill Force</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s102">Which is seventy feet in height, consisting of four separate leaps.</s> <s id="s103">Owing to the superabundance of wood, and undergrowth, it is not easy to obtain a good view of this fall.</s> <s id="s104">Visitors usually view it from the top of the bank, which is the worst position in which any fall can be seen.</s> <s id="s105">By a little scrambling, however, the view presented in our engraving may be obtained.</s> <s id="s106">This fall being easy of access, will naturally engage the visitors attention first.</s> <s id="s107">Afterwards he will visit</s></p>
<p><s id="s108"><enamex sw="w14487" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s109">This is the largest of all the English lakes, but the character of the scenery is not so grand as that of the others.</s> <s id="s110">The visitor is, therefore, in danger of being disappointed if he be not prepared for a much softer - but to some minds not less pleasing - style of scenery than that through which he has already passed.</s> <s id="s111">The landscape generally is characterized more by grace and richness than by grandeur.</s> <s id="s112">Measured by the road, <enamex sw="w14929" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex> is upwards of thirteen miles long - in a straight line it is not much more than ten miles - and about a mile broad at its widest part.</s> <s id="s113">There are two principal feeders to this lake, - the rivers Rothay and Brathay.</s> <s id="s114">The first, rising in the mountains near <enamex sw="w15194" long="-3.060646544049678" lat="54.54323368129527" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403099" name="St. John's Castlerigg and Wythburn CP" conf="2.4">Wythburn</enamex>, passes through the lakes of <enamex sw="w15232" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> and <enamex sw="w15245" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275806" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex> before entering <enamex sw="w15267" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s115">The second rises in a mountain range called <enamex sw="w15323" long="-3.118464887566315" lat="54.45756762847756" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11191353" name="Langdale Pikes" conf="2.4">Langdale Pikes</enamex>, and unites with the Rothay near <enamex sw="w15371" long="-1.240323069455941" lat="52.55454224170197" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11122199" name="Croft Lodge" conf="0.9758180231">Croft Lodge</enamex>, a short distance from the lake.</s> <s id="s116">There is a very curious and interesting circumstance connected with the fish of these rivers.</s> <s id="s117">As the spawning season approaches, the trout and charr ascend the stream together until they arrive at the point where the waters unite.</s> <s id="s118">Here they always separate; all the trout proceeding up the Rothay, while all the charr go up the Brathay.</s> <s id="s119">It is difficult to conjecture the cause of this separation, but the perfectness of the understanding on both sides, and the unvarying regularity of the arrangement, would incline us to suppose that their Creator had endowed these fish with an instinct little, if at all, short of reason.</s> <s id="s120">Among other tributary streams is the <enamex sw="w16078" long="-2.916539146877075" lat="54.39634869266406" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11306429" name="Troutbeck Bridge" conf="2.6">Troutbeck</enamex>, which falls into the lake near <enamex sw="w16120" long="-2.931737280270144" lat="54.38724387708846" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11096668" name="Calgarth Hall" conf="2.2">Calgarth</enamex>.</s> <s id="s121">Its waters are discharged at <enamex sw="w16159" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex> where they receive the name of the River <enamex sw="w16213" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex>, which, two miles farther on, falls into the estuary called the <enamex sw="w16283" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex> Sands.</s> <s id="s122">At <enamex sw="w16299" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex> there is a ferry over the lake, from which a fine view of the mountains and scenery at its head is obtained.</s> <s id="s123"><enamex sw="w16416" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex> is very deep, varying from thirty to a hundred and twenty feet; and it is remarkably clear, permitting the eye to penetrate far into its depths, where the finny inhabitants gambol in shoals.</s> <s id="s124">Owing to its great depth heavy rains do not make any perceptible increase in its volume.</s> <s id="s125">At <enamex sw="w16710" long="-2.963375971597467" lat="54.42294965090946" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11314358" name="Waterhead" conf="2.6">Waterhead</enamex>, scarcely a mile distant, boats may be procured for excursions on the lake.</s> <s id="s126">These excursions, of course, will be made to various parts according to the taste of the visitors.</s> <s id="s127">One good route to take is along the Brathay coast, and across the lake to <enamex sw="w16969" long="-3.000560623790019" lat="54.24386305141168" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16529" name="Low Wood" conf="2.6">Low Wood</enamex> Inn.</s> <s id="s128">The island of <enamex sw="w16997" long="-2.931127009816036" lat="54.36028298374819" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11074690" name="Belle Isle" conf="2.4">Belle Isle</enamex>, near <enamex sw="w17014" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, is a point of interest.</s> <s id="s129">It is upwards of a mile in circumference, and belongs to H. Curwen Esq., who has a summer residence on it.</s> <s id="s130">Strangers are allowed to land and walk among the groves and woods with which abounds, and, as plants and underwood are luxuriant, it presents a rich field of research to the botanist.</s> <s id="s131">From its upper end the prospect is very fine, embracing the head of the lake with its bays and wooded promontories; its islands and its back ground of mountains, - the Kentmore range, <enamex sw="w17522" long="-2.85" lat="54.48333" type="other" gazref="unlock:4571317" name="High Street" conf="2">High Street</enamex>, <enamex sw="w17535" name="Wansfield">Wansfield</enamex> Pike, <enamex sw="w17551" long="-2.8708" lat="54.4619" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_NY43650774" name="Hill Bell" conf="99991">Hill Bell</enamex>, <enamex sw="w17562" long="-2.99223" lat="54.49726" type="other" gazref="unlock:4574128" name="Fairfield" conf="2">Fairfield</enamex> and <enamex sw="w17576" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275806" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex> Nab.</s> <s id="s132">The islands in view are Hen Holm, and <enamex sw="w17625" long="-2.9278" lat="54.3693" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD39829748" name="Lady Holm" conf="99992">Lady Holm</enamex>.</s> <s id="s133">There is a point just behind the <enamex sw="w17669" long="0.8941297567209112" lat="51.35229136809566" type="other" gazref="unlock:11143456" name="Ferry Inn, The" conf="0.7065073503">Ferry Inn</enamex> which ought to be visited, as a fine view of the surrounding scenery may be obtained from it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s134">In this neighbourhood are many interesting walks; among others there is a foot-path to the top of <enamex sw="w17871" long="-2.9142" lat="54.3659" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD407971" name="Biscot How" conf="99992">Bisket</enamex> How, and a walk through the <enamex sw="w17906" long="0.4711875455860139" lat="51.76672616130932" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11240909" name="Parsonage Green" conf="1.435205914">Parsonage</enamex> Land to the <enamex  sw="w17928" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Ferry Point</enamex>.</s> <s id="s135"><enamex sw="w17941" long="-2.650576036698101" lat="54.1374080041431" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11293604" name="Storrs Hall" conf="2.2">Storrs Hall</enamex> is finely situated, and worthy of a visit.</s> <s id="s136">Excursions to the various islets of the lake will also be found interesting, an, for those who wish to take a rapid survey of its entire length, there are steamers which make daily trips from one end of the lake to the other.</s> <s id="s137">The road from <enamex sw="w18236" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex> to the head of <enamex sw="w18259" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex> is picturesque, and being little more than four miles in length, might, for the sake of variety, be taken by those who make the downward journey by water.</s> <s id="s138"><enamex sw="w18425" long="-3.000560623790019" lat="54.24386305141168" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16529" name="Low Wood" conf="2.6">Low Wood</enamex> inn is passed on the way; it affords a fine view of the lake.</s> <s id="s139">The lower part of <enamex sw="w18514" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex> is not often visited, but there are many interesting points of view there, and the <enamex sw="w18608" long="-3.3297" lat="54.3116" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11116309" name="Coniston Fells" conf="99992">Coniston mountains</enamex> are seen rising in the distance above the western shores.</s> <s id="s140">Should the visitor have sufficient time he would find a drive round the entire lake( about thirty miles) an agreeable and interesting excursion.</s></p>
<p><s id="s141">At the ferry near <enamex sw="w18848" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, about the year 1635, a marriage party was crossing in a boat, when one of those squalls, to which <enamex sw="w18955" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex> is rather liable, upset the boat, and all its occupants, about fifty in number, including the bride and bridegroom, were drowned.</s></p>
<p><s id="s142">A branch from the <enamex sw="w19114" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> and <enamex sw="w19128" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> railway conducts from <enamex sw="w19159" long="-2.745809060481465" lat="54.32561646560368" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185036" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex> to <enamex sw="w19169" long="-1.539173377063468" lat="53.58995452007683" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11077930" name="Birthwaite Hall" conf="1.063856512">Birthwaite</enamex>, a mile to the north of <enamex sw="w19204" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, and near the shores of the lake.</s> <s id="s143">From the station here coaches run to <enamex sw="w19283" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> and <enamex sw="w19297" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, <enamex sw="w19306" long="-2.993112822792783" lat="54.37776609422815" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167809" name="Hawkshead" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex> and <enamex sw="w19320" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex>; and the mail goes daily to <enamex sw="w19357" long="-3.360999570010009" lat="54.6624702211972" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10233" name="Cockermouth" conf="2.6">Cockermouth</enamex>, from which there is a railway to <enamex sw="w19403" long="-3.574638671553102" lat="54.54261524067765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063" name="Whitehaven" conf="3.078900843">Whitehaven</enamex>.</s> <s id="s144">The numerous elegant villas, and picturesque cottages, which nestle amid the luxuriant woodlands, and cover the verdant slopes and shores of <enamex sw="w19556" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>, add greatly to the richness of the landscape.</s> <s id="s145">Besides the stations already mentioned, <enamex sw="w19654" long="0.8941297567209112" lat="51.35229136809566" type="other" gazref="unlock:11143456" name="Ferry Inn, The" conf="0.7065073503">Ferry Inn</enamex>, on the promontory over against <enamex sw="w19696" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w19709" long="-2.632510351825869" lat="54.58500679477122" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:38029" name="Newby" conf="2.6">Newby</enamex> Bridge at the foot of the lake, afford good accommodation, guides and boats, to the tourist.</s></p>
<p><s id="s146">In the route we have laid down, <enamex sw="w19840" long="-3.069150080092114" lat="54.34116196598502" type="water" gazref="unlock:11115206" name="Coniston Water" conf="2.4">Coniston Water</enamex> and <enamex sw="w19859" long="-2.977291334332336" lat="54.3599180438576" type="water" gazref="unlock:11140740" name="Esthwaite Water" conf="2.4">Esthwaite</enamex> Lake are omitted, neither of them being equal to the other scenery of the lake district; but, for the benefit of the tourist who has much time on his hands, we subjoin a brief outline of these lakes and their environs.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s147"><enamex sw="w20089" long="-2.993112822792783" lat="54.37776609422815" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167809" name="Hawkshead" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s148">A small town with an inn( the <enamex sw="w20132" long="-2.45814" lat="54.97075" type="other" gazref="unlock:5826225" name="Haltwhistle Red Lion Tower" conf="0.9013853057">Red Lion</enamex>), is scarcely five miles from <enamex sw="w20171" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>.</s> <s id="s149">There is nothing of particular interest about it except that Wordsworth the poet and his brother were educated at the school there.</s> <s id="s150">Close to this town lies the lake of</s></p>
<p> <s id="s151"><enamex sw="w20351" long="-2.977291334332336" lat="54.3599180438576" type="water" gazref="unlock:11140740" name="Esthwaite Water" conf="2.4">Esthwaite</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s152">About two miles long, and scarcely half a mile broad.</s> <s id="s153">The scenery around this lake is tame, but pleasing, and a curious floating island, of about thirty or forty yards in circumference, lies on a pond near the head of the lake; during windy weather, this island, with the trees and bushes which cover it, is observed to move about.</s> <s id="s154">After leaving <enamex sw="w20710" long="-2.993112822792783" lat="54.37776609422815" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167809" name="Hawkshead" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex> the road passes an old farm house, formerly the residence of some of the monks of <enamex sw="w20802" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.175673707">Furness Abbey</enamex>.</s> <s id="s155">From the height here there is a fine view of the mountains around <enamex sw="w20883" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>.</s> <s id="s156">Beyond this the road becomes bare and uninteresting, until the valley of <enamex sw="w20967" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> is reached.</s> <s id="s157">The view of the vale with its varied scenery, amid which rises the <enamex sw="w21055" long="-3.1221" lat="54.3704" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:4565407" name="Coniston Old Man" conf="99991">Old Man Mountain</enamex>, is rich, and particularly gratifying to the eye after the bleak road-scenery from which it has just emerged.</s> <s id="s158">Shortly after, <enamex sw="w21197" long="-2.963375971597467" lat="54.42294965090946" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11314358" name="Waterhead" conf="2.6">Waterhead</enamex> Inn is reached.</s> <s id="s159">It is six miles from <enamex sw="w21244" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, and forms a convenient resting point from which to make excursions in the neighbourhood.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s160"><enamex sw="w21345" long="-3.069150080092114" lat="54.34116196598502" type="water" gazref="unlock:11115206" name="Coniston Water" conf="2.4">Coniston Water</enamex>,,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s161">Or <enamex sw="w21367" long="-3.0765" lat="54.3361" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2652425" name="Thurstain water" conf="99991">Thurston Lake</enamex>, is six miles in length, and nearly a mile in breadth.</s> <s id="s162">The village of <enamex sw="w21451" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> is pleasantly situated under a hill on the west side of the water.</s> <s id="s163"><enamex sw="w21527" long="-3.07188" lat="54.35783" type="other" gazref="unlock:5826053" name="Coniston Hall" conf="2">Coniston hall</enamex>, an ancient building, is also on this side of the lake, and cottages are thinly scattered over the heights that encircle its head.</s> <s id="s164">A pleasant road runs through the margin, sometimes passing through groves and coppices, at other times crossing over open ground and commanding a fine prospect.</s> <s id="s165">At the north-west angle of the lake, near its outlet, rises the <enamex sw="w21897" long="-3.1221" lat="54.3704" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:4565407" name="Coniston Old Man" conf="99991">Old Man Mountain</enamex>, the ascent of which should be made, as it commands an extensive prospect towards the south and west, while in other directions it is surrounded by the frowning heights of the neighbouring mountains.</s> <s id="s166">The <enamex sw="w22118" long="-3.12208" lat="54.37042" type="other" gazref="unlock:4565407" name="Old Man of Coniston" conf="2">Old Man</enamex> is the highest peak of the <enamex sw="w22153" long="-3.3297" lat="54.3116" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11116309" name="Coniston Fells" conf="99992">Coniston Fell</enamex> range, and is about 2580 feet high.</s> <s id="s167">In very clear weather, <enamex sw="w22226" long="-1.500309168183582" lat="54.64543028105785" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13372576" name="Bradbury and the Isle CP" conf="1.279890826">the Isle</enamex> of Man may be seen from its summit.</s> <s id="s168">It consists chiefly of slate, which being admirably adapted for roofing, is excavated in large quantities.</s> <s id="s169">Besides this there are extensive copper mines situated about half way up the hill, into which they penetrate horizontally for half a mile, while the shafts are upwards of two hundred yards deep.</s> <s id="s170">Great numbers of people are employed in the working of those mines which belong to Lady Le <enamex  sw="w22664" name="Not a placename">Fleming</enamex> of <enamex sw="w22675" long="-2.98" lat="54.4483" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36550632" name="Rydal Hall" conf="99992">Rydal Hall</enamex>, who is also proprietor of the slate quarries.</s> <s id="s171">At a village called Low Nibthwaite, near <enamex sw="w22774" long="-3.082642082112015" lat="54.26913154387659" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209126" name="Lowick Bridge" conf="2.6">Lowick Bridge</enamex>, where the lake terminates in the Crake rivulet, there is an iron forge.</s> <s id="s172">The feeders of <enamex sw="w22876" long="-3.069150080092114" lat="54.34116196598502" type="water" gazref="unlock:11115206" name="Coniston Water" conf="2.4">Coniston Water</enamex> are, <enamex sw="w22896" long="-3.407509781674068" lat="54.60622591156607" type="water" gazref="unlock:8782323" name="Black Beck" conf="2.4">Black Beck</enamex> and <enamex sw="w22911" long="-3.0665" lat="54.3632" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD30809693" name="Coniston Beck" conf="99992">Coniston Beck</enamex>, and the charr in the lake are said to be the finest in <enamex  sw="w22981" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s> <s id="s173">In ascending the <enamex sw="w23007" long="-3.12208" lat="54.37042" type="other" gazref="unlock:4565407" name="Old Man of Coniston" conf="2">Old Man</enamex>, start from the village at its base and follow the road leading to the copper mines.</s> <s id="s174">At the distance of half a mile from the village is a foot-bridge over the stream, which must be crossed; after this the traveller may be left to find his way to the top.</s> <s id="s175">Instead of returning to <enamex sw="w23294" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> by the same road, through <enamex sw="w23330" long="-2.993112822792783" lat="54.37776609422815" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167809" name="Hawkshead" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex>, the pedestrian may take the road leading from <enamex sw="w23387" long="-2.963375971597467" lat="54.42294965090946" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11314358" name="Waterhead" conf="2.6">Waterhead</enamex> Inn through <enamex sw="w23409" long="-3.071689835487597" lat="54.38230622281267" type="water" gazref="unlock:8774875" name="Yewdale Beck" conf="2.4">Yewdale</enamex>, which, at little more than three miles distant, joins the <enamex sw="w23476" long="-3.051865815747152" lat="54.42093505077031" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:34442" name="Little Langdale" conf="2.6">Little Langdale</enamex> road at a point about three miles from <enamex sw="w23531" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>.</s> <s id="s176">Walks and excursions around <enamex sw="w23570" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> are innumerable and full of interest.</s> <s id="s177">We can only enumerate a few of them.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s178">The <enamex sw="w23660" long="-3.1185" lat="54.4576" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11191353" name="Langdale Pikes" conf="99991">Great and Little</enamex> <enamex sw="w23677" long="-3.1185" lat="54.4576" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11191353" name="Langdale Pikes" conf="99991">Langdales</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s179">Of which <enamex sw="w23699" long="-3.087378732080662" lat="54.44886278925754" type="water" gazref="unlock:11158973" name="Great Langdale Beck" conf="2.4">Great Langdale</enamex> is the finer.</s> <s id="s180">If the tourist desires to visit both <enamex sw="w23765" long="-3.1185" lat="54.4576" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11191353" name="Langdale Pikes" conf="99991">Langdales</enamex> let him go by <enamex sw="w23789" long="-2.977323760699877" lat="54.42251395329949" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33323" name="Clappersgate" conf="2.6">Clappersgate</enamex>, along the banks of the Brathay.</s> <s id="s181">About three miles from <enamex sw="w23858" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> there is a fall of about twenty feet in height, which is embosomed in remarkably fine scenery.</s> <s id="s182">It is a little above <enamex sw="w23984" long="-3.009610244816154" lat="54.42257207345681" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11284612" name="Skelwith Bridge" conf="2.6">Skelwith Bridge</enamex>.</s> <s id="s183">About a mile further on, the road re-crosses the stream at <enamex sw="w24060" long="-3.0373" lat="54.4191" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY32790313" name="Colwith Bridge" conf="99992">Colwith Bridge</enamex>, above which there is another fell named <enamex sw="w24116" long="-3.037259078" lat="54.41914884" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00142" name="Colwith Force" conf="99992">Colwith Force</enamex>, about seventy feet in height.</s> <s id="s184">It is in a dell close to the road.</s> <s id="s185">A short distance farther on is <enamex sw="w24227" long="-3.065707950389127" lat="54.41916885039083" type="water" gazref="unlock:8792815" name="Little Langdale Tarn" conf="2.4">Little Langdale Tarn</enamex>, after which the road diverging to the right ascends into a solitary scene, in the midst of which is <enamex sw="w24349" long="-2.770858020526925" lat="54.0198429259591" type="water" gazref="unlock:11080945" name="Blea Tarn Resr" conf="2.4">Blea Tarn</enamex>, and thence descends into <enamex sw="w24385" long="-3.087378732080662" lat="54.44886278925754" type="water" gazref="unlock:11158973" name="Great Langdale Beck" conf="2.4">Great Langdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s186">At a farm house called <enamex sw="w24424" long="-2.493908568695039" lat="54.62513531970662" type="water" gazref="unlock:8786657" name="Mill Beck" conf="2.4">Mill Beck</enamex> refreshment can be obtained.</s> <s id="s187"><enamex sw="w24463" long="-3.051865815747152" lat="54.42093505077031" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:34442" name="Little Langdale" conf="2.6">Langdale</enamex> pikes may be ascended, and Dungeon Gill Force visited.</s> <s id="s188"><enamex sw="w24527" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.4">Over</enamex> this fall there is a natural bridge of which Wordsworth writes:</s></p>
<p><s id="s189">" There is a spot which you may see, If ever you to <enamex sw="w24647" long="-3.051865815747152" lat="54.42093505077031" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:34442" name="Little Langdale" conf="2.6">Langdale</enamex> go; Into a chasm a mighty block Hath fallen, and made a bridge of rock.</s> <s id="s190">The gulf is deep below, And in a basin black and small Receives a lofty waterfall."</s></p>
<p><s id="s191">There are two roads through <enamex sw="w24840" long="-3.087378732080662" lat="54.44886278925754" type="water" gazref="unlock:11158973" name="Great Langdale Beck" conf="2.4">Great Langdale</enamex> by which to return.</s> <s id="s192">The one near the hills on the left is to be preferred by pedestrians; the other is more suitable for carriages, and both pass through lovely scenery.</s> <s id="s193">They separate at the chapel a mile and a half from <enamex sw="w25076" long="-2.493908568695039" lat="54.62513531970662" type="water" gazref="unlock:8786657" name="Mill Beck" conf="2.4">Mill Beck</enamex>.</s> <s id="s194">The first conducts by <enamex sw="w25109" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> and <enamex sw="w25122" long="-2.999" lat="54.4472" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_7288050" name="Rydal Water" conf="99991">Rydalmere</enamex> to the <enamex sw="w25139" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> road; the other, passing <enamex sw="w25172" long="-3.025245753231923" lat="54.43142891663435" type="water" gazref="unlock:11139812" name="Elter Water" conf="2.4">Elter Water</enamex>, <enamex sw="w25185" long="-3.010052272531424" lat="54.4405454128785" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11206667" name="Loughrigg Fell" conf="2.4">Loughrigg Fell</enamex> and Tarn, joins the <enamex sw="w25220" long="-2.977323760699877" lat="54.42251395329949" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33323" name="Clappersgate" conf="2.6">Clappersgate</enamex> road.</s> <s id="s195">The whole walk, by either way, from <enamex sw="w25275" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> to Dungeon Gill Force and back, is not more than seventeen or eighteen miles.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s196"><enamex sw="w25364" long="-3.010052272531424" lat="54.4405454128785" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11206667" name="Loughrigg Fell" conf="2.4">Loughrigg Fell</enamex></s> </p>
<p><s id="s197">Should be ascended.</s> <s id="s198">It is not much above 1100 feet in height, and commands a fine view of all the lakes and mountains in its immediate vicinity.</s> <s id="s199">It is little more than a mile from the village.</s></p>
<p><s id="s200">The vale of</s></p>
<p> <s id="s201"><enamex sw="w25586" long="-2.916539146877075" lat="54.39634869266406" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11306429" name="Troutbeck Bridge" conf="2.6">Troutbeck</enamex></s> </p>
<p><s id="s202">is another charming scene.</s> <s id="s203">Go from <enamex sw="w25632" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> to near <enamex sw="w25650" long="-2.91667" lat="54.45" type="other" gazref="unlock:4569619" name="Kirkstone Pass" conf="2">Kirkstone Pass</enamex>, then turn to the right and walk down the vale along the banks of the <enamex sw="w25735" long="-2.916539146877075" lat="54.39634869266406" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11306429" name="Troutbeck Bridge" conf="2.6">Troutbeck</enamex> to <enamex sw="w25748" long="-3.000560623790019" lat="54.24386305141168" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16529" name="Low Wood" conf="2.6">Low Wood</enamex>, and back along <enamex sw="w25773" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex> to <enamex sw="w25787" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>; being a circuit of about ten miles through very agreeable scenery.</s> <s id="s204">One of the finest views that can be had of <enamex sw="w25908" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex> is from this road.</s> <s id="s205">There are also several interesting walks around <enamex sw="w25986" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, which is about eight miles from <enamex sw="w26027" long="-2.745809060481465" lat="54.32561646560368" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185036" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex>; but to particularize them would be impossible within our limits, and perhaps unnecessary, as the tourist will find it more convenient to obtain minute local information on the spot, as occasion may require.</s></p>
<p><s id="s206"><enamex sw="w26242" long="-2.993866462466064" lat="54.44746550347175" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796733" name="Rydal Water" conf="2.4">Rydal Water</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s207">And <enamex sw="w26260" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, now claim our attention.</s> <s id="s208">The highway to <enamex sw="w26310" long="-2.9842" lat="54.4476" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2638912" name="Rydal" conf="99992">Rydal village</enamex> is not more than a mile and a quarter from <enamex sw="w26367" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>; but for pedestrians, we recommend the footpath along the banks of the Rothay, under <enamex sw="w26462" long="-3.010052272531424" lat="54.4405454128785" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11206667" name="Loughrigg Fell" conf="2.4">Loughrigg Fell</enamex>, as being much more sylvan and agreeable.</s> <s id="s209">By this route the traveller proceeds along the road to <enamex sw="w26574" long="-2.977323760699877" lat="54.42251395329949" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33323" name="Clappersgate" conf="2.6">Clappersgate</enamex>, until he reaches <enamex sw="w26605" long="-2.9693" lat="54.4265" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY37210388" name="Rothay Bridge" conf="99992">Rothay Bridge</enamex>; crosses this, enters the first gate on the right, and proceeds thence along the river to <enamex sw="w26709" long="-2.9792" lat="54.4449" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36600594" name="Pelter Bridge" conf="99992">Pelter Bridge</enamex>.</s> <s id="s210">About a mile is thus added to the distance.</s> <s id="s211">Instead of crossing the bridge, the pedestrian may, if disposed for a longer walk, keep to the left, along the road which passes behind <enamex sw="w26904" long="-2.9838" lat="54.4453" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36300599" name="Coat How" conf="99992">Coat How</enamex> farm, by which he will gain the southern shore of the lake, and ultimately, by a steep ascent, reach a fine terrace, which commands a magnificent view of <enamex sw="w27067" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s212">It is from this point that our drawing of that lake is taken.</s> <s id="s213">A little farther on, the road joins the <enamex sw="w27179" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> road, which conducts to the village of that name.</s> <s id="s214">By the route first mentioned, the northern shore of the lake is kept, and the pretty village of <enamex sw="w27334" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275806" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex> is passed.</s> <s id="s215">Here, on the right, is <enamex sw="w27374" long="-2.98" lat="54.4483" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36550632" name="Rydal Hall" conf="99992">Rydal Hall</enamex>, where are two picturesque falls, that ought to be seen.</s> <s id="s216">It is necessary to make application at the cottage near the chapel, in order to accomplish this.</s> <s id="s217">The lower fall is the finer of the two, and may be seen from a summerhouse in the grounds.</s> <s id="s218">There are some splendid trees in <enamex sw="w27663" long="-81.47375" lat="28.58473" type="other" gazref="unlock:10792570" name="The Groves Mobile Home Park" conf="0.6546106913">the park</enamex>, well worth seeing.</s> <s id="s219">The main road beyond does not afford good views of this the smallest, but one of the most beautiful, of the English lakes.</s> <s id="s220">One of the few good points is <enamex sw="w27845" long="-3.099191618291894" lat="54.31392581612592" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11300248" name="Thrang Crag Wood" conf="2.4">Thrang Crag</enamex>, through which the road is cut, a few hundred yards beyond <enamex sw="w27916" long="-2.9842" lat="54.4476" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2638912" name="Rydal" conf="99992">Rydal village</enamex>, on the <enamex sw="w27938" long="-3.137682216" lat="54.60042036" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00107" name="Keswick" conf="99992">Keswick side</enamex>.</s> <s id="s221">On this lake, also, is <enamex sw="w27975" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11275810" name="Rydal Mount" conf="2.2">Rydal Mount</enamex>, long the dwelling-place of Wordsworth.</s> <s id="s222">It stands on the hill called <enamex sw="w28056" long="-3.984187152787255" lat="51.56910854941358" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11188501" name="Knab, The" conf="1.242494269">Knab</enamex> <enamex sw="w28061" long="-2.053812050986411" lat="54.31892107938371" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11226948" name="Nappa Scar" conf="1.597940748">Scar</enamex>.</s> <s id="s223">From this point there are some fine views.</s> <s id="s224">But we cannot too strongly recommend the bridle-path, on the southern shore, to those who are anxious to see the lake, with its two little grass islets, to advantage.</s> <s id="s225">From <enamex sw="w28282" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11275810" name="Rydal Mount" conf="2.2">Rydal Mount</enamex>, a footpath passes under <enamex sw="w28319" long="-3.984187152787255" lat="51.56910854941358" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11188501" name="Knab, The" conf="1.242494269">Knab</enamex> <enamex sw="w28324" long="-2.053812050986411" lat="54.31892107938371" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11226948" name="Nappa Scar" conf="1.597940748">Scar</enamex>, and rejoins the main road at <enamex sw="w28359" long="-3.007031653" lat="54.44969239" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00211" name="White Moss Quarry" conf="99992">White Moss Quarry</enamex>.</s> <s id="s226">From this walk many charming views may be had of the scenery around <enamex sw="w28446" long="-2.999" lat="54.4472" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7288050" name="Rydal Water" conf="99992">Rydal Lake</enamex>, which is eminently beautiful.</s> <s id="s227">Near <enamex sw="w28493" long="-3.007031653" lat="54.44969239" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00211" name="White Moss Quarry" conf="99992">White Moss Quarry</enamex>, there are two old roads to</s></p>
<p><s id="s228"><enamex sw="w28539" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>,( Inns - The <enamex sw="w28561" long="-2.45814" lat="54.97075" type="other" gazref="unlock:5826225" name="Haltwhistle Red Lion Tower" conf="0.9013853057">Red Lion</enamex>, And The Swan,)</s> </p>
<p><s id="s229">The lower one is the best, and ought to be taken in preference to the other, or to the main road, as the views from it are finer.</s> <s id="s230">It conducts past the celebrated" <enamex sw="w28750" long="-3.0144" lat="54.4496" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_NY34320650" name="Wishing Gate" conf="99991">Wishing</enamex> Gate," and joins the new road, near Wordsworth's old house, at <enamex sw="w28821" long="-2.916940042416563" lat="54.4143226017226" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11303657" name="Town End" conf="2.6">Town End</enamex>.</s> <s id="s231">This lake is larger than <enamex sw="w28856" long="-2.999" lat="54.4472" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_7288050" name="Rydal Water" conf="99991">Rydalmere</enamex>, and the vale is remarkably beautiful.</s> <s id="s232">The little hill called <enamex sw="w28928" long="-3.0259" lat="54.4623" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY33600792" name="Butterlip How" conf="99992">Butterlip</enamex> How affords a fine view, and <enamex sw="w28967" long="-3.020752642" lat="54.44328602" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00054" name="Red Bank" conf="99991">Red Bank</enamex> should be visited.</s> <s id="s233"><enamex sw="w28995" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> is, moreover, peculiarly interesting, as having been the residence for many years of Wordsworth, whose magic verse has sung of almost every nook, knoll, and rivulet around it.</s> <s id="s234">To this vale he brought his young bride in 1802.</s> <s id="s235">Here many of his brightest and happiest days were spent, - and his dust reposes in the village church of <enamex sw="w29334" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s236">Our view is taken from the road passing round <enamex sw="w29390" long="-3.010052272531424" lat="54.4405454128785" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11206667" name="Loughrigg Fell" conf="2.4">Loughrigg Fell</enamex>.</s> <s id="s237">It shows the village in the centre, with <enamex sw="w29447" long="-3.057695522673377" lat="54.49406878163224" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11291661" name="Steel Fell" conf="2.4">Steel Fell</enamex> and <enamex sw="w29462" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex> immediately behind it.</s> <s id="s238"><enamex sw="w29496" long="-3.041800543566656" lat="54.47622985854962" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169680" name="Helm Crag" conf="2.4">Helm Crag</enamex> is on the left, and part of <enamex sw="w29534" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169753" name="Helvellyn" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex> on the right.</s> <s id="s239"><enamex sw="w29558" long="-3.041800543566656" lat="54.47622985854962" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169680" name="Helm Crag" conf="2.4">Helm Crag</enamex> may be ascended, for the sake of the commanding view.</s> <s id="s240">It is about two miles from the inn to the top, and it has a curious formation of broken rocks on its summit, which has been compared by Wordsworth to an old woman seated on the crag.</s> <s id="s241">The view from this crag embraces the whole of the vale of <enamex sw="w29863" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, <enamex sw="w29873" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169753" name="Helvellyn" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex>, <enamex sw="w29884" long="-3.042257566142511" lat="54.49420285694539" type="other" gazref="unlock:11134276" name="Dunmail Raise" conf="2">Dunmail Raise</enamex>, <enamex sw="w29899" long="-2.93275663555211" lat="54.43217842069659" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11313036" name="Wansfell Pike" conf="2.4">Wansfell Pike</enamex>, <enamex sw="w29914" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex>, <enamex sw="w29926" long="-3.118464887566315" lat="54.45756762847756" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11191353" name="Langdale Pikes" conf="2.4">Langdale Pikes</enamex>, <enamex sw="w29942" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>, <enamex sw="w29954" long="-2.977291334332336" lat="54.3599180438576" type="water" gazref="unlock:11140740" name="Esthwaite Water" conf="2.4">Esthwaite Water</enamex>, and the <enamex sw="w29979" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> range.</s> <s id="s242">We would recommend the tourist to take up his abode at <enamex sw="w30050" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99992">Grasmere village</enamex>, for short time, as it is a convenient station for visiting the objects of beauty and interest which cluster round it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s243">The secluded little valley of</s></p>
<p> <s id="s244"><enamex sw="w30217" long="-3.0414" lat="54.4656" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_NY326083" name="Easdale" conf="99991">Easdale</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s245">Lying between <enamex sw="w30241" long="-3.041800543566656" lat="54.47622985854962" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169680" name="Helm Crag" conf="2.4">Helm Crag</enamex> and <enamex sw="w30255" long="-3.041115952192079" lat="54.44927025558928" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284001" name="Silver How" conf="2.4">Silver How</enamex>, is extremely picturesque.</s> <s id="s246">Being elevated above <enamex sw="w30314" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, the ascent affords many fine prospects of the valley.</s> <s id="s247">About a mile and a half up the vale is a small cascade, called <enamex sw="w30441" long="-3.196893714794284" lat="54.50175942580831" type="water" gazref="unlock:11286918" name="Sour Milk Gill" conf="2.4">Sour Milk Gill</enamex>, on a stream which issues from a large tarn, less than half a mile further up.</s> <s id="s248">Beyond this there is another tarn, named <enamex sw="w30576" long="-3.0878" lat="54.4697" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY296088" name="Coddale" conf="99992">Coddale</enamex>; and further on, to the left, is a third, called <enamex sw="w30633" long="-3.100130073195233" lat="54.45845497536493" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796834" name="Stickle Tarn" conf="2.4">Stickle Tarn</enamex>, where trout fishing is good.</s> <s id="s249">It lies at the foot of <enamex sw="w30699" long="-3.118464887566315" lat="54.45756762847756" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11191353" name="Langdale Pikes" conf="2.4">Langdale Pikes</enamex>, about three miles from <enamex sw="w30738" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s250">Those who are fond of climbing can ascend <enamex sw="w30790" long="-2.872764887218234" lat="55.23254273841246" type="other" gazref="unlock:11245240" name="Pikes, The" conf="0.8862142527">the Pikes</enamex> from this valley, or cross the <enamex sw="w30831" long="-3.0878" lat="54.4697" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY296088" name="Coddale" conf="99992">Coddale</enamex> Fell, into <enamex sw="w30850" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s251">One of the summits of <enamex sw="w30884" long="-3.118464887566315" lat="54.45756762847756" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11191353" name="Langdale Pikes" conf="2.4">Langdale Pikes</enamex> is 2400 feet high, and is named <enamex sw="w30931" long="-3.10304097696897" lat="54.45770939997526" type="other" gazref="unlock:11166509" name="Harrison Stickle" conf="2">Harrison Stickle</enamex>; the other, 2300 feet, is called Pike o' Stickle.</s> <s id="s252">From either of these tops the view is very fine, embracing, of course, all that has been already seen from the summit of <enamex sw="w31119" long="-3.041800543566656" lat="54.47622985854962" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169680" name="Helm Crag" conf="2.4">Helm Crag</enamex>.</s> <s id="s253">The highest peak has the most extensive range, including part of the distant sea.</s> <s id="s254"><enamex sw="w31212" long="-2.872764887218234" lat="55.23254273841246" type="other" gazref="unlock:11245240" name="Pikes, The" conf="0.8862142527">The Pikes</enamex> are usually ascended from <enamex sw="w31248" long="-3.051865815747152" lat="54.42093505077031" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:34442" name="Little Langdale" conf="2.6">Langdale</enamex>; but, if the present route be adopted, it will be found more convenient and agreeable every way to ascend them from <enamex sw="w31373" long="-3.0414" lat="54.4656" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_NY326083" name="Easdale" conf="99991">Easdale</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s255">Having explored <enamex sw="w31398" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, the traveller should now proceed to <enamex sw="w31444" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s256">Soon after quitting the village, the Swan Inn is passed.</s> <s id="s257">Should the tourist have omitted to ascend <enamex sw="w31552" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169753" name="Helvellyn" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex> from <enamex sw="w31567" long="-2.935009110358855" lat="54.53103319127506" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241197" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>, he may do so very conveniently from this point, from which the mountain is about four miles distant.</s> <s id="s258">The road then rises gradually until the pass of <enamex sw="w31728" long="-3.042257566142511" lat="54.49420285694539" type="other" gazref="unlock:11134276" name="Dunmail Raise" conf="2">Dunmail Raise</enamex> is reached, from which a fine retrospective view is to be had.</s> <s id="s259">There is a tradition connected with this pass, - that Dunmail, King of Cumberland, was defeated here in 945 by the Saxon King Edmund, who put out the eyes of Dunmail's two sons, and gave his lands to Malcolm King of <enamex  sw="w32021" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s260">There is a cairn in memory of the victory.</s> <s id="s261">In reference to this, Wordsworth writes as follows: -</s></p>
<p><s id="s262">" They now have reached that pile of stones, Heaped over brave King Dunmail's bones: He who once held supreme command, Last king of rocky <enamex  sw="w32264" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>: His bones, and those of all his power, Slain here in a disastrous hour."</s></p>
<p><s id="s263"><enamex sw="w32349" long="-3.057695522673377" lat="54.49406878163224" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11291661" name="Steel Fell" conf="2.4">Steel Fell</enamex> lies to the west and <enamex sw="w32381" long="-3.01138127729091" lat="54.49446509482051" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11279836" name="Seat Sandal" conf="2.4">Seat Sandal</enamex> to the east.</s> <s id="s264">A little more than a mile farther, at the foot of <enamex sw="w32456" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169753" name="Helvellyn" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex>, are <enamex sw="w32471" long="-2.318664919124773" lat="54.76790955907933" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11226122" name="Nag's Head" conf="2.339604894">Nag's Head</enamex> and <enamex sw="w32486" long="-3.060646544049678" lat="54.54323368129527" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403099" name="St. John's Castlerigg and Wythburn CP" conf="2.4">Wythburn</enamex>.</s> <s id="s265">At the inn near the chapel here inquiry ought to be made as to the proper point from which to quit the main road, in order to follow the western shores of</s></p>
<p><s id="s266"><enamex sw="w32651" long="-3.058713394258698" lat="54.53486670386065" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796940" name="Thirlmere" conf="2.4">Thirlmere</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s267">As neither this lake nor its surrounding scenery can be seen to advantage from the direct road to <enamex sw="w32761" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s268">A fine view of the vale of Legberthwaite is obtained by this route.</s> <s id="s269">Our drawing gives the lake, with <enamex sw="w32871" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex> immediately behind it, - <enamex sw="w32907" long="-3.119691681724922" lat="54.50249902257166" type="other" gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="2">Eagle Crag</enamex> on the left, and <enamex sw="w32935" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169753" name="Helvellyn" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex> filling up the right of the picture.</s> <s id="s270">The main road is rejoined at <enamex sw="w33011" long="-2.857951289777057" lat="54.79741691110291" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33008" name="Southwaite" conf="2.6">Southwaite</enamex> <enamex  sw="w33022" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Moss</enamex>, about four miles from <enamex sw="w33050" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>; but, if the tourist be a pedestrian, he will find a much more agreeable route, by proceeding from this point down the beautiful vale of <enamex sw="w33195" long="-1.683939854346278" lat="54.49795383225262" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35385" name="Aldbrough St John" conf="1.6">St. John</enamex>'s, by which deviation the road will be lengthened by little more than a mile.</s> <s id="s271">About a mile from <enamex sw="w33300" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, on the main road, there is an eminence called <enamex sw="w33355" long="-3.106680651426865" lat="54.59250322469962" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11101332" name="Castlerigg" conf="2.6">Castlerigg</enamex>, from the top of which can be enjoyed one of the finest scenes in the district.</s></p>
<p><s id="s272">From <enamex sw="w33451" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> to <enamex sw="w33463" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> is little more than twelve miles by the direct road; but for those who disdain distance and fatigue, we cannot too strongly recommend a deviation from the highway into the mountain tracks.</s> <s id="s273">Start from <enamex sw="w33671" long="-3.02591946706321" lat="54.45838873427238" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11158165" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, pass the western side of <enamex sw="w33706" long="-3.041800543566656" lat="54.47622985854962" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169680" name="Helm Crag" conf="2.4">Helm Crag</enamex>, and go up the valley of <enamex sw="w33741" long="-3.0414" lat="54.4656" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_NY326083" name="Easdale" conf="99991">Easdale</enamex>; a somewhat laborious climb conducts to a level track called <enamex sw="w33810" long="-3.0878" lat="54.4697" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY296088" name="Coddale" conf="99992">Coddale</enamex> Fell; cross this, and descend by <enamex sw="w33851" long="-3.135381518068899" lat="54.51134123469644" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11293322" name="Stonethwaite" conf="2.6">Stonethwaite</enamex> and <enamex sw="w33868" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>, and so on to <enamex sw="w33893" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s274">This route is about twenty miles long, but the difference in distance is more than compensated for by the exhilarating air of the hill-sides, and the commanding views of the surrounding country.</s></p>
<p><s id="s275"><enamex sw="w34097" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s276">Hotels - Royal Oak And <enamex sw="w34129" long="-2.972334427597534" lat="52.8317086031685" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11251527" name="Queen's Head" conf="1.37521765">Queen's Head</enamex>.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s277">The tourist ought to make this town his head-quarters for some time, in order to explore and enjoy thoroughly the beauties of the surrounding district.</s> <s id="s278">Besides the hotels noted above, there are several excellent inns, where boats, guides, and all requisites for the comfort and convenience of the traveller are to be had.</s> <s id="s279">Should he determine upon spending some time in the vicinity, good board and lodging may be obtained at reasonable terms.</s> <s id="s280"><enamex sw="w34587" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> is a little market-town, consisting of one large street, situate in a fine fertile valley on the south bank of the Greta, at the foot of <enamex sw="w34732" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, and half a mile from <enamex sw="w34762" long="-3.152850781702139" lat="54.58308385381825" type="water" gazref="unlock:11128993" name="Derwent Water" conf="2.4">Derwent Water</enamex>.</s> <s id="s281"><enamex sw="w34777" long="-3.2167" lat="54.65" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2656187" name="Basenthwaite" conf="99992">Bassenthwaite Mere</enamex> is also in the vicinity; it is connected by a river with the former lake; and the whole of the charming landscape is studded with villages and detached cottages, embosomed among the richest verdure.</s> <s id="s282">There are about 2000 inhabitants in the town, who are chiefly engaged in the manufacture of the linsey-woolsey stuffs and black lead pencils, the lead for which is procured in the mines of <enamex sw="w35184" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s283">The chief points of interest in and near the town are, the town-hall, erected in 1813; the parish church, upwards of half a mile distant, in which lie the remains of Dr. Southey; and the new church, an elegant building, standing on an eminence at the south end of the town, which commands a fine view of the surrounding country.</s> <s id="s284">There are two museums, kept by Messrs. <enamex sw="w35564" long="-2.854944961198364" lat="54.31585808236491" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:17293" name="Crosthwaite" conf="2.6">Crosthwaite</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w35580" name="Not a placename">Hutton</enamex>, which ought to be visited, as they contain many curiosities and interesting specimens of the products of the neighbourhood.</s> <s id="s285">There is a remarkably fine model of the lake district, exhibited by its ingenious constructor, which deserves a visit, as it is wonderfully minute and correct, and coloured according to nature.</s> <s id="s286">It is on the scale of three inches to the mile.</s> <s id="s287">There is an old bell here, which has the letters H. D. R. O. 1001, stamped on it.</s> <s id="s288">Great Hall, the residence of the late Dr. Southey, stands on an eminence not far from the town.</s> <s id="s289">The whole neighbourhood of <enamex sw="w36159" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> is extremely beautiful, and rich in tempting rambles.</s></p>
<p><s id="s290"><enamex sw="w36221" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s291">Sometimes called <enamex sw="w36253" long="-3.14956" lat="54.584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2651313" name="Derwentwater" conf="99991">Keswick Lake</enamex>, is certainly one of the finest in the whole district.</s> <s id="s292">It is about three miles long by upwards of a mile broad, and lies within an amphitheatre of rocky, broken, picturesque mountains and precipices, whose peaks, lights, shadows, and wooded eminences are reflected from waters of peculiar clearness and considerable depth.</s> <s id="s293">Its surface is adorned by several islands, which are thickly wooded, and add greatly to the beauty of the scene.</s> <s id="s294">The chief of these are, <enamex sw="w36726" long="-3.137379681649069" lat="54.58323023593808" type="other" gazref="unlock:11206449" name="Lord's Island" conf="2">Lord's Island</enamex>, near the shore under <enamex sw="w36763" long="-2.780479631391105" lat="54.53212900095247" type="other" gazref="unlock:11312627" name="Wallow Crag" conf="2">Wallow Crag</enamex>, which formerly belonged to the family of the <enamex sw="w36821" long="-3.482586434530548" lat="50.7850781718509" type="other" gazref="unlock:11252793" name="Ratcliffes" conf="0.7192486825">Ratcliffes</enamex>, Earls of <enamex sw="w36842" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>; Vicar's Island, near the foot of the lake, which belongs to Captain Henry, whose residence stands on it; St. Herbert's Isle, in the centre, so called from a hermit who had his cell on it, and lived there in the seventh century; and Ramp's <enamex  sw="w37097" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Holm</enamex>. There is also here a singular floating island, which rises to the surface at intervals, and then sinks again.</s> <s id="s295">It varies in size, is covered with vegetation, and appeared last in 1842.</s> <s id="s296">It is supposed that its rise to the surface is caused by accumulation of gas formed by the decomposition of vegetable matter.</s> <s id="s297">The circuit of <enamex sw="w37429" long="-3.14956" lat="54.584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2651313" name="Derwentwater" conf="99991">Keswick lake</enamex> is a delightful excursion, affording many fine prospects of surpassing grandeur, wildness, and magnificence.</s> <s id="s298">The best views of it are to be had from <enamex sw="w37591" long="-2.251388186979562" lat="53.9411523182988" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11123427" name="Crow Park" conf="1.189138843">Crow Park</enamex>, <enamex sw="w37602" long="-3.137630072408776" lat="54.59221629737263" type="other" gazref="unlock:11148139" name="Friar's Crag" conf="2">Friar's Crag</enamex>, and the Vicarage.</s> <s id="s299">The whole vale extends almost in a straight line from the head of <enamex sw="w37700" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> to the foot of <enamex sw="w37728" long="-3.216877183061965" lat="54.65436466085852" type="water" gazref="unlock:11071446" name="Bassenthwaite Lake" conf="2.4">Bassenthwaite Lake</enamex>, and is connected with <enamex sw="w37770" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex> on the south, and <enamex sw="w37799" long="-3.058713394258698" lat="54.53486670386065" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796940" name="Thirlmere" conf="2.4">Thirlmere</enamex> on the east, while on the west is <enamex sw="w37843" long="-3.2987" lat="54.5273" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY16051545" name="Newlands Vale" conf="99992">Newlands Vale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s300"><enamex sw="w37858" long="-3.8" lat="54.85" type="other" gazref="unlock:4577958" name="Castlehill Point" conf="1.780387707">Castlehill</enamex>, one mile from <enamex sw="w37884" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> on the <enamex sw="w37899" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> road, and <enamex sw="w37919" long="-3.118118399185776" lat="54.56296039880927" type="water" gazref="unlock:8781684" name="Ashness Gill" conf="2.4">Ashness</enamex>, afford good bird's - eye views, while more distant views may be had from <enamex sw="w37999" long="-3.122649812250939" lat="54.61033292579526" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11192243" name="Latrigg" conf="2.4">Latrigg</enamex>, <enamex sw="w38008" long="-3.13838207425008" lat="54.61917439673673" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11237096" name="Ormathwaite" conf="2.6">Ormathwaite</enamex>, <enamex sw="w38021" long="-3.138227965646173" lat="54.62029924283214" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:43955" name="Applethwaite" conf="2.6">Applethwaite</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w38039" long="-3.188768947493764" lat="54.60298286610163" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36855" name="Braithwaite" conf="2.6">Braithwaite</enamex>.</s> <s id="s301"><enamex sw="w38052" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>'s Cub is worth ascending.</s></p>
<p><s id="s302">In making the circuit of the lake, start by <enamex sw="w38130" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex> road, passing on the left <enamex sw="w38167" long="-2.925256525348697" lat="54.78277548656492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11171827" name="High Head Castle" conf="2.2">Castle Head</enamex>, <enamex sw="w38180" long="-2.780479631391105" lat="54.53212900095247" type="other" gazref="unlock:11312627" name="Wallow Crag" conf="2">Wallow Crag</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w38197" long="-3.121661593153267" lat="54.57438851761556" type="other" gazref="unlock:11141692" name="Falcon Crag" conf="2">Falcon Crag</enamex>.</s> <s id="s303">There is a cleft in <enamex sw="w38230" long="-2.780479631391105" lat="54.53212900095247" type="other" gazref="unlock:11312627" name="Wallow Crag" conf="2">Wallow Crag</enamex> called the Lady's <enamex sw="w38260" long="-2.234742025321316" lat="53.68949365659972" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11252279" name="Rake Head" conf="1.478155426">Rake</enamex>, from the circumstance of the Countess of <enamex sw="w38307" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> having escaped up this gorge when her husband was arrested for high treason.</s> <s id="s304">About two miles from <enamex sw="w38418" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> is <enamex sw="w38429" long="-3.132967518" lat="54.56999747" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00063" name="Barrow House" conf="99992">Barrow House</enamex>, embosomed in very fine trees.</s> <s id="s305">There is a pretty cascade, upwards of 100 feet high, in the grounds, which is shown to the strangers on application at the lodge.</s> <s id="s306">A mile beyond this is the celebrated fall of</s></p>
<p><s id="s307"><enamex sw="w38648" long="-3.13662933748405" lat="54.55627196668239" type="water" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="2.4">Lodore</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s308">hich, though comparatively a small cascade, is surrounded by grand and impressive scenery.</s> <s id="s309">The stream falls through a chasm between the two immense upright rocks of <enamex sw="w38822" long="-3.138052024" lat="54.55817628" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00158" name="Gowder Crag" conf="99992">Gowdar Crag</enamex> on the left, and Shepherd's Crag on the right.</s> <s id="s310">Its height is about 150 feet, and its rocky sides are covered with clinging trees and pendant herbage.</s> <s id="s311">Southey notices this fall in an amusing piece, which, as it were, lays bare the inexhaustible fountain whence the poet's numbers flowed.</s> <s id="s312">Our space will not admit of more than the following extract: -</s></p>
<p><s id="s313">" How does the water come down at <enamex sw="w39216" long="-3.13662933748405" lat="54.55627196668239" type="water" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="2.4">Lodore</enamex>?</s> <s id="s314">Here it come sparkling, And there it lies darkling; Here smoking and frothing, Its tumult and wrath in.</s> <s id="s315">It hastens along, conflictingly strong, Now striking and raging, as if a war waging, In caverns and rocks among.</s> <s id="s316">***** And gleaming and streaming, and steaming and beaming, And rushing and flushing, and gushing and brushing, And flapping and sapping, and clapping and slapping, And curling and whirling, and purling and twirling, Retreating and meeting, and beating and sheeting, Delaying and straying, and playing and spraying,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s317">Advancing and prancing, and glancing and dancing, Recalling, turmoiling, and belling and toiling, And thumping and bumping, and jumping and plumping, And dashing and flashing, and splashing and clashing, And so never ending, but always descending, Sounds and motions for ever and ever are blending, All at one and all over, with a mighty uproar - And this way the water comes down at <enamex sw="w40146" long="-3.13662933748405" lat="54.55627196668239" type="water" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="2.4">Lodore</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s318">These lines, however, are only applicable to this fall after heavy rains, as during dry weather its vagaries are by no means so outrageous.</s> <s id="s319">From the top of the cascade there is a very fine view of <enamex sw="w40351" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> and <enamex sw="w40368" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>.</s> <s id="s320">When flooded by rains, and swelled by the tributary waters of a thousand mountain rills, <enamex sw="w40466" long="-3.13662933748405" lat="54.55627196668239" type="water" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="2.4">Lodore</enamex> becomes truly magnificent.</s> <s id="s321">The tremendous roar of the rushing water, as it dashes from rock to rock, and leaps in white foam impetuously along its rugged course, is so loud, that it can be heard at a distance of nine or ten miles, in calm weather.</s> <s id="s322">Those who possess an adventurous spirit will find the rocky scenery in this neighbourhood worthy of being clambered over, even at the risk of a few sprains and bruises! At the inn here a canon is kept to gratify the curiosity of visitors who wish to hear the grand echoes of the locality reverberate from rock to rock.</s></p>
<p><s id="s323">Little more than a mile beyond this is Grange Bridge, which crosses <enamex sw="w41108" long="-3.14943" lat="54.52301" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00056" name="Borrowdale Beck" conf="99992">Borrowdale Beck</enamex>; but, before crossing it, pursue the road into <enamex sw="w41171" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>, a mile farther, in order to see the</s></p>
<p><s id="s324"><enamex sw="w41219" long="-3.151583904821857" lat="54.53815357559134" type="other" gazref="unlock:11084123" name="Bowder Stone" conf="2">Bowder Stone</enamex>.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s325">This huge mass of rock lies a little to the left of the road, and, from the similarity of its veins to those of the adjoining cliffs, it has evidently fallen from them.</s> <s id="s326">In shape it bears some slight resemblance to a ship on its keel, and it is 62 feet long by 36 feet high, and 84 feet in circumference.</s> <s id="s327">It is estimated to weigh 1771 tons.</s> <s id="s328">A gentleman in the neigh - bourhood, who thought that he could improve upon nature, committed some depredations on the native simplicity of this rock and its locality; among other things he erected a ladder against the side of the rock, to enable aspiring strangers to reach the top of it.</s> <s id="s329">No good was gained by this, as the view is not nearly equal to that which may be obtained from any of the adjacent heights, while the rude wooden structure spoils the rugged outline of the stone.</s> <s id="s330">Just opposite to <enamex sw="w42076" long="-3.151583904821857" lat="54.53815357559134" type="other" gazref="unlock:11084123" name="Bowder Stone" conf="2">Bowder Stone</enamex>, <enamex sw="w42090" long="-3.090245821198284" lat="54.55669882687418" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11100762" name="Castle Crag (Fort)" conf="2.2">Castle Crag</enamex> rears its head.</s> <s id="s331">Its name is derived from a Roman fortress which once crowned its summit, and guarded the pass of <enamex sw="w42215" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s332">The views from this mount are grand and extensive.</s> <s id="s333">On one side are <enamex sw="w42294" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>; its wooded islands, and the rich vale, speckled with human habitations, and mingled field and woodland scenery, with <enamex sw="w42425" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> for a background.</s> <s id="s334">On the other side is the pass of <enamex sw="w42484" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>, where the mountains are congregated in massive confusion and wild grandeur.</s></p>
<p><s id="s335">Returning to Grange Bridge, cross over and follow the road which leads past a hamlet called <enamex sw="w42664" long="-3.152090236518966" lat="54.55612572942691" type="other" gazref="unlock:11211914" name="Manesty" conf="2">Manesty</enamex>.</s> <s id="s336">Here there is as medicinal spring.</s> <s id="s337">Passing under <enamex sw="w42722" long="-3.167807769536402" lat="54.5649635236995" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11101455" name="Cat Bells" conf="2.4">Cat Bells</enamex>, which commands one of the best views of the valley and lake, the road enters the village of <enamex sw="w42825" long="-3.160383346954682" lat="54.60035046101643" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13221" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex>, beyond which <enamex sw="w42851" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> is little more than a mile.</s> <s id="s338">Another pleasant excursion is round</s></p>
<p><s id="s339"><enamex sw="w42923" long="-3.216877183061965" lat="54.65436466085852" type="water" gazref="unlock:11071446" name="Bassenthwaite Lake" conf="2.4">Bassenthwaite Lake</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s340">Which lies between three and four miles to the north of <enamex sw="w43000" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, with which it is connected by a small stream.</s> <s id="s341">It is four miles long, and a mile broad.</s> <s id="s342">Proceed by the road which leads to the village of <enamex sw="w43151" long="-3.188768947493764" lat="54.60298286610163" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36855" name="Braithwaite" conf="2.6">Braithwaite</enamex>, on reaching which, turn to the right, and follow the road along the southern shore of the lake, which undulates pleasantly through varied and picturesque scenery, and skirts the base of the rugged hills called Lord's <enamex sw="w43381" long="-2.26667" lat="54.4" type="other" gazref="unlock:4571320" name="High Seat" conf="2">Seat</enamex> and <enamex sw="w43390" long="-0.3073836879912962" lat="54.1632247044874" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11069908" name="Barf Fm" conf="1.084099971">Barf</enamex>.</s> <s id="s343">From this road are seen the three beautiful vales of <enamex sw="w43449" long="-3.188768947493764" lat="54.60298286610163" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36855" name="Braithwaite" conf="2.6">Braithwaite</enamex>, <enamex sw="w43462" long="-3.203698642775882" lat="54.62020548450492" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:28634" name="Thornthwaite" conf="2.6">Thornthwaite</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w43480" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, as well as <enamex sw="w43500" long="-3.216877183061965" lat="54.65436466085852" type="water" gazref="unlock:11071446" name="Bassenthwaite Lake" conf="2.4">Bassenthwaite Lake</enamex>, along the margin of which it runs.</s> <s id="s344">At <enamex sw="w43558" long="-4.692535773887674" lat="54.22593372544603" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241712" name="Peel" conf="1.38256869">Peel</enamex> <enamex sw="w43563" long="-1.765057760872319" lat="53.72544996072846" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209012" name="Lower Wyke" conf="1.52649893">Wyke</enamex> there is a small tavern, and a little beyond it the road diverges to the right, where a guide-post directs to <enamex sw="w43678" long="0.3389997069709487" lat="52.56983893920285" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11237512" name="Ouse Bridge Fm" conf="0.9332059238">Ouse Bridge</enamex>.</s> <s id="s345">This bridge spans the <enamex sw="w43713" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex> at its source.</s> <s id="s346">From this point, and at <enamex sw="w43760" long="-2.76942593006839" lat="54.80675553693109" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:27289" name="Armathwaite" conf="2.6">Armathwaite</enamex>, a little farther on, the best views are to be had.</s> <s id="s347">A little beyond this is <enamex sw="w43848" long="-3.194" lat="54.68" type="other" gazref="unlock:5829203" name="Castle Inn" conf="2">Castle Inn</enamex>, from which to <enamex sw="w43874" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> is eight miles, by the northern shore of the lake.</s> <s id="s348"><enamex sw="w43933" long="0.3389997069709487" lat="52.56983893920285" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11237512" name="Ouse Bridge Fm" conf="0.9332059238">Ouse Bridge</enamex>, by the south shore, is nine and a half miles from the same town, and the whole excursion is about eighteen miles.</s> <s id="s349">While at <enamex sw="w44069" long="-3.194" lat="54.68" type="other" gazref="unlock:5829203" name="Castle Inn" conf="2">Castle Inn</enamex> a walk may be taken up to the top of the <enamex sw="w44121" long="-3.069616771498404" lat="54.35913520912058" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167901" name="Haws Bank" conf="2.6">Haws</enamex>, from which is seen a magnificent view of the lake, and the vales of <enamex sw="w44195" long="-3.283308583781152" lat="54.66455927231237" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37097" name="Embleton" conf="2.6">Embleton</enamex> and <enamex sw="w44208" name="Isell">Isell</enamex>.</s> <s id="s350">The way to this point is along the <enamex sw="w44250" long="-2.814378231084673" lat="54.79394667307044" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:39070" name="High Hesket" conf="2.6">Hesket</enamex> road for about a mile, and then turn to the right, and ascend the <enamex sw="w44323" long="-3.069616771498404" lat="54.35913520912058" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167901" name="Haws Bank" conf="2.6">Haws</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s351">The secluded Vale of <enamex sw="w44350" long="-1.683939854346278" lat="54.49795383225262" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35385" name="Aldbrough St John" conf="1.6">St. John</enamex>'s is another interesting excursion of about thirteen miles.</s> <s id="s352">Follow the <enamex sw="w44430" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> road for four miles towards the village of <enamex sw="w44481" long="-3.060956395941065" lat="54.61987757675598" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11300453" name="Threlkeld" conf="2.6">Threlkeld</enamex>, and just before reaching it, turn to the right into a road which follows the banks of the meandering Greta.</s> <s id="s353">The valley is narrow, and extremely picturesque, having Great <enamex sw="w44662" long="-2.82474894803935" lat="54.56225995962338" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785686" name="Dodd Beck" conf="2.4">Dodd</enamex> on the left, and <enamex sw="w44684" long="-3.0737" lat="54.5821" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY307213" name="High Rigg" conf="99992">Naddle Fell</enamex> on the right.</s> <s id="s354">In the midst of this valley is the celebrated rock mentioned by <enamex  sw="w44774" name="Not a placename">Sir Walter Scott</enamex> in his Bridal of <enamex sw="w44808" long="-2.63503" lat="54.99422" type="other" gazref="unlock:5824912" name="Triermain Castle" conf="1">Triermain</enamex>. It bears a striking resemblance to an old castle standing on the summit of a slight elevation.</s> <s id="s355">At the end of the Vale of <enamex sw="w44941" long="-1.683939854346278" lat="54.49795383225262" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35385" name="Aldbrough St John" conf="1.6">St John</enamex>'s the road joins the highway, about four and a half miles from <enamex sw="w45012" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s356">In this walk a visit should be paid to the</s></p>
<p> <s id="s357">Druid's Temple,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s358">The path to which diverges to the right, from the old road to <enamex sw="w45145" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, a quarter of a mile from the toll-bar.</s> <s id="s359">There are forty - eight stones, chiefly granite, in this temple, which describe a circle of between eighty and a hundred feet in diameter.</s> <s id="s360">A little to one side is a small enclosure, formed by ten stones.</s> <s id="s361">The circle is about two miles from <enamex sw="w45430" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, and stands on a hill, from which there is a very fine view of <enamex sw="w45501" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, <enamex sw="w45510" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169753" name="Helvellyn" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex>, <enamex sw="w45521" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex>, and other mountains.</s> <s id="s362">This romantic vale is interesting, as having been the subject of poems by Scott and Wordsworth.</s></p>
<p><s id="s363">The valley of</s></p>
<p> <s id="s364"><enamex sw="w45665" long="-3.120675551813501" lat="54.53844388322693" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11314116" name="Watendlath" conf="2.6">Watendlath</enamex></s> </p>
<p><s id="s365">Is a lonely secluded vale, which lies parallel with <enamex sw="w45729" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s366">It forms a delightful ride or walk, but cannot easily be visited in a carriage.</s> <s id="s367">To reach it, proceed along the <enamex sw="w45852" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex> road, past <enamex sw="w45874" long="-2.780479631391105" lat="54.53212900095247" type="other" gazref="unlock:11312627" name="Wallow Crag" conf="2">Wallow Crag</enamex>, towards <enamex sw="w45895" long="-3.132967518" lat="54.56999747" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00063" name="Barrow House" conf="99992">Barrow House</enamex>, behind which the road runs towards a pretty tarn, out of which the stream which forms <enamex sw="w45995" long="-3.13662933748405" lat="54.55627196668239" type="water" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="2.4">Lodore</enamex> waterfall issues.</s> <s id="s368">A rustic bridge crosses the stream here.</s> <s id="s369">The walk may be prolonged, if desired, over the <enamex sw="w46109" long="-3.060646544049678" lat="54.54323368129527" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403099" name="St. John's Castlerigg and Wythburn CP" conf="2.4">Wythburn</enamex> Fells to <enamex sw="w46127" long="-3.058713394258698" lat="54.53486670386065" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796940" name="Thirlmere" conf="2.4">Thirlmere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s370">The route is over rough heathy hills, which will delight the heart of a mountaineer.</s></p>
<p><s id="s371">From <enamex sw="w46228" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> to</s></p>
<p> <s id="s372"><enamex sw="w46240" long="-3.196106481840324" lat="54.4748013630062" type="other" gazref="unlock:11295029" name="Sty Head" conf="2">Sty Head</enamex></s> </p>
<p><s id="s373">Is twelve miles.</s> <s id="s374">Take the <enamex sw="w46276" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex> road, which has already been described as far as the <enamex sw="w46340" long="-3.151583904821857" lat="54.53815357559134" type="other" gazref="unlock:11084123" name="Bowder Stone" conf="2">Bowder Stone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s375">A little beyond <enamex sw="w46370" long="-3.151078130890484" lat="54.52018136502127" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11272959" name="Rosthwaite" conf="2.6">Rosthwaite</enamex>( six miles from <enamex sw="w46397" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>) the valley divides into two, that on the left being <enamex sw="w46458" long="-3.135381518068899" lat="54.51134123469644" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11293322" name="Stonethwaite" conf="2.6">Stonethwaite</enamex>, the one on the right <enamex sw="w46493" long="-3.187330149320035" lat="54.35366593329518" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:12520" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>.</s> <s id="s376">Follow the latter for a mile or so, when you reach a farm-house called <enamex sw="w46576" long="-3.166269248455024" lat="54.51104727027651" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279858" name="Seatoller" conf="2.6">Seatoller</enamex>.</s> <s id="s377">A mile further are the Blacklead or" Wad" mines.</s> <s id="s378">Just under the mines are the celebrated <enamex sw="w46676" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="other" gazref="unlock:11083297" name="Borrowdale Yews" conf="2">Yews</enamex> of <enamex sw="w46684" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>, one of which is seven yards in circumference.</s> <s id="s379">They are said to be the finest in <enamex  sw="w46776" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s> <s id="s380">Like almost every other object in the Lake district, these yews have been made the subject of Wordsworth's muse.</s> <s id="s381">At <enamex sw="w46901" long="-3.166269248455024" lat="54.51104727027651" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279858" name="Seatoller" conf="2.6">Seatoller</enamex> a mountain track, diverging to the right, leads to <enamex sw="w46962" long="-3.275491839681807" lat="54.54589906722578" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094751" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s382">At <enamex sw="w46977" long="-3.187330149320035" lat="54.35366593329518" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:12520" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex> the road ends, and a bridle path follows the stream to a little bridge, a mile farther up, which it crosses, and ascends <enamex sw="w47109" long="-3.196106481840324" lat="54.4748013630062" type="other" gazref="unlock:11295029" name="Sty Head" conf="2">Sty Head</enamex>.</s> <s id="s383">Stockley Bride is a curious specimen of native architecture, and the little cascade above it is very picturesque.</s> <s id="s384">Sty head is 1250 feet above the sea, and commands a splendid view of Wastdale and <enamex sw="w47315" long="-2.872764887218234" lat="55.23254273841246" type="other" gazref="unlock:11245240" name="Pikes, The" conf="0.8862142527">the Pikes</enamex>.</s> <s id="s385">On the first level in the ascent lies a tarn, which is fed by a streamlet from <enamex sw="w47405" long="-3.196106481840324" lat="54.4748013630062" type="water" gazref="unlock:11289687" name="Sprinkling Tarn" conf="2.4">Sprinkling Tarn</enamex>, a few hundred feet higher up.</s> <s id="s386">In this excursion may be included the ascent of</s></p>
<p> <s id="s387">Scawfell,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s388">The highest mountain in <enamex  sw="w47537" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s> <s id="s389">It s 3160 feet above the sea, and commands, of course, a most extensive view of all the mountains and valleys of the district for many miles around; including <enamex sw="w47705" long="-2.971573845828191" lat="54.11726758179064" type="water" gazref="unlock:11222778" name="Morecambe Bay" conf="2.359898905">Morecambe Bay</enamex> and the Welsh Highlands to the south, and the <enamex sw="w47765" long="-4.559389442420779" lat="54.05800177506696" type="water" gazref="unlock:11183258" name="Irish Sea" conf="1.198837083">Irish Sea</enamex> along the western horizon, while the prospect is bounded in the north by the blue mountains of <enamex  sw="w47870" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s390">In clear weather <enamex sw="w47897" long="-1.500309168183582" lat="54.64543028105785" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13372576" name="Bradbury and the Isle CP" conf="1.279890826">the Isle</enamex> of Man can be seen.</s> <s id="s391">The best point for commencing the ascent is from <enamex sw="w47975" long="-3.25097916800018" lat="54.2495244452591" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11293904" name="Strands" conf="2.6">Strands</enamex>, at the foot of <enamex sw="w47999" long="-3.287554581645747" lat="54.43790671074923" type="water" gazref="unlock:11314030" name="Wast Water" conf="2.4">Wast Water</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s392">There are many delightful short walks about <enamex sw="w48055" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, which the tourist will easily discover, by a survey of the country from its various heights.</s> <s id="s393">Among them are <enamex sw="w48172" long="-2.925256525348697" lat="54.78277548656492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11171827" name="High Head Castle" conf="2.2">Castle Head</enamex>, or, as the inhabitants call it, <enamex sw="w48218" long="-3.132864841" lat="54.59417441" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00072" name="Castle Head" conf="99992">Castlet</enamex>, one mile from the town.</s> <s id="s394">Friars Crag, a promontory stretching out into the lake, of which it commands a fine view, and also a distant one of <enamex sw="w48369" long="-3.13662933748405" lat="54.55627196668239" type="water" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="2.4">Lodore</enamex>; and a walk to the Druidical circle, already alluded to.</s> <s id="s395">The next excursion we shall describe is that to</s></p>
<p><s id="s396"><enamex sw="w48481" long="-3.275491839681807" lat="54.54589906722578" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094751" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s397">There are two roads to this lake, both of which are interesting; but only one admits of carriage travelling.</s> <s id="s398">We shall describe it first.</s> <s id="s399">Passing the village of <enamex sw="w48654" long="-3.160383346954682" lat="54.60035046101643" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13221" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex>, the road runs between Foe <enamex sw="w48693" long="0.2703295185877284" lat="51.51894955779243" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11074570" name="Belhus Woods Country Park" conf="1.183904077">Park Woods</enamex> and <enamex sw="w48708" long="-3.168321741791226" lat="54.58293549454491" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11296646" name="Swinside" conf="2.6">Swinside</enamex> to the Three Road Ends.</s> <s id="s400">Take the one on the right, which, skirting <enamex sw="w48784" long="-3.168321741791226" lat="54.58293549454491" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11296646" name="Swinside" conf="2.6">Swinside</enamex>, leads through <enamex sw="w48808" long="-3.185804700514816" lat="54.57418107642148" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790063" name="Newlands Beck" conf="2.4">Newlands</enamex> to <enamex sw="w48820" long="-3.275491839681807" lat="54.54589906722578" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094751" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s401">The scenery along this road is fine, particularly at a mountain called <enamex sw="w48903" long="-3.1938" lat="54.5755" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY22932069" name="Rawling End" conf="99992">Rawling End</enamex>.</s> <s id="s402">Just after passing <enamex sw="w48935" long="-3.219115517686562" lat="54.55346020786543" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772374" name="Keskadale Beck" conf="2.4">Keskadale</enamex>, the road ascends abruptly to <enamex sw="w48975" long="-3.076287446746557" lat="54.22462373102203" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790061" name="Newland Beck" conf="2.4">Newland</enamex>'s <enamex sw="w48985" long="-3.069616771498404" lat="54.35913520912058" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167901" name="Haws Bank" conf="2.6">Haws</enamex>, after passing which it runs at a great height above the ravine, between it and the opposite hill.</s> <s id="s403">The view in this descent is magnificent, comprehending an immense range of mountains.</s> <s id="s404">The road passes a small chapel, near to which is the inn famous as being the residence of Mary Robinson, the Beauty of <enamex sw="w49294" long="-3.275491839681807" lat="54.54589906722578" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094751" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s405">Mary's history is briefly as follows: - She was the daughter of the innkeeper, whose house was not a little indebted for its custom to the attractions of Mary.</s> <s id="s406">Of course she had many wooers, but rejected them all in favour of a man named <enamex sw="w49543" long="-0.2251403519228295" lat="51.752326922915" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167209" name="Hatfield" conf="1.397777082">Hatfield</enamex>, who gave himself out to be Colonel Hope.</s> <s id="s407">This man, who had fled from the arm of justice into these sequestered mountains, saw, loved, and married Mary in 1802; but not long afterwards was arrested for forgery, and carried to <enamex sw="w49778" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex>, where he was tried, found guilty, and hanged.</s> <s id="s408">Poor May remained an interesting young widow in her native valley for some time after this, and became famous in consequence of the reports of tourists regarding her beauty; but ultimately she became unromantic enough to marry a respectable farmer of Calbeck.</s> <s id="s409">She dies a few years ago.</s></p>
<p><s id="s410">The other road to this lake runs by <enamex sw="w50156" long="-3.13662933748405" lat="54.55627196668239" type="water" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="2.4">Lodore</enamex>, <enamex sw="w50164" long="-3.151583904821857" lat="54.53815357559134" type="other" gazref="unlock:11084123" name="Bowder Stone" conf="2">Bowder Stone</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w50182" long="-3.151078130890484" lat="54.52018136502127" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11272959" name="Rosthwaite" conf="2.6">Rosthwaite</enamex>, where there is an inn.</s> <s id="s411">A little father, the valley divides; follow that on the right, called <enamex sw="w50287" long="-3.187330149320035" lat="54.35366593329518" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:12520" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>, for a mile, to <enamex sw="w50314" long="-3.166269248455024" lat="54.51104727027651" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279858" name="Seatoller" conf="2.6">Seatoller</enamex>, where the road diverges to the right.</s> <s id="s412">It is rough and steep, and the pass is 1100 feet in height.</s> <s id="s413">From this point is a rapid descent into the vale at <enamex sw="w50475" long="-3.219864602" lat="54.51702496" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00169" name="Honister Crag" conf="99991">Honister Crag</enamex>, three miles from <enamex sw="w50507" long="-3.166269248455024" lat="54.51104727027651" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279858" name="Seatoller" conf="2.6">Seatoller</enamex>, which rises like a wall on the left to a height of 1500 feet.</s> <s id="s414">There are extensive slate quarries in this rock, the face of which is excavated into tiers of caverns for a considerable height.</s> <s id="s415"><enamex sw="w50709" long="-3.275491839681807" lat="54.54589906722578" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094751" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> is a small lake, about a mile and a half in length by a quarter of a mile in breadth.</s> <s id="s416">In form it is oblong, and sweeps round a promontory at one end.</s> <s id="s417">The scenery around it is grand.</s> <s id="s418">Its eastern side is well wooded, while on the western side a long range of mountain slopes stretch from end to end, terminating everywhere precipitously in water.</s> <s id="s419">At the bottom of the valley, Sour Milk-Gill falls down the steep mountains, appearing like a thread of silver on their dark sides.</s> <s id="s420">The mountains that surround the lake - <enamex sw="w51235" long="-3.259205395006423" lat="54.51910382382491" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11171493" name="High Crag" conf="2.4">High Crag</enamex>, <enamex sw="w51246" long="-3.290097556376177" lat="54.51877820351508" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11172424" name="High Stile" conf="2.4">High Stile</enamex>, <enamex sw="w51258" long="-3.290380887698875" lat="54.52776385298422" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11253798" name="Red Pike" conf="2.4">Red Pike</enamex>,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s421">- almost overshadow its waters, and give to it a somewhat gloomy appearance, which is not a little heightened by the comparative want of cultivation and human habitations.</s> <s id="s422">The village of <enamex sw="w51459" long="-3.275491839681807" lat="54.54589906722578" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094751" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> stands on a slope near the foot of the lake.</s> <s id="s423">There is said to be good fishing here.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s424"><enamex sw="w51555" long="-3.306404041715465" lat="54.54556917612459" type="water" gazref="unlock:11278597" name="Scale Force" conf="2.4">Scale Force</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s425">One of the highest waterfalls in the country, is on the opposite side of the lake.</s> <s id="s426">A footpath, leading over the ground that divides the two lakes, conducts to it; but the tourist had better go by boat from the head of <enamex sw="w51787" long="-3.30669123730051" lat="54.55455472767663" type="water" gazref="unlock:11124107" name="Crummock Water" conf="2.4">Crummock Water</enamex>, as the footpath is disagreeably dirty in wet weather.</s> <s id="s427">The fall is a mile from the landing-place.</s> <s id="s428">It is 160 feet high, and descends between two immense perpendicular walls of rock.</s> <s id="s429">From a point a little above the promontory, called <enamex sw="w52034" long="-3.307956417" lat="54.55196461" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00178" name="Ling Crag" conf="99992">Ling Crag</enamex>, is obtained the best view of</s></p>
<p><s id="s430"><enamex sw="w52074" long="-3.30669123730051" lat="54.55455472767663" type="water" gazref="unlock:11124107" name="Crummock Water" conf="2.4">Crummock Water</enamex>,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s431">And also the Late of <enamex sw="w52112" long="-3.275491839681807" lat="54.54589906722578" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094751" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, and the surrounding country.</s> <s id="s432">On the east of this lake are the mountains called <enamex sw="w52203" long="-4.261446695791236" lat="54.87471735350928" type="water" gazref="unlock:8774669" name="Whiteside Burn" conf="1.106224126">Whiteside</enamex>, <enamex sw="w52214" long="-1.393684349529748" lat="53.19742790376169" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:17880" name="Grassmoor" conf="1.459239568">Grassmoor</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w52229" long="-3.36025516272461" lat="54.76968977457732" type="other" gazref="unlock:11321621" name="Whitelees" conf="1.990140299">Whitelees</enamex>, while Melbreak lies to the west.</s> <s id="s433">At <enamex sw="w52276" long="-3.307553774708791" lat="54.58151129588074" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11278601" name="Scale Hill" conf="2.4">Scale Hill</enamex>, three miles beyond <enamex sw="w52307" long="-3.307956417" lat="54.55196461" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00178" name="Ling Crag" conf="99992">Ling Crag</enamex>, there is an excellent inn.</s> <s id="s434">The lake is three miles long, and nearly a mile broad, and it has three small islands at its head.</s> <s id="s435">A boat excursion ought to be made upon it in order to see the surrounding mountains properly.</s> <s id="s436">The road to this lake from <enamex sw="w52565" long="-3.275491839681807" lat="54.54589906722578" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094751" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> is through pleasant groves and fields, and at its foot there is a pretty hill, partly wooded and partly cultivated, beyond which are the sloping fields of Lowes Water.</s> <s id="s437">An old writer says," The two lakes bear a great resemblance to each other.</s> <s id="s438">Both are oblong; both wind round promontories, and both are surrounded by mountains.</s> <s id="s439">But the lower lake is nearly a mile longer than the upper; the lines it forms are much easier, and though it has less wood on its banks, the loss is compensated by a richer display of rock scenery."</s> <s id="s440">At the north-east corner of this lake the waters find an outlet in the <enamex sw="w53174" long="-3.338634083115587" lat="54.61981992774946" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791056" name="River Cocker" conf="2.4">River Cocker</enamex>, which flows through a pleasant country, a distance of about eight miles to <enamex sw="w53263" long="-3.360999570010009" lat="54.6624702211972" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10233" name="Cockermouth" conf="2.6">Cockermouth</enamex>, the birth-place of the poet Wordsworth.</s></p>
<p><s id="s441"><enamex sw="w53316" long="-3.307553774708791" lat="54.58151129588074" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11278601" name="Scale Hill" conf="2.4">Scale Hill</enamex> is a good point from which to visit many interesting scenes, and might be found a convenient place to rest for a few days.</s> <s id="s442">There is a pleasant walk to an eminence in Mr. Marshall's woods, and another in the direction of <enamex sw="w53547" long="-3.304525443741675" lat="54.62013154745584" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15472" name="Lorton" conf="2.6">Lorton</enamex>.</s> <s id="s443"><enamex sw="w53555" long="-3.437363629991824" lat="54.53063642381277" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:23123" name="Ennerdale Bridge" conf="2.6">Ennerdale</enamex> may be visited by following the stream which flows from <enamex sw="w53621" long="-3.352771153257395" lat="54.5450595336237" type="water" gazref="unlock:11145719" name="Floutern Tarn" conf="2.4">Floutern Tarn</enamex>.</s> <s id="s444">Besides the two routes above described, to <enamex sw="w53679" long="-3.275491839681807" lat="54.54589906722578" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094751" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> and <enamex sw="w53694" long="-3.30669123730051" lat="54.55455472767663" type="water" gazref="unlock:11124107" name="Crummock Water" conf="2.4">Crummock Water</enamex>, there is another, which, though lengthened and circuitous, is in some respects better than either of them.</s> <s id="s445">This road leaves <enamex sw="w53834" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> by the village of <enamex sw="w53860" long="-3.160383346954682" lat="54.60035046101643" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13221" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex>; <enamex sw="w53873" long="-3.246772154112804" lat="54.61810679409508" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11319972" name="Whinlatter" conf="2.4">Whinlatter</enamex>, passing the celebrated yew tree; through the vale of <enamex sw="w53938" long="-3.304525443741675" lat="54.62013154745584" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15472" name="Lorton" conf="2.6">Lorton</enamex> to <enamex sw="w53948" long="-3.307553774708791" lat="54.58151129588074" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11278601" name="Scale Hill" conf="2.4">Scale Hill</enamex> - a distance of twelve miles - and thence return to <enamex sw="w54011" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> by <enamex sw="w54022" long="-3.275491839681807" lat="54.54589906722578" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094751" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> and <enamex sw="w54037" long="-3.185804700514816" lat="54.57418107642148" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790063" name="Newlands Beck" conf="2.4">Newlands</enamex>, or by the slate quarries at <enamex sw="w54075" long="-3.219864602" lat="54.51702496" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00169" name="Honister Crag" conf="99991">Honister Crag</enamex>, and reverse the second route described above.</s> <s id="s446">Two miles from <enamex sw="w54151" long="-3.30669123730051" lat="54.55455472767663" type="water" gazref="unlock:11124107" name="Crummock Water" conf="2.4">Crummock Water</enamex>, in a secluded, thickly wooded valley, and surrounded by the wild mountains of <enamex sw="w54245" long="-3.338787164036787" lat="54.59015844435803" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11207035" name="Low Fell" conf="2.4">Low Fell</enamex>, <enamex sw="w54255" long="-3.368828250405294" lat="54.56285634226108" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11080598" name="Blake Fell" conf="2.4">Blake Fell</enamex>, and Melbreck, lies the small lake called</s></p>
<p><s id="s447">Lowes Water.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s448">This lake is not more than a mile in length.</s> <s id="s449">As the finest scenery lies around its foot, it is necessary to go to the head of it and look back, in order to see it to advantage.</s> <s id="s450">The walk round it is about seven miles.</s></p>
<p><s id="s451">While resident at <enamex sw="w54557" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> the ascent of</s></p>
<p> <s id="s452"><enamex sw="w54580" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex></s> </p>
<p><s id="s453">Should be made.</s> <s id="s454">Its height is 3022 feet above the sea, and is so easy of access that horses may be taken to the summit.</s> <s id="s455">From <enamex sw="w54714" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> to the top is six miles; along the <enamex sw="w54757" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> road, to a bridge beyond the toll-bar; cross the bridge, after which the road ascends steeply, skirting <enamex sw="w54869" long="-3.1179" lat="54.6123" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY279247" name="Latrigg" conf="99992">Latrig</enamex> and traversing a plantation, after which another road is entered on the right; pursue this only for a few yards to a gate, just beyond which take the road to the left by the side of a fence to a hollow at the base of the steepest hill, on the right of which is a deep ravine; for a mile beyond this road ascends precipitously by the side of a stone wall which it crosses and proceeds straight forward, leaving the wall on the right, until it arrives at a barren moor called <enamex sw="w55350" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw Forest</enamex>, where there is a spring of clear water, which will prove extremely refreshing to the thirsty climber.</s> <s id="s456">Beyond this the ascent, passing five elevations called men, to the summit, is easy.</s> <s id="s457">The views from various points in ascending are remarkably fine - better, it is thought, than from the summit itself.</s> <s id="s458">The mountain is called</s></p>
<p> <s id="s459"><enamex sw="w55694" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex></s> </p>
<p><s id="s460">Is also worth ascending, but is usually omitted by tourists in consequence of its vicinity to <enamex sw="w55800" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, although the views from it are thought to be finer.</s> <s id="s461"><enamex sw="w55861" long="-3.045931937510582" lat="54.63798482205417" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11276096" name="Saddleback/Blencathra" conf="2.4">Blencathra</enamex> was the ancient name of this mountain, on which is the <enamex sw="w55927" long="-3.0428" lat="54.6435" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY328281" name="Threlkeld Tarn" conf="99992">Threlkeld Tarn</enamex>, alluded to by Sir Walter, in his Bridal of <enamex sw="w55986" long="-2.63503" lat="54.99422" type="other" gazref="unlock:5824912" name="Triermain Castle" conf="1">Triermain</enamex>, in the following lines: -</s></p>
<p><s id="s462">" Above her solitary tract <enamex sw="w56049" long="-74.7223827" lat="40.3673286" type="other" gazref="unlock:7843883" name="Mount Rose" conf="0.6714540943">Rose</enamex> <enamex sw="w56054" long="-3.165501892757764" lat="54.4840889517741" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11153221" name="Glaramara" conf="2.4">Glaramara</enamex>'s ridgy back,</s> </p>
<p><s id="s463">Amid whose yawning gulfs the sun Cast umbered radiance red and dun; Though never sunbeam could discern The surface of that sable tarn, In whose black mirror you may spy The stars while noontide lights the sky."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s464"><enamex sw="w56291" long="-3.287554581645747" lat="54.43790671074923" type="water" gazref="unlock:11314030" name="Wast Water" conf="2.4">Wast Water</enamex> and <enamex sw="w56306" long="-3.437363629991824" lat="54.53063642381277" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:23123" name="Ennerdale Bridge" conf="2.6">Ennerdale</enamex></s>
</p>
<p><s id="s465">Are usually visited from <enamex sw="w56342" long="-3.574638671553102" lat="54.54261524067765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063" name="Whitehaven" conf="3.078900843">Whitehaven</enamex>, but they can also be reached from <enamex sw="w56388" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>; part of the way, however, has to be accomplished on foot.</s> <s id="s466">One route is by <enamex sw="w56471" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>, over Styhead; another is as follows: - Proceed past <enamex sw="w56534" long="-3.307553774708791" lat="54.58151129588074" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11278601" name="Scale Hill" conf="2.4">Scale Hill</enamex>, by any of the routes before mentioned, to Lowes Water, and thence to <enamex sw="w56615" long="-3.4306" lat="54.5659" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY076199" name="Lampleugh Cross" conf="99992">Lampleugh</enamex> Cross and <enamex sw="w56635" long="-3.437363629991824" lat="54.53063642381277" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:23123" name="Ennerdale Bridge" conf="2.6">Ennerdale Bridge</enamex>.</s> <s id="s467">Thence to <enamex sw="w56663" long="-3.477074728151211" lat="54.44083920280129" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33981" name="Calder Bridge" conf="2.6">Calder Bridge</enamex>, where there are two good inns, and on to <enamex sw="w56719" long="-3.430727081830428" lat="54.42077129657136" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36706" name="Gosforth" conf="2.6">Gosforth</enamex> and <enamex sw="w56732" long="-3.3518" lat="54.4241" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY12390403" name="Strands" conf="99992">the Strands</enamex> in Wastdale; but this route is very circuitous.</s> <s id="s468"><enamex sw="w56792" long="-3.287554581645747" lat="54.43790671074923" type="water" gazref="unlock:11314030" name="Wast Water" conf="2.4">Wast Water</enamex> is three miles in length, and three quarters of a mile in breadth, and the scenery around it is rugged and less attractive than that of most of the other lakes, from which circumstance, and the difficulty of access to it, it is seldom visited.</s> <s id="s469">There is nothing very striking in the features and character of <enamex sw="w57111" long="-3.3736" lat="54.519" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2649985" name="Ennderdale" conf="99992">Ennerdale Lake</enamex>, though it is not without its beauties; but, after the romantic and superb scenery which the tourist has already passed, we would recommend him to rest satisfied with the view of those lakes that is to be had from the various mountain tops he may have scaled during his progress through the Lake District -</s></p>
<p><s id="s470">" Then, casting back one lingering glance On river, lake, and fell, We quit the bright scene, murmuring Regretfully - Farewell!"</s></p>
</text>
</document>