<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1802_a"><p><s id="s1">To Sara Hutchinson</s></p>
<p><s id="s2">On Sunday Augt.</s> <s id="s3">1st - half after 12 I had a Shirt, cravat, 2 pair of Stockings, a little paper&amp; half a dozen Pens, a German Book( Voss's Poems)&amp; a little Tea&amp; Sugar, with my Night Cap, packed up in my natty green oil-skin, neatly squared, and put into my net Knapsack/ and the Knap Sack on my back&amp; the Besom stick in my hand, which for want of a better, and in spite of Mrs C.&amp; Mary, who both raised their voices against it, especially as I left the Besom scattered on the Kitchen Floor, off I sallied - over the Bridge, through the Hop Field, through the Prospect Bridge at <enamex sw="w615" long="-3.153358511469882" lat="54.60105586584796" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11249032" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex>, so on by the tall Birch that grows out of the center of the huge Oak, along into <enamex sw="w710" long="-3.185804700514816" lat="54.57418107642148" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790063" name="Newlands Beck" conf="2.4">Newlands</enamex>-- <enamex sw="w722" long="-3.185804700514816" lat="54.57418107642148" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790063" name="Newlands Beck" conf="2.4">Newlands</enamex> is indeed a lovely Place The houses, each in it's little Shelter of <enamex sw="w799" long="-3.014585422546117" lat="54.297813160102" type="water" gazref="unlock:8781683" name="Ashes Beck" conf="2.4">Ashes</enamex>&amp; Sycamores, just under the Road, so that in some places you might leap down on the Roof, seemingly at least-the exceeding greenness&amp; pastoral beauty of the Vale itself, with the savage wildness of the Mountains, their Coves, and long arm-shaped&amp; elbow-shaped Ridges Yet this wildness softened down into a congruity with the Vale by the semicircular <enamex sw="w1157" long="-0.7603098256494568" lat="51.25558432678506" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11221885" name="Montgomery Lines" conf="1.40555089">Lines</enamex> of the Crags,&amp; of the bason-like Concavities.</s> <s id="s4">The Cataract between <enamex sw="w1231" long="-3.185804700514816" lat="54.57418107642148" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790063" name="Newlands Beck" conf="2.4">Newlands</enamex>&amp; Kescadale had but little water in it/ of course, was of no particular Interest -/ I passed on through the green steep smooth bare Kescadale/ a sort of unfurnished Passage or antechamber between <enamex sw="w1438" long="-3.185804700514816" lat="54.57418107642148" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790063" name="Newlands Beck" conf="2.4">Newlands</enamex>&amp; <enamex sw="w1449" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, came out on <enamex sw="w1474" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>&amp; drank Tea at the little Inn,&amp; read the greater part of the Revelations The only part of the New Testament, which the Scotch Cobler read-because why?</s> <s id="s5">Because it was the only part that he understood.</s> <s id="s6">O' twas a wise Cobler!. . .</s></p>
<p><s id="s7">Conceive an enormous round Bason mountain-high of solid Stone/ cracked in half&amp; one half gone/ exactly in the remaining half of this enormous <enamex sw="w1861" long="-2.826657965378976" lat="54.52283399655146" type="other" gazref="unlock:11071427" name="Bason Crag" conf="2">Bason</enamex>, does <enamex sw="w1873" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> lie, in this beautiful&amp; stern Embracement of Rock/ I left it, passed by <enamex sw="w1958" long="-3.306404041715465" lat="54.54556917612459" type="water" gazref="unlock:11278597" name="Scale Force" conf="2.4">Scale Force</enamex>, the white downfal of which glimmered through the <enamex sw="w2021" long="-0.9214981485461977" lat="53.56319006165395" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785380" name="Crow Trees Moor Drain East" conf="1.288481918">Trees</enamex>, that hang before it like bushy Hair over a madman's Eyes, and climbed' till I gained the first Level/ here it was' every man his own pathmaker,'&amp; I went directly cross it-upon soft mossy Ground, with many a <enamex sw="w2237" long="-68.1552883" lat="44.4123015" type="other" gazref="unlock:7708376" name="The Hop" conf="0.7857135392">hop</enamex>, skip,&amp; jump,&amp; many an occasion for observing the Truth of the old Saying: where Rushes grow, A Man may go.</s> <s id="s8"><enamex sw="w2351" long="-3.288965790172139" lat="54.48283546175173" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11253797" name="Red Pike" conf="2.4">Red Pike</enamex>, a dolphin-shaped Peak of a deep red, looked in upon me from over <enamex sw="w2427" long="-3.972325756997933" lat="54.88713027476024" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11142935" name="Fell, The" conf="1.118624154">the Fell</enamex> on my Left, on my right I had, first Melbreak( the Mountain on the right of Crummock, as you ascend the Lake) then a Vale running down with a pretty Stream in it, to <enamex sw="w2604" long="-3.322732159981248" lat="54.5723577144906" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209070" name="Loweswater" conf="2.6">Loweswater</enamex>/ then Heck Comb, a Fell of the same height&amp; running in the same direction with Melbreak, a Vale on the other side too, - and at the bottom of both these Vales the <enamex sw="w2780" long="-3.322732159981248" lat="54.5723577144906" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209070" name="Loweswater" conf="2.6">Loweswater</enamex> Fells running abreast.</s> <s id="s9">Again I reached an ascent, climbed up&amp; came to a ruined Sheepfold - a wild green view all around me, bleating of Sheep&amp; noise of waters-I sate there near 20 minutes, the Sun setting on <enamex sw="w3001" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex> behind with a soft watery gleam;&amp; in front of me the upper Halves of huge deep-furrowed <enamex sw="w3099" long="-3.277799126" lat="54.5715203" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00159" name="Grasmoor" conf="99992">Grasmire</enamex>( the mountain on the other side of Crummock)&amp; the huge <enamex sw="w3165" long="-3.076287446746557" lat="54.22462373102203" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790061" name="Newland Beck" conf="2.4">Newland</enamex>&amp; <enamex sw="w3175" long="-3.29607" lat="54.52447" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00077" name="Buttermere Mountains" conf="99992">Buttermere Mountains</enamex>,&amp; peeping in from behind the Top of <enamex sw="w3233" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex>. Two Fields were visible, the highest cultivated Ground on the <enamex sw="w3308" name="Newland side">Newland side</enamex> of <enamex sw="w3324" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, and the <enamex sw="w3345" long="-0.9214981485461977" lat="53.56319006165395" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785380" name="Crow Trees Moor Drain East" conf="1.288481918">Trees</enamex> in those Fields were the only trees visible in the whole Prospect. - I left the Sheepfold with regret-for of all things a ruined Sheepfold in a desolate place is the dearest to me, and fills me most with Dreams&amp; Visions&amp; tender thoughts of those I love best.</s></p>
<p><s id="s10">- Well! I passed a bulging roundish-headed green Hill to my Left,( and to the left of it was a frightful <enamex sw="w3714" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Crag</enamex>) with a very high round-head right before me; this latter is called <enamex sw="w3788" long="-3.429418179792764" lat="54.52620042627977" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140131" name="Ennerdale Bridge" conf="2.6">Ennerdale</enamex> <enamex sw="w3798" long="-2.82474894803935" lat="54.56225995962338" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785686" name="Dodd Beck" conf="2.4">Dodd</enamex>, and bisects the ridge between <enamex sw="w3835" long="-3.429418179792764" lat="54.52620042627977" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140131" name="Ennerdale Bridge" conf="2.6">Ennerdale</enamex>&amp; <enamex sw="w3847" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>&amp; Crummock - I took it on my right hand,&amp; came to the top of the bulging green Hill, on which I found a small Tarn, called <enamex sw="w3981" long="-3.3555" lat="54.5407" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY124170" name="Flattern Tarn" conf="99992">Flattern</enamex> Tarn, about 100 yds.</s> <s id="s11">in length,&amp; not more than 7 or 8 in breadth, but O! what a grand Precipice it lay at the foot of! The half of the Precipice( called Herd House) nearest to <enamex sw="w4169" long="-3.429418179792764" lat="54.52620042627977" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140131" name="Ennerdale Bridge" conf="2.6">Ennerdale</enamex> was black, with green moss-cushions on the Ledges; the half nearest to <enamex sw="w4250" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> a pale pink,&amp; divided from the black part by a great streamy Torrent of crimson Shiver,&amp; <enamex sw="w4353" long="-3.214466500836419" lat="54.57349272667725" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11256013" name="Rigg Screes" conf="2.4">Screes</enamex>, or Shilly( as they call it).</s> <s id="s12">I never saw a more heart-raising Scene.</s> <s id="s13">I turned&amp; looked on the Scene which I had left behind, a marvellous group of mountains, wonderfully&amp; admirably arranged-not a single minute object to interrupt the oneness of the view, excepting those two green Fields in <enamex sw="w4653" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> - but before me the glorious Sea with the high Coast&amp; Mountains of <enamex sw="w4731" long="-1.500309168183582" lat="54.64543028105785" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13372576" name="Bradbury and the Isle CP" conf="1.260508216">the Isle</enamex> of <enamex sw="w4743" long="-70.75504189999999" lat="42.2212124" type="other" gazref="unlock:7683948" name="Mann Hill" conf="0.6987255544">Mann</enamex>, perfectly distinct -&amp; three Ships in view.</s></p>
<p><s id="s14">A little further on, the Lake of <enamex sw="w4825" long="-3.429418179792764" lat="54.52620042627977" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140131" name="Ennerdale Bridge" conf="2.6">Ennerdale</enamex>( the lower part of it) came into view, shaped like a clumsy battle-dore-but it is, in reality, exactly fiddle-shaped. The further Bank&amp; the higher part, steep, lofty, bare bulging Crags; the nether Bank green&amp; pastoral, with Houses in the shelter of their own dear Trees. - On the opposite Shore in the middle&amp; narrow part of the Lake there bulges out a huge <enamex sw="w5197" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Crag</enamex>, called angling Stone/ being a famous Station for anglers-and the reflection of this <enamex sw="w5288" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Crag</enamex> in the Water is admirable-pillars or rather it looks like the pipes of some enormous Organ in a rich golden Color. - I travelled on to <enamex sw="w5426" long="-2.484088002944673" lat="54.2999852610784" type="other" gazref="unlock:11205587" name="Long Moor" conf="1.986314046">Long Moor</enamex>, two miles below the Foot of the Lake,&amp; met a very hearty welcome from John <enamex sw="w5515" long="-3.457115296600183" lat="54.43598051808319" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11247683" name="Ponsonby" conf="2.6">Ponsonby</enamex>, a Friend of Mr. Jackson's - here I stayed the night&amp; the greater part of Monday.</s></p>
<p><s id="s15">The old man went to the head of the Lake with me/ the mountains at the head of this Lake&amp; <enamex sw="w5699" long="-3.3488" lat="54.4251" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:31029" name="Wasdale" conf="99992">Wast Dale</enamex> are the Monsters of the Country, bare bleak Heads, evermore doing deeds of Darkness, weather-plots,&amp; storm-conspiracies in the <enamex sw="w5837" long="-2.411843342259774" lat="54.38262720582438" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771932" name="Clouds Gill" conf="2.4">Clouds</enamex> Their names are Herd House, <enamex sw="w5873" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, <enamex sw="w5883" name="Wha Head">Wha Head</enamex>, <enamex sw="w5894" long="-3.21929208" lat="54.48224887" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00108" name="Great Gable" conf="99992">Great Gavel</enamex>, the <enamex sw="w5912" long="-0.98333" lat="51.93333" type="other" gazref="unlock:4561374" name="Steeple Claydon" conf="0.8709304437">Steeple</enamex>, the <enamex sw="w5926" long="-3.2825" lat="54.49917" type="other" gazref="unlock:4564691" name="Pillar" conf="2">Pillar</enamex>&amp; <enamex sw="w5935" long="-2.26667" lat="54.4" type="other" gazref="unlock:4571320" name="High Seat" conf="1.967026088">Seat</enamex> Allian. - I left <enamex sw="w5956" long="-2.484088002944673" lat="54.2999852610784" type="other" gazref="unlock:11205587" name="Long Moor" conf="1.986314046">Long Moor</enamex> after Tea,&amp; proceeded to <enamex sw="w5992" long="-3.520433015525314" lat="54.48014542681776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11138309" name="Egremont" conf="2.6">Egremont</enamex>, 5 miles-through a very pleasant Country, part of the way by the River Enna, with well wooded Banks,&amp; nice green Fields,&amp; pretty houses with <enamex sw="w6146" long="-0.9214981485461977" lat="53.56319006165395" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785380" name="Crow Trees Moor Drain East" conf="1.288481918">Trees</enamex>, and two huge Sail Cloth Manufactories - went to Girtskill, a mercer, for whom I had a Letter, but he was at <enamex sw="w6261" long="-3.551571779176866" lat="54.62740111743355" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11386" name="Workington" conf="3.011556949">Workington</enamex>, so I walked on to <enamex sw="w6292" long="-3.591588743814815" lat="54.48997074986357" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:12225" name="St Bees" conf="2.6">St. Bees</enamex>, 3 miles from <enamex sw="w6316" long="-3.520433015525314" lat="54.48014542681776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11138309" name="Egremont" conf="2.6">Egremont</enamex> - when I came there could not get a Bed At last got an apology for one, at a miserable Pot House; slept or rather dozed in my Clothes -</s></p>
<p><s id="s16">Breakfasted there - and went to the School&amp; Church ruins - had read in the history of Cumbd.</s> <s id="s17">that there was an' excellent Library presented to the School by James <enamex sw="w6623" long="-2.719930910627173" lat="54.6044092845645" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209204" name="Lowther" conf="2.554256965">Lowther</enamex>,' which proved to be some 30 odd Volumes of commentaries on the Scripture utterly worthless-amp which with all my passion for ragged old Folios I should certainly make serviceable. . . for fire-lighting.</s> <s id="s18">Men who write Tours and County histories I have by woeful experience found out to be damned Liars, harsh words, but true! - It was a wet woeful oppressive morning-I was sore with my bad night-walked down to the Beach, which is a very nice hard Sand for more than a mile/ but the <enamex sw="w7117" long="-3.629509176855379" lat="54.5056914847759" type="other" gazref="unlock:11276283" name="St Bees Head" conf="2">St. Bees Head</enamex> which I had read much of as a noble Cliff, might be made a song of on the Flats of the Dutch Coast But in <enamex  sw="w7237" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>' twill scarcely bear a looking-at.</s> <s id="s19">Returned to <enamex sw="w7292" long="-3.520433015525314" lat="54.48014542681776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11138309" name="Egremont" conf="2.6">Egremont</enamex>, a miserable walk-dined there, visited <enamex sw="w7341" long="-2.890464102233929" lat="53.18298073394839" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11101187" name="Castle, The" conf="1.059493477">the Castle</enamex>, the Views from which are uncommonly interesting-I looked through an old wild Arch Slovenly black Houses,&amp; gardens, as wild as a Dream, over the hills beyond them, which slip down in one place making a noticeable <enamex  sw="w7567" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Gap</enamex> Had a good Bed, slept well.</s></p>
<p><s id="s20">After Breakfast, had a pleasant walk to <enamex sw="w7639" long="-3.472851292970033" lat="54.44477869607492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11096504" name="Calder Abbey" conf="2.2">Calder Abbey</enamex> - an elegant but not very interesting Ruin, joining to a very hansome Gentleman's House built of red freestone, which has the comfortable warm look of Brick without it's meanness and multitude of puny squares.</s> <s id="s21">This place lies just within the Line of circumference of a Circle of woody Hills The area, a pretty Plain half a mile perhaps in diameter-and completely cloathed&amp; hid with wood, except one red hollow in these steep hills,&amp; except behind the Abbey, where the Hills are far higher,&amp; consist of green Fields almost( but not quite) to the Top.</s> <s id="s22">Just opposite to <enamex sw="w8221" long="-3.472851292970033" lat="54.44477869607492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11096504" name="Calder Abbey" conf="2.2">Calder Abbey</enamex>,&amp; on the Line of the Circumference, rises <enamex sw="w8278" long="-3.4567" lat="54.4316" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY056050" name="Ponsonby" conf="99992">Ponsonby Hill</enamex>, the Village of <enamex sw="w8309" long="-3.472528891961726" lat="54.43579361347319" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11096506" name="Calder Bridge" conf="2.6">Calder Bridge</enamex>,&amp; it's interesting Mill, all in Wood, some hidden, some roofs just on a line with the <enamex sw="w8411" long="-0.9214981485461977" lat="53.56319006165395" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785380" name="Crow Trees Moor Drain East" conf="1.288481918">Trees</enamex>, some higher, but <enamex sw="w8435" long="-3.457115296600183" lat="54.43598051808319" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11247685" name="Ponsonby Old Hall" conf="2.2">Ponsonby Hall</enamex> far higher than the rest. - I regained the Road, and came to Bonewood a single Alehouse on the top of the hill above the Village <enamex sw="w8577" long="-3.430727081830428" lat="54.42077129657136" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36706" name="Gosforth" conf="2.6">Gosforth</enamex> - drank a pint of Beer( I forgot to tell you that the whole of my expences at <enamex sw="w8663" long="-3.591588743814815" lat="54.48997074986357" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:12225" name="St Bees" conf="2.6">St. Bees</enamex>, a glass of Gin&amp; Water, my Bed,&amp; Breakfast amounted to 11d.) - from this Bonewood is a noble view of <enamex sw="w8774" long="-1.500309168183582" lat="54.64543028105785" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13372576" name="Bradbury and the Isle CP" conf="1.260508216">the Isle</enamex> of Man on the one side,&amp; on the other side all the bold dread tops of the <enamex sw="w8858" long="-3.429418179792764" lat="54.52620042627977" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140131" name="Ennerdale Bridge" conf="2.6">Ennerdale</enamex>&amp; <enamex sw="w8870" long="-3.3488" lat="54.4251" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:31029" name="Wasdale" conf="99992">Wastdale</enamex> Mountains/. Indeed the whole way from <enamex sw="w8919" long="-3.520433015525314" lat="54.48014542681776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11138309" name="Egremont" conf="2.6">Egremont</enamex> I had beautiful Sea Views, the low hills to my right dipping down into inverted <enamex sw="w9008" long="0.1287978888109703" lat="50.95496665893109" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11063084" name="Arches Manor" conf="1.035467902">Arches</enamex>, or Angles,&amp; the Sea, often with a Ship seen through-while on my left the the <enamex sw="w9095" long="-0.98333" lat="51.93333" type="other" gazref="unlock:4561374" name="Steeple Claydon" conf="0.8709304437">Steeple</enamex>,&amp; Sca' Fell facing each other, far above the other Fells, formed in their interspace a great <enamex  sw="w9198" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Gap</enamex> in the Heaven. - So I went on, turned eastward, up the Irt, the Sea behind&amp; <enamex sw="w9278" long="-3.3488" lat="54.4251" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:31029" name="Wasdale" conf="99992">Wastdale</enamex> Mountains before -&amp; here I am -</s></p>
<p><s id="s23">Wed.</s> <s id="s24">Afternoon half past 3, Augt.</s> <s id="s25">4th 1802 -</s></p>
<p> <s id="s26"><enamex sw="w9363" long="-3.3488" lat="54.4251" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:31029" name="Wasdale" conf="99992">Wastdale</enamex>, a mile&amp; half below the Foot of the Lake, at an Alehouse without a Sign Inn, 20 strides from the Door, under the Shade of a huge Sycamore Tree, without my coat-but that I will now put on, in prudence-yes here I am/ and have been for something more than an hour,&amp; have enjoyed a good Dish of Tea( I carried my Tea&amp; sugar with me) under this delightful Tree.</s> <s id="s27">In the House Inn there are only a feeble Woman, and a' Tallyeur' Lad upon the Table All the rest of the Wastdale World is a haymaking, rejoicing and thanking God for this first downright summer Day that we have had since the beginning of May. - And now I must go&amp; see the Lake/ for immediately at the Foot of the Lake runs a low Ridge so that you can see nothing of the Water till you are at it's very Edge.</s></p>
<p><s id="s28">Between the Lake and the Mountains on the left, a low ridge of hill runs parallel with the Lake, for more than half it's length;&amp; just at the foot of the Lake there is a Bank even&amp; smooth&amp; low like a grassy Bank in a Gentleman's Park.</s> <s id="s29">Along the hilly Ridge I walked through a Lane of green Hazels, with hay-fields&amp; <enamex sw="w10465" long="-3.117875647990246" lat="52.07216474126196" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275" name="Hay-On-Wye" conf="1.302439617">Hay</enamex> Makers on my Right, beyond the <enamex sw="w10500" long="-3.37913921746831" lat="54.40992913749553" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270535" name="River Irt" conf="2.4">River Irt</enamex>,&amp; on the other side of the River, <enamex sw="w10547" long="-3.332925188156983" lat="54.41044805184386" type="other" gazref="unlock:11183342" name="Irton Fell" conf="2">Irton Fell</enamex> with a deep perpendicular Ravine&amp; a curious fretted <enamex sw="w10611" long="-3.2825" lat="54.49917" type="other" gazref="unlock:4564691" name="Pillar" conf="2">Pillar</enamex> of Clay crossier-shaped, standing up in it-next to Ireton Fells&amp; in the same line as the <enamex sw="w10708" long="-3.214466500836419" lat="54.57349272667725" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11256013" name="Rigg Screes" conf="2.4">Screes</enamex>,&amp; you can look at nothing but the <enamex sw="w10751" long="-3.214466500836419" lat="54.57349272667725" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11256013" name="Rigg Screes" conf="2.4">Screes</enamex> though there were 20 quaint Pillars close by you.</s> <s id="s30">The Lake is wholly hidden' till your very Feet touch it, as one may say/ and to a Stranger the Burst would be almost overwhelming.</s> <s id="s31">The Lake itself seen from it's Foot appears indeed of too regular shape; exactly like the sheet of Paper on which I am writing, except it is still narrower in respect of it's length.</s> <s id="s32">( In reality however the Lake widens as it ascends, and at the head is very considerably broader than at the foot.) But yet, in spite of this it is a marvellous sight/ a sheet of water between 3&amp; 4 miles in length, the whole( or very nearly the whole) of it's right Bank formed by the <enamex sw="w11409" long="-3.214466500836419" lat="54.57349272667725" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11256013" name="Rigg Screes" conf="2.4">Screes</enamex>, or facing of bare Rock of enormous Height, two thirds of it's height downwards almost perpendicular;&amp; then slanting off in <enamex sw="w11542" long="-3.214466500836419" lat="54.57349272667725" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11256013" name="Rigg Screes" conf="2.4">Screes</enamex>, or Shiver, consisting of fine red Streaks running in broad <enamex sw="w11610" long="-2.393600018873607" lat="54.48007838645531" type="other" gazref="unlock:11294467" name="Stripes" conf="2">Stripes</enamex> through a stone colour-slanting off from the Perpendicular, as steep as the meal newly ground from the Miller's spout. - So it is at the foot of the Lake; but higher up this streaky Shiver occupies two thirds of the whole height, like a pointed Decanter in shape, or an outspread Fan, or a long-waisted old maid with a fine prim Apron, or-no, other things that would only fill up the Paper.</s></p>
<p><s id="s33">When I first came the Lake was a perfect Mirror;&amp; what must have been the Glory of the reflections in it! This huge facing of Rock said to be half a mile in perpendicular height, with deep <enamex sw="w12198" long="-108.7881556" lat="38.3819334" type="other" gazref="unlock:8176071" name="Ravin Mine" conf="0.487095309">Ravin</enamex> s the whole winded&amp; torrent-worn, except where the pink-striped <enamex sw="w12269" long="-3.214466500836419" lat="54.57349272667725" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11256013" name="Rigg Screes" conf="2.4">Screes</enamex> come in, as smooth as silk/ all this reflected, turned into Pillars, dells, and a whole new-world of Images in the water! The head of the Lake is crowned by three huge pyramidal mountains, <enamex sw="w12466" long="-2.99073383468145" lat="54.27891049248326" type="other" gazref="unlock:11328622" name="Yew Barrow" conf="2">Yew Barrow</enamex>, Sca' Fell,&amp; the great <enamex sw="w12503" long="-3.368527308226295" lat="54.55387103075659" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11151229" name="Gavel Fell" conf="2.4">Gavel</enamex>; <enamex sw="w12511" long="-3.272975138161649" lat="54.46502747709917" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11328681" name="Yewbarrow" conf="2.4">Yewbarrow</enamex>&amp; Sca'Fell nearly opposite to each other, yet so that the Ness( or Ridge Line, like the line of a fine Nose,) of Sca' Fell runs in behind that of <enamex sw="w12667" long="-3.272975138161649" lat="54.46502747709917" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11328681" name="Yewbarrow" conf="2.4">Yewbarrow</enamex>, while the Ness of great <enamex sw="w12703" long="-3.368527308226295" lat="54.55387103075659" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11151229" name="Gavel Fell" conf="2.4">Gavel</enamex> is still farther back, between the two others,&amp; of course, instead of running athwart the Vale it directly faces you.</s> <s id="s34">The Lake&amp; Vale run nearly from East to west and this figure below will give you some idea of it. -</s></p>
<p><s id="s35"><enamex sw="w12927" long="-2.9358" lat="54.6199" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY39672538" name="Melfell" conf="99992">Melfell</enamex>( lying South of the Lake) consists of great mountain steps decreasing in size as they approach the Lake.</s></p>
<p><s id="s36">My Road led along under <enamex sw="w13065" long="-2.9358" lat="54.6199" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY39672538" name="Melfell" conf="99992">Melfell</enamex>&amp; by <enamex sw="w13078" long="-3.272975138161649" lat="54.46502747709917" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11328681" name="Yewbarrow" conf="2.4">Yewbarrow</enamex> -&amp; now I came in sight of it's other side called <enamex sw="w13137" long="-3.2381" lat="54.3882" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD197999" name="Keppel Crag" conf="99992">Keppel Crag</enamex>&amp; then a huge enormous bason-like Cove called <enamex sw="w13195" long="-3.224016423635085" lat="54.37564582289723" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159627" name="Green Crag" conf="2">Green Crag</enamex>/ as I suppose, from there being no single Patch of Green to be seen on any one of it's perpendicular sides-so on to <enamex sw="w13323" long="-3.278021056241832" lat="54.62676949401982" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11187717" name="Kirk Fell" conf="2.4">Kirk Fell</enamex>, at the foot of which is Thomas Tyson' s House where W&amp; I slept Novr.</s> <s id="s37">will be 3 years -&amp; there I was welcomed kindly, had a good Bed, and left it after Breakfast.</s></p>
<p><s id="s38">Thursday Morning, Augt.</s> <s id="s39">5th-went down the Vale almost to the water head,&amp; ascended the low Reach between Sca' Fell and the <enamex sw="w13622" long="-3.214466500836419" lat="54.57349272667725" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11256013" name="Rigg Screes" conf="2.4">Screes</enamex>, and soon after I had gained it's height came in sight <enamex sw="w13685" long="-3.256448240380571" lat="54.4292454660531" type="water" gazref="unlock:11093457" name="Burnmoor Tarn" conf="2.4">Burnmoor</enamex> Water, a large Tairn nearly of that shape, it's Tail towards Sca' Fell, at its head a gap forming an inverted arch with Black Coomb&amp; a peep of the Sea seen through it.-- It lies directly at the <enamex sw="w13890" long="-53.464789812" lat="47.69849353" type="other" gazref="unlock:5151464" name="Camels Back" conf="0.6319546883">Back</enamex> of the <enamex sw="w13902" long="-3.214466500836419" lat="54.57349272667725" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11256013" name="Rigg Screes" conf="2.4">Screes</enamex>,&amp; the stream that flows from it down through the gap, is called the Mite - and runs through a Vale of it's own called <enamex sw="w14028" long="-3.324756248527244" lat="54.40069300266786" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:26800" name="Miterdale Forest" conf="2.4">Miterdale</enamex>, parallel with the lower part of <enamex sw="w14072" long="-3.3488" lat="54.4251" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:31029" name="Wasdale" conf="99992">Wastdale</enamex> and divided from it by the high Ridge called Ireton Fells. I ascended Sca' Fell by the side of a torrent, and climbed&amp; rested, rested&amp; climbed,' till I gained the very summit of Sca' Fell - believed by the Shepherds here to be higher than either <enamex sw="w14329" long="-3.043402327204126" lat="54.53913510713601" type="water" gazref="unlock:11169754" name="Helvellyn Gill" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex> or <enamex sw="w14342" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> - Even to Black Coomb - before me all the Mountains die away, running down westward to the Sea, apparently in eleven Ridges&amp; three parallel Vales with their three Rivers seen from their very Sources to their falling into the Sea, where they form( excepting their Screw Like flexures) the Trident of the Irish Channel at <enamex sw="w14671" long="-3.406748881310928" lat="54.35437318902203" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:43249" name="Ravenglass" conf="2.6">Ravenglass</enamex>-- O my God! what enormous Mountains these are close by me,&amp; yet below <enamex sw="w14753" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex> I stand on/ <enamex sw="w14775" long="-3.21929208" lat="54.48224887" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00108" name="Great Gable" conf="99992">Great Gavel</enamex>, <enamex sw="w14789" long="-3.278021056241832" lat="54.62676949401982" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11187717" name="Kirk Fell" conf="2.4">Kirk Fell</enamex>, <enamex sw="w14801" long="-3.224016423635085" lat="54.37564582289723" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159627" name="Green Crag" conf="2">Green Crag</enamex>,&amp; behind the <enamex sw="w14827" long="-3.2825" lat="54.49917" type="other" gazref="unlock:4564691" name="Pillar" conf="2">Pillar</enamex>, then the <enamex sw="w14845" long="-0.98333" lat="51.93333" type="other" gazref="unlock:4561374" name="Steeple Claydon" conf="0.8709304437">Steeple</enamex>, then the <enamex sw="w14864" long="-3.117875647990246" lat="52.07216474126196" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275" name="Hay-On-Wye" conf="1.302439617">Hay</enamex> Cock - on the other side&amp; behind me, <enamex sw="w14905" long="-3.195844359582791" lat="54.46581531356443" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11158711" name="Great End" conf="2.4">Great End</enamex>, <enamex sw="w14917" long="-3.25" lat="54.3955" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00021" name="Esk Carse" conf="99992">Esk Carse</enamex>, <enamex sw="w14929" long="-3.164480720837862" lat="54.44814432815852" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11084014" name="Bow Fell" conf="2.4">Bow Fell</enamex>&amp; close to my back two huge Pyramids, nearly as high as Sca' Fell itself,&amp; indeed parts&amp; parts of Sca' Fell known far&amp; near by these names, the hither one of <enamex sw="w15099" long="-3.195582381509362" lat="54.45682924986744" type="other" gazref="unlock:11087626" name="Broad Crag" conf="2">Broad Crag</enamex>, and the next to it but divided from it by a low Ridge Doe <enamex sw="w15170" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Crag</enamex>, which is indeed of itself a great Mountain of stones from a pound to 20 Ton weight embedded in wooly <enamex  sw="w15278" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Moss</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s40">And here I am so lounded - so fully lounded-that though the wind is strong,&amp; the <enamex sw="w15365" long="-2.411843342259774" lat="54.38262720582438" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771932" name="Clouds Gill" conf="2.4">Clouds</enamex> are hastening hither from the Sea - and the whole air seaward has a lurid Look And we shall certainly have Thunder Yet here( but that I am hungered&amp; provisionless) here I could lie warm, and wait methinks for tomorrow's Sun/ and on a nice Stone Table am I now at this moment writing to you-between 2 and 3 o' Clock as I guess/ surely the first Letter ever written from the Top of Sca' Fell! But O! what a look down just under my Feet! The frightfullest Cove that might ever be seen/ huge perpendicular Precipices, and one Sheep upon it's only Ledge, that surely must be crag! Tyson told me of this place,&amp; called it <enamex sw="w15992" long="-3.226428383545314" lat="54.45652012263416" type="other" gazref="unlock:11177191" name="Hollow Stones" conf="2">Hollow Stones</enamex>. Just by it&amp; joining together, rise two huge Pillars of bare lead-colored stone -/ I am no measurer/ but their height&amp; depth is terrible.</s> <s id="s41">I know how unfair it is to judge of these Things by a comparison of past Impressions with present-but I have no shadow of hesitation in saying that the Coves&amp; Precipices of Helvellin are nothing to these! But this sweet lounding Place I see directly through <enamex sw="w16407" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>, <enamex sw="w16420" long="-3.162071998" lat="54.53278308" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00025" name="Castle Crag" conf="99992">the Castle Crag</enamex>, the whole of <enamex sw="w16451" long="-3.152850781702139" lat="54.58308385381825" type="water" gazref="unlock:11128993" name="Derwent Water" conf="2.4">Derwent Water</enamex>,&amp; but for the haziness of the Air I could see own House - I see clear enough where it stands -</s></p>
<p><s id="s42">Here I will fold up this Letter-I have Wafers in my Inkhorn/&amp; you shall call this letter when it passes before you the Sca' Fell Letter/ - I must now drop down, how I may into <enamex sw="w16737" long="-3.316944260268746" lat="54.39264562595323" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140645" name="Eskdale Green" conf="2.6">Eskdale</enamex> - that lies under to my right-the upper part of it the wildest&amp; savagest surely of all the Vales that were ever seen from the Top of an <enamex  sw="w16881" name="Large admin unit">English Mountain</enamex>/ and the lower part the loveliest. -</s></p>
<p> <s id="s43">There is one sort of gambling, to which I am much addicted; and that not of the least criminal kind for a man who has children&amp; a concern.</s> <s id="s44">It is this.</s> <s id="s45">When I find it convenient to descend from a mountain, I am too confident&amp; too indolent to look round about&amp; wind about' till I find a track or other symptom of safety; but I wander on,&amp; where it is first possible to descend, there I go-relying upon fortune for how far down this possibility will continue.</s> <s id="s46">So it was yesterday afternoon. I passed down from Broadcrag, skirted the Precipices, and found myself cut off from a most sublime <enamex sw="w17530" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Crag</enamex> Summit, that seemed to rival Sca' Fell Man in height,&amp; to outdo it in fierceness.</s> <s id="s47">A Ridge of Hill lay low down,&amp; divided this <enamex sw="w17664" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Crag</enamex>( called Doe <enamex sw="w17681" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Crag</enamex>)&amp; <enamex sw="w17690" long="-3.195582381509362" lat="54.45682924986744" type="other" gazref="unlock:11087626" name="Broad Crag" conf="2">Broad Crag</enamex> - even as the Hyphen divides the words broad&amp; crag.</s> <s id="s48">I determined to go thither; the first place I came to, that was not direct Rock, I slipped down,&amp; went on for a while with tolerable ease-but now I came( it was midway down) to a smooth perpendicular Rock about 7 feet high-this was nothing-I put my hands on the Ledge,&amp; dropped down/ in a few yards came just such another/ I dropped that too/ and yet another, seemed not higher-I would not stand for a trifle/ so I dropped that too/ but the stretching of the muscle of my hands&amp; arms,&amp; the jolt of the Fall on my Feet, put my whole Limbs in a Tremble, and I paused,&amp; looking down, saw that I had little else to encounter but a succession of these little Precipices It was in truth a Path that in a very hard Rain is, no doubt, the channel of a most splendid <enamex sw="w18522" long="-1.88333" lat="53.05" type="other" gazref="unlock:4559105" name="Waterfall" conf="0.8446467695">Waterfall</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s49">So I began to suspect that I ought not to go on/ but then unfortunately though I could with ease drop down a smooth Rock 7 feet high, I could not climb it/ so go on I must/ and on I went/ the next 3 drops were not half a Foot, at least not a foot more than my own height/ but every Drop increased the Palsy of my Limbs-I shook all over, Heaven knows without the least influence of Fear/ and now I had only two more to drop down/ to return was impossible-but of these two the first was tremendous/ it was twice my own height,&amp; the Ledge at the bottom was exceedingly narrow, that if I dropt down upon it I must of necessity have fallen backwards&amp; of course killed myself.</s> <s id="s50">My Limbs were all in a tremble-I lay upon my <enamex sw="w19259" long="-53.464789812" lat="47.69849353" type="other" gazref="unlock:5151464" name="Camels Back" conf="0.6319546883">Back</enamex> to rest myself,&amp; was beginning according to my Custom to laugh at myself for a Madman, when the sight of the Crags above me on each side,&amp; the impestuous <enamex sw="w19420" long="-2.411843342259774" lat="54.38262720582438" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771932" name="Clouds Gill" conf="2.4">Clouds</enamex> just over them, posting so luridly&amp; so rapidly northward, overawed me/ I lay in a state of almost prophetic Trance&amp; Delight -&amp; blessed God aloud, for the powers of Reason&amp; of the Will, which remaining no Danger can overpower us! O God, I exclaimed aloud-how calm, how blessed am I now/ I know not how to proceed, how to return/ but if I am calm&amp; fearless&amp; confident/ if this Reality were a Dream, if I were asleep, what agonies had I suffered! what screams! - When the Reason&amp; the Will are away, what remain to us but Darkness&amp; Dimness&amp; a bewildering shame, and Pain that is utterly Lord over us, or fantastic Pleasure, that draws the Soul along swimming through the air in many shapes, even as a Flight of Starlings in a Wind.</s></p>
<p><s id="s51">I arose,&amp; looking down saw at the bottom a heap of Stones Which had fallen abroad-and rendered the narrow Ledge on which they had been piled, doubly dangerous/ at the bottom of the third Rock that I dropt from, I met a dead Sheep quite rotten-This heap of Stones, I guessed,&amp; have since found that I guessed aright, had been piled up by the Shepherd to enable him to climb up&amp; free the poor creature whom he had observed to be crag-fast-but seeing nothing but rock over rock, he had desisted&amp; gone for help -&amp; in the mean time the poor creature had fallen down&amp; killed itself. - As I was looking at these I glanced my eye to my left,&amp; observed that the Rock was rent from top to bottom-I measured the breadth of the Rent, and found that there was no danger of my being wedged in/ so I put my Knap Sack round to my side,&amp; slipped down as between two walls, without any danger or difficulty-the next Drop brought me down on the Ridge called <enamex  sw="w21109" name="Too ambigious to allocate">the How</enamex>/ I hunted out my Besom Stick, which I had flung before me when I first came to the Rocks And wisely gave over all thoughts of ascending Doe <enamex sw="w21258" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Crag</enamex> - for now the <enamex sw="w21276" long="-2.411843342259774" lat="54.38262720582438" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771932" name="Clouds Gill" conf="2.4">Clouds</enamex> were again coming in most tumultously-so I began to descend/ when I felt an odd sensation across my whole <enamex sw="w21390" long="-2.989012648806927" lat="54.20701444437348" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11139329" name="Ellerside Breast Plantn" conf="2.4">Breast</enamex> Not pain nor itching -&amp; putting my hand on it I found it all bumpy-and on looking saw the whole of my <enamex sw="w21498" long="-2.989012648806927" lat="54.20701444437348" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11139329" name="Ellerside Breast Plantn" conf="2.4">Breast</enamex> from my Neck -&amp; exactly all that my Kamell Hair <enamex sw="w21553" long="-2.989012648806927" lat="54.20701444437348" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11139329" name="Ellerside Breast Plantn" conf="2.4">Breast</enamex> <enamex sw="w21560" long="-2.420589291526738" lat="54.84556635825046" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771442" name="Shield Sike" conf="2.245676577">Shield</enamex> covers, filled with great red heat-bumps, so thick that no hair could lie between them.</s> <s id="s52">They still remain/ but are evidently less -&amp; I have no doubt will wholly disappear in a few Days.</s> <s id="s53">It was however a startling proof to me of the violent exertions which I had made.</s></p>
<p><s id="s54">- I descended this low Hill which was all hollow beneath me-and was like the rough green <enamex sw="w21923" long="-3.418173873318998" lat="55.5330023850274" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11251659" name="Quilt Hill" conf="1.232681365">Quilt</enamex> of a Bed of waters-at length two streams burst out&amp; took their way down, one on side a high Ground upon this Ridge, the other on the other-I took that to my right( having on my left this high Ground,&amp; the other Stream,&amp; beyond that Doe <enamex sw="w22168" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Crag</enamex>, on the other side of which is <enamex sw="w22205" name="Esk Halse">Esk Halse</enamex>, where the head-spring of the <enamex sw="w22246" long="-3.30009716472156" lat="54.3940525814659" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771979" name="River Esk" conf="2.4">Esk</enamex> rises,&amp; running down <enamex sw="w22272" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex>&amp; in upon the Vale looks and actually deceived me, as a great Turnpike Road In which, as in many other respects the Head of <enamex sw="w22405" long="-3.316944260268746" lat="54.39264562595323" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140645" name="Eskdale Green" conf="2.6">Eskdale</enamex> much resembles <enamex sw="w22428" long="-3.051865815747152" lat="54.42093505077031" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:34442" name="Little Langdale" conf="2.6">Langdale</enamex>)&amp; soon the channel sank all at once, at least 40 yards,&amp; formed a magnificent <enamex sw="w22518" long="-1.88333" lat="53.05" type="other" gazref="unlock:4559105" name="Waterfall" conf="0.8446467695">Waterfall</enamex> - and close under this a succession of <enamex  sw="w22566" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Waterfalls</enamex> 7 in number, the third of which is nearly as high as the first.</s> <s id="s55">When I had almost reached the bottom of <enamex sw="w22681" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex>, I stood so as to command the whole 8 <enamex  sw="w22728" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Waterfalls</enamex>, with the great triangle-Crag looking in above them,&amp; on the one side of them the enormous&amp; more than perpendicular Precipices&amp; Bull's Brows of Sca' Fell! And now the Thunder Storm was coming on, again&amp; again! - Just at the bottom of <enamex sw="w22976" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex> I saw on before me in the Vale, lying just under the River on the side of a Hill, one, two, three, four Objects I could not distinguish whether Peat Hovels, or hovel-shaped Stones-I thought in my mind, that 3 of them would turn out to be stones-but that the fourth was certainly a <enamex sw="w23268" long="-1.125009156210115" lat="52.41887710230649" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11180185" name="Hovel Hill" conf="1.161353552">Hovel</enamex>.</s> <s id="s56">I went on toward them, crossing&amp; recrossing the <enamex sw="w23324" long="-3.029493379823134" lat="55.151196701557" type="water" gazref="unlock:8782138" name="Becks Burn" conf="1.357638343">Becks</enamex>&amp; the River&amp; found that they were all huge Stones - the one nearest <enamex sw="w23398" long="-2.773201062785302" lat="54.96359343038616" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11072907" name="Beck Fm, The" conf="2.034000955">the Beck</enamex> which I had determined to be really a <enamex sw="w23445" long="-1.125009156210115" lat="52.41887710230649" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11180185" name="Hovel Hill" conf="1.161353552">Hovel</enamex>, retained it's likeness when I was close beside/ in size it it nearly equal to the famous Bowder stone, but in every other respect greatly <enamex sw="w23592" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="0.9991750664">superior</enamex> to it-it has a complete Roof,&amp; that perfectly thatched with weeds,&amp; Heath,&amp; Mountain Ash Bushes -</s></p>
<p><s id="s57">I now was obliged to ascend again, as the River ran greatly to the Left,&amp; the Vale was nothing more than the Channel of the River, all the rest of the interspace between the mountains was a tossing up&amp; down of the Hills of all sizes-and the place at which I am now writing is called - Te As,&amp; spelt, Toes - as the Toes of Sca'Fell -.</s> <s id="s58">It is not possible that any name can be more descriptive of the Head of <enamex sw="w24110" long="-3.316944260268746" lat="54.39264562595323" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140645" name="Eskdale Green" conf="2.6">Eskdale</enamex> - I ascended close under Sca' Fell,&amp; came to a little village of Sheep <enamex sw="w24190" long="-2.532511887632666" lat="54.47954629224139" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11100875" name="Castle Folds" conf="2.2">Folds</enamex>/ there were 5 together/&amp; the redding Stuff,&amp; the Shears,&amp; an old Pot, was in the Passage of the first of them.</s> <s id="s59">Here I found an imperfect Shelter from a Thunder Shower - accompanied with such Echoes! O God! what thoughts were mine! O how I wishes for Health&amp; Strength that I might wander about for a Month together, in the stormiest month of the year, among these Places, so lonely&amp; savage&amp; full of sounds!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s60">After the Thunder Storm I shouted out all your names in the Sheep Fold-when Echo came upon Echo/ and then <enamex  sw="w24716" name="Not a placename">Hartley</enamex>&amp; <enamex sw="w24726" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>&amp; then I laughed&amp; shouted Joanna/ It leaves all the Echoes I ever heard far behind, in number, distinctness&amp; humanness of Voice -&amp; then not to forget an old Friend I made them all say Dr. <enamex sw="w24924" long="-2.82474894803935" lat="54.56225995962338" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785686" name="Dodd Beck" conf="2.4">Dodd</enamex>&amp; c.</s></p>
<p><s id="s61">After the Storm I passed on&amp; came to a great Peat Road, that wound down a hill, called <enamex sw="w25021" long="-3.2141" lat="54.4115" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY21300246" name="Maddock" conf="99992">Maddock How</enamex>,&amp; now came out upon the first cultivated Land which begins with a Bridge that goes over a Stream, a <enamex sw="w25135" long="-1.88333" lat="53.05" type="other" gazref="unlock:4559105" name="Waterfall" conf="0.8446467695">Waterfall</enamex> of considerable height&amp; beautifully wooded above you,&amp; a great water-slope under you/ <enamex  sw="w25234" name="Too ambigious to allocate">the Gill down</enamex> which it falls, is called <enamex sw="w25274" long="-2.360755396747951" lat="54.25547538712051" type="other" gazref="unlock:11278598" name="Scale Gill Foot Moss" conf="1.976612788">Scale Gill</enamex> -&amp; the Fall <enamex sw="w25297" long="-3.2129" lat="54.411" type="manual update" gazref="Norhgate_ID_NY21380241" name="Scale Gill Beck" conf="99992">Scale Gill Force</enamex>.( The word Scale&amp; Scales is common in this Country -&amp; is said by. . . to be derived from the Saxon Sceala; the wattling of Sheep But judging from the places themselves, <enamex sw="w25485" long="-3.306404041715465" lat="54.54556917612459" type="water" gazref="unlock:11278597" name="Scale Force" conf="2.4">Scale Force</enamex>&amp; this <enamex sw="w25504" long="-2.360755396747951" lat="54.25547538712051" type="other" gazref="unlock:11278598" name="Scale Gill Foot Moss" conf="1.976612788">Scale Gill</enamex> Force-I think it as probable that it is derived from Scalle Which signifies a deafening Noise.) Well, I passed through some sweet pretty Fields,&amp; came to a large Farm House where I am now writing/ The place is called Toes or Te as-the master's name John Vicars Towers - they received me hospitably-I drank Tea here&amp; they begged me to pass the Night Which I did&amp; supped of some excellent Salmonlings, which Towers had brought from <enamex sw="w25948" long="-3.406748881310928" lat="54.35437318902203" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:43249" name="Ravenglass" conf="2.6">Ravenglass</enamex> whither he had been, as holding under the Earl of Egremont,&amp; obliged' to ride the Fair' - a custom introduced during the times of Insecurity&amp; piratical Incursion for the Protection of <enamex sw="w26144" long="-3.406748881310928" lat="54.35437318902203" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:43249" name="Ravenglass" conf="2.6">Ravenglass</enamex> Fair.</s> <s id="s62">They were a fine Family And a Girl who did not look more than 12 years old, but was nearly 15, was very beautiful-with hair like vine-tendrils -.</s> <s id="s63">She had been long ill -&amp; was a sickly child - Ah poor Bairn!( said the Mother) worse luck for her/ she looks like a Quality Bairn, as you may say.'</s> <s id="s64">This man's Ancestors have been time out of mind in the Vale/ and here I found that the common Names, Towers&amp; Tozers are the same -/ er signifies' upon' - as Mite Er-dale <enamex sw="w26624" long="-2.209297314157944" lat="54.66029554589857" type="other" gazref="unlock:11126474" name="Dale, The" conf="2">the Dale</enamex> upon the <enamex sw="w26642" long="-3.377934191644771" lat="54.37398704776693" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270727" name="River Mite" conf="2.4">River Mite</enamex>/ <enamex sw="w26655" long="-3.1786" lat="54.3532" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7294790" name="Dunnerdale" conf="99992">Donnerdale</enamex> - a contraction of <enamex sw="w26684" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> Er-dale <enamex sw="w26699" long="-2.209297314157944" lat="54.66029554589857" type="other" gazref="unlock:11126474" name="Dale, The" conf="2">the Dale</enamex> upon the River <enamex sw="w26723" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> - So Towers, pronounced in the Vale Te - ars -&amp; Tozers is those who live on Toes - i.e. upon the Knobby feet of the Mountain/ Mr. Tears has mended my pen. -</s></p>
<p><s id="s65">This morning after breakfast I went out with him,&amp; passed up the Vale again due East, along a higher Road, over a heathy upland, crossed the upper part of <enamex sw="w27041" long="-2.360755396747951" lat="54.25547538712051" type="other" gazref="unlock:11278598" name="Scale Gill Foot Moss" conf="1.976612788">Scale Gill</enamex>, came out upon <enamex sw="w27068" long="-3.2141" lat="54.4115" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY21300246" name="Maddock" conf="99992">Maddock How</enamex>,&amp; then ascending turned directly Northward, into the Heart of the mountains; on my left the wild Crags under which flows the <enamex sw="w27207" long="-3.2129" lat="54.411" type="manual update" gazref="Norhgate_ID_NY21380241" name="Scale Gill Beck" conf="99992">Scale Gill Beck</enamex>, the most remarkable of them callled <enamex sw="w27261" long="-2.9691" lat="54.313" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD37059126" name="Cat Crag" conf="99992">Cat Crag</enamex>( a wild Cat being killed there)&amp; on my right hand six great Crags, which appeared in the mist all in a file-and they were all, though of different sizes, yet the same shape all triangles -.</s> <s id="s66">Other Crags far above them, higher up the Vale, appeared&amp; disappeared as the mists passed&amp; came/ one with a waterfall, called <enamex sw="w27590" long="-3.098473619501757" lat="54.28696599116789" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11289247" name="Spout Crag" conf="2.4">Spout Crag</enamex> - and another most tremendous one, called Earn <enamex sw="w27647" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Crag</enamex> - I passed on, a little way, till I came close under a huge <enamex sw="w27711" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Crag</enamex>, called <enamex sw="w27724" long="-2.871094953961352" lat="54.43263875854286" type="other" gazref="unlock:11091582" name="Buck Crag" conf="2">Buck Crag</enamex> -&amp; immediately under this is Four Foot Stone - having on it the clear marks of four foot-steps.</s> <s id="s67">The Stone is in it's whole breadth just 36 inches,( I measured it exactly) but the part that contains the marks is raised above the other part,&amp; is just 20 and a half Inches.</s> <s id="s68">The first foot-mark is an Ox's foot-nothing can be conceived more exact-this is 5 and thee quarter Inches wide-the second is a Boy's shoe in the Snow, 9 and a half Inches in length/ this too is the very Thing itself, the Heel, the bend the Foot, etc[ check] - the third is the Foot Step to the very Life of a Mastiff Dog And the fourth is <enamex sw="w28343" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>'s very own first little Shoe, 4 Inches in length&amp; o! it is the sweetest Baby shoe that ever was seen. - The wie-foot in <enamex sw="w28471" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex> is contemptible; but this really does work upon my imagination very powerfully/&amp; I will try to construct a Tale upon it/ the place too is so very, very wild.</s> <s id="s69">I delighted the Shepherd by my admiration/&amp; the four foot Stone is my own Christening,&amp; Towers undertakes it shall hereafter go by that name for hitherto it has been nameless. - And so I returned&amp; have found a Pedlar here of an interesting Physiognomy -&amp; here I must leave off-for Dinner is ready -</s></p>
<p> <s id="s70">Dined at Towers' -&amp; quitted him at half past one.</s> <s id="s71"><enamex sw="w28993" long="-3.316944260268746" lat="54.39264562595323" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140645" name="Eskdale Green" conf="2.6">Eskdale</enamex>, more descriptively Eskerdales, for it is a dale by the reluctant Mercy of the mountains, and the Hills, their children/ some but Babes, others striplings, who stand breast-high to their Fathers It is mainly however two Dales, like Stanley's in <enamex sw="w29249" long="-3.062036251617709" lat="54.58674605217004" type="water" gazref="unlock:8773419" name="St Johns Beck" conf="2.4">St Johns</enamex>/ only that the intervening ridge of Hills, is higher than those of <enamex sw="w29326" long="-3.359050759819266" lat="54.73374954392006" type="other" gazref="unlock:11207353" name="Low Leathes" conf="1.96473205">Leathes</enamex>' water&amp; lower than the <enamex sw="w29358" long="-3.0737" lat="54.5821" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY307213" name="High Rigg" conf="99992">Naddle Fell</enamex> - The <enamex sw="w29375" long="-3.30009716472156" lat="54.3940525814659" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771979" name="River Esk" conf="2.4">Esk</enamex> runs down the left hand of the ridge( as you go down) - both vales are in their course of very unequal breadths, often little more than the River Channel in the one, and as much space as would serve for the bed of a good river in the other/ - Now then <enamex  sw="w29627" name="Too ambigious to allocate">the Hill Ridge</enamex> intermits and the vales become one/ but never sure were lovelyer human Dwellings than these nested in <enamex sw="w29745" long="-0.9214981485461977" lat="53.56319006165395" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785380" name="Crow Trees Moor Drain East" conf="1.288481918">Trees</enamex> at the foot of the Fells,&amp; in among the intervening Hills/ - After you have left Sca' Fell&amp; his Progeny behind you, the Fells on each side are low, rough,&amp; ragged with <enamex sw="w29922" long="-1.738191395265293" lat="52.31552863710075" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13393529" name="Bushwood CP" conf="1.344100575">Bushwood</enamex>, but low -</s></p>
<p><s id="s72">Inclosures made on the <enamex sw="w29964" long="-3.214466500836419" lat="54.57349272667725" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11256013" name="Rigg Screes" conf="2.4">Screes</enamex> partly for saving the Sheep from falling down, partly to reserve the Grass for the Hogs</s></p>
<p><s id="s73">After the junction&amp; re-disjunction of the vales came to a Beck, with a Bridge which I crossed-a pretty Beck with well wooded Banks, chiefly Oak, Ash, Alder,&amp; Birch, not without Thorns, Hazels,&amp; Hollies/ 2 or 3 houses very pleasantly situated on the <enamex sw="w30313" long="-3.0667" lat="54.9667" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2649904" name="Esk" conf="99992">Esk side</enamex> of the Bridge,&amp; on the other side a grand picture view of the Ridge&amp; Top of <enamex sw="w30400" long="-3.093856465711642" lat="54.69149101904309" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11159225" name="Great Sca Fell" conf="2.4">Sca Fell</enamex> seen through a with a road at the bottom/.</s></p>
<p><s id="s74">This Beck( from <enamex sw="w30468" long="-3.208887855126327" lat="54.38478705157009" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11166663" name="Harter Fell" conf="2.4">Harter Fell</enamex>?) slants from the Bridge directly into the <enamex sw="w30524" long="-3.30009716472156" lat="54.3940525814659" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771979" name="River Esk" conf="2.4">Esk</enamex>,&amp; in a few hundred yards after, the vale narrows, unites,&amp; you walk by the side of the <enamex sw="w30617" long="-3.30009716472156" lat="54.3940525814659" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771979" name="River Esk" conf="2.4">Esk</enamex>, now as broad as the Greta/ the front side of the last Hill a pretty regular farmhouse with a noble <enamex sw="w30723" long="-53.464789812" lat="47.69849353" type="other" gazref="unlock:5151464" name="Camels Back" conf="0.6319546883">Back</enamex> of Wood/ situated just as the House by the Brig at <enamex sw="w30780" long="-3.241035730229108" lat="54.42940479168539" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11158930" name="Great How" conf="2.4">Great How</enamex>/ only <enamex sw="w30797" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex> is not as quarter as high/</s></p>
<p><s id="s75">I walk however not a furlong, before the <enamex sw="w30875" long="-3.30009716472156" lat="54.3940525814659" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771979" name="River Esk" conf="2.4">Esk</enamex> slants away from me to the left again, but presents a beautiful reach/ - <enamex sw="w30953" long="-3.208887855126327" lat="54.38478705157009" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11166663" name="Harter Fell" conf="2.4">Harter Fell</enamex> is next to Lowfell,&amp; that Beck which I crossed the Bridge over, is <enamex sw="w31034" long="-3.25762" lat="54.41359" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY17660111" name="Whillan Beck" conf="99992">Whillah</enamex> Beck, comes from <enamex sw="w31060" long="-3.256448240380571" lat="54.4292454660531" type="water" gazref="unlock:11093457" name="Burnmoor Tarn" conf="2.4">Burnmoor</enamex> Tairn/ on my right I have low Fells, <enamex sw="w31107" long="-3.3244" lat="54.3879" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7733089" name="Eskdale" conf="99992">Eskdale Moors</enamex>, exceedingly rocky&amp; woody, huge perpend.</s> <s id="s76">smooth stones, now hidden,&amp; encircled by young wood, now starting out.</s> <s id="s77">The regular House is a shooting seat of Mr Stanley's - I come again to a view of the river over some Hayfields and an Islet in the River/ the opposite fells <enamex sw="w31394" long="-3.270470867839839" lat="54.38415472311014" type="water" gazref="unlock:11077710" name="Birker Beck" conf="2.4">Birker</enamex> Fells. -</s></p>
<p><s id="s78">Remember the large Scotch Fir in <enamex sw="w31444" long="-3.429418179792764" lat="54.52620042627977" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140131" name="Ennerdale Bridge" conf="2.6">Ennerdale</enamex> -</s></p>
<p><s id="s79">Come to the Public House, with a beautiful low Hill of wood&amp; Rock close behind, cross the <enamex sw="w31548" long="-3.0089" lat="54.9742" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY18940072" name="Esk Bridge" conf="99992">Esk Bridge</enamex>,&amp; pass at the end of <enamex sw="w31582" long="-3.2743" lat="54.3663" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD173975" name="Birker Moor" conf="99992">Birker Moor</enamex>, a piece of wooded Rock Grander, exactly like the other side of <enamex sw="w31659" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, opposite Tail End front-windows, except that it rises&amp; falls in full large obtuse Triangles,&amp; not so much in small Nipple Work-at the end of this <enamex sw="w31818" long="-3.316944260268746" lat="54.39264562595323" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140645" name="Eskdale Green" conf="2.6">Eskdale</enamex> becomes a broad spacious Vale, completely land-locked, though the Fells at the end are low-indeed only green cultivated Hills The vale now seems to consist of very large Fields, with corn&amp; potatoes&amp; grass Land growing, all in one field, in broad stripes. - To the right hand <enamex sw="w32101" long="-3.362543127981755" lat="54.37416175316758" type="other" gazref="unlock:11225126" name="Muncaster Fell" conf="2">Muncaster Fell</enamex>, to the left <enamex sw="w32130" long="-3.28" lat="54.3896" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_6288078" name="Easterfield" conf="99992">Easterfield Common</enamex>, over which I ascended by a Peat Road. It seems I have gone 2 miles round about&amp; ought to have crossed over at <enamex sw="w32263" long="-3.286147247643601" lat="54.3929775998885" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11126501" name="Dalegarth Hall" conf="2.2">Dalegarth Hall</enamex>( from Stanley's Shooting Box) - sate&amp; wrote this near the top of <enamex sw="w32342" long="-3.28" lat="54.3896" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_6288078" name="Easterfield" conf="99992">Easterfield Common</enamex>( Fern, Heath,&amp; <enamex  sw="w32377" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Moss</enamex>) - a pretty view of the Sea through a sink in <enamex sw="w32427" long="-76.049367735" lat="44.350114941" type="other" gazref="unlock:5321559" name="Mulcaster Island" conf="0.6004127678">Mulcaster</enamex> a small Dip in the shape of an inverted triangle-the Sea,&amp; a triangle of Green Coast.</s></p>
<p><s id="s80">Descended on the other side of <enamex sw="w32556" long="-3.28" lat="54.3896" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_6288078" name="Easterfield" conf="99992">Easterfield Common</enamex>, crossed a moss, and ascended another&amp; came out upon/ a good large Tairn with naked Banks,&amp; a tiny Island covered with Sea fowl, two of which,&amp; afterwards four, flew round about above me, wailing&amp;, then dipped down low,&amp; made a dead dart along over my head, so that I could hear the clang of the wings,&amp; altering its Notes to a noise of anger&amp; menace/ I stand in the ruins of the city of <enamex sw="w32974" long="-3.330888682769162" lat="54.34754804746417" type="other" gazref="unlock:11070615" name="Barnscar" conf="2">Barnscar</enamex>/ fill 5 pages; but nevertheless I found nothing, after most patient search, that I could distinguish from any part of <enamex sw="w33102" long="-3.972325756997933" lat="54.88713027476024" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11142935" name="Fell, The" conf="1.118624154">the Fell</enamex> Two heaps of Stones, on each of which some Boys had built up a Shelter in the Shape of a large Chimney, wanting the one side fronting the Lake - it is a flat-round hill-Albinus omnino nihil. - However the view is very fine-Sauce better than the fish-behind to my left a noble sea-view-to my right a break in the Fells,&amp; a bold view of the huge Mountains at the head of Wastdale directly across the Lake&amp; in front of me.</s> <s id="s81"><enamex sw="w33530" long="-3.329728473676685" lat="54.31160486942807" type="other" gazref="unlock:11116309" name="Corney Fell" conf="2">Corney Fell</enamex>, Stones' Head Fell, <enamex sw="w33564" long="-3.3293" lat="54.2578" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD135855" name="Black Comb" conf="99992">Black Comb</enamex>, of a very wild, various,&amp; angular outline, running in ridges, rising in triangles, sinking in inverting arches, or darting down in Nesses Mountain seen behind mountain, either the backward overtopping the hitherward, - or the nearer mountain dipping down in an inverted arch or triangle/ - at the bottom of <enamex sw="w33881" long="-3.2977" lat="54.361" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2651293" name="Devoke Water" conf="99992">Devock</enamex>, i.e. between the mountain view&amp; the water,&amp; forming its immediate is a small Hill with a curious round large stoney Head/ I shall ascend to my right, gain a still more extensive view of the Sea,&amp; go round to it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s82">The angry clapper of the Bird's Bill, as it passed over my head. -</s></p>
<p><s id="s83">I was not in the <enamex sw="w34188" long="-3.3354" lat="54.3512" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD133959" name="City of Bardscar" conf="99992">City of Bardscar</enamex>, it is half a mile from the Foot of the Lake, toward <enamex sw="w34260" long="-76.049367735" lat="44.350114941" type="other" gazref="unlock:5321559" name="Mulcaster Island" conf="0.6004127678">Mulcaster</enamex>// but however it differs from what I did see/ - <enamex sw="w34317" long="-3.2977" lat="54.361" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2651293" name="Devoke Water" conf="99992">Devock</enamex> Lake is prettily shaped,&amp; runs from South to North/ at <enamex sw="w34379" long="0.2111083961682288" lat="52.37445689956457" type="other" gazref="unlock:11248083" name="Pools, The or Valley Bottom" conf="0.6615295076">the Bottom</enamex>, just under <enamex  sw="w34402" name="Not a placename">Wadness</enamex> How, or <enamex sw="w34419" long="-3.215804290008471" lat="54.6184217216403" type="other" gazref="unlock:11279832" name="Seat How" conf="2">Seat How</enamex> by the Boat House, standing/ <enamex sw="w34456" long="-2.231596649578127" lat="53.11416323201878" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11298965" name="The Bank" conf="1.406777736">the Bank</enamex> to my left is strait, but the other, the head left&amp; the whole of the left is pretty in bays,&amp; the Island close on its left Bank is pretty with some <enamex sw="w34615" long="-0.9214981485461977" lat="53.56319006165395" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785380" name="Crow Trees Moor Drain East" conf="1.288481918">Trees</enamex>&amp; Bushes on it/ and if the whole of its right Bank, which is an ascent of 120 yards perhaps, were completely cloathed with wood,&amp; the other Banks judiciously plante, it would cap' em a/ sea views/&amp; fell views! - Saw the pith of a Sieve two feet long, with a small strip of <enamex sw="w34892" long="-2.973048054234086" lat="54.18017794107498" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11299050" name="The Green" conf="2.6">the Green</enamex> suffered to remain,&amp; keep the pith firm/ dipped in hot fat/ - A Candle Stick/ with a back formed of half a[ hollow] cylinder of Iron, with holes in it,&amp; a solid Cylinder of Iron with a bent hook at the End to put in to those <enamex sw="w35125" long="-1.88333" lat="53.3" type="other" gazref="unlock:4575432" name="Dove Holes" conf="0.8055949795">Holes</enamex>, so as to lengthen or shorten the stick as occasion/ its whole length when the hook[ is] in its last hole, is nearly a yard/ one of these long sieves will burn an Hour -</s></p>
<p><s id="s84">Passed over a common, wild,&amp; dreary, and descending a hill came down upon <enamex sw="w35373" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex> Kirk, with a sweet view up the River, with a[ large] mirror over a rapid/ <enamex sw="w35455" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex> Kirk is a most romantic vale, the mountains that embosom it, low&amp; of a remarkably wild outline/ and higher mountains looking in from behind.</s> <s id="s85">The view from the Bridge, consisting of a reach of the River, the Road&amp; the Kirk to the left at the end of the Reach.</s> <s id="s86">The Kirk standing on the low rough Hill up which the Road climbs, the fields level and high, beyond that;&amp; then the different flights of mountains in the back ground, with wild ridges from the right&amp; the left, running like Arms&amp; confining the middle view to these level fields on high ground is eminently picturesque-A little step( 50 or 60 yards) beyond the Bridge, you gain a compleatly different picture-the Houses&amp; the Kirk forming more important parts,&amp; the view bounded at once by a high wooded rock, shaped as an obtuse-triangle/ or segments of a circle forming an angle at their point of junction, now compleat in a Mirror&amp; equally delightful as a view.</s></p>
<p><s id="s87">I pass along for a furlong or so upon the road, the river winding through the narrow vale,&amp; then turn off to my left athwart a Cove on <enamex sw="w36529" long="-3.1786" lat="54.3532" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7294790" name="Dunnerdale" conf="99992">Donnerdale</enamex> Fell - a very rocky Fell, yew-trees on the Rocks/( each crag a lownding-place for sheep) the outer line running in the segment of a circle so as to form the cove athwart which I went-this outline most wildly saw-toothed/ and sheep-tracks every where-O lovely lovely Vale! -</s></p>
<p><s id="s88">Here it was seated on this Mount, on Saturday, August 7, that I resolved to write under the name of The Soother of Absence, the topographical poem which I had long mummeled about in my mind,&amp; the day before thought of under the name of the Bards of Helvellin or the Stone Hovels/ - The public house at <enamex sw="w37112" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex> a very nice one/&amp; the Landlord, a very intelligent man <enamex sw="w37173" long="-74.178478" lat="40.8387109" type="other" gazref="unlock:7845397" name="State Police Bloomfield Heliport" conf="1.22446103">Bloomfield</enamex>/ - I climb over <enamex sw="w37199" long="-3.972325756997933" lat="54.88713027476024" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11142935" name="Fell, The" conf="1.118624154">the Fell</enamex>, taking to my left a little, wind around[ under&amp; between low] crags,&amp; come to two <enamex sw="w37293" long="-2.962113370137919" lat="54.36902855076801" type="water" gazref="unlock:11300323" name="Three Dubs Tarn" conf="2.4">Dubs</enamex> in the shape of an 8, the hither one with 30 or 40 little Islets,[ each] of a yard or so of breadth/&amp; now suddenly burst upon me a blunt-angled triangle Hill, a Peak of great height&amp; singularity, rocky,&amp; hetherey, with patches of yellow Green Pasture intermixed/ behind me, right over the <enamex sw="w37588" long="-2.888096328127128" lat="54.40599874465142" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791733" name="Dubbs Beck" conf="2.4">Dubbs</enamex>, a fine water view, of rivers&amp; flat land,&amp; the Sea.</s></p>
<p><s id="s89">- It must have been here that I lost my way, for I now went on till I found myself coming down upon <enamex sw="w37747" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex> again, about a mile above the House&amp; Kirk which I had just quitted/ however I was not sorry, to have another view of that lovely Place, and it brought me in full sight of a fine water fall on the opposite Hill on the other side of the <enamex sw="w37989" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>, seemingly a short mile above the Kirk/ I saw Houses to my right,&amp; an[ old] Man with his <enamex sw="w38087" long="-1.808523477504122" lat="54.16597893974405" type="other" gazref="unlock:11183990" name="Jenny Twigg and her Daughter Tib" conf="0.9032294157">Daughter</enamex>, a sweet Girl, burning Bracken Went up to him&amp; talked with him&amp; the lovely Girl in the[ midst] of the huge Volumes of Smoke,&amp; found I had gone two miles wrong-which yet I could scarcely believe/ however he sent me to the Road, which which hard by,&amp; winded down through <enamex sw="w38369" long="-3.1786" lat="54.3532" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7294790" name="Dunnerdale" conf="99992">Donnerdale</enamex> <enamex sw="w38380" long="-1.175382158350924" lat="52.05786619379407" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:42798" name="Halse" conf="1.455376764">Halse</enamex>, a sloping vale between the <enamex sw="w38415" long="-3.1786" lat="54.3532" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7294790" name="Dunnerdale" conf="99992">Donnerdale</enamex> Common&amp; <enamex sw="w38435" long="-3.1786" lat="54.3532" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7294790" name="Dunnerdale" conf="99992">Donnerdale</enamex> Fell/ a most lovely narrow vale with several Houses, and[ after I had passed the first house] on my Right the sound of a Beck, deep hidden&amp; with a wooden bank between me&amp; it,&amp; its other bank a Hill with a ravin bisecting it, but all covered with fine wood,&amp; completely hidden, ravin&amp; all - nd now, being a short mile from <enamex sw="w38774" long="-3.191150710673775" lat="54.30406398518605" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11089775" name="Broughton Mills" conf="2.6">Broughton Mills</enamex>, this wood-covered Hill&amp; sounding Beck to my right, there burst on me a lovely Prospect About a quarter of mile on before me the woody Hill ran down[ with] a very gentle descent in a long Ness, and the Hilly Ridge, directly in front of me, cultivated&amp; inclosed to the top, ran down in a Ness far on behind the Ness of the woody Hill,&amp; so as to form an inverted obtuse-angled triangle with the upper Half of the woody Nose,&amp; through this the sea,&amp; an Island in the distance/ two or three Houses immediately upon the Sea Ness,&amp; just where the Wood Ness reached the ground, a beautiful Road came in sight leading up the cultivated Hill, with houses&amp; trees&amp; hedges directly on to the little village upon the Ness As I proceed a few yards, the view is completely altered, and a round smooth rises up beyond the Sea Ness,&amp; bisects the distance/ and on the other side of the round Hill is the high lands on the Coast nd now I descend,&amp; cross the Wood Beck, which preserves its character to the last, running all under <enamex sw="w39815" long="-1.711813088316407" lat="52.63754642241833" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11298959" name="The Alders" conf="1.422215691">Alders</enamex>, into a beck of a similar character from the Woods on <enamex sw="w39876" long="-3.1786" lat="54.3532" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7294790" name="Dunnerdale" conf="99992">Donnerdale</enamex> Fell -&amp; now come into a lovely vale,&amp; a Bridge covered with Ivy, its wall 20 yards in length/ the vale is completely land-locked by segments of circles folding in behind each other/ before me a[ strait] ridge slants across, <enamex sw="w40111" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex> on my right folds in a long Ellipse behind, while <enamex sw="w40170" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex> on my left in more of a segment of a circle folds in before it/ so is it, with my back to the sea <enamex sw="w40276" long="-4.559389442420779" lat="54.05800177506696" type="water" gazref="unlock:11183258" name="Irish Sea" conf="1.019299192">Irish Sea</enamex>,&amp; my face looking up the Stream that runs between alders&amp; birch elms-the name of <enamex sw="w40370" long="-2.773201062785302" lat="54.96359343038616" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11072907" name="Beck Fm, The" conf="2.034000955">the Beck</enamex> <enamex sw="w40379" long="-2.770076421821211" lat="54.47197437152141" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788548" name="Little Mosedale Beck" conf="2.4">Little Beck</enamex>, that springs out of <enamex sw="w40413" long="-3.1583" lat="54.3441" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD248949" name="Coe Moss" conf="99992">Coe Moss</enamex>/ - Turning round&amp; looking sea-ward <enamex sw="w40457" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex> that is now to my left&amp; makes an elliptical line to my back, curves in a circle-segment, while <enamex sw="w40562" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex> to my right folds round about it/./ The place <enamex sw="w40616" long="-3.191150710673775" lat="54.30406398518605" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11089775" name="Broughton Mills" conf="2.6">Broughton Mills</enamex>/ Corn Mills/ - <enamex sw="w40645" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex> that came upon when I lost my way Stickle <enamex sw="w40696" long="-84.4385489" lat="36.6509124" type="other" gazref="unlock:7053984" name="Pine Knot" conf="0.6599311618">Knot</enamex>/ -/</s></p>
<p> <s id="s90">Mr. Thomas Robinson's <enamex sw="w40728" long="-1.837678400925536" lat="54.54352586804922" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11078317" name="Black Bull Fm" conf="1.095075293">Black Bull</enamex>, <enamex sw="w40741" long="-2.029395714329929" lat="54.10128439740299" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36725" name="Conistone" conf="1.540984751">Conistone</enamex> -</s></p>
<p><s id="s91">Dined on Oatcake&amp; Cheese, with a pint of Ale,&amp; 2 glasses of Rum&amp; water sweetened with preserved Gooseberries at the Ale house - Cassons' - the son, William Casson, got a pleurisy&amp; abscess in his side by overheating himself&amp; then starving himself in breaking up the Ice for <enamex sw="w41029" long="-0.4544624170487661" lat="54.32701126757493" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11236062" name="Old Mill, The" conf="1.154758609">the Mill</enamex> But being a Scholar, he gets his cloathes&amp; a little money besides by teaching a lile lock of Bairns/ his Father&amp; Mother that keep the Public House Blacksmith's Arms, <enamex sw="w41205" long="-3.191150710673775" lat="54.30406398518605" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11089775" name="Broughton Mills" conf="2.6">Broughton Mills</enamex>, give him his meat. - The road[ to Torvill or Torva] turns off at the Inn/ the views on your left hand exceedingly interesting/ a few hundred yards from the one Inn one eminently picturesque-a Cottage among <enamex sw="w41426" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex> with 9 main feautures of Sight having their point of unity in it/ but all the way for a mile by our Left is a great bulging rocky Hill covered with wood, with two or three deep wooded Ravines in it, and the unseen ever-heard Brook winding at its feet-between the road&amp; the brook inclosed fields, of steep descent, and near to the head of the woody <enamex sw="w41783" long="-3.155767318842949" lat="55.23019052713254" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11069192" name="Bank Head Hill" conf="1.31078875">Hill Bank</enamex> a House&amp; outhouses with 10 tall Firs at its <enamex sw="w41838" long="-53.464789812" lat="47.69849353" type="other" gazref="unlock:5151464" name="Camels Back" conf="0.6319546883">Back</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s92">The Roads upon[&amp; between] the Hills from here a very interesting part of the Picture&amp;[ views to the right were of] open fields, steep ascending/ Beyond the House with the Firs, he Brook becomes visible sloping down a descent/ and still I ascend, ferney Common to my right, to my left woods with fields&amp; inclosures intermixed,&amp; above the woods-and now nearly in the bottom you see a House with 2 outhouses, the House itself ivied all over its sea-ward <enamex sw="w42298" long="-3.368527308226295" lat="54.55387103075659" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11151229" name="Gavel Fell" conf="2.4">Gavel</enamex>/ - and from this House the[ line of the] Beck runs almost straight up to its Fountain head/ and a beautiful Road serpentizes over <enamex sw="w42431" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex> just above its head, and for a small space down along its hither Bank/ it rises or seems to rise between 2 round stony Hills, each of which the Mountain Ridges now rise over, now sink under, in a jagged saw-toothed outline.</s></p>
<p><s id="s93">I am sitting in the road, with the ivied House beneath me, and right opposite me, through an inverted arch in the Fells, a very singular pike looks in - N.B. - one effect of the magnitude of surrounding objects-it gives to shapes a narrowness of width, exceedingly favorable to boldness, an approximating to a sharp point, which being comparative loses its effect upon paper-because you can scarcely give the real shape, preserving its true relative dimensions, besides in a picture you only take a part of the view; but in nature the whole, perhaps 20 fold more than you draw, appears to you, each part modified by all the rest -</s></p>
<p><s id="s94">- at this ivied house another Beck comes from the Fells, close by my road/&amp; joins the former/&amp; now a ridge rises gradually like a fish, increasing[ all the way] from the Tail up to the head, rises between my road&amp; the source of the former Beck -&amp; about a furlong higher up, a bridge crosses the latter Beck,&amp; the road which I before observed serpentizing at the head of the main beck runs down in a sweet Curve upon the Bridge;&amp; goes by <enamex sw="w43731" name="the Beck side">the Beck side</enamex> down to the Ivied House in a strait Line/ all before me, as far as I can see, which indeed is not more than a quarter of a mile, a gentle ascent, ferney Common - Steep on my right, the wider view on my left a descending Fell with green stony bulging Hills on either side, which unite at its head in a shelving ridge, over behind which a higher ridge shelves in the same Direction/ I now pass on, beyond the source of the hither Beck, to the top of <enamex sw="w44193" long="-2.65803" lat="52.27539" type="other" gazref="unlock:13900253" name="Middleton on the Hill" conf="0.8078423091">the Hill</enamex>, along which&amp; up which my road had ever been winding,&amp; see behind me to my right a grand <enamex sw="w44294" long="-1.11454233533464" lat="50.71918870572928" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279920" name="Seaview" conf="1.207782758">Seaview</enamex>&amp; the flat lands upon the Sea, with 3 Hills, the largest of which looks like a <enamex  sw="w44382" name="Mythical place">Paradise</enamex> in the wild, the fields so sweetly shaped&amp; so green, the smaller is not unlike it, the hither one is bleak/ I go on, descend a little&amp; to my right a low cultivated Dell, with stony Fells above it; to my left a bleak Common,&amp; stony Fells over which the <enamex sw="w44645" long="-2.411843342259774" lat="54.38262720582438" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771932" name="Clouds Gill" conf="2.4">Clouds</enamex> are sweeping, and on my right far onward long ridges of fells, all running[ abreast] with long arms sea-ward,&amp; seen either by dips&amp; gaps in the the hithermost ridges, or by the <enamex sw="w44831" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="0.9991750664">superior</enamex> height of the furthermost-but all alike-grey&amp; stoney-it is a day of sun&amp; <enamex sw="w44915" long="-2.411843342259774" lat="54.38262720582438" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771932" name="Clouds Gill" conf="2.4">Clouds</enamex>, with a thousand Shadows on the Hills -</s></p>
<p> <s id="s95"><enamex sw="w44962" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex>/ <enamex sw="w44973" long="-3.068542713" lat="54.383555" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00094" name="Yewdale Crag" conf="99992">Yewdale Crag</enamex> is that noblest Ness, the main feature of the Head of the Lake/ the next to it <enamex sw="w45065" long="-3.070317770113821" lat="54.38609496807895" type="other" gazref="unlock:11328684" name="Yewdale Fells" conf="2">Yewdale Fells</enamex> -</s></p>
<p><s id="s96">The water fall I saw is Levers' Water Force - and a Tarn to the south of it, behind two compleat Negro Breasts - a full Bosom/ called Scrow&amp; Bell. The Tairn behind Scrow/ The <enamex sw="w45256" long="-3.12208" lat="54.37042" type="other" gazref="unlock:4565407" name="Old Man of Coniston" conf="2">Old Man</enamex> is just above/ next to that <enamex sw="w45291" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex> Fells - then <enamex sw="w45314" long="-3.163207410991242" lat="54.40321322882879" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11111654" name="Cockley Beck" conf="2.6">Cockley Beck</enamex> Fells - then Wrey Nose&amp; c&amp; c</s></p>
<p> <s id="s97"><enamex sw="w45356" long="-3.0765" lat="54.3361" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2653454" name="Coniston Water" conf="99991">Coniston Lake</enamex> a fine mixture of the aweful&amp; the pleasing Simple Of one - colored dark Rocks,&amp; pastoral Hills below.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s98"><enamex sw="w45473" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> is doubtless a worthy Compeer of the Stateliest/ an equal coheir of Nature with <enamex sw="w45561" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, Wyndermere,&amp; Ulswater/ Its distinguishing character I think it its perfect&amp; easy comprehensibility.</s> <s id="s99">At its foot the Hills are low, but of a various outline/ from the Foot to within a mile of the Head, the Hills on either side are of no great permanent Interest, though susceptible no doubt of a very high one from the accidents of Nature, that must be so frequent here, of broken Sunlights, <enamex sw="w45964" long="-2.411843342259774" lat="54.38262720582438" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771932" name="Clouds Gill" conf="2.4">Clouds</enamex>,&amp; Storm/ <enamex  sw="w45980" name="Too ambigious to allocate">The Head</enamex> of the Lake is an admirable junction of awful&amp; of pleasing Simplicity./ its is beyond all lakes perfectly intelligible-Conceive a crescent of Hills, or rather a crescent hill, enfolding the first mile of water/ this hill of various height&amp; various outline, but no where high/ above this hill at the head of the Lake, but somewhat to the Left of it( as you ascend the Lake) high mountain of a remarkable sternness&amp; simplicity, one - colored, as seen at a distance,&amp; dark-colored/ its boldest parts are first, the Bell&amp; the Scrow, two black Peaks, perfectly breast-shaped&amp; lying abreast of each other, the whole Bosom of a Brobdignag Negress,&amp; on one side of them the Lever's water-fall/ 2 - the very bold Ness called <enamex sw="w46707" long="-3.068542713" lat="54.383555" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00094" name="Yewdale Crag" conf="99992">Yewdale Crag</enamex>, its ridge line rounded/ and about 150 yards from Gateskarth's, the house close upon the Lake, at its very head, the simple, most unfantastic, <enamex sw="w46865" long="-3.068542713" lat="54.383555" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00094" name="Yewdale Crag" conf="99992">Yewdale Crag</enamex> seen through a Dip in the woody pastoral Crescent below, this Dip a very gentle curve, the under half of an ellipse/ The Houses, Gardens, fields,&amp; woodland upon this crescent Hill are all in admirable keeping, various as heart can wish, yet all sweet Brothers&amp; Sisters So various that when together you see small likeness/ so like that when separate, you might mistake one for the other-I pass by Gateskarth,&amp; go for Skelleth/ - Add <enamex sw="w47314" long="-3.07188" lat="54.35783" type="other" gazref="unlock:5826053" name="Coniston Hall" conf="2">Coniston Hall</enamex> as the first bold feature, with its four Round Chimneys, two cloathed so warmly cap a pie with ivy&amp; down on the wall far below/</s></p>
<p><s id="s100">observe from <enamex sw="w47470" long="-3.1022" lat="54.3385" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2635622" name="Torver" conf="99992">Torva</enamex> through <enamex sw="w47484" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> the force of imitation in the Gardens&amp; sweet Porches,&amp; every where clipped yews, in obelisks,&amp; fine arches/ about 2 miles from <enamex sw="w47622" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> just where <enamex sw="w47642" long="-3.023901654228874" lat="54.37750890240144" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167814" name="Hawkshead Hill" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex>&amp; <enamex sw="w47654" long="-2.977291334332336" lat="54.3599180438576" type="water" gazref="unlock:11140740" name="Esthwaite Water" conf="2.4">Esthwaite</enamex> with <enamex sw="w47669" long="-1.694261121405827" lat="54.77499735884657" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790643" name="Priest Burn" conf="1.300386261">Priest</enamex> Pot and its floating Isle with <enamex sw="w47707" long="-0.9214981485461977" lat="53.56319006165395" type="water" gazref="unlock:8785380" name="Crow Trees Moor Drain East" conf="1.288481918">Trees</enamex>, then at the farther end( nearest <enamex sw="w47747" long="-2.977291334332336" lat="54.3599180438576" type="water" gazref="unlock:11140740" name="Esthwaite Water" conf="2.4">Esthwaite</enamex>) 15 yards long/ - there there is on your left, belonging to one John Swainson, with a compleate colonnade of clipped yews-an old man with his wife-had small else to do-was a Tanner, but long given over/ has children, his they are grown up&amp; married off - some time before this I came upon the view of Wyndermere.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s101">I slept at Bratha on Sunday night-amp; did not go on to <enamex sw="w48126" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, though I had time enough, and was not over-fatigued; but though I have no objection to sleep in a lonely House, I did not like to sleep in their lonely House</s></p>
<p><s id="s102">I called the next day-went into the garden-pulled some Peas,&amp; shelled&amp; drest them,&amp; eat them for dinner with one rasher of Bacon boiled-but I did not go up stairs, nor indeed any where but the Kitchen.</s> <s id="s103">Partly I was very wet&amp; my boots very dirty -&amp; Molly had set the Pride of her Heart upon it's niceness -&amp; still more-I had small desire to go up!</s></p>
<p><s id="s104">It was very kind of you, my Darlings! to send the 5 ( which I have now sent back) but it was not very wise.</s> <s id="s105">I could have easily procured 3 or 4  from Mr Jackson/ but I gave up the Residence at <enamex sw="w48838" long="-3.582497849760178" lat="54.48833781762206" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11276282" name="St Bees" conf="2.6">St Bees</enamex>, because I began to reflect that in the present state of my finances I ought not to spend so much money.</s> <s id="s106">Thomas Ashburner's call was the occasion of my resolve not to go to <enamex sw="w49019" long="-3.582497849760178" lat="54.48833781762206" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11276282" name="St Bees" conf="2.6">St Bees</enamex>; but my own after reflections were the cause. - In the course of my Tour(&amp; I was absent 9 days) I gave away to Bairns,&amp; foot-sore Wayfarers four shillings,&amp; some odd pence;&amp; I spent nine shillings-sum total,  0" 13s 0D-but to this must be added the wear&amp; tear of my Boots, which are gone to be mended;&amp; sixpence for a great knee-patch for my Pantaloons, which will not however be worn an hour the shorter time for the said large knee-patch.</s> <s id="s107">I have now no clothes but what are patched at the elbows,&amp; knees,&amp; in the seat -&amp; I am determined to wear them out&amp; out -&amp; to have none till after Christmas -</s></p>
</text>
</document>