<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1812_a"><p><s id="s1">Advertisement.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s2">The following Poem, if it may be allowed to deserve the name, was written under circumstances, whose peculiarity may be thought to justify a communication of them.</s> <s id="s3">- - I undertook to give metrical Illustrations of the Prints with which Mr. Ackermann decorated the Poetical Magazine, a Work published by him in Monthly Numbers, for the reception of original compositions.</s> <s id="s4">Many of these Engravings were miscellaneous, and those,( which were, indeed, the far greater part of them,) whose description was submitted to such a Muse as mine, represented views of interesting objects, and beautiful Scenery, or were occasional decorations appropriate to the work.</s> <s id="s5">The designs to which this volume is so greatly indebted, I was informed would follow in a Series, and it was proposed to me to shape out a story from them.</s> <s id="s6">- - An Etching or a Drawing was accordingly sent to me every month, and I composed a certain proportion of pages in verse, in which, of course, the subject of the design was included: the rest depended upon what my imagination could furnish.</s> <s id="s7">When the first print was sent to me, I did not know what would be the subject of the second; and in this manner, in a great measure, the Artist continued designing, and I continued writing, every month for two years,' till a Work, containing near ten thousand <enamex sw="w1347" long="-0.7603098256494568" lat="51.25558432678506" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11221885" name="Montgomery Lines" conf="1.281704923">Lines</enamex> was produced: the Artist and the Writer having no personal communication with, or knowledge of each other.</s> <s id="s8">This vast collection of verses, however, appeared to advance the purpose of the Magazine in which they grew into such an unexpected accumulation.</s> <s id="s9">- - Mr. Ackermann was satisfied with my Service, and I was satisfied with the remuneration of it.</s> <s id="s10">- - I felt no parental fondness for the work though it was written at that very advanced period of Life, when we are apt to attach Importance to any little unexpected exertion of decaying strength.</s> <s id="s11">- - It would have been no more thought of by me: - - But Mr. Ackermann has his reasons for risquing a republication of it, in its present form; and I now feel more than common solicitude that it should answer his expectations.</s> <s id="s12">My own vanity has a very small share in my wishes for its success; and in the indulgence of them I can truly declare, that I am principally actuated by the part I take in the interests of a man, who, in the course of my concerns with him, has grown in my esteem and regard - - I have, therefore, given my best attention to the correction of the whole; and have endeavoured to lessen those defects which naturally arose from the irregular and undetermined mode of its composition.</s> <s id="s13">- - The Battle of the Books was an after though: and forms the Novelty of this volume.</s></p>
<p><s id="s14">Liberius si Dixero quid, si forte jocosius; hoc mihi juris, Cum venia dabis.</s> <s id="s15">- - Hor, s.</s> <s id="s16">Lib.</s> <s id="s17">i.</s> <s id="s18">Sat.</s> <s id="s19">iv.</s></p>
<p><s id="s20">I have only to add - that though on a first view of some of the prints, it may appear as if the Clerical Character was treated with Levity, I am confident in announcing a very opposite Impression from a perusal of the Work.</s></p>
<p><s id="s21">The Author.</s></p>
<p><s id="s22">Advertisement.</s> <s id="s23">To The.</s> <s id="s24">Sixth Edition.</s> <s id="s25">Another very large Impression having been exhausted by the Public Favour, a Sixth Edition appears to be required to succeed it.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s26">A. Tour, In Search Of.</s> <s id="s27">The Picturesque, By The Reverend Doctor Syntax.</s> <s id="s28">The Sixth Edition.</s> <s id="s29">Canto I.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s30">The school was done, the buseness over, When, tired of Greek and Latin lore, Good Syntax sought his easy chair, And sat in calm composure there.</s> <s id="s31">His wife was to a neighbour gone, To hear the chit-chat of the town; And left him the unfrequent power Of brooding through a quiet hour.</s> <s id="s32">Thus, while he sat, a busy train Of images besieged his brain.</s> <s id="s33">Of church-preferment he had none: Nay, all his hope of that was gone.</s> <s id="s34">He felt that he content must be With drudging in a Curacy.</s> <s id="s35">Indeed, on every Sabbath day, Through eight long miles he took his way, To preach, to grumble, and to pray; To cheer the good, to warn the sinner, And, if he got it, - - eat a dinner:</s> </p><p><s id="s36">To bury these, to christen those, And marry such fond folks as chose To change the tenor of their life, And risk the matrimonial strife.</s> <s id="s37">Thus were his weekly journeys made,' Neath summer suns and wintry shade; And all his gains, it did appear, Were only thirty pounds a year.</s> <s id="s38">Besides, the augmenting taxes press To aid expense and add distress: Mutton and beef, and bread and beer, And every thing was grown so dear; The boys were always prone to eat, Delighting less in books than meat; That, when the time of Christmas came, His earnings ceased to be the same; And now, alas, could do no more, Than keep the wolf without the door.</s> <s id="s39">Even birch, the pedant master's boast, Was so increased in worth and cost, That oft, prudentially beguiled, To save the rod, he spared the child.</s> <s id="s40">Thus, if the times refused to mend, He to his school must put an end.</s> <s id="s41">How hard his lot! how blind his fate! What shall he do to mend his state? Thus did poor Syntax ruminate.</s></p>
<p><s id="s42">When, as the vivid meteors fly, And instant light the gloomy sky, A sudden thought across him came, And told the way to wealth and fame; And, as the expanding vision grew Wider and wider to his view,</s> </p><p><s id="s43">The painted fancy did beguile His woe-worn phiz into a smile: But, while he paced the room around, Or stood immersed in thought profound, The Doctor,' midst his rumination, Was wakened by a visitation Which troubles many a poor man's life - - The visitation of his wife.</s> <s id="s44">Good Mrs. Syntax was a lady Ten years, perhaps, beyond her hey-day; But though the blooming charms had flown, That graced her youth, it still was known The love of power she never lost, As Syntax found it to his cost: For as her words were used to flow, He but replied or, Yes, or No. - - When ever enraged by some disaster, Sheed shake the boys, and cuff the master; Nay, to avenge the slightest wrong, She could employ both arms and tongue; And, if we list to country tales, She sometimes would enforce her nails.</s> <s id="s45">Her face was red, her form was fat, A round-about, and rather squat; And, when in angry humour stalking, Was like a dumpling set a-walking.</s> <s id="s46">' Twas not the custom of this spouse To suffer long a quiet house: She was among those busy wives Who hurry-scurry through their lives; And make amends for fading beauty By telling husbands of their duty.</s></p>
<p><s id="s47">' Twas at this moment, when, inspired, And by his new ambition fired, The pious man his hands upreared, That Mrs. Syntax re-appeared, Amazed she looked, and loud she shrieked, Or, rather like a pig she squeaked, To see her humble husband dare Thus quit his sober evening chair, And pace, with varying steps, about, Now in the room, and now without.</s> <s id="s48">At first, she did not find her tongue,( A thing which seldom happened long,) But soon that organ grew unquiet, To ask the cause of all this riot.</s> <s id="s49">The Doctor smiled, and thus addressed The secrets of his labering breast - -" Sit down, by love, my dearest dear, Nay, prithee do, and patient hear; Let me, for once, throughout my life, Receive this kindness from my wife; It will oblige me so: - - in troth, It will, my dear, oblige us both; For such a plan has come athwart me, Which some kind sprite from Heaven has brought me; That, if you will your councils join, To aid this golden scheme of mine, New days will come - - new times appear, And teeming plenty crown the year: We then on dainty bits shall dine, And change our home-brewed ale for wine: On summer days, to take the air, We'll put our Grizzle to a chair; While you, in silks and muslins fine, The grocer's wife shall far outshine.</s> </p><p><s id="s50">And neighbering folks be forced to own, In this fair town you give the ton."" Oh! tell me," cried the smiling dame," Tell me this golden road to fame: You charm my heart, you quite delight it." - -" - - I'll make a Tour - - and then I'll Write It.</s> <s id="s51">You well know what my pen can do, And I'll employ my pencil too: - - I'll ride and write, and sketch and print, And thus create a real mint; I'll prose it here, I'll verse it there, And picturesque it every where: I'll do what all have done before; I think I shall - - and some what more.</s> <s id="s52">At Doctor Pompous give a look; He made his fortune by a book: And if my volume dose not beat it, When I return I'll fry and eat it.</s> <s id="s53">Next week the boys will all go home.</s> <s id="s54">And I shall have a month to come.</s> <s id="s55">My clothes, my cash, my all prepare; Let Ralph looks to the grizzle mare: Though wondering folks may laugh or scoff, By this day fortnight I'll be off; And when old Time a month has run, Our buseness, Lovey, will be done.</s> <s id="s56">I will in search of fortune roam, While you enjoy yourself at home."</s></p>
<p><s id="s57">The story told, the Doctor eased Of his grand plan, and Madam pleased, No pains were spared by night or day To set him forward on his way:</s> </p><p><s id="s58">She trimmed his coat - - she mended all His various clothing, great and small; And better still, a purse was found With twenty notes, of each a poimd.</s> <s id="s59">Thus furnished, and in full condition To prosper in his expedition, At length the lingering moment came That gave the dawn of wealth and fame.</s> <s id="s60">Incurious Ralph, exact at four, Led Grizzle, saddled, to the door; And soon, with more than common state, The Doctor stood before the gate.</s> <s id="s61">Behind him was his faithful wife; - -" One more embrace, my dearest life!" Then his grey palfrey he bestrode, And gave a nod, and off he rode.</s> <s id="s62">" Good luck! good luck!" she loudly cried;'' Vale! Vale!" he replied.</s></p><p><s id="s63">Canto Ii.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s64">The farewell ceremony over, Madam went in and banged the door: No woeful tear bedewed her eye, Nor did she heave a single sigh; But soon began her daily trade, To chide the man and scold the maid; While Syntax, with his scheme besotted, Along the village gently trotted.</s> <s id="s65">The folks, on daily labour bent, Whistled and carroled as they went; But, as the Doctor passed along, Bowed down their heads, and ceased their song: He gravely nodded to the people; Then looking upwards to the steeple, He thus, in muttering tones, expressed The disappointments of his breast: - -" That thankless parent, Mother Church, Has ever left me in the lurch; And, while so many fools are seen To strut a Rector or a <enamex sw="w10090" long="-2.47619" lat="51.80857" type="other" gazref="unlock:13896283" name="Forest of Dean District" conf="0.7023050592">Dean</enamex>, Who live in ease and find good cheer On every day of every year, So small her share of true discerning, She turned her back on all my learning.</s> <s id="s66">I've in her vineyard laboured hard, And what has been my lean reward?</s> </p><p><s id="s67">I've dug the ground, while some rich Vicar Pressed the ripe grape, and drank the liquor; I fed the flock, while others eat The mutton's nice, delicious meat; I've kept the hive, and made the honey, While the drones pocketed the money.</s> <s id="s68">But now, on better things intent, On far more grateful labours bent, New prospects open to my view; So, thankless Mother Church, adieu!" Thus, having said his angry say, Syntax proceeded on his way.</s></p>
<p><s id="s69">The morning lark ascends on high, And with its music greets the sky: The blackbird whistles, and the thrush Warbles his wild notes in the bush; While every hedge and every tree Resound with vocal minstrelsy: But Syntax, wrapt in thought profound, Is deaf to each enlivening sound: Revolving many a golden scheme, And yielding to the pleasing dream, The reins hung loosely from his hand; While Grizzle, senseless of command, Unguided, paced the road along, Nor knew if it were right or wrong.</s> <s id="s70">Through the deep vale, and up the hill, By rapid stream and tinkling rill, Grizzle her thoughtful master bore, Who, counting future treasure over, And, on his weighty projects bent, Observed not whither Grizzle went.</s> </p><p><s id="s71">Thus did Fancy's soothing power Cheat him of many a fleeting hour; Nor did he know the pacing Sun Had half his daily circuit run.</s> <s id="s72">Sweet, airy sprite, that can bestow A pleasing respite to our woe, That can corroding care beguile, And make the woe-worn face to smile! But, ah! too soon the vision passes, Confounded by a pack of asses! The donkies brayed; and lo! the sound Awaked him from his thought profound; And as he stared, and looked around, He said - - or else he seemed to say - -" I find that I have lost my way.</s> <s id="s73">Oh what a wide expanse I see, Without a wood, without a tree; No one's at hand, no house is near, To tell the way, or give good cheer; For now a sign would be a treat, To tell us we might drink and eat: But sure there is not in my sight The sign of any living wight; And all around upon this common I see not either man or woman; Nor dogs to bark, nor cocks to crow, Nor sheep to bleat, nor herds to low; And if these asses did not bray, And thus some signs of life betray, I well might think that I were hurled Into some sad, unpeopled world.</s> <s id="s74">How could I come, misguided wretch! To where I cannot make a sketch?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s75">Thus, as he pondered what to do, A guide-post erose within his view; And, when the pleasing shape he spied, He pricked his steed, and thither hied; But some unheeding, senseless wight, Who to fair learning owed a spite, Had every lettered mark defaced, Which once its several pointers graced.</s> <s id="s76">The mangled post thus long had stood, An uninforming piece of wood; Like other guides, as some folks say, Who neither lead, nor point the way.</s> <s id="s77">The Sun, as hot as he was bright, Had got to his meridian height;' Twas sultry noon - - for not a breath Of cooling zephyr fanned the heath - - When Syntax cried - -"' Tis all in vain To find my way across the plain; So here my fortune I will try, And wait till some one passes by: Upon that bank awhile I'll sit, And let poor Grizzle graze a bit; But, as my time shall not be lost, I'll make a drawing of the post; And, though your flimsy taste may flout it, There's something picturesque about it:' Tis rude and rough, without a gloss, And is well covered over with moss; And I've a right - -( who dares deny it?) To place yon group of asses by it.</s> <s id="s78">Ay! this will do: and now I'm thinking, That self-same pond where Grizzle's drinking, If hither brought' twould better seem, And faith I'll turn it to a stream:</s> </p><p><s id="s79">I'll make this flat a shaggy ridge, And over the water throw a bridge: I'll do as other sketchers do - - Put any thing into the view; And any object recollect, To add a grace, and give effect.</s> <s id="s80">Thus, though from truth I haply err, The scene preserves its character.</s> <s id="s81">What man of taste my right will doubt, To put things in, or leave them out?' Tis more than right, it is a duty, If we consider landscape beauty: - - He never will as an artist shine, Who copies Nature line by line: Whoever from Nature takes a view, Must copy and improve it too.</s> <s id="s82">To heighten every work of art, Fancy should take an active part: Thus I( which few I think can boast) Have made a Landscape of a Post.</s></p>
<p><s id="s83">" So far, so good - - but no one passes, No living creature but these asses; And, should I sit and hear them bray, I were as great a beast as they: So I'll be off; - - from yonder down I may, perhaps, descry a town; Or some tall spire, among the trees, May give my way-worn spirits ease."</s></p>
<p><s id="s84">Grizzle again he soon bestrode, And waved his whip, and off he rode: But all around was dingy green, No spire arose, no town was seen.</s> </p><p><s id="s85">At length he reached a beaten road: How great a joy the sight bestowed! So on he went, in pleasant mood, And shortly gained a stately wood, Where the refreshing zephyrs played And cooled the air beneath the shade.</s> <s id="s86">Oh! what a change, how great the treat, To fanning breeze from sultry heat! But, ah! how false is human joy! When least we think it, ills annoy: For now, with fierce impetuous rush, Three ruffians issued from a bush; One Grizzle stopped, and seized the reins, While they all threat the Doctor's brains.</s> <s id="s87">Poor Syntax, trembling with affright, Resists not such <enamex sw="w15574" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="0.915490599">superior</enamex> might, But yields him to their savage pleasure, And gives his purse, with all its treasure.</s> <s id="s88">Fearing, however, the Doctor's view Might be to follow and pursue; The cunning robbers wisely counted That he, of course, should be dismounted; And still that it would safer be, If he were fastened to a tree.</s> <s id="s89">Thus to a tree they quickly bound him - - The cruel cords went round and round him; And, having of all power bereft him, They tied him fast - - and then they left him.</s></p><p><s id="s90">Canto Iii.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s91">By the road side, within the wood, In this sad state poor Syntax stood; His bosom heaved with many a sigh, And the tears stood in either eye.</s> <s id="s92">What could he do? - - he durst not bawl; The noise the robbers might recall; The villains might again surround him, And hang him up where they had bound him.</s> <s id="s93">Sure never was an hapless wight In more uncomfortable plight; Nor was this all; his pate was bare, Unsheltered by one lock of hair; For when the sturdy robbers took him, His hat and peruke both forsook him.</s> <s id="s94">The insect world were on the wing, Whose talent is to buz and sting; And soon his bare-worn head they sought, By instinct led, by nature taught; And dug their little forks within The tender texture of his skin.</s> <s id="s95">He raged and roared, but all in vain, No means he found to ease his pain.</s> <s id="s96">The cords, which to the tree had tied him, All help from either hand denied him:</s> </p><p><s id="s97">He shook his head, he writhed his face With painful look, with sad grimace, And thus he spoke his hapless case:</s></p>
<p><s id="s98">" Ah! miserable man," he cried," What perils do my course betide! In this sad melancholy state, Must I, alas! impatient wait Till some kind soul shall haply find me, And with his friendly hands unbind me; Nay, I throughout the night may stay,' Tis such an unfrequented way: Though what with hunger, thirst and fright, I never shall last throughout the night; And could I even these ills survive, The flies will eat me up alive.</s> <s id="s99">What mad ambition made me roam! Ah, wherefore did I quit my home! For there I lived, remote from harm; My meals were good, my house was warm; And, though I was not free from strife, With other ills that trouble life, Yet I had learned full well to bear The nightly scold, the daily care; And, after many a season past, I should have found repose at last: Fate would have signed my long release, And Syntax would have died in peace; Nor thus been robbed, and tied and beaten, And all alive by insects eaten."</s></p>
<p><s id="s100">But while he thus at Fate was railing, And Fortune's angry frown bewailing,</s> </p><p><s id="s101">A dog's approaching bark he hears;' Tis sweet as music to his ears, And soon a sure relief appears.</s> <s id="s102">For, though it bore that general form, Which oft at home, foretold a storm, It now appeared an angel's shape That promised him a quick escape: Nor did <enamex sw="w18339" long="-3.147244334220886" lat="39.67287635803223" type="civil" gazref="unlock:14128265" name="Castilla-La Mancha" conf="0.5919497366">La Mancha</enamex>'s valerous knight Feel greater pleasure at the sight, When, overwhelmed with love and awe, His <enamex  sw="w18444" name="Not a placename">Dulcinea</enamex> first he saw: - - For on two trotting palfreys came, And each one bore a comely dame: They started as his form they view; The horses, also, started too: The dog with insult seemed to treat him, And looked as if he longed to eat him.</s> <s id="s103">In piteous tones he humbly prayed Theyed turn aside, and give him aid; When each leaped quickly from her steed, To join in charitable deed.</s> <s id="s104">They drew their knives to cut the noose, And let the mounful prisener loose; With kindest words his fate bewail, While grateful Syntax tells his tale.</s> <s id="s105">The rustic matrons sooth his grief, Nor offer, but afford, relief; And, turning from the beaten road, Their well-lined panniers they unload; When soon upon the bank appeared A sight his fainting spirits cheered.</s> <s id="s106">They spread the fare with cheerful grace, And gave a banquet to the place:</s> </p><p><s id="s107">Most haply, too, as they untied him, He saw his hat and wig beside him: So, thus bewigged and thus behatted, Down on the grass the Doctor squatted; He then uplifted either eye, With grateful accents to the sky.</s> <s id="s108">"' Tis thus," he humbly said," we read In sacred books of heavenly deed: And thus, I find, in my distress, The manna of the wilderness:' Tis Hermit's fare; but thanks to Heaven, And those kind souls by whom' tis given."</s> <s id="s109">' Tis true that bread, and curds, and fruit, Do with the pious hermits suit; But Syntax surely was mistaken To think their meals partake of bacon; Or that those reverend men regale, As our good Doctors do - - with ale: And these kind dames, in nothing loth, Took care that he partook of both.</s></p>
<p><s id="s110">At length' twas time to bid adieu, And each their different way pursue: A kind farewell, a kiss as kind, He gave them both with heart and mind: Then off he trudged, and, as he walked, Thus to himself the Parson talked.</s> <s id="s111">"' Tis well, I think, it is no worse, For I have only lost my purse.</s> <s id="s112">With all their cruelty and pains, The rogues have got but trifling gains; Poor four and-four-pence is the measure Of all their mighty pilfered treasure;</s> </p><p><s id="s113">For haply there was no divining Ied a snug pocket in my lining: And, thanks to Spousy, every note Was well sewed up within my coat.</s> <s id="s114">But where is Grizzle? - - Never mind her; I'll have her cried, and soon shall find her."</s> <s id="s115">Thus he pursued the winding way, Big with the evils of the day: Though the good Doctor kept in view The favour of its blessings too.</s> <s id="s116">Nor had he paced it half an hour Before he saw a parish tower, And soon, with sore fatigue opprest, An inn received him as its guest: But still his mind, with anxious care, Pondered upon his wandering mare: He therefore sent the Bellman round, To try if Grizzle might be found.</s></p>
<p><s id="s117">Grizzle, ungrateful to her master, And careless of his foul disaster, Left him tied up, and took her way, In hopes to meet with com or hay; But, as that did not come to pass, She sought a meadow fiill of grass: The farmer in the meadow found her, And ordered John, his man, to pound her.</s> <s id="s118">Now John was one of those droll folk, Who oft take mischief for a joke; And thought' twould make the master stare, When he again beheld his mare,( Perhaps the gem' man might be shockt) To find her ready cropt and dockt: At all events, he played his fun: No sooner was it said than done.</s> </p><p><s id="s119">But Grizzle was a patient beast, And minded nought, if she could feast: Like many others, prone to think The best of life was meat and drink; Who feel to-day nor care nor sorrow, If they are sure to feast to-morrow.</s> <s id="s120">Thus Grizzle, as she paced around The purlieu of the barren pound, In hungry mood might seem to neigh - -" If I had water, corn, and hay, I should not thus my fate bewail, Nor mourn the loss of ears or tail."</s></p>
<p><s id="s121">In the mean time, securely housed, The Doctor boozed it, and caroused, The Hostess spread her fairest cheer, Her best beef-steak, her strongest beer; And soothed him with her winning chat, Of" Pray eat this - - and now take that.</s> <s id="s122">Your Reverence, after all your fright, Wants meat and drink, to set you right."</s> <s id="s123">His Reverence praised the golden rule, Nor did he let his victuals cool: And, having drunk his liquor out, He took a turn to look about; - - When to the folks about the door He told the dismal story over.</s> <s id="s124">The country-people on him gazed, And heard his perils all amazed: How the thieves twined the cords around him; How to a tree the villains bound him: What angels came to his relief, To loose his bonds, and soothe his grief: His loss of cash, and what was worse, His saddle, saddle-bags, and horse.</s> </p><p><s id="s125">Thus as their rude attention hung Upon the wonders of his tongue, Lo! Grizzle's altered form appears, With half its tail, and half its ears!" Is there no law?" the Doctor cries: - -" Plenty," a lawyer straight replies:" Employ me, and those thieves shall swing On gallows-tree, in hempen-string: And, for the rogue, the law shall flea him, Who maimed your horse, as now you see him."</s> <s id="s126">" No," quoth the Don," your pardon pray; I've had enough of thieves to-day: I've lost four shillings and a groat, But you would strip me of my coat: And ears and tail wo n't fatten you, You'll want the head and carcase too."</s> <s id="s127">He chuckled as he made the stroke, And all around enjoyed the joke: But still it was a sorry sight To see the beast in such a plight: Yet what could angry Syntax do?' Twas all in vain to fret and stew: - - His well-stuffed bags, with all their hoard Of sketching-tools, were safe restored; The saddle, too, which he had sought For small reward was quickly brought; He therefore thought it far more sage To stop his threats and check his rage; So to the ostler's faithful care He gave his mutilated mare; And while poor Grizzle, free from danger, Cropped the full rack and cleaned the manger, Syntax, to ease his aching head, Smoked out his pipe, and went to bed.</s></p><p><s id="s128">Canto Iv.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s129">Bless'D be the man, said he, of yore, Who Quixote's lance and target bore! Blessed be the man, who first taught sleep Throughout our wearied frames to creep: And kindly gave to human woes The oblivious mantle of repose! Hail! balmy power! that canst repair The constant waste of human care; To the sad heart afford relief, And give a respite to its grief! Canst calm, through night's composing hours The threatening storm that daily lowers: On the rude flint the wretched cheer, And to a smile transform the tear!</s></p>
<p><s id="s130">Thus wrapt in slumber, Syntax lay - - Forgot the troubles of the day: So sound his sleep, so sweet his rest, By no disturbing dreams distrest; That, all at ease, he lay entranced, Till the fair morn was far advanced.</s> <s id="s131">At length, the hostess thought it wrong He should be left to sleep so long; So bid the maid to let him know That breakfast was prepared below.</s> </p><p><s id="s132">Betty then oped the chamber door, And, tripping onwards' cross the floor.</s> <s id="s133">Undrew the curtains, one by one; When, in a most ear-piercing tone, Such as would grace the <enamex sw="w25265" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.762992967">London</enamex> cries, She told him it was time to rise.</s> <s id="s134">The noise his peaceful slumbers broke; - - He gave a snort or two - - and' woke.</s></p>
<p><s id="s135">Now, as the Doctor turned his head, Betty was court' sying by the bed: - -" What brought you here, fair maid, I pray?" - -" To tell you, Sir, how wears the day; And that it is my special care To get your worship's morning fare.</s> <s id="s136">The kettle boils, and I can boast No small renown for making toast.</s> <s id="s137">There's coffee, Sir, and tea, and meat, And surely you must want to eat! For ten long hours have passed away Since down upon this bed you lay."</s> <s id="s138">The Doctor rubbed his opening eyes, Then stretched his arms, and' gan to rise: But Betty still demurely stands, To hear him utter his commands.</s> <s id="s139">" Be gone," he cried," get something nice, And I'll be with you in a trice."</s></p>
<p><s id="s140">Behold him then, renewed by rest, His chin well shaved, his peruke dressed, Conning with solemn air the news, His welcome breakfast to amuse; - - And when the well-fed meal was over, Grizzle was ordered to the door:</s></p>
<p><s id="s141">Betty was also told to say, The mighty sum there was to pay: Betty, obedient to his will, Her court' sey makes, and gives the bill.</s> <s id="s142">Down the long page he cast his eye, Then shook his head, and heaved a sigh," What! am I doomed, wherever I go, In all I meet to find a foe? Wherever I wander, to be cheated, To be bamboozled and ill-treated!" Thus, as he read each item over, The hostess oped the parlour door; When Syntax rose in solemn state, And thus began the fierce debate: - -</s></p>
<p> <s id="s143">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s144">" Good woman; here, your bill retake, And, prithee, some abatement make; I could not such demands afford, Were I a bishop or a lord: And though I hold myself as good As any of my brotherhood, However, by bounteous Fortune crowned, In wealth and honours they abound; - - It is not in my power to pay Such long-drawn bills as well as they.</s> <s id="s145">The paper fills me with affright; - - I surely do not read it right: For, at the bottom here, I see The enormous total - - one pound, three!"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s146">Hostess.</s></p>
<p><s id="s147">" The charges all are fairly made, If you will eat, I must be paid.</s> <s id="s148">My bills have never found reproaches From Lords and <enamex sw="w27393" long="-1.77831968367031" lat="54.08503022708322" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11189841" name="Ladies Riggs" conf="1.32037322">Ladies</enamex>, in their coaches.</s> </p><p><s id="s149">This house, that's called the Royal Crown, Is the first Inn throughout the town: The best of gentry, every day, Become my guests, and freely pay: Besides, I took you in at night, Half Dead, with hunger and affiight, Just' scaped from robbers,"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s150">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s151">- - - - - -" That's most true, And now I'm to be robbed by you."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s152">Hostess.</s></p>
<p><s id="s153">" Sir, you mistake; and did not I Disdain rude words, Ied say - - you lie.</s> <s id="s154">I took you in last-night, I say," - -</s></p>
<p> <s id="s155">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s156">"' Tis true; - - and if this bill I pay You'll take me in again to-day."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s157">Hostess.</s></p>
<p><s id="s158">" I gave you all my choicest cheer, The best of meat, the best of beer; And then you snored yourself to rest In the best bed - - I say the best.</s> <s id="s159">You've had such tea as few can boast, With a whole loaf turned into toast."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s160">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s161">" And for your beef, and beer and tea, You kindly charge me - - one pound three!"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s162">Hostess.</s></p>
<p><s id="s163">"' Tis cheap as dirt - - for well I know How things with country Curates go: And I profess that I am loth To deal unkindly with the cloth:</s> </p><p><s id="s164">Nay, oft and oft, as I'm a sinner, I've given hungry Clerks a dinner."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s165">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s166">" And there's a proverb, as they say, That for the Clerks the Parsons pay; Which you, I trow, can well fulfil, Whenever you make a Parson's bill.</s> <s id="s167">Why, one pound three, the truth I speak, Would keep my household for a week.</s> <s id="s168">Dear Mrs. Syntax, how sheed vapour Were she to read this curious paper!"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s169">Hostess.</s></p>
<p><s id="s170">" If that's your living, on my life, You starve your servants and your wife."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s171">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s172">" I wish my wife were here to meet you, In your own fashion she would greet you: With looks as fierce, and voice as shrill, Sheed make you, mistress, change your bill."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s173">Hostess.</s></p>
<p><s id="s174">" Think you, besides, there's nought to pay For all your horse's corn and hay? And ointments too to cure the ail Of her cropped ears, and mangled tail?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s175">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s176">" I wish the wight would bring the shears Which docked that tail and cropped those ears, And just exert the self-same skill To crop and dock your monstrous bill.</s> <s id="s177">But, I'm in haste to get away, Though one pound three I will not pay: So, if you'll take one - half the amount, We'll quickly settle the account.</s> </p><p><s id="s178">There is your money, do you see? And let us part in Charity."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s179">Hostess.</s></p>
<p><s id="s180">" Well, as a charitable deed, I'll even consent - - so, mount your steed, And on your journey straight proceed: But well you know, wherever you roam, That Charity begins at home."</s></p><p><s id="s181">Canto V.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s182">The Doctor smiled - - the bill was paid, The hostess left him to the maid, When Betty stood in humble guise, With expectation in her eyes, That he was, surely, so good-hearted, Heed give her something ere they parted.</s> <s id="s183">Now, Nature, in her wanton freaks, Had given Betty rosy cheeks; And caused her raven locks to break In native ringlets on her neck.</s> <s id="s184">The roving bee might wish to sip The sweetness of her pouting lip; So red, so tempting to the view,' Twas what the Doctor longed to do.</s> <s id="s185">" Youere a nice girl," he smiling said;" Am I?" replied the simpering maid.</s> <s id="s186">" I swear you are, and if youere willing To give a kiss, I'll give a shilling."" - - If' tis the same thing, Sir, to you, Make the gift two - fold, and take two."</s> <s id="s187">He grimly grinned, with inward pleasure, And soon he seized the purchased treasure.</s> <s id="s188">" Your lips, my dear, are sweet as honey: So one smack more - - and there's your money."</s></p>
<p><s id="s189">This charming ceremony over, The Parson strutted to the door; Where his poor wounded mare appears In cruel state of tail and ears.</s> <s id="s190">The neighbours all impatient wait To see him issue from the gate; For country-town or village-green, Has seldom such a figure seen.</s> <s id="s191">Labour stood still to see him pass, While every lad and every lass <enamex sw="w31045" long="3.61667" lat="49.56667" type="other" gazref="unlock:14209752" name="Laon" conf="0.3217282967">Ran</enamex> forward to enjoy the feast, To jeer the Don, and mourn the beast.</s> <s id="s192">But one and all aloud declare' Twas a fit sight for country fair, Far better than a dancing bear.</s></p>
<p><s id="s193">At length, escaped from all the noise Of women, men, and girls and boys, In the recesses of a lane He thus gave utterance to his pain: - -" It seems to be my luckless case, At every point, in every place, To meet with trouble and disgrace.</s> <s id="s194">But yesterday I left my home, In search of fancied wealth to roam: And nought, I think, but ills betide me; Sure some foul spirit runs beside me: Some blasting demon from the east, A deadly foe to man and beast, That loves to riot in disaster, And plague alike both horse and master.</s> <s id="s195">Grizzle, who full five years, and more, A trumpeter in triumph bore;</s> </p><p><s id="s196">Who had in many a battle been, And many a bloody conflict seen; Who, having' scaped with scarce a scar,' Mid all the angry threats of war; When her best days are almost past, Feels these ignoble wounds at last.</s> <s id="s197">Ah! what can thy fond master do! He's cut and slashed as well as you: But, though no more with housing gay, And prancing step, you take your way; Or, with your stately rider, lead The armed troop to warlike deed; While you've a leg, you never shall cease To bear the minister of peace.</s> <s id="s198">Long have you borne him, nor ever grumbled, Nor ever started, kicked or stumbled."</s></p>
<p><s id="s199">But mildest natures sometimes err From the strict rules of character: The timerous bird defends its young, And beasts will kick when they are stung.</s> <s id="s200">' Twas burning hot, and hosts of flies, With venomed stings, around them rise: They seized on Grizzle's wounded part, Who straight began to snort and start: Kicked up behind, reared up before, And played a dozen antics more.</s> <s id="s201">The Doctor coaxed, but all in vain, She snorted, kicked, and reared again:" Alas!" said Syntax," could I pop Just now, upon a blacksmith's shop, Where cooling unguents would avail To save poor Grizzle's ears and tail!" When scarce had he his wishes spoke, Than he beheld a cloud of smoke,</s> </p><p><s id="s202">That from a forge appeared to rise And for a moment veiled the skies; While the rude hammers, to his ear, Proclaimed the aid he wished was near.</s> <s id="s203">By the way-side the cottage rose, Around it many a willow grows, Where Syntax, in a tone of grief, Shewed Grizzle's wounds, and prayed relief.</s> <s id="s204">The sooty Galen soon appeared, And with fair hopes the Doctor cheered.</s> <s id="s205">" Trust me, good Sir, I've got a plaster, Will cure the beast of her disaster; And while the dressing I prepare, With all becoming skill and care, You in that arbour may regale With a cool pipe and jug of ale: I've long a two - fold trade professed, And med' cine sell for man and beast."</s> <s id="s206">Syntax now sought the cooling shade, While Galen's dame the banquet made: She well knew how her guests to please, And added meat, and bread, and cheese: Besides, she told the village-tale - - Who came to drink their home-brewed ale; How that the laughter-loving Vicar Would sometimes walk to taste their liquor; That their gay landlord was renowned, For hunting fox, with horn and hound; That heed a daughter passing fair, Who was his honour's only heir; But she was proud, nor could a' Squire Approach to tell his amerous fire; A Lord alone, as it was said, She woued receive into her bed.</s> </p><p><s id="s207">Throughout the village, every name Became a subject for the dame; And thus she played her chattering part, Till Syntax thought it time to part.</s></p>
<p><s id="s208">And now poor Grizzle, re-appears, With plastered tail, and plastered ears, Which thus cased up, might well defy The sharpest sting of gnat or fly.</s> <s id="s209">The Doctor having had his fill, Without a word discharged his bill: But, as it was the close of day, He trotted briskly on his way; And, ever the Sun withdrew his light, An Inn received him for the night.</s> <s id="s210">His frame fatigued, his mind oppressed, He tiffed his punch, and went to rest.</s> <s id="s211">The morning came, when he arose In spirits from his calm repose; And, while the maid prepared the tea, He looked around the room to see What story did the walls disclose, Of human joys, of human woes.</s> <s id="s212">The window quickly caught his eye, On whose clear panes he could descry The motley works of many a Muse: There was enough to pick and choose; And," faith," said he," I'll strive to hook Some of these lines into my book; For here there are both grave and witty, And some, I see, are rather pretty."</s> <s id="s213">From a small pocket in his coat He drew his tablets, - - and he wrote Whatever the pregnant panes possessed; And these choice lays among the rest.</s></p>
<p><s id="s214">" If my breast were made of glass, And you could see what there doth pass, Kitty, my ever charming fair! Youed see your own sweet image there."</s></p>
<p><s id="s215">" I once came here a free-booting, And on this fine manor went shooting; And if the' Squire this truth denies, This glass shall tell the' Squire - - he lies."</s></p>
<p><s id="s216">" Dolly's as fat as any sow, And, if I'm not mistaken, Dolly is well disposed, I trow, To trim her husband's bacon."</s></p>
<p><s id="s217">" Jenny, while now your name I hear, No transient glow my bosom heats: And when I meet your eye, my dear, My fluttering heart no longer beats.</s> <s id="s218">I dream, but I no longer find Your form still present to my view; I wake, but now my vacant mind No longer waking dreams of you.</s> <s id="s219">I can find maids, in every rout, With smiles as false and forms as fine: But you must hunt the world throughout, To find a heart as true as mine."</s></p>
<p><s id="s220">" I hither came down From fair <enamex sw="w36420" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.762992967">London</enamex> town With Lucy so mild and so kind; But Lucy grew cool, And called me a fool, So I started and left her behind."</s></p>
<p><s id="s221">But as he copied qmte delighted, All that the Muse had thus indited, A hungry dog, and prone to steal, <enamex sw="w36644" long="3.61667" lat="49.56667" type="other" gazref="unlock:14209752" name="Laon" conf="0.3217282967">Ran</enamex> off with half his breakfast meal; While Dolly, entering with a kettle, Was followed by a man of mettle, Who swore heed have the promised kiss; And, as he seized the melting bliss, From the hot ill-poised kettle's spout, The boiling stream came pouring out, And drove the Doctor from the Muse, By quickly filling both his shoes.</s></p><p><s id="s222">Canto Vi.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s223">What various evils man await, In this sad, sublunary state! No sooner is he cheered by joy, Than sorrows come, and pains annoy; And scarce his lips are oped to bless The transient gleam of happiness, Than some dark cloud obscures the sky, And grief's sad moisture fills his eye.</s></p>
<p><s id="s224">Thus, while the Doctor smiling stole From the clear glass each witty scroll, He felt, to interrupt the treat, The scalding torment in his feet: And, thus awakened from his trance, Began to skip, and jump, and dance.</s> <s id="s225">" Take off my shoes," he raving cried, And let my gaiters be untied."</s> <s id="s226">When Dolly with her nimble hand, Instant obeyed the loud command; And, as he lolled upon the chair, His feet and ancles soon were bare.</s> <s id="s227">Away the impatient damsel run, To cure the mischief she had done;</s> </p><p><s id="s228">And quick returned with liquid store, To rub his feet and ancles over: Nor was the tender office vain, That soon assuaged the burning pain.</s> <s id="s229">A tear was seen on Dolly's cheek; Who sighed as if her heart would break.</s> <s id="s230">" Be not, my girl, with care oppress' t; I'm now," says Syntax," quite at rest; My anger's vanished with the pain, No more, my dear, shall I complain, Since to get rid of my disaster, So fair a maid presents the plaster."</s> <s id="s231">Thus did he Dolly's care beguile, And turned her tears into a smile: But, while she cooled the raging part, She somehow warmed the Doctor's heart; And, as she rubbed the ointment in, He pinched her cheeks and chucked her chin; And, when she had redressed his shanks, He with a kiss bestowed his thanks: While gentle Dolly, nothing loth, Consenting smiled, and took them both.</s> <s id="s232">" I think," said she," youed better stay, Nor travel further on to-day:" - - And though she said it with a smile, His steady purpose to beguile, The Doctor closed the kind debate, By ordering Grizzle to the gate.</s></p>
<p><s id="s233">Now, undisturbed, he took his way, And travelled till the close of day; When, to delight his wearied eyes, Before him Oxford's towers arise.</s> <s id="s234">" O, Alma Mater!" Syntax cried," My present boast, my early pride;</s> </p><p><s id="s235">To whose protecting care I owe All I've forgot, and all I know: Deign from your nursling to receive The homage that his heart can give.</s> <s id="s236">Hail! sacred, ever-honoured shades Where oft I wooed the immortal maids; Where strolling oft, at break of day, My feet have brushed the dews away! By Isis and by Cherwell's stream, How oft I wove the classic dream, Or sought the Cloisters dim, to meet Pale Science in her lone retreat! The sight of you, again inspires My bosom with its former fires: I feel again the genial glow That makes me half forget the woe And all my aching heart could tell, Since last I bid these scenes farewell."</s></p>
<p><s id="s237">Thus Syntax moved in sober pace, Beset with academic grace; While Grizzle bore him up the town, And at the Mitre set him down.</s> <s id="s238">The night was passed in sound repose, And as the clock struck nine, he erose.</s> <s id="s239">The barber now applies his art, To shave him clean, and make him smart: From him he learned that Dicky Bend, His early academic friend, As a reward for all his knowledge, Was now the Provost of his College; And fame declared that he had clear At least twelve hundred pounds a year.</s> <s id="s240">" O ho!" says Syntax," if that's true, I cannot surely better do</s> </p><p><s id="s241">Than further progress to delay, And with Friend Dicky pass a day."</s> <s id="s242">Away he hied, and soon he found him.</s> <s id="s243">With all his many comforts round him.</s> <s id="s244">The Provost hailed the happy meeting, And, after kind and mutual greeting, To make inquiries he began: And thus the conversation ran.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s245">Provost.</s></p>
<p><s id="s246">" Good Doctor Syntax, I rejoice Once more to hear your well-known voice; To dine with us I hope you'll stay, And share a college-feast to-day.</s> <s id="s247">Full many a year is gone and past Since we beheld each other last: Fortune has kindly dealt with me.</s> <s id="s248">As you, my friend, may clearly see; And pray how has she dealt with thee?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s249">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s250">" Alas! alas! I've played the fool; I took a wife, and keep a school; And, while on dainties you are fed, I scarce get butter to my bread."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s251">Provost.</s></p>
<p><s id="s252">" For my part, I have never married, And grieve to hear your plans miscarried: I hope, then, my old worthy friend, Your visit here your fate will mend.</s> <s id="s253">My services you may command; - - I offer them with heart and hand: And while you think it right to stay, You'll make this house your home, I pray."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s254">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s255">" I'm going further, on a scheme, Which you may think an idle dream; At the famed Lakes to take a look, And of my Journey make a Book.''</s></p>
<p> <s id="s256">Provost.</s></p>
<p><s id="s257">" I know full well that you have store Of modem as of classic lore; And, surely, with your weight of learning, And all your critical discerning, You might produce a work of name, To fill your purse and give you fame.</s> <s id="s258">How oft have we together sought Whatever the ancient sages taught!"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s259">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s260">" I now perceive that all your knowledge Is pent, my friend, within your college? Learning's become a very bore - - That Fashion long since has been over.</s> <s id="s261">A Bookseller may keep his carriage, And ask ten thousand pounds in marriage; May have his mansion in a square, And build a house for country air; And yet' tis odds the fellow knows If <enamex  sw="w42069" name="Not a placename">Horace</enamex> wrote in verse or prose.</s> <s id="s262">Could Doctor G - - - - in chariot ride, And take each day his wine beside, If he did not contrive to cook, Each year, his Tour into a book; A flippant, flashy, flowery style, A lazy morning to beguile; With, every other leaf, a print Of some fine view in aqua-tint?</s> </p><p><s id="s263">Such is the book I mean to make, And I've no doubt the work will take: For though your wisdom may decry it, The simple folk will surely buy it.</s> <s id="s264">I will allow it is but trash, But then it furnishes the cash."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s265">Provost.</s></p>
<p><s id="s266">" Why things are not the same, I fear, As when we both were scholars here; But still, I doubt not your success, And wish you every happiness; Myself, and my whole college tribe, Depend upon it will subscribe."</s></p>
<p><s id="s267">At length the bell began to call To dinner, in the college-hall; Nor did the guests delay to meet, Lured by the bounty of the treat.</s> <s id="s268">The formal salutations over, Each drew his chair and seized his cover; The Provost, in collegiate pride, Placed Doctor Syntax by his side; And soon they heard the hurrying feet Of those that bore the smoaking meat.</s></p>
<p><s id="s269">Behold the dishes due appear - - Fish in the van, beef in the rear; But he who the procession led, By some false step or awkward tread, Or cursed by some malignant power, Fell headlong on the marble floor! Ah, heedless wight! ah, hapless dish! Ah! all the luxury of fish,</s> </p><p><s id="s270">Thus in a moment spoiled and wasted; Ah! never, never to be tasted! But one false step begets another, So they all tumbled one over t' other: And now the pavement was bestrewed With roast and boiled, and fried and stewed.</s> <s id="s271">The waiters squalled, their backs bespattered With scalding sauce; the dishes clattered In various discord; while the brawl Re Echoed through the astonished hall.</s> <s id="s272">" Well," said a Don," as I'm a sinner, We must go elsewhere for a dinner.""' Tis no such thing," the Head replied," You all shall soon be satisfied: We are but ten: and sure there's plenty; I ordered full enough for twenty.</s> <s id="s273">I see, my friends, the haunch unspoiled, With chickens roast, and turkey boiled; The ven' son pasty is secure, The marrow puddings safe and sure; With ham, and many good things more, And tarts, and custards, full a score.</s> <s id="s274">Sure, here's enough to cut and carve; To Day, I think, we shall not starve: But still I'll make the boobies pay For the good things they've thrown away."</s> <s id="s275">Thus every eye was quickly cheered With all the plenty that appeared; They eat, they drank, they smoked, they talked, And round the college-garden walked: But the time came( for time will fly) When Syntax was to say - - good bye.</s> <s id="s276">His tongue could scarce his feeling tell, Could scarce pronounce the word, farewell!</s> </p><p><s id="s277">The Provost too, whose generous heart In those same feelings bore a part, Told him, when he should want a friend, To write, or come, to Dicky Bend</s></p>
<p><s id="s278">Next morning, at an early hour, Syntax proceeded on his tour; And, as he sauntered on his way, The scene of many a youthful day, He thought' twould give his book an air, If Oxford were well painted there; And, as he curious looked around, He saw a spot of rising ground, From whence the turrets of the city Would make a picture very pretty; Where <enamex  sw="w45242" name="Not a placename">Radcliff</enamex>' s dome would intervene, And Magd' len tower crown the scene.</s> <s id="s279">So Grizzle to a hedge he tied, And onward he impatient hied; But, as he sought to choose a part Where he might best display his art, A wicked bull no sooner viewed him, Than loud he roared, and straight pursued him.</s> <s id="s280">The Doctor finding danger near, Flew swiftly on the wings of Fear, And nimbly clambered up a tree, That gave him full security; But as he ran to save his bacon, By hat and wig he was forsaken; His sketch-book too he left behind, A prey to the unlucky wind; While Grizzle, startled by the rout, Broke from the hedge, and pranced about.</s> <s id="s281">Syntax, still trembling with affright, Clung to the tree with all his might;</s> </p><p><s id="s282">Then called for help - - and help was near, For dogs, and men, and boys appear; So that his foe was forced to yield, And leave him master of the field.</s> <s id="s283">No more of roaring bulls afraid, He left the tree's protecting shade; And as he paced the meadow round, His hat, his wig, his book he found.</s> <s id="s284">" Come, my old girl," the Doctor said; The faithful steed the call obeyed, So Grizzle once more he bestrode, Nor looked behind - - but off he rode.</s></p><p><s id="s285">Canto Vii.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s286">Fix'D in cogitation deep, Adown the hill and up the steep, Along the moor and through the wood, Syntax his pensive way pursued: And now his thoughts began to roam To the good woman left at home; How she employed the passing day When her fond mate was far away: For they possessed, with all their pother, A sneaking kindness for each other: Proud of her husband's stock of learning, His classic skill and deep discerning, No tongue she suffered to dethrone His fond importance - - but her own.</s> <s id="s287">Besides, she was a very bee In bustle and in industry; And though a pointed sting she bore, That sometimes made the Doctor sore, She helped to make the household thrive, And brought home honey to the hive.</s> <s id="s288">He too had not forgot her charms, When first he took her to his arms; For, if Report relates the truth, She was a beauty in her youth: - -</s> </p><p><s id="s289">The charming Dolly was well known To be the toast of all the town; And, though full many a year had flown Since this good dame was twenty - one, She still retained the air and mien Of the nice girl she once had been.</s> <s id="s290">For these, and other charms beside, She was indeed the Doctor's pride; Nay, he would sometimes on her gaze With the fond looks of former days; And, whatsoever she did or said, He kept his silence and obeyed.</s> <s id="s291">Besides his mind he thus consoled;"' Tis classical to be a scold; For, as the ancient tomes record, Zantippe's tongue was like a sword: She was about my Dolly's age, And was the wife too of a sage.</s> <s id="s292">Thus Socrates, in days of yore, The self-same persecution bore: Nor shall I blush to share the fate Of one so good - - of one so great."</s></p>
<p><s id="s293">' Twas now five days since they had parted, And he was ever tender-hearted: Whenever he heard the wretched sigh, He felt a Christian sympathy; For though he played the demi-god Among his boys, with rule and rod; What! though he spoke in pompous phrase, And kept the vulgar in amaze; Though self-important he would stride Along <enamex sw="w48342" long="-2.550537094982595" lat="51.15293732249635" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11294325" name="Street on the Fosse" conf="1.272393948">the street</enamex> with priestly pride;</s> </p><p><s id="s294">Though his strange figure would provoke The passing smile, the passing joke; Among the high, or with the low, Syntax had never made a foe; And, though the jest of all he knew, Yet, while they laughed, they loved him too: No wonder then, so far from home, His head would shake, the sigh would come.</s> <s id="s295">- - Thus he went gently on his way, Till the sun marked declining day.</s></p>
<p><s id="s296">But Thought as well as Grief is dry, And, lo! a friendly cot was nigh, Whose sign, high dangling in the air, Invites the trav' ller to repair, Where he in comfort may regale With cooling pipe and foaming ale.</s> <s id="s297">The Doctor gave the loud command, And sees the Host beside him stand; Then quits his steed with usual state, And passes through the wicket-gate; The Hostess opes the willing door, And then recounts the humble store Which her poor cottage could afford, To place upon the frugal board.</s> <s id="s298">The home-spun napkin soon was laid, The table all its ware displayed; The well-broiled rasher then appeared.</s> <s id="s299">And with fresh eggs his stomach cheered; The crusty pie, with apples stored, Was placed in order on the board; And liquor, that was brewed at home, Among the rest was seen to foam.</s> </p><p><s id="s300">The Doctor drank - - the Doctor eat, Well pleased to find so fair a treat; Then to his pipe he kindly took, And, with a condescending look, Called on the Hostess to relate What was the village name, and state; And to whose office it was given To teach them all the ways to Heaven</s></p>
<p> <s id="s301">Hostess.</s></p>
<p><s id="s302">The land belongs to' Squire Bounty, No better man lives in the county: I wish the Rector were the same, One Doctor Squeez' em is his name; But we never see him - - more's the shame! And while in wealth he cuts and carves, The worthy Curate prays and starves.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s303">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s304">I truly wish that he were here, To take a pipe, and share my beer; I know what' tis, as well as he, To serve a man I never see.</s></p>
<p><s id="s305">Just as he spoke, the Curate came: - -" This, this is he!" exclaimed the dame.</s> <s id="s306">Syntax his brother Parson greeted, And begged him to be quickly seated;" Come, take a pipe, and taste the liquor,' Tis good enough for any Vicar."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s307">Curate.</s></p>
<p><s id="s308">Alas! Sir, I'm no vicar; - - I, Bound to an humble Curacy, With all my care can scarce contrive To keep my family alive.</s> </p><p><s id="s309">While the fat Rector can afford To eat and drink like any Lord; But know, Sir, I'm a man of letters, And never speak evil of my betters.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s310">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s311">That's good; - - but, when we suffer pain,' Tis Nature's office to complain; And when the strong oppress the weak, Justice, though blind, will always speak.</s> <s id="s312">Tell me, have you explained your case.</s> <s id="s313">With due humility and grace? The great and wealthy must be flattered, They love with praise to be bespattered: Indeed, I cannot see the harm, If thus you can their favour charm; If by fine phrases you can bend The pride of Power to be your friend.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s314">Curate.</s></p>
<p><s id="s315">I wrote, I'm sure, in humblest style, And praised his goodness all the while: I begged, as things had grown so dear, Heed raise my pay ten pounds a year: And, as I now had children five, The finest little bairns alive; While their poor, fond and faithful mother, Would soon present me with another: And, as the living brought him, clear, At least a thousand pounds a year, Heed grant the favour I implore, Nor let me starve upon threescore.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s316">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s317">Now I should like, without delay; To hear what this rich man could say;</s> </p><p><s id="s318">For I can well perceive, my friend, That you did not obtain your end.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s319">Curate.</s></p>
<p><s id="s320">The postman soon a letter brought, Which cost me sixpence and a groat; Nor can your friendly heart suggest The rudeness which the page expressed.</s> <s id="s321">" Such suits as yours may well miscarry, For beggars should not dare to marry; At least, for I will not deceive you, I never, never will relieve you; And, if you trouble me, be sure You shall be ousted from the Cure."</s> <s id="s322">But I shall now, good Sir, refrain, Because I know' twould give you pain, From telling all that, in his spite, The arch old scoundrel chose to write; For know, Sir, I'm a man of letters, And never will abuse my betters.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s323">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s324">Zounds! - -' tis enough to make one swear, Nor can I such a monster bear: But, think, my friend, on that great day Of strict account, when he must pay For all his cruelty and lies - - Then he shall sink, and you will rise."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s325">Curate.</s></p>
<p><s id="s326">The terms, I own, are not quite civil, But he's the offspring of the devil; And, when the day of life is past, He'll with his father dwell at last;</s> </p><p><s id="s327">But know, Sir, I'm a man of letters, And never wish evil to my betters.</s></p>
<p><s id="s328">' Twas thus they talked, and drank their ale, Till the dim shades of eve prevail; When Syntax settled each demand.</s> <s id="s329">And, while he held the Curate's hand, Bid him be stout, and not despair: - -" The poor are God's peculiar care: Youere not the only one, my friend, Who has with evil to contend: Resign yourself to what is given: Be good, and leave the rest to Heaven."</s> <s id="s330">Syntax, we've said, was tender hearted, - - He dropped a tear, and then departed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s331">The evening lowered: - - a drizzly rain Had spread a mist over all the plain; Besides, the home-brewed beer began To prey upon the inward man: And Syntax, muddled, did not know Or where he was, or where to go.</s></p>
<p><s id="s332">An active horseman by him trotted, And Syntax was not so besotted But he could hiccup out" My friend, Do tell me if this way will tend To bring me to some place of rest?"" Yes,"' twas replied - -" the very best Of all our inns, within a mile.</s> <s id="s333">Will soon your weariness beguile."</s> <s id="s334">Who should this be but' Squire Bounty, So much beloved throughout the county; And he resolved by way of jest, To have the Parson for his guest;</s> </p><p><s id="s335">So on he galloped, to prepare His people for the friendly snare.</s> <s id="s336">The Doctor came in tipsy state: The' Squire received him at the gate, And to a parlour led him straight; Then placed him in an easy chair, And asked to know his pleasure there.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s337">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s338">Landlord, I'm sadly splashed with mire, And chilled with rain, so light a fire; And tell the Ostler to take care Of that good beast, my Grizzle mare; And what your larder can afford, Pray place it quickly on the board.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s339">' Squire.</s></p>
<p><s id="s340">We've butcher's meat, of every kind; But, if that is not to your mind, There's poultry, Sir, and if you please, Our cook excels in fricassees.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s341">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s342">Tell me, my honest friend, I pray, What kind of fowl or fish are they? Besides, my very civil Host, I wish to know what they will cost; For a poor Parson ca n't afford To live on dainties like a Lord.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s343">' Squire.</s></p>
<p><s id="s344">The Clergy, Sir, when here they stay, Are never, never asked to pay; I love the Church, and, for its sake, I never make bills or reckenings take: Proud if its ministers receive The little that I have to give.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s345">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s346">Why then, my friend, youere never dull; Your inn, I trow, is always full: - -' Tis a good rule, must be confest, But, though I blink, I see a jest.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s347">' Squire.</s></p>
<p><s id="s348">No, Sir; you see the cloth is laid, And not a farthing to be paid.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s349">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s350">I find my head's not very clear; My eyes see double too, I fear; For all these things can never be Prepared for such a guest as me: A banquet, it must be allowed, Of which Olympus might be proud.</s></p>
<p><s id="s351">Thus Syntax eat and drank his fill, Regardless of the morrow's bill; He rang the bell, and called the waiters, To take his shoes off, and his gaiters.</s> <s id="s352">" Go tell the maid to shew the bed, Where I may lay my aching head; Here, take my wig, and bring a cap, My eye-lids languish for a nap: No court' sying, pray; I want no fawning, For I shall break my jaws with yawning."</s> <s id="s353">Now Kitty, to adorn his crown, Brought him a night-cap of her own; And, having put it on, she bound it With a pink ribbon round and round it.</s> <s id="s354">In this fine guise was Syntax led Up the best Stairs, and put to bed.</s> <s id="s355">Though mirth prevailed the house throughout, Though it was all one revel rout,</s> </p><p><s id="s356">He heard it not, nor did he know The merriment he caused below; For, with fatigue and wine oppressed, He grunted, groaned, and went to rest.</s> <s id="s357">But when the sun in Thetis lap, Had taken out his usual nap, - - Syntax awoke; and, looking eround, The sight his senses did confound.</s> <s id="s358">He saw that he had laid his head Within a fine-wrought silken bed: A gaudy carpet graced the floor, And gilded mouldings decked the door, Nor did the mirror fail to shew His own sweet form from top to toe.</s> <s id="s359">" If I," said he," remember right, I was most lordly drunk last night: And, as the Tinker in the play Was taken, when dead drunk he lay, And made a Lord for half a day; I think that some one has made free To play the self-same trick with me; But I'll contrive to be possest Of this same secret when I'm drest: To find it out - - I'll ring the bell; The chamber-maid the truth may tell."</s> <s id="s360">She soon appeared, and court' sying low: Requested his commands to know.</s> <s id="s361">- -" When and how did I come here? You'll be so good to say my dear."" - - You came last night, not very late, About the time the clock struck eight; And I have heard the servants say, They thought that you had lost your way."</s> </p><p><s id="s362">" - - Inform me, also, how you call This noble inn?" - -' Tis Welcome Hall."" And pray who have you in the house?"" We've' Squire Bounty and his spouse; With Lady and Sir William Hearty, And, if you choose, you'll join the party, Indeed, I'm ordered to request That you will be their morning guest."</s></p>
<p><s id="s363">To question more he did not stay, But bade the damsel shew the way.</s> <s id="s364">O!' twas a very pleasant meeting: The Landlord gave a hearty greeting, And placed the Doctor in a chair, Between two ladies, young and fair.</s> <s id="s365">Syntax, well-pleased, began to prate, And all his history to relate; While mirth and laughter loud prevail, As he let forth the curious tale.</s> <s id="s366">At length the' Squire explained the joke; When thus the Doctor quaintly spoke: - -</s></p>
<p><s id="s367">" I beg, Sir, no excuse you'll make, Your merriment I kindly take; And only wish the gods would give Such jesting every day I live."</s></p>
<p><s id="s368">The ladies pressed his longer stay, But Syntax said - - he must away; So Grizzle soon her master bore, Some new adventure to explore.</s></p><p><s id="s369">Canto Viii.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s370">" In every way, in every sense, Man is the care of Providence; And whensoever he goeth wrong, The errors to himself belong: Nor do we always judge aright Of Fortune's favours, or her spite.</s> <s id="s371">How oft with pleasure we pursue Some glittering phantom in our view; Not rightly seen or understood, We chase it as a real good: At length the air-born vision flies And each fond expectation dies! Sometimes the clouds appear to lower, And threat Misfortune's direful hour: We tremble at the approaching blast; Each hope is fled - - we look aghast; When lo! the darkness disappears, The glowing sun all Nature cheers: The drooping heart again acquires Its former joys, its former fires.</s> <s id="s372">Last night I wandered over the plain, Through unknown ways and beating rain, Nor thought' twould be my lot to fall On such an inn as Welcome Hall;</s> </p><p><s id="s373">Indeed with truth I cannot say, When there I came I lost my way, For all was good, and nought to pay."</s></p>
<p><s id="s374">Thus Syntax, with reflection fraught, Soliloquized the moral thought; While Grizzle, all alive and gay, Ambled along the ready way.</s> <s id="s375">Last night she found it no disaster To share the fortune of her master; She,' mong the finest hunters stood, And shared with them the choicest food: In a fine roomy stable placed, With every well-trimmed clothing graced, Poor Grizzle was as fair a joke To all the merry stable-folk As the good Doctor's self had been, To the kind gentry of the inn.</s></p>
<p><s id="s376">Enrapt by Contemplation's power, Syntax forgot the fleeting hour; Till, looking round, he saw the sun Had past his bright meridian run.</s> <s id="s377">A shepherd-boy he now espyed, Strolling along the highway side; And on his wandering flock intent, The stripling whistled as he went.</s> <s id="s378">" My honest lad, perhaps you know What distance I shall have to go, Before my eager eyes may greet Some place where I may drink and eat."</s></p>
<p><s id="s379">" Continue, Master, over the Down, And soon you'll reach the neighbering town:</s> </p><p><s id="s380">In less, I think, than half an hour, You'll pass by yonder lofty tower: Keep onward by the church-yard wall, And soon you'll see an house of call: The sign's a Dragon - - there you'll find Eating and drinking to your mind."</s> <s id="s381">Across the down the Doctor went, And towards the Church his way he bent.</s> <s id="s382">" Thus," Syntax said," when man is hurled Upwards and downwards in the world; When some strong impulse makes him stray From Virtue's path to <enamex sw="w60681" long="-2.995963732845728" lat="54.74590404084094" type="water" gazref="unlock:8786581" name="Folly Beck" conf="2.155375048">Folly</enamex>'s way, The church, - - Religion's holy seat, Will guide to peace his wandering feet! But, hark! the death-bell's solemn toll Tells the departure of a soul; The Sexton, too, I see prepares The place where end all human cares: And, lo, a crowd of tombs appear: I may find something curious here; - - For oft poetic flowers are found To flourish in sepulchral ground.</s> <s id="s383">I'll just walk in to take a look, And pick up matter for my book: The living, some wise man has said, Delight in reading of the dead.</s> <s id="s384">What golden gains my book would boast, If I could meet a chatty ghost, Who would some news communicate Of its unknown and present state: Some pallid figure in a shroud, Or sitting on a murky cloud; Or kicking up a new-made grave, And screaming forth some horrid stave;</s> </p><p><s id="s385">Or bursting from the hollow tomb, To tell of bloody deeds to come: Or adverse skeletons embattling, With ghastly grins, and bones a-rattling; Something to make the misses stare, And force upright their curly hair; To cause their pretty forms to shake, And make them doubt if theyere awake; And thus to tonish folks present The Picturesque of Sentiment.</s> <s id="s386">But' tis, I fear, some hours too soon - - Ghosts slumber all the afternoon: I'll ask the Sexton, if, at night, I may perchance pick up a sprite."</s></p>
<p><s id="s387">The Doctor in canonic state, Now oped at once the church-yard gate; While Grizzle too thought fit to pass, Who knew the taste of church-yard grass.</s> <s id="s388">" Sir," cried the Sexton," let me say That you must take your mare away, Or else, believe me, I am bound To lead her quickly to the pound."</s></p>
<p><s id="s389">" You do mistake my honest friend - -' Tis a foul wrong that you intend; A Parson's mare will claim a right In a church-yard to take a bite; And, as I'm come to meditate Among these signs of human fate, I beg you will not make a riot, But let the poor beast feed in quiet."</s> <s id="s390">No more the conscious Sexton said, But urged his labours for the dead;</s> </p><p><s id="s391">While Syntax culled, with critic care, What the sad muse had written there.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s392">Epitaphs.</s></p>
<p><s id="s393">Here lies poor Thomas and his wife, Who led a pretty jarring life; But all is ended, do you see? He holds his tongue, and so does she.</s></p>
<p><s id="s394">If drugs and physic could but save Us mortals from the dreary grave,' Tis known that I took full enough, Of the Apothecary's stuff, To have prolonged life's busy feast To a full century at least; But, spite of all the Doctor's skill, Of daily draught and nightly pill, Reader, as sure as youere alive, I was sent here at twenty - five.</s></p>
<p><s id="s395">Within this tomb a lover lies, Who fell an early sacrifice To Dolly's unrelenting eyes.</s> <s id="s396">For Dolly's charms poor Damon burned - - Disdain the cruel maid returned: But, as she danced in May Day pride, Dolly fell down, and Dolly died, And now she lays by Damon's side.</s> <s id="s397">' Be not hard-hearted then, ye fair! Of Dolly's hapless fate beware! For sure youed better go to bed, To one alive, than one who's dead.</s></p>
<p><s id="s398">Beneath the sod the soldier sleeps, Whom cruel War refused to spare: Beside his grave the maiden weeps, And Glory plants the laurel there.</s> <s id="s399">Honour is the warrior's meed, Or spared to live, or doomed to die; Whether' tis his lot to bleed, Or join the shout of Victory; Alike the laurel to the truly brave; That binds the brow, or consecrates the grave.</s></p>
<p><s id="s400">Beneath this stone her ashes rest, Whose memory fills my aching breast: She sleeps unconscious of the tear That tells the tale of sorrow here: But still the hope allays my pain That we may live and love again: Love with a pure seraphic fire, That never, never, shall expire.</s></p>
<p><s id="s401">Syntax the Sexton now addressed, As on his spade he leaned to rest.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s402">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s403">" We both, my friend, pursue one trade; I for the living, you the dead.</s> <s id="s404">For whom that grave do you prepare, With such keen haste, and cheerful air?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s405">Sexton.</s></p>
<p><s id="s406">" And please yourReverence, Lawyer Thrust, Thank Heaven, will moulder here to dust: Never before did I take measure Of any grave with half the pleasure:</s> </p><p><s id="s407">And when within this hole he's laid, I'll ram the earth down with my spade: I'll take good care he shall not rise, Till summoned to the last assize; And, when he sues for Heaven's grace, I would not wish to take his place.</s> <s id="s408">He once, on cruel deed intent, Seized on my goods for want of rent; Nay, I declare, as I'm a sinner, He took away the childrens' dinner: For, as they sat around the table, Eating as fast as they were able, He seized the dishes, great and small, The childrens' bread, and milk and all! The urchins cried, the mother prayed, I begged his rigour might be stayed Till I could on our Parson call, Who would engage to pay it all; But he disdained a Parson's word, And mocked the suit which I preferred.</s> <s id="s409">He knew a better way to thrive; To pay two pounds by taking five.</s> <s id="s410">Bursting with rage, I knocked him down, And broke the cruel rascal's crown; For which in county-gaol I lay, Half Starving, many a bitter day.</s> <s id="s411">But our good Parson brought relief, And kindly soothed a mother's grief: He, while in prison I remained, My little family sustained; And, when I was from durance free, Made me his Sexton, as you see.</s> <s id="s412">But Doctor Worthy, he is gone; - - You'll read his virtues on the stone</s> </p><p><s id="s413">That's placed aloft upon the wall, Where you may see the ivy crawl.</s> <s id="s414">The good man's ashes rest below; - - He's gone where all the righteous go.</s> <s id="s415">I dug his grave with many a moan, And almost wished it were my own.</s> <s id="s416">I daily view the earthy bed, Where Death has laid his reverend head; And, when I see a weed appear, I pluck it up, and shed a tear.</s> <s id="s417">The parish grieved, for not an eye In all its large extent was dry, Save one: - - but such a kindly grace Never decked the Lawyer's iron face.</s> <s id="s418">The aged wept a friend long known, The young a parent's loss bemoan: While we, alas! shall long deplore The bounteous patron of the poor."</s></p>
<p><s id="s419">The Doctor heard, with tearful eye, The Sexton's grateful eulogy: Then sought the stone with gentle tread As fearing to disturb the dead, And thus, in measured tones, he read:</s></p>
<p><s id="s420">" For fifty hears the Pastor trod The way commanded by his God; For fifty years his flock he fed With that divine celestial bread Which nourishes the better part, And fortifies man's failing heart.</s> <s id="s421">His wide, his hospitable door, Was ever open to the poor;</s> </p><p><s id="s422">While he was sought, for counsel sage, By eyery rank and every age.</s> <s id="s423">That counsel sage he always gave, To warn, to strengthen, and to save; He sought the sheep that went astray, And pointed out the better way; - - But while he with his smiles approved The virtue he so dearly loved, He did not spare the harsher part, To probe the ulcer in the heart: He sternly gave the wholesome pain That brought it back to health again.</s> <s id="s424">Thus, the commands of Heaven his guide, He lived, - - and then in peace he died."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s425">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s426">" Pray tell me, friend, who now succeeds This Pastor, famed for virtuous deeds?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s427">Sexton.</s></p>
<p><s id="s428">" A very worthy, pious man, Who does us all the good he can; But he, good Sir, has got a wife."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s429">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s430">" Who may perhaps disturb his life; A tongue sometimes engenders strife."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s431">Sexton.</s></p>
<p><s id="s432">" No: - - she's a worthy woman too; - - But then they've children not a few; I think it is the will of Heaven That they are blessed with six or seven; And then you will agree with me, That home's the scene of charity."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s433">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s434">"' Tis true; - - nor can your Parson preach A sounder doctrine than you teach.</s> <s id="s435">And now, good Sexton, let me ask, While you perform your mortal task, As day and night you frequent tread The dreary mansions of the dead, If you, in very truth, can boast, That you have ever seen a ghost?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s436">Sexton.</s></p>
<p><s id="s437">" Your Reverence, no; - - Though some folks say That such things have been seen as they.</s> <s id="s438">Old women talk, in idle chat, Of ghosts and goblins, and all that; While, round the glimmering fire at night, They fill their hearers with affright.</s> <s id="s439">' Tis said that Doctor Worthy walks, And up and down the church-yard stalks; That often, when the moon shines bright, His form appears all clad in white: But to his soul it is not given To walk on earth - - for that's in Heaven.</s> <s id="s440">I, at all hours, have crossed this place, And never beheld a spirit's face.</s> <s id="s441">Once, I remember, late at night, I something saw, both large and white, Which made me stop, and made me stare, - - But' twas the Parson's grizzle mare.</s> <s id="s442">Such things as these, I do believe, The foolish people oft deceive; And then the parish gossips talk, How witches dance, and spectres walk."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s443">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s444">" Your reasoning I much commend; So fare you well, my honest friend.</s> <s id="s445">If we act right we need not dread Either the living or the dead: The spirit that disturbs our rest Is a bad conscience in our breast; With that a man is doubly curst:"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s446">Sexton.</s></p>
<p><s id="s447">" That spirit haunted Lawyer Thrust.''</s></p>
<p> <s id="s448">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s449">" His race is run, his work is over - - The wicked man can sin no more: He's gone where justice will be done To all who live beneath the sun: And, though he wronged you when alive, Let not your vengeance thus survive: Forgive him, now he's laid so low - - Nor trample on a fallen foe.</s> <s id="s450">Once more, farewel l! But ere we part, There's something that will cheer your heart."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s451">Sexton.</s></p>
<p><s id="s452">" Your Reverence,' twill be some time yet Ere I forgive; - - but to forget - - No, no, for though I may forgive, I ca n't forget him while I live.</s> <s id="s453">For your good gift, kind Heaven I bless, And wish you health and happiness: I thank my God, each coming day, For what he gives and takes away; And now I thank Him, good and just, That he has taken Lawyer Thrust."</s></p>
<p><s id="s454">Syntax along the village passed, And to the Dragon came at last; Where, as the shepherd-boy had said, There seemed to be a busy trade: And, seated in an easy chair, He found that all he wished was there.</s></p><p><s id="s455">Canto Ix.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s456">Along the varying road of Life, In calm content, in toil or strife; At morn or noon, by night or day, As time conducts him on his way.</s> <s id="s457">How oft doth man, by Care oppressed, Find in an Inn a place of rest? Whether intent on worldly views, He, in deep thought, his way pursues; Whether by airy Pleasure led, Or by Hope's fond delusions fed, He bids adieu to home, and strays Through unknown paths and distant ways; Wherever his fancy bids him roam, In every Inn he finds a home.</s> <s id="s458">Should Fortune change her favering wind, Though former friends should prove unkind, Will not an Inn his cares beguile, Where on each face he sees a smile? When cold winds blow, and tempests lour, And the rain pours in angry shower, The dripping trav' ller looks around, To see what shelter may be found; Then on he drives, through thick and thin, To the warm shelter of an Inn.</s> <s id="s459">Whoever would turn their wandering feet, Assured the kindest smiles to meet;</s> </p><p><s id="s460">Whoever would go, and not depart But with kind wishes from the heart, O let them quit the world's loud din, And seek the comforts of an Inn: And as the Doric Shenstone sung, With plaintive music on his tongue - -" Whoever has travelled Life's dull round, Wherever his changeful tour has been, Will sigh to think how oft he found His warmest welcome at an inn."</s></p>
<p><s id="s461">' Twas at an Inn, in calm repose, Heedless of human joys or woes, That Syntax passed a quiet night In pleasing dreams and slumbers light: But in the morn the thunder roared, The clouds their streaming torrents poured: The angry winds impetuous blew, The rattling casement open flew.</s> <s id="s462">Scared at the noise, he reared his head; Then, starting quickly from the bed," Is it," he cried," the day of doom?" As he bestrode the trembling room.</s> <s id="s463">The houses' tops with water streamed, The village-street a river seemed: While, at the tempest all amazed, The rustics from their windows gazed.</s> <s id="s464">" I'm not," he said," disposed to fear, But faith I will not loiter here; I'll change the scene; I'll soon retire From flaming flash to kitchen fire: And, while rude Nature's threats prevail, I'll lose the storm in toast and ale."</s> <s id="s465">Half Dressed he made a quick retreat, And in the kitchen took his seat,</s> </p><p><s id="s466">Where an old woman told the Host, What by the lightning she had lost; How a blue flash her sow had struck, Had killed a cock, and lamed a duck.</s> <s id="s467">With open mouth another came, To tell a rick was in a flame; And then declared that on the spire He saw the weathercock on fire: Nay, that so loud the winds were singing, Theyed set the peal of bells a-ringing.</s> <s id="s468">A dripping tailor entered next, And preached upon the self-same text: He swore, that sitting on his board, While the wind blew and thunder roared, A kind of fiery flame came pop, And bounced, and ran about his shop; Now here, now there, so quick and nimble, It singed his finger through his thimble; That all about his needles ran, If there was any truth in man; While buttons, at least half a score, Were driven through the kitchen door.</s> <s id="s469">The Sexton, with important mien, Gave his opinion on the scene: And, to the Doctor drawing near, Thus gently whispered in his ear:" The Devil himself his cell has burst, To fly away with Lawyer Thrust."</s></p>
<p><s id="s470">Now, having with due patience heard The story which each wight preferred, Syntax was to the parlour shown, Where he might breakfast all alone.</s> <s id="s471">" I see," said he," I here must stay And at the Dragon pass the day:</s> </p><p><s id="s472">And this same Dragon, on my life, Just hints that I have got a wife; Nor can I pass the morning better Than to indite this wife a letter."</s> <s id="s473">He paused - - and sighed ever he began, When thus the fond epistle ran.</s></p>
<p><s id="s474">" My dearest Doll, - - Full many a day From you and home I've been away; But, though we thus are doomed to part, Youere ever present in my heart: Whenever my prayers to Heaven arise, At morn or evening sacrifice, - - Whenever for Heaven's care they sue, I ask it for my Dolly too.</s> <s id="s475">My Journey, like Life's common road, Has had its evils and its good: But I've no reason to complain, When pleasure has outweighed the pain.</s> <s id="s476">With flattering Fortune in my view, Glad I the toilsome way pursue; For I've no fear to make a book, In which the world will like to look: Nor do I doubt' twill prove a mine For my own comfort, and for thine! But should all fail, I've found a friend In my old school-mate, Dicky Bend; Who, kind and wealthy, will repay, If Hope should cheat me on my way, My every loss I may sustain, And ease ill-fortune of its pain: - - He has engaged to glad our home, With promise of much good to come.</s> <s id="s477">Particulars of what I've seen, What I have done - - where I have been,</s> </p><p><s id="s478">I shall reserve for my return, When as the crackling faggots burn, I will in all domestic glory, Smoke out my pipe, and tell my story: But, be assured, I'm free from danger; - - To the world's tricks I'm not a stranger: Whatever risks I'm forced to run, I shall take care of number one; While you, at home, will keep in view, The self-same care of number two.</s> <s id="s479">To my kind neighbours I commend The wishes of their distant friend: Within ten days, perhaps a week, I shall <enamex sw="w75399" long="" lat="" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:9659" name="" conf="99991">York</enamex>'s famous city seek.</s> <s id="s480">Where at the post, I hope to find A line from Dolly, ever kind: And, if you will the pleasure crown, Tell me the prattle of our town; Of all that's passing, and has past, Since your dear Hub beheld it last: And know the truth which I impart, The offspring of my honest heart, That wheresoever I'm doomed to roam, I still shall find that home is home: That true to Love and nuptial vows, I shall remain your loving spouse.</s> <s id="s481">Such are the tender truths I tell: Conjux carissima - - farewell!"</s></p>
<p><s id="s482">Thus he his kindest thoughts revealed - - But scarce had he the letter sealed, When straight appeared the trembling Host, Looking as pale as any ghost: - -" A man's just come into the town, Who says the castle's tumbled down:</s> </p><p><s id="s483">And that with one tremendous blow, The lightning's force has laid it low."" What castle, friend?" the Doctor cryed, - -" The castle by the river side: A famous place, where as folks say, Some great King lived in former day: But this fine building long has been A sad and ruinated scene, Where owls, and bats, and starlings dwell, - - And where, alas, as people tell, At the dark hour when midnight reigns, Ghosts walk, all armed, and rattle chains."</s> <s id="s484">" Peace, peace," said Syntax," peace, my friend, Nor to such tales attention lend.</s> <s id="s485">- - But this new thought I must pursue: A castle, and a ruin too; I'll hasten there, - - and take a view.</s></p>
<p><s id="s486">The storm was past, and many a ray Of <enamex  sw="w76832" name="Not a placename">Phoebus</enamex> now revived the day, When Grizzle to the door was brought, And this famed spot the Doctor sought.</s> <s id="s487">Upon a rock the castle stood, Three sides environed by a flood, Where confluent streams uniting lave, The craggy rift with foaming wave.</s> <s id="s488">Around the moss-clad walls he walked, Then through the inner chambers stalked; And thus exclaimed, with look profound, The echoes giving back the sound.</s> <s id="s489">" Let me expatiate here awhile: I think this antiquated pile Is, doubtless, in the Saxon style.</s> <s id="s490">This was a noble, spacious hall, But why the chapel made so small?</s> </p><p><s id="s491">I fear our fathers took more care Of festive hall than house of prayer.</s> <s id="s492">I find these Barons fierce and bold, Who proudly lived in days of old, To prayer preferred a sumptuous treat, Nor went to pray when they could eat.</s> <s id="s493">Here all along the banners hung, And here the welcome minstrels sung: The walls with glittering arms bedight, Displayed an animating sight: Beneath that arch-way, once a gate, With helmed crest, in warlike state The bands marched forth, nor feared the toil, Of bloody war that gave the spoil.</s> <s id="s494">But now, alas! no more remains Than will reward the painter's pains: The palace of the feudal victor Now serves for nought but for a picture.</s> <s id="s495">Plenty of water here I see, But what's a view without a tree? There's something grand in yonder tower, But not a shrub to make a bower; However, I'll try to take the view, As well as my best art can do."</s></p>
<p><s id="s496">A heap of stones the Doctor found, Which loosely lay upon the ground, To form a seat, where he might trace The antique beauty of the place: But, while his eye observed the line That was to limit the design The stones gave way, and sad to tell, Down from the bank he headlong fell.</s> </p><p><s id="s497">The slush collected for an age, Received the venerable sage; For, at the time, the ebbing flood Was just retreating from the mud: So, after floundering about, Syntax contrived to waddle out, Half stunned, amazed, and covered over As seldom wight had been before.</s> <s id="s498">- - Overwhelmed with mud, and stink, and grief, He saw no house to give relief; So thus, amid the village din, He ran the gauntlet to the inn.</s> <s id="s499">An angler threw his hook so pat, He caught at once the Doctor's hat: A bathing boy, who naked stood, Dashed boldly in the eddying flood, And, swimming onward like a grig, Soon overtook the Doctor's wig.</s> <s id="s500">Grizzle had traced the barren spot, Where not a blade of grass was got: And, finding nought to tempt her stay, She to the Dragon took her way.</s> <s id="s501">The ostler cried," here's some disaster - - The mare's returned without her master!" But soon he came, amid the noise Of men and women, girls and boys: Glad in the inn to find retreat From the rude insult of <enamex sw="w79509" long="-2.550537094982595" lat="51.15293732249635" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11294325" name="Street on the Fosse" conf="1.272393948">the street</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s502">Undressed, well-washed, and put to bed, With mind disturbed, and aching head, In vain poor Syntax sought repose, But lay and counted all his woes.</s> </p><p><s id="s503">The friendly Host, with anxious care, Now hastes the posset to prepare: - - The cordial draught he kindly gives; Which Syntax with a smile receives: Then seeks, in sleep, a pause from sorrow, In hopes of better fate to-morrow.</s></p><p><s id="s504">Canto X.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s505">Poor mortal man, in every state, What troubles and what ills await! His transient joy is chased by sorrow, - - To Day he's blest; - - a wretch to-morrow.</s> <s id="s506">When in the world he first appears, He hails the light with cries and tears: A school-boy next, he fears the nod Of pedant power, and feels the rod: When to an active stripling grown, The Passions seize him as their own; Now lead him here, now drive him there, The alternate sport of Joy and Care; Allure him with their glittering treasure, Or give the brimming cup of pleasure; While one eludes his eager haste, The other palls upon the taste.</s> <s id="s507">The pointed darts from Cupid's quiver Wound his warm heart, and pierce his liver; While charmed by fair Belinda's eyes, He dines on groans, and sups on sighs.</s> <s id="s508">If from this gay and giddy round He should escape both safe and sound, Perhaps, if all things else miscarry, He takes it in his head to marry;</s> </p><p><s id="s509">And in this lottery of life, If he should draw a scolding wife, With a few children, eight or ten( For such things happen now and then), Poor hapless man! he knows not where To look around without a care.</s> <s id="s510">Ambition, in its airy flight, May tempt him to some giddy height; But, ere the point he can attain, He tumbles, never to rise again.</s> <s id="s511">Pale Averice may his heart possess, The bane of human happiness, Which never feels for other's woe, Which never does a smile bestow; A wretched, meagre, griping elf, A foe to all, and to himself.</s> <s id="s512">Then comes Disease, with baneful train, And all the family of Pain; Till Death appears in awful state, And calls him to the realms of Fate.</s> <s id="s513">How oft is Virtue seen to feel The woeful turn of Fortune's wheel, While she with golden stores awaits The wicked in their very gates.</s> <s id="s514">But Virtue still the value knows Of honest deeds, and can repose Upon the flint her naked head; While Vice lays restless on the bed Of softest down, and courts in vain The opiate to relieve its pain.</s></p>
<p><s id="s515">It was not Vice that ever could keep Poor Syntax from refreshing sleep;</s> </p><p><s id="s516">For no foul thought, no wicked art, In his pure life ever bore a part: Some ailment dire his slumbers broke, And, ere the sun arose, he woke: When such a tremor over him passed; He thought that hour would prove his last.</s> <s id="s517">His limbs were all besieged by pain; He now grew hot, then cold again: His tongue was parched, his lips were dry, And, heaving the unbidden sigh, He rang the bell, and called for aid, And groaned so loud, the affrighted maid Spread the alarm throughout the house; - - When straight the landlord and his spouse Made all despatch to do their best, And ease the sufferings of their guest.</s> <s id="s518">" Have you a doctor?"</s> <s id="s519">Syntax said;" If not, I shortly shall be dead."" - - O yes; a very famous man; He'll cure you, Sir, if physic can.</s> <s id="s520">I'll fetch him quick; - - a man renowned For his great skill the country round."</s></p>
<p><s id="s521">The Landlord soon the Doctor brought, Whose words were grave, whose looks were thought: By the bed-side he took his stand, And felt the patient's burning hand; Then, with a scientific face, He told the symptoms of the case: - -" His frame's assailed with feverish heats; His pulse with rapid movement beats; - - And now, I think,' twould do him good, Were he to lose a little blood:</s> </p><p><s id="s522">Some other useful matters too, To ease his pain, I have in view.</s> <s id="s523">I'll just step home, and, in a trice, Will bring the fruits of my advice; In the mean time, his thirst assuage With tea that's made of balm, or sage."</s> <s id="s524">He soon returned - - his skill applied - - From the vein flowed the crimson tide: And, as the folk behind him stand, He thus declared his stern command:" At nine these powders let him take; At ten this draught, - - the phial shake; And you'll remember, at eleven, Three of these pills must then be given: This course you'll carefully pursue, And give, at twelve, the bolus too: If he should wander, in a crack Clap this broad blister on his back; And, after he has had the blister, Within an hour give the clyster.</s> <s id="s525">I must be gone; at three or four I shall return with something more.</s> <s id="s526">''</s></p>
<p><s id="s527">Now Syntax and his feverish state Became the subject of debate.</s> <s id="s528">The mistress said she was afraid No medicine would give him aid; For she had heard the screech-owl scream, And had besides a horrid dream.</s> <s id="s529">Last night the candle burned so blue; While from the fire a coffin flew; And, as she sleepless lay in bed, She heard a death-watch at her head.</s> </p><p><s id="s530">The maid and ostler too declared That noises strange they both had heard.</s> <s id="s531">" Aye," cried the Sexton," these protend To the sick man a speedy end; And, when that I have drunk my liquor, I'll even go straight and fetch the Vicar."</s></p>
<p><s id="s532">The Vicar came, a worthy man, And, like a good Samaritan, Approached in haste the stranger's bed, Where Syntax lay with aching head; And, without any fuss or pother, He offered to his reverend brother His purse, his house, and all the care Which a kind heart could give him there.</s></p>
<p><s id="s533">Says Syntax, in a languid voice," You make my very soul rejoice; For, if within this house I stay, My flesh will soon be turned to clay, For the good Doctor means to pop Into my stomach, all his shop.</s> <s id="s534">I think, dear Sir, that I could eat, And physic's but a nauseous treat: - - If all that stuff's to be endured, I shall be killed in being cured."" O," said the Vicar," never fear; We'll leave the apparatus here.</s> <s id="s535">Come, quit your bed - - I pray you, come, - - My arm shall bear you to my home, Where I, and my dear mate will find Med' cine more suited to your mind.</s> <s id="s536">"</s></p>
<p><s id="s537">Syntax now rose, but feeble stood, From want of meat, and loss of blood;</s> </p><p><s id="s538">But still he ventured to repair To the good Vicar's house and care; And found at dinner pretty picking, In pudding boiled and roasted chicken.</s> <s id="s539">Again,' twas honest Grizzle's fate To take her way through church-yard gate; And, undisturbed, once more to riot In the green feast of church-yard diet.</s> <s id="s540">The Vicar was at Oxford bred, And had much learning in his head; But, what was far the better part, He had much goodness in his heart.</s> <s id="s541">The Vicar also had a wife, The pride and pleasure of his life; A loving, kind, and friendly creature, As blest in virtue as in feature, Who, without blisters, drugs, or pills, Her patient cured of all his ills.</s> <s id="s542">Three days he stayed, a welcome guest, And eat and drank of what was best: When, on the fourth, in health renewed, His anxious journey he pursued.</s></p>
<p><s id="s543">In two days more before his eyes The stately towers of <enamex sw="w86300" long="" lat="" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:9659" name="" conf="99991">York</enamex> arise.</s> <s id="s544">" But what," said he," can all this mean? What is yon crowded busy scene? Ten thousand souls, I do maintain, Are scattered over yonder plain."" Ay, more than that," a man replied, - - Who trotted briskly by his side," And if you choose, I'll be your guide: For sure you will not pass this way, And miss the pleasure of the day.</s> </p><p><s id="s545">These are the races, to whose sport Nobles and gentry all resort."</s> <s id="s546">Thought Syntax I'll just take a look;' Twill give a subject to my book.</s> <s id="s547">So on they went; - - the highway friend His services did oft commend.</s> <s id="s548">" I will attend you to the course, And tell the name of every horse; But first we'll go and take a whet, And then I'll teach you how to bet: I'll name the horse that's doomed to win - - We'll take the knowing fellows in."</s> <s id="s549">Just as he spoke, the sports began; The jockies whipped, the horses ran, - - And, when the coursers reached the post, The man screamed out - -" Your horse has lost: I've had the luck - - I've won the day, And you have twenty pounds to pay."</s> <s id="s550">Syntax looked wild - - the man said" Zounds! You know you betted twenty pounds; So pay them down, or you'll fare worse, For I will flog you off the course."</s> <s id="s551">The Doctor raved, and disavowed The bold assertion to the crowd.</s> <s id="s552">What would have been his hapless fate, In this most unexpected state, May well be guessed.</s> <s id="s553">But, lo! a friend Fortune was kind enough to send.</s> <s id="s554">An honest' Squire, who smoked the trick, Appeared well armed with oaken stick, And, placing many a sturdy blow Upon the shoulders of the foe," It is with all my soul I beat This vile, this most notorious cheat,"</s> </p><p><s id="s555">The' Squire exclaimed;" and you, good folk, Who sometimes love a pleasant joke, As I am partly tired with thumping, Should treat the scoundrel with a pumping."</s> <s id="s556">The crowd, with their commission pleased, Rudely the trembling Black Leg seized, Who, to their justice forced to yield, Soon ran off dripping from the field.</s></p>
<p><s id="s557">Syntax his simple story told, - - The' Squire, as kind as he was bold, His full protection now affords, And cheered him both with wine and words; - -" I love the Clergy from my heart, And always take a Parson's part.</s> <s id="s558">My father, Doctor, wore the gown - - A better man was never known: But an old uncle, a poor elf, Who, to save riches, starved himself, By his last will bequeathed me clear At least two thousand pounds a year, And saved me all the pains at college, To pour over books, and aim at knowledge.</s> <s id="s559">Thus free from care, I live at ease - - Go where I will, do what I please - - Pursue my sports, enjoy my pleasure, Nor envy Lords their splendid treasure.</s> <s id="s560">I have a house at <enamex sw="w88909" long="" lat="" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:9659" name="" conf="99991">York</enamex> beside, Where you shall go and straight reside; And every kindness shall be shown, Both for my dad's sake, and your own: For know, good Sir, I'm never loth To mark my friendship for the Cloth.</s>  <s id="s561">Hearty' s my name, and you shall find A welcome, Doctor, to your mind:</s> </p><p><s id="s562">And I've a wife, so blithe and gay, Who never says yes when I say nay.'' Syntax observed that was a blessing A man might boast of in possessing.</s></p>
<p><s id="s563">At length arrived, a lady fair Received them with a winning air.</s> <s id="s564">" Ah," said the' Squire," I always come, My dearest girl, with pleasure home: You see a reverend Doctor here, So give him of your choicest cheer:" Yes," she replied," O yes, my dear."" Nor fail all kindness to bestow:"" O no, my dear," she said," O no." Thus happy Syntax joined the party Of Madam and of' Squire Hearty.</s></p><p><s id="s565">Canto Xi.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s566">In this sad, variegated life, Evil and good, in daily strife, Contend, we find, which shall be master: Now Fortune smiles - - then sad Disaster Assumes, in turn, its frowning power, And gives to man his chequered hour.</s> <s id="s567">With chequered hours good Syntax thought, And well he might, his journey fraught: But still he hoped, when all was past, That he should comfort find at last.</s> <s id="s568">Thus, with the' Squire's kindness blest No fears alarm his tranquil breast; He eats, and drinks, and goes to rest: And, when the welcome morrow came, The' Squire and Madam were the same.</s> <s id="s569">Just as the Minster Clock struck nine, Coffee and tea, and fowl and chine, Appeared in all their due array, To give the breakfast of the day.</s> <s id="s570">The' Squire then the talk began, And thus the conversation ran.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s571">' Squire Hearty.</s></p>
<p><s id="s572">" Doctor, you truly may believe The pleasure which I now receive In seeing you as you sit there, On what was once my father's chair.</s> </p><p><s id="s573">I pray you, think this house your home, - - Ay, though it were three months to come.</s> <s id="s574">Here you will find yourself at ease - - May read or write - - just as you please.</s> <s id="s575">At nine we breakfast, as you see, - - Dinner is always here at three; At six my wife will give you tea."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s576">Mrs. Hearty.</s></p>
<p><s id="s577">" And should you find the evening long, I'll play a tune or sing a song."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s578">' Squire Hearty.</s></p>
<p><s id="s579">" Besides, you'll range the country round, - - Some curious things may there be found: Your genius too may chance to trace, Within this celebrated place, Some ancient building worth a look, That may, perhaps, enrich your book.</s> <s id="s580">I'm a true Briton, as you'll see: I love good cheer, and liberty; And what I love myself, I'll give To others, while I'm doomed to live.</s> <s id="s581">This morning I intend to go To see the military show.</s> <s id="s582">The light dragoons, now quartered here, Will all in grand review appear: They are a regiment of renown, And some great General is come down To see them all, in bright array, Act the fierce battle of the day.</s> <s id="s583">If you should like such sights as these; If warlike feats your fancy please, We'll to the Common take a ride, And I myself will be your guide:</s> </p><p><s id="s584">So, if you please, within an hour Our nags shall be before the door."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s585">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s586">" I will be ready to attend The summons of my worthy friend.</s> <s id="s587">The laurelled Hero's my delight, With plumed crest and helmet bright: Even when a boy, at early age, I read in Homer's lofty page How the stout Greeks, in times of yore, Brought havoc to the Phrygian shore: I revelled in that ancient story, And burned with ardent love of glory.</s> <s id="s588">Whenever I traced the fields of Troy, My heart beat high with martial joy.</s> <s id="s589">' Tis true, I pray that war may cease, And <enamex  sw="w92352" name="Large admin unit">Europe</enamex> hail returning Peace; Yet still I feel my bosom glow When British heroes meet the foe: When our armed legions make him fly.</s> <s id="s590">And yield the palm of victory: Or when our naval thunders roar, And terrify the Gallic shore.</s> <s id="s591">This grand review will give me pleasure, And I shall wait upon your leisure."</s></p>
<p><s id="s592">But, as no time was to be lost, Syntax now hastened to the post: The post obeyed his loud command, And gave a letter to his hand.</s> <s id="s593">With eager haste the seal he broke, And thus the fond epistle spoke.</s></p>
<p><s id="s594">" My dearest husband, - - on my life I thought you had forgot your wife: While she, to her affection true, Was always thinking, Love, on you.</s> <s id="s595">By this time, I presume, you've made No small advancement in your trade: I mean, my dear, that this same book, To which I with impatience look, Is full of promise; and I'm bold To hope for a return in gold.</s> <s id="s596">I have no doubt that ample gains Will well reward your learned pains, And will, with bounteous store, repay Your anxious toil of many a day; For well, my dearest friend, I know, Wherever you are compelled to go, You still must sigh that you should be So long away from Love and me.</s> <s id="s597">I truly say my heart doth burn With ardent wish for your return; And that I may my Syntax greet With all due honour when we meet, The milliner is now preparing A dress that will be worth the wearing; Just such an one as I have seen In Ackermann's Last Magazine, Where, by the skilful painter's aid, Each fashion is so well displayed.</s> <s id="s598">A robe of crape, with satin boddice, Will make me look like any goddess: A mantle too is all the ton, And therefore I have ordered one:</s> </p><p><s id="s599">I've also got a lilac bonnet, And placed a yellow feather on it: Thus I shall be so very smart,' Twill vex Miss Raisin to the heart; Oh! it will make me burst with laughter, To plague the purse-proud grocer's daughter; While through the town, as you shall see No one will be so fine as me.</s> <s id="s600">Oh! with what pleasure and delight I shall present me to your sight; How shall I hug you, dearest honey, When you return brimful of money."</s></p>
<p><s id="s601">Syntax exclaimed, in accents sad," The woman's surely gone stark mad! To ruin, all her airs will tend; But I'll read on, and see the end."</s></p>
<p><s id="s602">" As to the news, why you must know, Things in their usual order go: <enamex sw="w94614" long="-92.6762981" lat="38.2289204" type="other" gazref="unlock:7142106" name="Jobson Hollow Cove" conf="0.3980404554">Jobson</enamex> the Tanner's run away, And has not left a doit to pay: Bet Bumpkin was last Thursday married, And Mrs. Stillborn has miscarryed.</s> <s id="s603">In <enamex sw="w94754" long="-2.8645" lat="54.4921" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_NY441111" name="Highstreet" conf="99991">the High Street</enamex>, the other day, Good Mrs. Squeamish swooned away, And was so ill, as it is said, That she was borne away for dead; But Mother Gossip, who knows all The neighbours round, both great and small, Has hinted to me, as she thinks, That pious Mrs. Squeamish drinks.</s> <s id="s604">There is a Lady just come down, A dashing, frisking dame from town, To visit Madam <enamex sw="w95113" long="-74.0776414" lat="40.6264929" type="other" gazref="unlock:7879842" name="Stapleton" conf="0.8189774144">Stapleton</enamex>:</s> </p><p><s id="s605">She's said to be a <enamex sw="w95144" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.762992967">London</enamex> toast, But has no mighty charms to boast; For it is clear to my keen sight, That she lays on both red and white.</s> <s id="s606">She drives about in chaise and pair, And, I have heard, can curse and swear: But I mind not these things, not I, I never deal in calumny.</s> <s id="s607">So fare you well, my dearest life, - - And I remain your loving wife."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s608">Postscript.</s></p>
<p><s id="s609">" But if you fear that you shall come Without a bag of money home,' Twere better far that you should take A leap at once into the Lake: - - Ied rather hear that you were drowned, Than that you should my hopes confound."</s></p>
<p><s id="s610">These tender lines did not impart Much comfort to the Doctor's heart; He therefore thought it would be better To lay aside this pretty letter; Nor suffer its contents to sour The pleasure of the present hour.</s></p>
<p><s id="s611">The' Squire now became his guide, So off they trotted, side by side; And, ever they passed a mile or two, Beheld the scene of the review.</s> <s id="s612">The troops drawn up in proud array, An animating sight display: The well-formed squadrons wheel around - - The standards wave, the trumpets sound;</s> </p><p><s id="s613">When Grizzle, long matured to war, And not without an honoured scar, Found all her former spirits glow As when she used to meet the foe: No ears she pricked, for she had none: Nor cocked her tail, for that was gone; But still she snorted, foamed, and flounced; Then up she reared, and off she bounced; And, having played these pretty pranks, Dashed all at once into the ranks; While Syntax, though unused to fear, Suspected that his end was near: But, though his courage' gan to addle, He still stuck close upon his saddle; While, to the trumpets on the hill, Grizzle sped fast, and then stood still: With them she closed her warlike race, And took with pride her ancient place; For Grizzle, as we've told before, Once to the wars a trumpet bore.</s></p>
<p><s id="s614">At length, recovered from his fright, The Doctor stayed and viewed the sight; And then, with heart as light as cork, He with his friend jogged back to <enamex sw="w97117" long="" lat="" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:9659" name="" conf="99991">York</enamex>, Where was renewed the friendly fare, And every comfort promised there.</s> <s id="s615">The time in chit-chat passed away, Till the chimes told the closing day: And now, says pleasant Madam Hearty, What think you if our little party Should each to sing a song agree?' Twill give a sweet variety.</s> <s id="s616">Thus, let the passing moments roll, Till Thomas brings the evening bowl:</s> </p><p><s id="s617">The Doctor, sure, will do his best And kindly grant my poor request.</s> <s id="s618">The Doctor, though by nature grave, And rather formed to tune a stave, Whenever he got a little mellow, Was a most merry, pleasant fellow; Would sing a song, or tell a riddle, Or play a hornpipe on the fiddle; And, being now a little gay, Declared his wishes to obey.</s> <s id="s619">Then I'll begin,' Squire Hearty said, But though by land my tours are made, Whenever I tune a song, or glee, I quit the land, and go to sea.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s620">The' Squire's Song.</s></p>
<p><s id="s621">The signal given, we seek the main, Where tempests rage, and billows roar; Nor know we if we ever again Shall anchor on our native shore.</s></p>
<p><s id="s622">But, as through surging waves we sail, And distant seas and isles explore, Hope whispers that some future gale Will waft us to our native shore.</s></p>
<p><s id="s623">When battle rages all amain, And hostile arms their vengeance pour, We British sailors will maintain The honour of our native shore.</s></p>
<p><s id="s624">But, should we find a watery grave, A nation will our loss deplore; And tears will mingle with the wave That breaks upon our native shore.</s></p>
<p><s id="s625">And after many a battle won, When every toil and danger's over, How great the joy, each duty done, To anchor on our native shore.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s626">Mrs. Hearty's Song.</s></p>
<p><s id="s627">Cupid, away! thy work is over, - - Go seek Idalia's flowery grove; Your pointed darts will pain no more, - - Hymen has healed the wounds of Love.</s></p>
<p><s id="s628">Hymen is here, and all is rest; To distant flight thy pinions move: No anxious doubts, no fears molest; Hymen has soothed the pangs of Love.</s></p>
<p><s id="s629">Cupid, away! - - the deed is done; - - Away,' mid other scenes to rove; For Ralph and Isabel are one, And Hymen guards the home of Love.</s></p>
<p><s id="s630">The Doctor now his reverence made, And Madam's smiling nod obeyed.</s> <s id="s631">" Your songs," he said," have given me pleasure, As well in subject as in measure; But, in some modern songs, the taste Is far, I'm sure, from being chaste.</s> <s id="s632">They do not make the least pretence To poetry or common sense.</s> <s id="s633">Some coarse conceits, a lively air, With a da capo, here and there, Of uncouth words, which never were found In any language above ground;</s> </p><p><s id="s634">And these, set off with some strange phrase; Compose our sing-song now-a-days.</s> <s id="s635">The dancing-master of my school In this way oft will play the fool And make one laugh - - one knows not why, - - But we had better laugh than cry.</s> <s id="s636">The song, which youere about to hear Will of this character appear; From <enamex sw="w99848" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.762992967">London</enamex> it was sent him down, As a great faverite through the town."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s637">Doctor Syntax's Song.</s></p>
<p><s id="s638">I've got a scold of a wife, The plague and storm of my life; O! were she in coal-pit bottom, And all such jades,' od rot' em! My cares would then be over, And I should live in clover.</s> <s id="s639">With harum scarum, horum scorum, - - Stewed prunes for ever! Stewed prunes for ever!</s></p>
<p><s id="s640">Brother Tom's in the codlin-tree, As blithe as blithe can be: While Dorothy sits below, Where the daffodillies grow; And many a slender rush, And blackberries all on a bush, With harum scarum,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s641">&amp; c.</s></p>
<p><s id="s642">We'll to the castle go Like grenadiers all of a row, While the horn and trump shall sound As we pace the ramparts round,</s> </p><p><s id="s643">Where many a lady fair Comes forth to take the air.</s> <s id="s644">With harum scarum,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s645">&amp; c.</s></p>
<p><s id="s646">The vessel spreads her sails To catch the rising gales, And dances over the wave; While many a lovelorn slave To his mistress tells his tale, Far off in the distant vale.</s> <s id="s647">With harum scarum,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s648">&amp; c.</s></p>
<p><s id="s649">When the dew is on the rose, And the wanton zephyr blows; When lilies raise their head, And harebells fragrance shed; Then I to the rocks will hie, And sing a lullaby.</s> <s id="s650">With harum scarum,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s651">&amp; c.</s></p>
<p><s id="s652">By famed Ilyssus' stream How oft I fondly dream, When I read in classic pages Of all the ancient sages; But they were born to die! And so were you and I. With harum scarum, horum scorum, - - Stewed prunes for ever! Stewed prunes for ever!</s></p>
<p><s id="s653">Thus with many a pleasant lay, The party closed the exhausted day.</s></p><p><s id="s654">Canto Xii.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s655">Life is a journey: - - on we go Through many a scene of joy and woe: Time flits along, and will not stay, Nor let us linger on the way: - - Like as a stream, whose varying course Now rushes with impetuous force; Now in successive eddies plays, Or in meanders gently strays, It still moves on, till spreading wide, It mingles with the briny tide; And, when it meets the ocean's roar, The limpid waves are seen no more.</s> <s id="s656">Such, such is life's uncertain way: - - Now the sun wakes the enlivening day: The scene around enchants the sight; To cool retreat the shades invite: The blossoms balmy fragrance shed; The meads a verdant carpet spread; While the clear rill reflects below The flowers that on its margin grow; And the sweet songsters of the grove Attune to harmony and love.</s> <s id="s657">But, lo! the clouds obscure the sky, And tell the blustering tempest nigh:</s> </p><p><s id="s658">The livid flash, the pelting storm, Fair Nature's every grace deform; While their assailing powers annoy The pensive pilgrim's tranquil joy: But, though no tempest should molest The Bower where he stops to rest, Care will not let him long remain, But sets him on his way again.</s> <s id="s659">Thus Syntax, whom the' Squire had pressed For three whole months to take his rest, Sighed when he found he could not stay To loiter through another day:" No," he exclaimed," I must away: - - I have a splendid book to make, To form a tour, - - to paint a lake; And, by that well-projected tome, To carry fame and money home: And, should I fail, my loving wife Will lead me such a precious life, That I had better never more Approach my then forbidden door."</s> <s id="s660">' Twas thus he pondered as he lay, When the sun told another day.</s> <s id="s661">Nor long the downy couch he pressed, Where busy thought disturbed his rest; But quick prepared, with grateful heart, From this warm mansion to depart.</s> <s id="s662">The' Squire, to his professions true, Thus spoke at once his kind adieu.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s663">' Squire.</s></p>
<p><s id="s664">" I'm sorry, Sir, with all my heart, That you and I so soon must part: Your virtues my regard engage; I venerate the reverend sage:</s> </p><p><s id="s665">And, though I've not the mind to toil In Learning's way, by midnight oil, Yet still I feel the reverence due To all such learned men as you: Nor can I urge your longer stay, When Science calls you far away: But still I hope you'll not refuse My friendly tribute to the Muse; And, when again you this way come, Again you'll find this house a home.</s> <s id="s666">Besides, I mean to recommend Your labours to a noble friend, Who well is known to rank as high In learning, as in quality; Who can your merits well review; A statesman, and a poet too: He will your genius truly scan, And, though a lord, a learned man.</s> <s id="s667">For C****** is an honoured name, Whose virtue and unsullyed fame Will decorate the historic page, And live through every future age.</s> <s id="s668">That courteous Lord doth condescend To know me for a faithful friend; And, when you to his Lordship give The letter which you now receive, You'll find, on his right noble part, A welcome that will cheer your heart.</s> <s id="s669">To - - - - - - - - then repair, And Honour will attend you there.</s> <s id="s670">Nor fear, my friend, that gilded state Will frown upon your humble fate; My Lord is good as he is great."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s671">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s672">" Your kindness, surely, knows no end; You are in truth a real friend; Nor can my feeble tongue express This unexpected happiness: For, if this noble Lord should deign My feeble labours to sustain, With the all-cheering, splendid rays Of his benign, protecting praise, My fortune will at once be made, And I shall bless the author's trade."</s></p>
<p><s id="s673">Thus, as he spoke, the' Squire gave The letter Syntax longed to have; And with it a soft silky note, On which two coal-black words were wrote; The sight of which his sense confounds, For these said words were Twenty Pounds.</s> <s id="s674">" Check," said the' Squire," your wondering look;' Tis my subscription to your book; And, when' tis printed, you will send A copy to your Yorkshire friend; Besides, I'll try to sell a score Among my neighbours here, or more."</s></p>
<p><s id="s675">The Doctor's tongue made no reply, But his heart heaved a grateful sigh.</s> <s id="s676">Thus, as he sits, we ca n't do better Than to repeat the promised letter: - -</s></p>
<p><s id="s677">" My Lord, This liberty I take, For laughter and for Merit's sake;</s> </p><p><s id="s678">And, when the bearer shall appear In your fine mansion's atmosphere, His figure will your spirits cheer.</s> <s id="s679">You need no other topic seek; He'll furnish laughter for a week: But still I say, and tell you true, You'll love him for his merit too.</s> <s id="s680">You'll see, at once, in this Divine, Quixote and Parson <enamex sw="w105835" long="-119.5722541809082" lat="51.19489097595215" type="water" gazref="unlock:14138535" name="Adams Lake" conf="0.758526282">Adams</enamex> shine: An hero well combined you'll view For Fielding and <enamex  sw="w105900" name="Not a placename">Cervantes</enamex> too: Besides, my Lord, if I can judge, In classic lore he's used to drudge.</s> <s id="s681">O do but hear his simple story; Let him but lay it all before you; And you will thank me for my letter, And say that you are Hearty' s debtor; Nay, when your sides are tired with mirth, Your heart will feel his real worth.</s> <s id="s682">I know full well how you'll receive him, And to your favour thus I leave him.</s> <s id="s683">So I remain with zeal most fervent, Your Lordship's true and hearty servant.</s>  <s id="s684"><enamex sw="w106369" long="" lat="" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:9659" name="" conf="99991">York</enamex>, Thursday."" R. H."</s></p>
<p><s id="s685">The Doctor now prepared to go, With heart of joy and look of woe; He silent squeezed the' Squire's hands, And asked of Madam her commands.</s> <s id="s686">The' Squire exclaimed," why so remiss? She bids you take a hearty kiss;</s> </p><p><s id="s687">And, if you think that one wo n't do, I beg, dear Sir, you'll give her two;" Nay, then, says Syntax," you shall see;" And straight he gave the Lady three; Nor did he linger to exclaim" He never had kissed a fairer dame."</s> <s id="s688">The Lady blushed, and thanked him too, And, in soft accents, said - - Adieu!</s></p>
<p><s id="s689">Syntax, since first he left his home, Had no such view of good to come, As now before his fancy rose, To bid him laugh at future woes.</s> <s id="s690">" Fortune," he cried," is kind at last, And I forgive her malice past: Clad in C - - - -' s benignant form, Her power no more will wake the storm, Nor ever again her anger shed In frequent showers upon my head."</s></p>
<p><s id="s691">Now, after a short morning's ride, In eager Hope and Fancy's pride, The Doctor views, with conscious smile, Fair - - - - - - - -' s splendid pile.</s> <s id="s692">Not <enamex sw="w107414" long="1.964634776115417" lat="48.8226146697998" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127426" name="Versailles" conf="1.733052399">Versailles</enamex> makes a finer show.</s> <s id="s693">As, passing over the lofty brow, The stately scene is viewed below.</s> <s id="s694">" My Lord received him with a grace Which marks the sovereign of the place; Nor was poor Syntax made to feel The pride which fools so oft reveal; Who think it a fine state decorum, When humble merit stands before' em:</s> </p><p><s id="s695">But here was birth from folly free, - - Here was the true nobility, Where human kindness gilds the crest; The first of virtues, and the best.</s></p>
<p><s id="s696">An hour in pleasant chit-chat past, The welcome dinner came at last; And now the hungry Syntax eats Of high ragouts and dainty meats; Nor was the good man found to shrink Whenever he was asked to drink.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s697">My Lord.</s></p>
<p><s id="s698">" What think you, Doctor, of the show Of pictures that around you glow?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s699">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s700">" I'll by-and-by enjoy the treat; But now, my Lord, Ied rather eat."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s701">My Lord.</s></p>
<p><s id="s702">" What say you to this statue here? Does it not flesh and blood appear?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s703">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s704">" I'm sure, my Lord,' tis very fine; But I, just now, prefer your wine."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s705">Sir John.</s></p>
<p><s id="s706">" I wonder you can keep your eye From forms that do with Nature vie; Nay, in my mind, my reverend friend, Nature's best works they far transcend.</s> </p><p><s id="s707">Look at that picture of the Graces, What lovely forms! - - what charming faces!"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s708">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s709">" Their charms, Sir John, I shall discover, I have no doubt, when dinner's over: At present, if to judge I'm able, The finest works are on the table.</s> <s id="s710">I should prefer the cook just now, To <enamex  sw="w108852" name="Not a placename">Rubens</enamex> or to Gerrard Dow.</s> <s id="s711">''</s></p>
<p> <s id="s712">My Lord.</s></p>
<p><s id="s713">" I wish to judge, by certain rules, The Flemish and Italian schools; And nicely to describe the merits Or beauties which each school inherits."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s714">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s715">" Though, in their way, theyere both bewitching; I now prefer your Lordship's kitchen."</s></p>
<p><s id="s716">The dinner done, the punch appears, And many a glass their spirits cheers.</s> <s id="s717">The festive hours thus passed away, Till time brought on the closing day: The Doctor talked, nor ceased his quaffing, While all around were sick with laughing.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s718">My Lord.</s></p>
<p><s id="s719">" Again the subject I renew, And wish you would the pictures view."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s720">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s721">" To view them now would be a trouble, For faith, my Lord, my eyes see double."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s722">My Lord.</s></p>
<p><s id="s723">" To bed then we had best repair, - - I give you to the Butler's care; A sage grave man, who will obey Whatever your Reverence has to say."</s></p>
<p><s id="s724">The sage grave man appeared, and bowed:" I am of this good office proud; But' tis the custom of this place, From country-yeoman to his Grace, Whenever a stranger guest we see, To make him of the cellar free.</s> <s id="s725">To you the same respect we bear, And therefore beg to lead you there; Where every noble butt doth claim The honour of some titled name."</s></p>
<p><s id="s726">The servants waited on the stairs, With cautious form and humble airs.</s> <s id="s727">" Lead on," says Syntax," I'll not stay, But follow where you lead the way."</s></p>
<p><s id="s728">The Butler cried," You'll understand It is our noble Lord's command To give this reverend Doctor here A sample of our strongest beer; So tap her Grace of <enamex  sw="w110343" name="Large admin unit">Devonshire</enamex>."</s> <s id="s729">At length the potent liquor flows, Which makes poor man forget his woes.</s> <s id="s730">Syntax exclaimed," Here's Honour's boast; - - The health of our most noble Host; - - And let fair <enamex sw="w110530" long="-3.715181112289429" lat="50.72997856140137" type="civila" gazref="unlock:14124384" name="Devon" conf="1.2743781">Devon</enamex> crown the toast."</s></p>
<p><s id="s731">The cups were cheered with loyal song; But cups like these never lasted long: And Syntax stammered," Do you see? Now I'm of this famed cellar free,</s> </p><p><s id="s732">I wish I might be quickly led T' enjoy my freedom in a bed."</s> <s id="s733">He wished but once, and was obeyed And soon within a bed was laid, Where, all the day's strange business over, He now was left to sleep and snore.</s></p><p><s id="s734">Canto Xiii.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s735">How oft, as through Life's vale we stray, Doth Fancy light us on the way! How oft, with many a vision bright, Doth she the wayward heart delight; And, with a fond enlivening smile, The heavy hour of care beguile! But though so oft she scatters flowers, To make more gay our waking hours; Night is the time when over the soul She exercises full control.</s> <s id="s736">While Life's more active functions pause, And sleep its sable curtain draws,' Tis then she waves her fairy wand: And strange things rise at her command: - - She then assumes her motley reign, And man lives over his life again; While many an airy dream invites Her wizard masks, her wanton sprites: Through the warm brain the phantoms play, And form a visionary day.</s></p>
<p><s id="s737">Thus Syntax, while the bed he prest, And passed the night in balmy rest, Was led in those unconscious hours, By Fancy, to her fairy bowers, Where the light spirits wander free In whimsical variety.</s></p>
<p><s id="s738">No more an humble Curate, now, He feels a mitre on his brow; The mildewed surplice, now withdrawn, Yields to the fine, transparent <enamex  sw="w111982" name="Too ambigious to allocate">lawn</enamex>; And peruke, that defied all weather, Is nicely dressed to ape a feather.</s> <s id="s739">Grizzle no more is seen to wail, Her mangled ears and butchered tail; - - Six Grizzles now, with every ear, And all their flowing tails appear; When, harnessed to a light barouche, The ground they do not seem to touch: Whirled onward in a wild surprise, The air-blown prelate thinks he flies.</s> <s id="s740">Now through the long cathedral aisle, Where vergers bow and virgins smile, With measured step and solemn air, He gains at length the sacred chair; And to the crowd, with look profound, Bestows his holy blessing round.</s> <s id="s741">Above the pealing organs blow, To the respondent choir below; When, bending to Religion's shrine, He feels an energy divine.</s> <s id="s742">Now,' scaped from Dolly's angry clutches, He thinks he's married to a Duchess; And that her rank and glowing beauty Enlivens his prelatic duty.</s></p>
<p><s id="s743">Thus Fancy, with her antic train, Passed nimbly through the Doctor's brain; But, while she told her varying story Of short-lived pomp and fading glory, A voice upon the vision broke, - - When Syntax gave a grunt - - and woke.</s></p>
<p><s id="s744">" And may it please you, I've a word To tell your Reverence, from my Lord."" A Lord," he cried," why, to be free, I've been as good a lord as he: Throughout the night, I've been as great As any Lord, with all his state: But now that fine-drawn scene is over, And I'm poor Syntax as before.</s> <s id="s745">You spoiled my fortune,' tis most certain, The moment you withdrew the curtain: So, if you please, my pretty maid, You'll tell me what my Lord has said."" - - My Lord has sent to let you know That breakfast is prepared below."" - - Let my respects upon him wait, And say that I'll be with him straight."</s> <s id="s746">Out then he bounced upon the floor: The maid ran shouting through the door, - - So much the figure of the Doctor, In his unrobed condition shocked her.</s></p>
<p><s id="s747">Syntax now hastened to obey The early summons of the day.</s> <s id="s748">He humbly bowed, and took his seat; Nor did his Lordship fail to greet With kindest words his reverend guest - - As how he had enjoyed his rest; Hoped every comfort he had found; That his night's slumbers had been sound; And that he was prepared to share With keen regard, his morning's fare.</s> <s id="s749">The Doctor smiled, and soon made free With my Lord's hospitality; Then told aloud his golden dream, Which proved of mirth a fruitful theme.</s> </p><p><s id="s750">"' Tis true," he said," when I awoke, The charm dissolved, the spell was broke; The mitre and its grand display, With my fine wife, all passed away.</s> <s id="s751">The awakening voice my fortune crossed; I oped my eyes, and all was lost; But still I find, to my delight, I have not lost my appetite."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s752">Sir John.</s></p>
<p><s id="s753">" As for the mitre and the gold, Which Fancy gave you to behold, They, to a mind with learning fraught, Do not deserve a passing thought: But I lament that such a bride Should thus be stolen from your side."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s754">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s755">" For that choice good I need not roam; I've got, Sir John, a wife at home, Who can from morn to night contrive To keep her family alive: Such sprightly measures she can take, That no one sleeps when she's awake.</s> <s id="s756">For me, if Fortune would but shower Some portion of her wealth and power, I would forgive her, on my life, Though she forgot to add a wife.</s> <s id="s757">Indeed, Sir John, we do n't agree, Nor join in our philosophy; For did you know what that man knows, Had you ever felt his cutting woes, Who has of taunts a daily plenty, Whose head is combed, whose pocket's empty;</s> </p><p><s id="s758">You never would call those shiners trash, Whose touch is life - - whose name is cash."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s759">My Lord.</s></p>
<p><s id="s760">" A truce, I pray, to your debate; The hunters all impatient wait; And much I hope our learned Clerk Will take a gallop in <enamex  sw="w115637" name="Too ambigious to allocate">the park</enamex>."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s761">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s762">" Your sport, my Lord, I cannot take, For I must go and hunt a lake; And while you chase the flying deer, I must fly off to <enamex sw="w115782" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.323387543">Windermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s763">' Stead of hallooing to a fox, I must catch echoes from the rocks, With curious eye and active scent, I on the picturesque am bent.</s> <s id="s764">This is my game; I must pursue it, And make it where I cannot view it.</s> <s id="s765">Though in good truth, but do not flout me, I bear that self-same thing about me.</s> <s id="s766">If in man's form you wish to see The picturesque - - pray look at me.</s> <s id="s767">I am myself without a flaw, The very picturesque I draw.</s> <s id="s768">A Rector, on whose face so sleek In vain you for a wrinkle seek; In whose fair form, so fat and round, No obtuse angle's to be found; On such a shape no man of taste Would his fine tints or canvass waste: But take a Curate who's so thin, His bones seem peeping through his skin; Make him to stand, or walk, or sit, In any posture you think fit;</s> </p><p><s id="s769">And, with all these nice points about him, No well-taught painter ever would scout him; For with his air, and look, and mien, Heed give effect to any scene.</s> <s id="s770">In my poor beast, as well as me, A fine example you may see: She's so abrupt in all her parts - - O what fine subjects for the arts! Thus we travel on together, With gentle gale or stormy weather; And, though we trot along the plains, Where one dead level ever reigns, Or pace where rocks and mountains rise, Who lift their heads, and brave the skies; I Doctor Syntax, and my horse, Give to the landscape double force.</s> <s id="s771">- - I have no doubt I shall produce A volume of uncommon use, That will be worthy to be placed Beneath the eye of men of taste; And I should hope, my Lord, that you Will praise it, and protect it too; Will let your all-sufficient name The double patronage proclaim: That time may know, till time doth end, That C - - - was my honoured friend."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s772">Sir John.</s></p>
<p><s id="s773">" And can you, learned Doctor, see When that important time will be?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s774">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s775">" Sir Knight, that was not wisely spoke; The point's too serious for a joke;</s> </p><p><s id="s776">And you must know, by Heaven's decree, That time will come to you and me, And then succeeds - - Eternity."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s777">My Lord.</s></p>
<p><s id="s778">" Peace, peace, Sir John, and let me tell The Doctor that I wish him well.</s> <s id="s779">I doubt not but his work will prove, Most useful to the arts I love.</s> <s id="s780">But pray, good Sir, come up to town, That seat of wealth and of renown: Come up to town nor fear the cost, Nor time nor labour shall be lost.</s> <s id="s781">I'll ope my door and take you in - - You've made me laugh, and you shall win: We'll then consult how I can best Advance your real interest: And here this piece of writing take; - - You'll use it for the donor's sake; I mean, you see, that it shall crown Your wishes while you stay in town: But you may, as it suits you, use it, - - No one, I fancy, will refuse it."</s> <s id="s782">The Doctor, when he viewed the paper.</s> <s id="s783">Instead of bowing - - cut a caper</s></p>
<p><s id="s784">My Lord now sought the expecting chase, And Syntax in his usual pace, When four long, tedious days had passed, The town of <enamex sw="w118623" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.36965951">Keswick</enamex> reached at last, Where he his famous work prepared, Of all his toil the hoped reward.</s></p>
<p><s id="s785">Soon as the morn began to break, Old Grizzle bore him to the lake;</s> </p><p><s id="s786">Along the banks he gravely paced, And all its various beauties traced; When, lo, a threatening storm appeared: <enamex  sw="w118898" name="Not a placename">Phoebus</enamex> the scene no longer cheered: The dark clouds sink on every hill: The floating mists the valleys fill: Nature, transformed, began to lour, And threatened a tremendous shower.</s> <s id="s787">" I love," he cried," to hear the rattle, When elements contend in battle; For I insist, though some may flout it, Who write about it and about it, That we the picturesque may find In thunder loud, or whistling wind: And often, as I fully ween, It may be heard as well as seen; For, though a pencil cannot trace A sound as it can paint a place, The pen, in its poetic rage, Can make it figure on the page."</s></p>
<p><s id="s788">A fisherman, who passed that way, Thought it civility to say - -" An' please you, Sir,' tis all is vain To take your prospects in the rain; On horseback too you'll never be able - -' Twere better, sure to get a table." - -" Thanks," Syntax said," for your advice, And faith I'll take it in a trice; For, as I'm moistened to the skin, I'll seek a table at the Inn; - - But Grizzle, in her haste to pass, Lured by a tempting tuft of grass, A luckless step now chanced to take, And soused the Doctor in the Lake;</s> </p><p><s id="s789">But, as it proved, no worse disaster Befel poor Grizzle and her master, Than both of them could well endure, And a warm Inn would shortly cure.</s> <s id="s790">To that warm Inn they quickly hied, Where Syntax, by the fire-side, Sat, in the landlord's garments clad, But neither sorrowful nor sad; Nor did he waste his hours away, But gave his pencil all its play, And traced the landscapes of the day.</s></p><p><s id="s791">Canto Xiv.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s792">Nature, dear Nature, is my goddess, Whether arrayed in rustic bodice, Or when the nicest touch of Art Doth to her charms new charms impart: But still I, somehow, love her best, When she's in ruder mantle drest: I do not mean in shape grotesque, But when she's truly picturesque.</s></p>
<p><s id="s793">Thus the next morning as he strayed, And the surrounding scene surveyed, Syntax exclaimed.</s> <s id="s794">- - A party stood Just on the margin of the flood; Who were in statu quo, to make A little voyage on the Lake.</s> <s id="s795">The Doctor forward stepped to show The wealth of his port-folio.</s> <s id="s796">The ladies were quite pleased to view Such pretty pictures as he drew; While a young man, a neighbering' Squire, Expressed a very warm desire, Which seemed to come from honest heart, That of their boat heed take a part.</s></p>
<p><s id="s797">Now from the shore they quickly sailed, And soon the Doctor's voice prevailed.</s> <s id="s798">" This is a lovely scene of Nature; But I've enough of land and water:</s> </p><p><s id="s799">I want some livings thing to show How far the picturesque will go.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s800">Lady.</s></p>
<p><s id="s801">" See, Sir, how swift the swallows fly: And lo, the lark ascends on high; We scarce can view him in the sky.</s> <s id="s802">Behold the wild fowl, how they spread Upon the Lake's expansive bed: The kite sails through the airy way, Prepared to pounce upon its prey: The rooks too, from their morning food, Pass cawing to the distant wood."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s803">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s804">" When with a philosophic eye The realms of Nature I descry, And view the grace that she can give To all the varying forms that live; I feel with awe the plastic art That doth such wonderous powers impart To all that wing the air, or creep Along the earth, or swim the deep; I love the winged world that flies Through the thin azure of the skies; Or, not ordained those heights to scan, Live the familiar friends of man, And, in his yard or round his cot, Enjoy, poor things! their destined lot: But though their plumes are gay with dies, In endless, bright diversities - - What, though such glowing tints prevail, When the proud peacock spreads his tail - - What though the nightingales prolong Through the charmed night the enchanting song - -</s> </p><p><s id="s805">What though the blackbird and the thrush Make vocal every verdant bush - - Not one among the winged kind Presents an object to my mind; Their grace and beauty's nought to me; In all their vast variety The picturesque I cannot see.</s> <s id="s806">A carrion fowl tyed to a stake Will a far better picture make, When as a scare-crow' tis displayed For thievish birds to be afraid.</s> <s id="s807">Than the white swan, in all its pride, Sailing upon the crystal tide.</s> <s id="s808">As a philosopher I scan Whatever kind Heaven has made for man; I feel it a religious duty To bless its use and praise its beauty; I care not whatsoever the creature, Whatever its name, its form and feature, So that fond Nature will aver The creature doth belong to her: - - But though indeed, I may admire The greyhound's form, and snake's attire, They neither will my object suit Like a good shaggy, ragged brute.</s> <s id="s809">I will acknowledge that a goose Is a fine fowl, of sovereign use: But for a picture, she's not fitted - - The bird was made but to be spitted.</s> <s id="s810">The pigeon, I'll be bound to show it, Is a fine subject for a poet; In the soft verse his mate he'll woo, Turns his gay neck, and bill and coo,</s> </p><p><s id="s811">And, as in amerous strut he moves, Soothes the fond heart of him who loves: But I'll not paint him, no, not I - - I like him better in a pye, Well rubbed with salt and spicy dust, And thus embodyed in a crust.</s> <s id="s812">How many a bird that haunts the wood, How many a fowl that cleaves the flood, With their sweet songs enchant my ear, Or please my eye as they appear, When in their flight, or as they row, Delighted on the lake below! But still, whatever their form or feather, You cannot make them group together: For, let them swim or let them fly, The picturesque they all defy.</s> <s id="s813">The bird that's sitting quit alone Is fit but to be carved in stone; And any man of taste' twould shock To paint those wild geese in a flock: - - Though I like not a single figure, Whether' tis lesser or' tis bigger; That fisherman, so lean and lank, Who sits alone upon the bank, Tempts not the eye; but, doff his coat, And quickly group him with a boat, You then will see the fellow make A pretty object on the Lake.</s> <s id="s814">If a boy's playing with a hoop,' Tis something, for it forms a group.</s> <s id="s815">In painters' eyes - - O what a joke To place a bird upon an oak: At the same time,' twould help the jest, Upon the branch to fix a nest.</s> </p><p><s id="s816">A trout, with all its pretty dies Of various hues, delights the eyes; But still it is a silly whim To make him on a canvas swim: Yet, I must own, that dainty fish Looks very handsome in a dish; And he must be a thankless sinner Who thinks a trout a paltry dinner.</s></p>
<p><s id="s817">" The first, the middle, and the last.</s> <s id="s818">In picturesque is bold contrast; And painting has no nobler use Than this grand object to produce.</s> <s id="s819">Such is my thought, and I'll pursue it; There's an example - - you shall view it: Look at that tree - - then take a glance At its fine, bold protuberance; Behold those branches - - how their shade Is by the mass of light displayed; Look at that light, and see how fine The backward shadows make it shine: The sombre clouds that spot the sky, Make the blue vaulting twice as high; And where the sun-beams warmly glow, They make the hollow twice as low.</s> <s id="s820">The Flemish painters all surpass In making pictures smooth as glass: In Cuyp's best works there's pretty painting: But the bold picturesque is wanting.</s></p>
<p><s id="s821">" Thus, though I leave the birds to sing, Or cleave the air with rapid wing - - Thus, though I leave the fish to play Till the net drags them into day - -</s> </p><p><s id="s822">Kind Nature, ever bounteous mother! Contrives it, in some way or other, Our proper wishes to supply In infinite variety.</s> <s id="s823">The world of quadrupeds displays The painter's art in various ways; But,' tis some shaggy, ragged brute That will my busy purpose suit; Or such as, from their shape and make, No fine-wrought, high-bred semblance take.</s> <s id="s824">A well-fed horse, with shining skin, Formed for the course, and plates to win, May have his beauties, but not those That will my graphic art disclose: My raw-boned mare is worth a score Of these fine pampered beasts, and more, To give effect to bold design, And decorate such views as mine.</s> <s id="s825">To the fine steed you sportsmen bow, But picturesque prefers a cow; On her high hips and horned head How true the light and shade are shed.</s> <s id="s826">Indeed I should prefer by half, To a fine colt, a common calf: The unshorn sheep, the shaggy goat, The ass with rugged, ragged coat, Would, to a taste-inspired mind, Leave the far-famed Eclipse behind: In a grand stable he might please, But never should graze beneath my trees."</s></p>
<p><s id="s827">Caught by his words, the northern' Squire Failed not his learning to admire:</s> </p><p><s id="s828">But yet he had a wish to quiz The Doctor's humour, and his phiz.</s> <s id="s829">" I have a house," he said," at hand, Where you my service may command; There I have cows, and asses too, And pigs and sheep, Sir, not a few, Where you, at your untroubled leisure, May draw them as it suits your pleasure.</s> <s id="s830">You shall be welcome, and your mare, And find a country' Squire's fare: With us a day or two you'll pass, - - We'll give you meat - - and give her grass."</s> <s id="s831">Thus' twas agreed; - - they came on shore; The party sauntered on before; But, ever they reached the mansion fair, Grizzle had borne her master there.</s> <s id="s832">It was, indeed, a pleasant spot That this same country' Squire had got: And Syntax now the party joined With salutation free and kind.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s833">' Squire.</s></p>
<p><s id="s834">" This, Doctor Syntax, is my sister: Why, my good Sir, you have not kissed her.'</s></p>
<p> <s id="s835">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s836">" Do not suppose I'm such a brute As to disdain the sweet salute."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s837">' Squire.</s></p>
<p><s id="s838">" And this, Sir, is my loving wife, The joy and honour of my life."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s839">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s840">" A lovely Lady to the view! And, with your leave, I'll kiss her too."</s></p>
<p><s id="s841">Thus pleasant words the converse cheered Till dinner on the board appeared Where a warm welcome gave a zest To the fair plenty of the feast.</s> <s id="s842">The Doctor eat, and talked and quaffed; The good Host smiled, the <enamex sw="w128418" long="-1.77831968367031" lat="54.08503022708322" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11189841" name="Ladies Riggs" conf="1.32037322">Ladies</enamex> laughed.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s843">' Squire.</s></p>
<p><s id="s844">" As you disdain both fowl and fish, Think you your art could paint that dish?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s845">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s846">" Though' twill to hunger give relief, - - There's nothing picturesque in Beef: But there are artists - - if you'll treat' em - - Will paint your dinners; that is - - eat' em."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s847">' Squire.</s></p>
<p><s id="s848">" But sure your pencil might command Whatever is noble, vast and grand, - - The beasts, forsooth, of Indian land: Where the fierce, savage tyger scowls, And the fell, hungry lion growls."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s849">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s850">" These beasts may all be subjects fit; But, for their likeness, will they sit? Ied only take a view askaunt, From the tall back of elephant; With half an hundred Indians round me, That such sharp claws might not confound me.</s> <s id="s851">But now, as we have ceased to dine, And I have had my share of wine, I should be glad to close the feast By drawing some more harmless beast."</s> <s id="s852">The Doctor found a quick consent, And to the farm their way they bent.</s> </p><p><s id="s853">A tub inverted, formed his seat; The animals their painter meet: Cows, asses, sheep, and ducks and geese, Present themselves, to grace the piece: Poor Grizzle, too, among the rest, Of the true picturesque possest, Quitted the meadow to appear, And took her station in the rear: The sheep all baaed, the asses brayed, The moo-cows lowed, and Grizzle neighed:" Stop, brutes," he cryed," your noisy glee; I do not want to hear - - but see; Though by the picturesquish laws, Youere better too with open jaws."</s></p>
<p><s id="s854">The Doctor now, with genius big, First drew a cow, and next a pig: A sheep now on the paper passes, And then he sketched a group of asses; Nor did he fail to do his duty In giving Grizzle all her beauty.</s> <s id="s855">" And now," says Miss,( a laughing elf)" I wish, Sir, you woued draw yourself."" With all my heart," the Doctor said," But not with horns upon my head."" - - And then I hope you'll draw my face!"" In vain, fair maid, my art would trace Those winning smiles, - - that native grace.</s> <s id="s856">The beams of beauty I disclaim; The picturesque' s my only aim: My pencil's skill is mostly shown In drawing faces like my own, Where Time, alas, and anxious Care, Have placed so many wrinkles there."</s></p>
<p><s id="s857">Now all beneath a spreading tree They chat, and sip their evening tea, Where Syntax told his various fate, His studious life and married state; And that he hoped his Tour would tend His comforts and his purse to mend.</s></p>
<p><s id="s858">At length they to the house retreated, And round the supper soon were seated; When the time quickly passed away, And gay good humour closed the day.</s></p><p><s id="s859">Canto XV.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s860">Virtue embraces every state; And, while it gilds the rich and great, It cheers their heart who humbly stray Along Life's more sequestered way: While, from beneath the portals proud, Wealth oft relieves the suppliant crowd; The wayworn pilgrim smiles to share, In lowly homes, the welcome fare.</s> <s id="s861">In splendid halls, and painted bowers Plenty may crown the festive hours; Yet still within the secret dell The hospitable Virtues dwell; And in this Isle, so brave and fair, Kind Charity is everywhere.</s> <s id="s862">Within the city's ample bound Her stately piles are seen around; Where every want, and every pain, That in man's feeble nature reign - - Where the sad heir of pining grief May, blessed be Heaven! obtain relief: While, on the humble village-green, How oft the low-roof'd pile is seen, Where poverty forgets its woes, And wearied age may find repose.</s></p>
<p><s id="s863">" Thrice happy Britons! while the car Of furious, unrelenting War Leaves the dire track of streaming gore On many a hapless, distant shore, - - While a remorseless tyrant's hand Deals misery, through each foreign land, And fell destruction, from the throne To him who doth the cottage own, - - Peace beams upon your sea-girt isle, Where the bright virtues ever smile; Where hostile shoutings never molest The happy inmate's genial rest.</s> <s id="s864">Wherever it is his lot to go, He will not meet an armed foe; Nay, wheresoever his way doth tend, He sure may chance to find a friend."</s></p>
<p><s id="s865">Thus, having rose at early day, As through the fields he took his way, The Doctor did his thoughts rehearse, And, as the Muse inspired, in verse: For, while with skill each form he drew, His Reverence was a poet too.</s></p>
<p><s id="s866">But soon a bell's shrill, tinkling sound Re Echoed all the meads around, And said as plain as bell could say - -" Breakfast is ready - - come away."</s> <s id="s867">The welcome summons he obeyed, And found an arbour's pleasing shade, Where, while the plenteous meal was spread, The woodbine flaunted over his head.</s></p>
<p><s id="s868">" Ah! little do the proud and great, Amid the pomp and toil of state,</s> </p><p><s id="s869"><enamex sw="w132972" long="-2.819475718201445" lat="54.16334316337664" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11189344" name="Know Hill" conf="2.079483676">Know</enamex> of those simple, real joys, With which the bosom never cloys! O! what a heart-reviving treat I find within this rural seat! All that can please the quickened taste.</s> <s id="s870">Is offered in this fair repast.</s> <s id="s871">The flowers, on their native bed, Around delicious odours shed; A bloom that with the floweret vies, On those fair cheeks, attracts my eyes; And what sweet music greets my ear, When that voice bids me welcome here! Indeed, each sense combines to bless The present hour with happiness."</s></p>
<p><s id="s872">Thus Syntax spoke, nor spoke in vain; The <enamex sw="w133509" long="-1.77831968367031" lat="54.08503022708322" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11189841" name="Ladies Riggs" conf="1.32037322">Ladies</enamex> felt the flattering strain; Nor could they do enough to please The Doctor for his courtesies: - -" All that you see, if that's a charm, Is, Sir, the produce of our farm: The rolls are nice, our oven bakes' em; Those oat-cakes too, my sister makes' em.</s> <s id="s873">The cream is rich, pray do not save it; The brindled cow you drew, Sir, gave it: And here is some fresh-gathered fruit - - I hope it will your palate suit:' Tis country fare which you receive, But' tis the best we have to give."</s></p>
<p><s id="s874">" O!" said the' Squire," the Doctor jokes With us poor harmless country folks: I wonder that with all his sense, And such a tickling eloquence,</s> </p><p><s id="s875">He has not tumed an humble priest Into a good fat dean, at least.</s> <s id="s876">We know how soon a Lady's ear Will list, the honey'd sound to hear: At the same time, I'm free to say I think the men as vain as they.</s> <s id="s877">How happens it my learned friend, That you have not attained your end; That all your figures and your tropes Have not fulfilled your rightful hopes? I should suppose your shining parts, And, above all, your flattering arts, Would soon have turned your grizzly mare Into a handsome chaise and pair.</s> <s id="s878">I live amidst my native groves, And the calm scene my nature loves: But still I know, and often see, What gains are made by flattery."</s></p>
<p><s id="s879">" That may be true," the Doctor said;" But flattery is not my trade.</s> <s id="s880">Indeed, dear Sir, you do me wrong - - No sordid interest guides my tongue.</s> <s id="s881">Honour and virtue I admire, Or in a Bishop, or a' Squire; But falsehood I most keenly hate, Though gilt with wealth, or crowned with state.</s> <s id="s882">For Truth I'm like a lion bold; And a base lie I never told: Indeed, I know, too many a sinner Will lie by dozens for a dinner; But from the days of earliest youth I've worshipped, as I've practised Truth: Nay, many a stormy, bitter strife I've had with my dear, loving wife,</s> </p><p><s id="s883">Who often says she might have seen Her husband a fine, pompous <enamex sw="w135421" long="-2.47619" lat="51.80857" type="other" gazref="unlock:13896283" name="Forest of Dean District" conf="0.7023050592">Dean</enamex>; - - Indeed, she sometimes thinks her spouse Might have a mitre on his brows, If, putting scruples out of view, Heed do as other people do.</s> <s id="s884">No - - I will never lie nor fawn, Nor flatter, to be robed in <enamex  sw="w135629" name="Too ambigious to allocate">lawn</enamex>.</s> <s id="s885">I too, can boast a certain rule Within the precincts of my school: Whatever faults I may pass by, I never can forgive a lie.</s> <s id="s886">I hate to use the birchen rod; But, when a boy forswears his God; When he in purposed falsehood deals, My heavy strokes the culprit feels.</s> <s id="s887">Vice I detest, whoever shows it, And, when I see it, I'll expose it: But, to kind hearts my homage due I willing pay, and pay to you; Nor will you, Sir, deny the share That's due to these two <enamex sw="w136096" long="-1.77831968367031" lat="54.08503022708322" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11189841" name="Ladies Riggs" conf="1.32037322">Ladies</enamex> fair."</s></p>
<p><s id="s888">The' Squire replied," I even must yield, And leave you master of the field: These ladies will, I'm sure agree That you have fairly conquered me; But, be assured, all joke apart, I feel your doctrine from my heart.</s> <s id="s889">Your free-born conduct I commend, And shall rejoice to call you friend; O! how it would my spirits cheer If you were but the Vicar here.</s> </p><p><s id="s890">Our Parson, I'm concerned to say, Had rather drink and game than pray.</s> <s id="s891">He makes no bones to curse and swear, In any rout to take a share, And what's still worse, he'll springe a hare.</s> <s id="s892">I wish his neck he would but break, Or tumble drunk into the Lake! For, know the Living's mine to give, And you should soon the Cure receive: The Benefice, I'm sure, is clear, At least three hundred pounds a year."</s></p>
<p><s id="s893">" I thank you, Sir, with all my heart," Said Syntax," but we now must part."</s> <s id="s894">The fair-ones cryed - -" We beg you'll stay, And pass with us another day."" - - <enamex sw="w137028" long="-1.77831968367031" lat="54.08503022708322" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11189841" name="Ladies Riggs" conf="1.32037322">Ladies</enamex>, I would' twere in my power, But I ca n't stay another hour: I feel your kindness to my soul, And wish I could my fate control.</s> <s id="s895">Within ten days the time will come When I shall be expected home; Nor is this all - - for strange to say, I must take <enamex sw="w137282" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.762992967">London</enamex> in my way."</s> <s id="s896">Thus converse kind the moments cheered, Till Grizzle at the gate appeared.</s> <s id="s897">" Well," said the' Squire," since you must go, Our hearty wishes we bestow: And if your genius bids you take Another journey to the Lake, Remember Worthy Hall, we pray, And come, and make a longer stay: Write too, and tell your distant friends With what success your journey ends.</s> </p><p><s id="s898">We do not mean it as a bribe, But to your work we must subscribe."</s> <s id="s899">The <enamex sw="w137731" long="-1.77831968367031" lat="54.08503022708322" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11189841" name="Ladies Riggs" conf="1.32037322">Ladies</enamex> too exclaimed - -" repeat Your visit to our northern seat."</s></p>
<p><s id="s900">Poor Syntax knew not how to tell The gratitude he felt so well; And, when at length he said - -" Good bye," A tear was bright in either eye.</s></p>
<p><s id="s901">The Doctor paced along the way Till it grew nigh the close of day, When the fair town appeared in sight, Where he proposed to pass the night: But when he reached the destined Inn, The landlord, with officious grin, At once declared he had no bed Where Syntax could repose his head: At least where such a reverend guest Would think it fit to take his rest.</s> <s id="s902">A main of cocks had fought that day, And all the gentry chose to stay.</s> <s id="s903">" Observe, my friend, I mind no cost," Says Syntax to his cringing host;" But still, at least, I may be able To sleep with Grizzle in the stable; And many a Doctor after all, Is proud to slumber in a stall: In short, I only want to sleep Where neither rogue nor knave can creep: I travel not with change of coats, But in these bags are all my notes; Which, should I lose, would prove my ruin, And be for ever, my undoing."</s> </p><p><s id="s904">Thus as he spoke, a lively blade, With dangling queue and smart cockade, Replyed at once," I have a room: The friend I looked for is not come; And of two beds where we may rest, You, my good Sir, shall have the best; So you may sleep without alarm; - - No living wight shall do you harm: You may depend upon my word; - - I serve the King, and wear a sword.'" Your offer, Sir, I kindly greet," Says Syntax," but you'll let me treat With what is best to drink and eat; And I request you will prepare To your own taste, the bill of fare."</s></p>
<p><s id="s905">The Doctor and the Captain sat, Till tired of each other's chat, They both agreed it would be best To seek the balmy sweets of rest.</s> <s id="s906">Syntax soon closed each weary eye, Nor thought of any danger nigh; While, like the ever-watchful snake, His sharp companion lay awake, Impatient to assail his prey; When, soon as it was dawn of day, He gently seized the fancied store; But, as he passed the creaking door, Syntax awoke, and saw the thief; When, loudly bawling for relief, He forward rushed in naked state, And caught the culprit at the gate: Against that gate his head he beat, Then kicked him headlong to <enamex sw="w139956" long="-2.550537094982595" lat="51.15293732249635" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11294325" name="Street on the Fosse" conf="1.272393948">the street</enamex>.</s> </p><p><s id="s907">The ostler, from his bed arose, In time to hear and see the blows.</s> <s id="s908">Says Syntax," I'll not make a riot; I've saved my notes, and I'll be quiet.</s> <s id="s909">The rascal, if I'm not mistaken, Will ask his legs to save his bacon: But what a figure I appear! I must not stand and shiver here; So take me back into the room, From whence in this strange way I'm come."</s> <s id="s910">The ostler then the Doctor led To the warm comforts of his bed.</s> <s id="s911">Into that bed he quickly crept, Beneath his head his bags he kept, And on that pillow safely slept.</s></p><p><s id="s912">Canto Xvi.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s913">Fair Virtue is its own reward, For Heaven remains its constant guard; And it becomes us all to trust In this grand truth - - that Heaven is just.</s> <s id="s914">Whatever forms the human lot, Whether in palace or in cot, In the calm track or frequent strife, Man leads his variegated life; Whether he feasts his smiling hours In stately halls or painted bowers; Whether he labours through the day In Winter cold, or Summer's ray; Or, in long nights of tortering pain, He strives to close his eyes in vain; Comfort will on his lot attend If Virtue be his bosom friend.</s> <s id="s915">In youth, when Love's creative power Forms the young Passion's roseate bower; When, life matured, the eager game That hunts for wealth, or seeks for fame, Is subtly played, with various art, To seize the mind and fill the heart: When Pleasure doth its charms display, And Syrens sing but to betray; If Virtue's called, it will defy The attack of every enemy.</s> </p><p><s id="s916">When age comes on, with stealing pace, And the crutch marks the closing race, Virtue supports her champion's cause, And cheers him with her fond applause: Nay, even at Death's resistless hour, She still displays her conscious power; Nor fails to make the flowerets bloom Round the dark confines of the tomb.</s></p>
<p><s id="s917">Thus Syntax pondered - - when around His head he turned, and grateful found His bags and notes all safe and sound: Pleased with the prospect, he was feign To yawn, and go to sleep again.</s></p>
<p><s id="s918">But, while he still enjoyed his dream, His story was the general theme Of every tongue, and made a din Through all the purlieus of the Inn.</s> <s id="s919">The ostler told it to the maid, And she the whole, and more, betrayed; Nay, in her idle eager prate, Mistook the window for the gate: For, though she lay all snug and quiet, And slept, unconscious of the riot, She swore that, all within her view, The Parson from the window threw A full-grown man into <enamex sw="w142358" long="-2.550537094982595" lat="51.15293732249635" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11294325" name="Street on the Fosse" conf="1.272393948">the street</enamex>, Who haply lighted on his feet, And then ran off, all through the dirt, With night-cap on, and half a shirt.</s></p>
<p><s id="s920">The Barber caught the story next, Who stuck no closer to the text; But left a man half - shaved and ran To tell it to the Clergyman.</s></p>
<p><s id="s921">" O! bless me, Sir," he cryed," I fear To utter, what you now must hear: At the <enamex sw="w142693" long="0.5105009608884064" lat="51.33753511696006" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:21003" name="Blue Bell Hill" conf="1.306290386">Blue Bell</enamex> there's been such doing - - The house, I'm certain, it must ruin; Nay, as I live, I'll tell no further, - - A Bishop has committed murther! He seized a Captain by the pate, And dashed it so against the gate, That all the planks are covered over With scattered brains and human gore.</s> <s id="s922">His Lordship gave him such a banging, That he will scarce escape with hanging.</s> <s id="s923">They quarrelled, Sir, as it was said, About the colours, black and red: The Captain manfully professed That the bright scarlet was the best; And they, who that fine colour wore, The first of all professions bore; - -" While black( it was not very civil) Was the known livery of the devil.</s> <s id="s924">Thus soon a loud dispute arose, Which from hard words went on to blows; And ended with this bloody strife, Which robbed the Captain of his life; And, if fair Justice does not faulter, Will deck the Bishop with a halter."</s> <s id="s925">The Parson smiled, and bid the calf Go home, and shave the other half: But, when he came, the impatient elf Had shaved the other half himself.</s></p>
<p><s id="s926">The Tailor laid aside his needle To hear the story from the Beadle, Who swore he had strange news to tell Of what had happened at the Bell: - -</s></p>
<p><s id="s927">" Would you believe it, that, last night, A highwayman, a man of might, Down in his bed a Lawyer bound, And robbed him of a thousand pound; Then gagged him, that he might not rouse The people sleeping in the house."" No, no," says Snip," however strong No gag will stop a Lawyer's tongue; And, after all, the stolen pelf, Is what, I'm sure, he stole himself; For, if the real truth we knew, He's the worst villain of the two! Theyere thieves in grain - - they never alter - - Attornies all deserve a halter.</s> <s id="s928">If that is all, I'll mind my stitches, Nor lay aside John Bumpkin's breeches.</s></p>
<p><s id="s929">The Blacksmith, while a trav' ller stayed That a new horse-shoe might be made, Informed him that a reverend Clerk Last night was strangled in the dark! No one knew how - -' twas at the Bell, - - The murderer - - not a soul could tell.</s> <s id="s930">The Justice though would make a rout, And try to find the fellow out.</s> <s id="s931">- - Thus Rumour spread the simple case, In every form, throughout the place.</s></p>
<p><s id="s932">The Doctor now unclosed his eyes, And thought that it was time to rise: So up he got, and down he went, To scold the Landlord fully bent; Who, pale, and trembling with affright At what had happened in the night,</s> </p><p><s id="s933">Approached with such an humble look, The Doctor's rage at once forsook His Christian breast; and with a voice That did the poor man's heart rejoice, He bid him soon as he was able, To let the coffee grace the table.</s> <s id="s934">" I do aver," the Landlord said," That, since I've carried on my trade, Since I've been master of the Bell, As all throughout the town can tell,( And that is now ten years or more,) I never knew such mishap before.</s> <s id="s935">The fellow, Sir, upon my word, Let loose his money like a Lord.</s> <s id="s936">I receive all who come this way, And care not, Sir, how long they stay, So they but eat and drink - - and pay.</s> <s id="s937">I ask not from whence people come, What is their name, or where their home.</s> <s id="s938">- - That he's a rogue, I think, is clear, Nor ever again shall enter here.</s> <s id="s939">He is some sharper, I suppose, Who round about the country goes; While to assist his lawless game, He takes the soldier's noble name.</s> <s id="s940">I understand the rogue you banged And in good time, Sir, he'll be hanged: I hope that all your notes you've found, - - I'm told theyere worth a thousand pound."" Prove that," says Syntax," my dear honey, And I will give you half the money.</s> <s id="s941">Think not, my friend, I'm such a fool, That I have been so late at school,</s> </p><p><s id="s942">To put my bank-notes in a bag That hangs across my Grizzle nag.</s> <s id="s943">No, they were notes to make a book; The thief my meaning, friend, mistook: For know, the man would not have found Them worth - - to him - - a single pound; Though much I hope that they will be The source of many a pound to me."</s> <s id="s944">Thus Syntax cheered the Landlord's heart Till the time warned him to depart; When soon, along the beaten road, Poor Grizzle bore her reverend load.</s></p>
<p><s id="s945">The Doctor's pleasant thoughts beguile The journey onward many a mile: For many a mile he had not seen But one unvarying, level green; Nor had the way one object brought, That waked a picturesquish thought.</s> <s id="s946">A spire, indeed, across the down, Seemed to denote a neighbering town; And that he viewed with some delight - - For there he hoped to pass the night.</s></p>
<p><s id="s947">A farmer now, so blithe and gay, Came trotting briskly on his way.</s> <s id="s948">" Will you," says Syntax," tell me, friend, If to yon town this way doth tend?"" This road, good Sir, will take you there: Youere surely going to the fair;' Tis the first mart both far and near, For horses, cows, and such-like gear; And, from the beast I've in my eye, Youere going, Sir, a nag to buy:</s> </p><p><s id="s949">I think, if I the truth may tell, You have not got a nag to sell; For not a person in the fair Will give ten shillings for your mare."</s> <s id="s950">Syntax, who dearly loved a joke, And long had lived' mong country folk; Thought he could work a little mirth Out of this rustic son of earth: So thus the conversation flowed, As they jogged on the beaten road.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s951">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s952">" Believe me, Farmer, long together, In sun-shine, and in stormy weather, My mare and I have trotted on, Nor is as yet our labour done; And, though her figure you despise, Did you but know her qualities, You would not rate her quite so low As now you seem disposed to do.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s953">Farmer.</s></p>
<p><s id="s954">" I'll lay a pound, if you are willing, She does not fetch you twenty shilling."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s955">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s956">" First, my good friend, one truth I'll tell; - - I do not want my mare to sell: While to lay wagers I am loth; - - The practice would disgrace my cloth: Nor ever, while Life's path I trace, Will I my sacred rank disgrace: But yet I think you under-rate Poor Grizzle's qualities and state:</s> </p><p><s id="s957">" Tis true, she's past the age of beauty; Yet still the old girl does her duty; And some one surely will be found To think, at least, she's worth a pound: Nay, to amuse the country-folk, We'll put her up, by way of joke, But no one must the wager smoke: And I propose that, if you lose,( No Christian will the bet refuse) The money to the poor you'll give, - -' Twill be a Christian donative: And if my old and faithful mare Should be so treated in the fair, That not a person would be willing To offer for her twenty shilling, On honour I will do the same, As sure as Syntax is my name.</s> <s id="s958">Such are the terms that I propose, So let us now the bargain close."" Give me your hand," the Farmer said," The terms I'll keep; - - the bargain's made."</s> <s id="s959">Thus they rode on and reached the town: - - The pipe and bowl the evening crown.</s></p>
<p><s id="s960">The morrow came, and through the fair The Farmer led the grizzle mare.</s> <s id="s961">Says one," I would not bid a pound; She's only fit to feed a hound; But would a hound the gift receive, For she has nought but bones to give? Where must we look her ears to find? And faith she's left her tail behind."" Why," says another," view her scars: She must have left them in the wars."</s></p>
<p><s id="s962">As a warm Yeoman passed along, He heard the jeerings of the throng, And felt a strong desire to know What pleased the laughing people so.</s> <s id="s963">" A parson, Sir," says one," distressed, Wants to sell that poor, wretched beast; And asks, I hear, a pound or two: I think he'll never get that from you."" If that's the case," the yeoman said, - -" I'll ease his heart, and buy the jade.</s> <s id="s964">I'll bid two pounds, my friend, that's plain, And give him back his beast again."</s></p>
<p><s id="s965">The Farmer owned the wager lost, And oped his bag to pay the cost.</s> <s id="s966">" No, Sir," says Syntax,""' tis to you To pay wherever you think it due: But, as we passed the Common over, I saw, beside a cottage door, A woman, with a spinning-wheel, Who turned her thread around the reel, While joyful frolicked by her side Three children, all in Nature's pride; And I resign it to your care To leave the welcome bounty there."</s></p>
<p><s id="s967">The Yeoman, when he heard the joke, In friendly words to Syntax spoke.</s> <s id="s968">" I, Sir, an humble mansion own, About five furlongs from the town; And there your Reverence I invite To go and dine, and pass the night.</s> <s id="s969">To Day I give an annual feast, Where you will be a welcome guest.</s> </p><p><s id="s970">I love the cloth, - - and humbly crave That we may there your blessing have.</s> <s id="s971">Come then, and bring your mare along: Come, share the feast, and hear the song; And in the evening will be seen The merry dancers on the green."" With joy," said Syntax," I receive The invitation which you give; In your kind feast I'll bear a part, And bring with me a grateful heart."" I," said the Yeoman," must be gone: But shall expect you, Sir, at one."</s> <s id="s972">Nor did the Doctor long delay: To the farm-house he took his way; And changed the bustle of the fair, For a kind, noiseless welcome there.</s></p><p><s id="s973">Canto Xvii.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s974">Ye Courtesies of life, all hail! Whether along the peaceful vale, Where the thatched cot alone is seen, The humble mansion of the green, Or in the city's crowded way, Man - - mortal man, is doomed to stray; You give to joy an added charm, And woe of half its pangs disarm.</s> <s id="s975">How much in every state he owes To what kind Courtesy bestows - - To that benign engaging art Which decorates the human heart - - And, free from jealousy and strife, Gilds all the charities of life.</s> <s id="s976">To every act it gives a grace; It adds a smile to every face: And Goodness' self we better see When dressed by gentle Courtesy.</s></p>
<p><s id="s977">Thus Syntax, as the house he sought, Indulged the grateful, pleasing thought; And soon he stepped the threshold over, Where the good Farmer went before.</s> <s id="s978">Plenty appeared, and many a guest Attended on the welcome feast.</s> <s id="s979">The Doctor then, with solemn face, Proceeded to the appointed place, And, in due form, pronounced the grace.</s> </p><p><s id="s980">That thankful ceremony done, The fierce attack was soon begun; While meat and pudding, fowl and fish, All vanished from each ample dish.</s> <s id="s981">The dinner over, the bowl appeared; The enlivening draughts their spirits cheered; Nor did the pleasant Doctor fail, Between the cups of foaming ale, To gain the laugh by many a tale.</s> <s id="s982">But it so haped - - among the rest - - The Farmer's Landlord was a guest; A buckish blade, who kept a horse, To try his fortune on the course; Was famous for his fighting cocks, And his staunch pack to chase <enamex sw="w152899" long="-1.848431612229573" lat="51.58578504263394" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11299036" name="The Fox" conf="1.285328219">the fox</enamex>: Indeed, could he a booby bite, Heed play at cards throughout the night; Nor was he without hopes to get Syntax to make some silly bet.</s> <s id="s983">" I never bet," the Doctor said, While a deep frown his thoughts betrayed:" Your gold I do not wish to gain, And mine shall in my purse remain: No tempting card, no gambling art, Shall make it from my pocket start.</s> <s id="s984">Gaming, my worthy Sir, I hate; It neither suits my means nor state:' Tis the worst passion, I protest, That's known to haunt the human breast; Of all vile habitudes the worst - - The most delusive and accurst: And, if you please, I'll lay before you A very melancholy story; Such as, I think, will wring your heart, And wound you in the tenderest part;</s> </p><p><s id="s985">That will in striking colours shew The biting pangs, the bitter woe, That do, too oft, from gaming flow."</s></p>
<p><s id="s986">" Nay," said the' Squire," I do n't deny I often like my luck to try; And no one here, I'm sure will say That when I lose I do not pay; But, as you think it such a sin, Pray try to cure me - - and begin."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s987">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s988">" How many of the human kind, Who to their common honour blind, Look not in any path to stray But where fell Passion leads the way; Who, born with every real claim To wear the fairest wreath of Fame, Reject the good by Nature given, And scoff at every boon of Heaven! Yes; such there are, and such we find At every point that gives the wind: But, when among the crowd we see One whom, in prodigality, Fortune and Nature had combined To fill his purse and form his mind: Whose manly strength is graced with ease, And has the happy power to please; Whose cooler moments never heard The frantic vow to Heaven preferred; And near whose steps Repentance bears The vase of purifying tears; When such a victim we behold, Urged by the rampant lust of gold, Yielding his health, his life, his fame, As off erings to the god of game;</s> </p><p><s id="s989">The tear grows big in Virtue's eye, Pale Reason heaves the poignant sigh; The guardian spirit turns away, And hell enjoys a holiday.</s></p>
<p><s id="s990">" Is there on earth a hellish vice? There is, my firiend - -' tis avarice.</s> <s id="s991">Has avarice a more hellish name? It has, my friend, - - the lust of game.</s> <s id="s992">All this, perhaps, you'll thus deny: - -" There's no one, with more grace than I, Lets shillings drop and guineas fly.</s> <s id="s993">To the dejected hapless friend My door I ope, my purse I lend; To purchase joy my wealth I give, And like a man of fashion live."</s> <s id="s994">This may be true - - but still your breast Is with the love of gold possest.</s> <s id="s995">Why watch whole nights the fatal card, Or look to dice for your reward? Why risk your real wealth with those Whom you know not, and no one knows: With maggots whom foul Fortune's ray Has raised from dunghills into day; Who would in your misfortune riot, And seek your ruin for their diet? Pleasure it cannot be, for pains Will mingle with your very gains - - Will hover round the golden store, Which, ere the passing moment's over, May, horrid chance! be your's no more.</s></p>
<p><s id="s996">" As yet, you cannot use the plea Of beggared men - - necessity.</s> </p><p><s id="s997">Plenty as yet adorns your board, And numerous vassals own you Lord.</s> <s id="s998">Your woods look fair - - their trunks increase The Hamadryads live in peace: But cards and dice, more powerful far Than even the sharpest axes are; At one dire stroke have oft been found To level forests with the ground: Have seized the mansion's lofty state, And turned its master from the gate.</s></p>
<p><s id="s999">" A youth in wealth and fashion bred, But by the love of gaming led, Soon found that ample wealth decay; Farm after farm was played away, Till, the sad histery to complete, His park, his lawns, his ancient seat, Were all in haste and hurry sold, To raise the heaps of ready gold.</s> <s id="s1000">They, like the rest, soon passed away, The villains' gain, the sharper's prey; While he, alas! resolved to shun The arts by which he was undone, Sought, by hard labour, to sustain His weary life of woe and pain; But Nature soon refused to give The strength by which he strove to live; And nought was left him but to try What casual pity would supply; To stray where chance or hunger led, And humbly ask for scanty bread.</s> <s id="s1001">One day, to his despairing eyes, He saw a stately mansion rise; Nor long he looked before he knew Each wood and copse that round it grew;</s> </p><p><s id="s1002">For all the scene that seemed so fair, Once knew in his a master's care.</s> <s id="s1003">Struck with the sight, and sore oppressed, He sought a bank whereon to rest: There long he lay, and sighed his grief; - - Tears came - - but did not bring relief.</s> <s id="s1004">At last he took his tottering way Where once he loved so well to stray, And, pressed by hunger, sought the gate Where suppliant Want was used to wait - - Where suppliant Want was never denyed The morsel left by glutted Pride.</s> <s id="s1005">But, ah! those generous times were over, And suppliant Want relieved no more.</s> <s id="s1006">The mastiff growled - - the liveried thief With insolence denyed relief.</s> <s id="s1007">The wretch, dissolving in a groan, Turned from the portal, once his own; But ere he turned, he told his name, And cursed once more the love of game: Then sought <enamex sw="w157924" long="-0.214" lat="51.43379" type="other" gazref="unlock:5830748" name="The All England Lawn Tennis Club" conf="0.9774804801">the lawn</enamex>, for Nature failed, And sorrow over his strength prevailed.</s> <s id="s1008">Beneath an oak's wide-spreading shade His weary limbs he careless laid; Then called on Heaven: - -( the bitter prayer Of Misery finds admittance there!) And ere the sun, with parting ray, Had heightened the last blush of day, Sunk and worn out with want and grief, He found in death a kind relief.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1009">" The oak records the doleful tale, Which makes the conscious reader pale; And tells - -" In this man's fate behold The love of play - - the lust of gold."</s> </p><p><s id="s1010">No moral, Sir, shall I impart; I trust you feel it in your heart.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1011">Youere young, you'll say, and must engage In the amusements of the age.</s> <s id="s1012">Go then, and let your mountain bare, The forest's verdant livery wear; Let Parian marble grace your hall, And Titian glow upon your wall; Its narrow channels boldly break, And swell your riv' let to a lake: To richer harvests bend your soil, While labour fattens in the toil: Encourage Nature, and impart The half - transparent veil of Art.</s> <s id="s1013">Let Music charm your melting breast, And soothe each passion into rest; Let Genius from your hand receive The bounty that can make it live; And call the Muses from on high, To give you immortality.</s> <s id="s1014">To these, the hardy pleasures join, Where Exercise and Health combine: At the first opening of the morn, <enamex sw="w159239" long="-4.359584582968855" lat="55.37465504283097" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11237782" name="Over Hill" conf="1.018406391">Over hill</enamex> and dale, with hound and horn, Boldly pursue the subtle prey, And share the triumphs of the day: Nor let the evening hours roll Unaided by the social bowl; Nor should fair Friendship be away, But crown with smiles the festive day.</s> <s id="s1015">Say, need I add the joys they prove Who live in bonds of virtuous love.</s> <s id="s1016">Where fond affection fills the heart, The baser passions shall depart:</s> </p><p><s id="s1017">While the babe hangs on Beauty's breast, While in a parent's arms caressed, Each low-bred thought, all vicious aims, The pure, domestic mind disclaims.</s> <s id="s1018">Virtue inspires his every sense, Who looks on cherub innocence: Then seek a shield' gainst passion's strife In the calm joys of wedded life.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1019">" This is to live, and to enjoy Those pleasures which our pains destroy: This is to live, and to receive The praises which the good will give: This is to make that use of wealth Which heightens even the flush of health; Improves the heart, and gives a claim To a fair, fragrant wreath of Fame.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1020">" I thank you, Sir," the Farmer said; - -"' Tis a sad tale you have displayed.</s> <s id="s1021">How I the poor man's lot deplore! The more I think, I feel the more; And much I wish my Landlord too Would keep his wretched fate in view; But while my poor good woman weeps, Behold how very sound he sleeps.</s> <s id="s1022">I beg that we may change the scene, And join the dancers on the green."</s>  <s id="s1023"><enamex sw="w160582" long="" lat="" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZC" name="" conf="99991">Sal</enamex> now exclaimed," The people say Ralph is so drunk he cannot play:"" Then I'll be fiddler," Syntax cryed;" By me his place shall be supplyed.</s> <s id="s1024">Never fear, my lasses, you shall soon Be ambling to some pretty tune,</s> </p><p><s id="s1025">And in a measured time shall beat The green sod with your nimble feet.</s> <s id="s1026">While Virtue over your pleasure reigns, Youere welcome to my merry strains; While Virtue smiles upon your joy, I'll gladly my best skill employ; For, sure,' twill give me great delight To be your fiddler through the night.</s> <s id="s1027">I know full well I do not err From any point of character: To Heaven I cannot give offence While I enliven innocence: For thus to virtuous man' tis given To dance, and sing, and go to Heaven.</s> <s id="s1028">Your merry minstrelsy prolong, And to your dances add the song: Even while you caper, loudly sing In honour of your noble King."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1029">Chorus Of Peasants.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1030">" Strike, strike the lyre! awake the sounding shell! How happy we who in these vallies dwell! How blest we live beneath his gentle sway, Whom mighty realms and distant seas obey! Make him, propitious Heaven! your choicest care! O make him happy as his people are!"</s></p>
<p><s id="s1031">' Twas thus they fiddled, danced, and sung: With harmless glee the village rung: At length dull Midnight bid them close A day of joy, with calm repose.</s></p><p><s id="s1032">Canto Xviii.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s1033">Let Grandeur blush, and think how few Of all the many - coloured crew, The motley group of fools and knaves, Who hourly prove themselves its slaves, However fashion gilds the dress, Attain the expected happiness! Let Grandeur blush, and blushing own How seldom is to greatness known, That pure and unembittered lot Which often cheers the peasant's cot; The hallowed bliss, the nameless charm, That decorates the fertile farm.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1034">Thus Syntax pondered as his eye Surveyed the cheerful family: Who eround the breakfast-table seated, With one accord his entrance greeted: At the same time, they all expressed Much sorrow that their reverend guest Had ordered Grizzle to the door, In order to pursue his Tour.</s> <s id="s1035">" Doctor, I'm grieved so soon to part," Burst from the Yeoman's friendly heart;" Yet hope, whenever you this way come, You'll not forget you have a home: - -</s> </p><p><s id="s1036">You see how we poor farmers live, - - A welcome's all we have to give; But that's sincere - - so come and try."</s> <s id="s1037">A few kind words were the reply.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1038">Syntax once more his beast bestrode; He bade farewell, and off he rode.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1039">Now Nature's beauties caught his eye, Arrayed in gay simplicity; And as he passed the road along, The blackbird's note, and thrush's song, With musical and native mirth, Seemed to do homage to his worth.</s> <s id="s1040">The varyed landscape here combined To fascinate the eye and mind, To charm the gazer's every sense From the commanding eminence.</s> <s id="s1041">The expanding plain, with plenty crowned, Diffuses health and fragrance round; While, on a lofty, craggy height, A castle rises to the sight, Which in its day of strength and pride, The arms of threatening foes defyed.</s> <s id="s1042">Beneath the mouldering abode In mazy course a riv' let flowed; And, free from the tempestuous gale, Its silent stream refreshed the vale.</s> <s id="s1043">The vale the scattered hamlet cheered, And many a straw-roof'd cot appeared; While smiling groups at every door Spoke grief a stranger to the poor.</s> <s id="s1044">With pious thought, and eye serene, Syntax surveyed the enchanting scene, And thus in grateful mood began: - -" So deals the omnipotent with man.</s> </p><p><s id="s1045">Such are thy gifts, all gracious power! To us, the creatures of an hour: And yet how oft we barter these; How oft we risk our health and ease, Thy best bequest, thy choicest treasure, For follies which we misname pleasure; And slaves to vanity and art, Check the best feelings of the heart.</s> <s id="s1046">How the scene charms the ravished eye! I cannot, will not, pass it by," He said, - - and from his pocket took The pencil, and the sketching-book; While Grizzle, in contented mood, Close by her busy master stood: When, clouds of dust proclaimed the approach Of something Syntax deemed a coach.</s> <s id="s1047">Four wheels in truth it had to boast, Although what it resembled most Were hard to say: - - suffice, this tub Was built in <enamex sw="w164669" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.762992967">London</enamex>, where a club, Yclept Four Horse, is now the rage, And famed for whims in equipage.</s> <s id="s1048">Dashers! who once a month assemble; Make creditors and coachmen tremble; And, dressed in colours vastly fine.</s> <s id="s1049">Drive to some public-house to dine; There game, and drink, and swear, and then - - Drive in disorder back again.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1050">Now Syntax, with some kind of fear, Beheld the vehicle draw near; And, like her master, Grizzle too Was far from happy at the view;</s> </p><p><s id="s1051">For a long whip had caught her eye Moving about most rapidly; Though little thought the hapless nag, The joke which the exalted wag, Who held the reins with skilful hand, Against both mare and master planned.</s> <s id="s1052">But now the curious Doctor spyed The emblem of Patrician pride; Which on the panels of the coach Proclaimed a noble Lord's approach: Nay,( for the facts will plainly prove it) It was a noble Lord who drove it; For' tis well known to men of rank That Lords will sometimes play a prank; And thus indulge themselves in jokes As low as those of vulgar folks.</s> <s id="s1053">But' tis not easy to express The wild surprize, the deep distress, Which Syntax felt, when this same Lord Aimed at his back the flaunting cord; And when the whip, with skilful turn, Was well applied to Grizzle's stern; - - That stern, enough to make one shudder, Which we all know, had lost its rudder: - - Her rage appeared in either eye, And then she neighed indignantly.</s> <s id="s1054">Such seemed she as when erst she bore A trumpeter to fields of gore; When, in the battle's heat, at large, She led whole squadrons to the charge; While Syntax, as she scoured the plain, Indulged the moralizing strain.</s> <s id="s1055">" Can I, in this foul conduct scan The Peer, or well bred Gentleman?</s> </p><p><s id="s1056">Or rather must not Virtue frown On such a high-born, titled clown? Thus, then, do Nobles play the fool? A conduct which in my poor school, If' mong my boys it dare appear; If they should ape that monkey there; They for their fun should pay full dearly; - - Ied whip the blackguards most severely.</s> <s id="s1057">But I'll not waste another word Upon this vulgar, booby Lord; For I have something else to do, - - And Grizzle, what's become of you?" A farmer's well-stored barn, hard by, Attracted her observing eye, Where many a truss of fragrant hay Induced the prudent beast to stay.</s> <s id="s1058">Meanwhile, her discontented master, Reflecting on the late disaster, Paced slowly on, brimful of care, And wondered who had got his mare.</s> <s id="s1059">Indeed, he feared she might be found Within the precincts of a pound; But soon his quadruped he saw, Up to her girths in hay and straw: While he, who owned the neighbering farm, Prepared to raise his weighty arm; And, having just observed the theft, Brandished a horsewhip right and left,( Alas! it cannot be denyed,) To lay about on Grizzle's hide.</s> <s id="s1060">Syntax beheld the harsh intent:" Forbear," he cried," the punishment! Why make her feel the chastening thong? She knows not she is doing wrong.</s> </p><p><s id="s1061">Forgive my warmth, but truly, Sir, This suits not with the character Of one who treads on British ground, - - A land for justice so renowned: I'll pay for all the straw that's wasted, And all the hay that she has tasted; Your courtesy I now invoke, So name the cost, and spare the stroke."</s></p>
<p><s id="s1062">The Farmer paused - - as by a charm - - And dropped at once the uplifted arm: - -" Forgive me, Sir, for what," he cried," Cannot indeed be justified: But for my haste, I'll make amends; And let us now, good Sir, be friends.</s> <s id="s1063">That is my house: - - you'll enter there, And, Thomas, take the Doctor's mare.</s> <s id="s1064">Come, reverend Sir, I'll lead the way:" The Doctor did not disobey, And soon was met with welcome glee, By all the Farmer's family.</s> <s id="s1065">At length some business of the day Summoned the honest host away; So Syntax thought heed look about, To find some curious object out; When, lo! a dairy met his view, Where, full of cream, in order due, The pans, the bowls, the jugs were placed, Which tempted the Divine to taste; But he found something better there: - - A village damsel young and fair Attracted his admiring eye; Who, as he entered, heaved a sigh.</s> </p><p><s id="s1066">Now Syntax, as we all must know, Never heard a sigh or tale of woe, But instant wished to bring relief - - To dry the tear and soothe the grief.</s> <s id="s1067">" Come here, sweet girl," he softly said;" Tell me your cares - - nor be afraid: Come here, and seat you by my side; You'll find in me a friendly guide.</s> <s id="s1068">Relate your sorrows, - - tell the truth; What is it? does some perjured youth Unfaithful to his promise prove, Nor make the fond return of love?' Tis so, I see; but raise your eye; On me, my pretty girl, rely: You have my tenderest sympathy Again, I say, your grief impart; You've gained an interest in my heart: For well I know the pangs they prove Who grieve for unrequited love."</s></p>
<p><s id="s1069">The listening mother, who had heard Love talked of, kindled at the word; And, rushing in, expressed her rage: - -" For shame! for shame! while hoary age Whitens your head, I see your eye Is beaming with iniquity.</s> <s id="s1070">Begone, you old, you wanton goat! Your heart is black as is your coat.</s> <s id="s1071">A parson too! may Heaven forgive The wicked age in which we live! I'll go and tell my honest spouse The snake he harbours in his house: He'll give such hypocrites their due, I'll warrant it;" and off she flew.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1072">The host arrived, but by that time The fidse alarm, the imputed crime, Nancy had ventured to unfold, And mother now had ceased to scold; While, the rude anger turned to mirth, They all confess the Doctor's worth.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1073">Dinner was soon upon the table, And Grizzle feeding in the stable; While joyful Syntax, once again, Forgot past accidents and pain; And, when night came, reposed his head In peace, upon the welcome bed: But never did he to sleep consign His weary limbs, till to the shrine Of Heaven, he had addressed the prayer Which ever finds admittance there.</s></p><p><s id="s1074">Canto Xix.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s1075">The sun arose in all its pride!" Hail the bright orb," the Doctor cried," That makes the distant mountains glow, And clears the misty vales below! O! let me bless the Power divine That bade its splendid fires to shine; Invigorating warmth to give To all that grow, and all that live: Which, in the bowels of the earth, Brings the rich metal into birth; Or, piercing through the secret mine, Makes rubies blush, and di' monds shine: While man, the first, the head of all That breathes upon this earthly ball, As freely feels its force as they, Of insect tribe, who, in its ray, Pass their short hour, and pass away.</s> <s id="s1076">O, what a picture greets my sight! How my heart revels in delight, While I behold the advancing day <enamex sw="w171226" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.136201402">Over</enamex> the wide scene its power display! While, as I gaze, the enchanted eye Drinks in the rich variety! How the gleam brightens yonder tower! How deep the shade within the bower! The spreading oak and elm between, How fine those blushes intervene!</s> </p><p><s id="s1077">Those brilliant lights! - - they would demand Claude's pencil, or a Titian's hand! Even while the distant hills I view, Their orient colours change to blue.</s> <s id="s1078">The stream, within whose silver wave, Poets might see the Naiads lave, Now, lost in shade, no more is seen To flow among the alders green: But, let the eye its course pursue, Again it brightens in the view, Reflecting as its current flows, Each flower that on the margin blows.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1079">Hail, favoured casement! where the sight Is courted to enjoy delight! T' ascend the hill, and trace the plain, Where lavish Nature's proud to reign; Unlike those pictures that impart The windows of Paladian art, From whence no other object's seen But gravel-walk, or shaven green; Planned by the artist on his desk; - - Pictures that are not picturesque. But I should not perform my duty Did I relinquish all this beauty; Nor snatch, from this expansive view, Some pretty little scene or two.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1080">The cot that's all bewhitened over, With children plajring at the door, A peasant hanging over the hatch, And the vine mantling on the thatch, While the thick coppice, down the hill, Throws its green umbrage over the rill, Whose stream drives on the busy mill; In pleasing group their forms combine, And suit a pencil such as mine.</s> </p><p><s id="s1081">Nor shall I miss the branchy screen Of those fine elms, that hide the green, <enamex sw="w172826" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.136201402">Over</enamex> which the tapering spire is seen.</s> <s id="s1082">I'll add no more - - for, to my mind, The scene's complete - - and well designed.</s> <s id="s1083">There are, indeed, who would insert Those pigs, which wallow in the dirt; And, though I hold a pig is good Upon a dish, prepared for food, I do not fear to say the brute Does not my taste in painting suit; For I most solemnly aver, That he from genuine taste must err, Who flouts at grace or character; And there's as much in my old wig As can be found about a pig; For, to say truth, I do n't inherit This self-same picturesquish spirit, That looks to nought but what is rough, And never thinks Nature coarse enough.</s> <s id="s1084">Their system does my genius shock, Who see such graces in a dock; Whose eye the picturesque admires In straggling brambles, and in briers; Nay, can a real beauty see In a decayed and rotten tree.</s> <s id="s1085">I hate with them the trim of Art; But from this rule I'll never depart - -; In grandame Nature's vast collection, To make a fair and fit selection, Which, when in happy contrast joined, Delights the informed, well-judging mind."</s></p>
<p><s id="s1086">But lo! the Farmer, at the gate, Proclaimed aloud, the hour of eight;</s> </p><p><s id="s1087">And Syntax now in haste descends.</s> <s id="s1088">To join his kind, expecting friends.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1089">" Well," said his host," another day I trust your Reverence will stay."" I thank you for the offer made, But that ca n't be," the Doctor said;" I have a weary way to go, And much to see, and more to know; Indeed so far I've got so roam, A fortnight scarce will take me home; And, thanking you for all your care, I must beg leave to seek my mare."</s> <s id="s1090">Grizzle was quickly to be found; And, as the good folks stood around, Syntax thought proper to discourse Upon the virtues of his horse; Nor did he fail at large to tell That she had served him passing well; While he forgot not to bewail Her loss of ears, and loss of tail: For though among the passing folk, His beast created many a joke; And though the foul and sad disaster Oft forced a laugh against the master; They should not part while he was able To keep himself and keep a stable; Nay, to the last heed cut and carve, That his poor Grizzle might not starve.</s> <s id="s1091">Thus, as her histery he recounted, Into the saddle up he mounted; And there for some time having sat, He closed at length, his farewell chat.</s> <s id="s1092">He thought it best t' avoid caressing; So gave no kiss, but gave his blessing.</s> </p><p><s id="s1093">- - On home, on book, on fame, intent, The Doctor pondered as he went: At night he looked his papers over, And added to the learned store: But the next morn, another scene, The vast expanse of liquid green - - The ocean's self - - broke on his eye, In inexpressive majesty.</s> <s id="s1094">There, as he looked, full many a sail Gave its white canvass to <enamex sw="w175527" long="-3.331238891935261" lat="54.83292999033717" type="other" gazref="unlock:11149426" name="Gale, The" conf="1.694606476">the gale</enamex>; And many a freighted vessel bore Its treasure to the British shore: When, as he traced the winding coast, In praise and admiration lost, Up Rising in the distant view, Half Seen through the ethereal blue, A city's stately form appeared; Upon the shore the mass was reared, With glistening spires, while below Masts like a forest seemed to grow.</s> <s id="s1095">' Twas Liverpool, that splendid mart, Imperial <enamex sw="w175931" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.762992967">London</enamex>'s counterpart, Where wandering Mersey's rapid streams Rival the honours of the <enamex sw="w176017" long="-0.2985421493649483" lat="51.43580055236816" type="civila" gazref="unlock:14121770" name="Richmond upon Thames" conf="1.753689498">Thames</enamex>; And bear, on each returning tide, Whatever by commerce is supplyed: Whatever the winds can hurry over From every clime and distant shore.</s> <s id="s1096">Thus Syntax paced along the strand, Through this fine scene of sea and land.</s> <s id="s1097">But nearer now the town appears, The hum of men salutes his ears; And soon amid the noisy din He found the comforts of an Inn.</s> </p><p><s id="s1098">He eat, he drank, his pipe he smoked, And with the Landlord quaintly joked; But, ever he slept, he passed an hour In adding something to his Tour; Then sought his couch, in hopes the morn Would with new thoughts the page adorn.</s> <s id="s1099">The morning came - - he sallied out To breathe the air, and look about.</s> <s id="s1100">Wherever he turned, his every sense Grasped one vast scene of opulence: In all he saw there was displayed The proud magnificence of trade.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1101">Syntax an humble scholar bred, With nought but learning in his head; Profound, indeed, in classic art, And goodness reigning in his heart; Yet forty pounds a year was all He could his fixed revenue call; For which, on every Sabbath Day, He went eight miles to preach and pray.</s> <s id="s1102">His school too, brought but little gains, And scarce repaid him for his pains: It gave,' tis true, to drink and eat; It furnished him with bread and meat, And kept the wolf without the door; But Syntax still was very poor.</s> <s id="s1103">His wife, indeed, had got the art, To keep herself a little smart; Yet he, good man, was always seen With scanty coat, and figure mean: But still he never threw aside The pedant's air - - the pedant's pride.</s> <s id="s1104">Thus, through the streets of this rich place, He strutted with his usual grace:</s> </p><p><s id="s1105">And thus he walked about the town, As if its wealth had been his own: But of his wealth he could not vapour - - Twelve guineas, and a piece of paper( The present of a noble Lord), Was all his pockets did afford: Though still the lining of his coat Secreted' Squire Hearty's note.</s> <s id="s1106">And now he thought' twould not be rash To turn the paper into cash.</s> <s id="s1107">Thus, at his breakfast, while he sat, And social joined the common chat, He took occasion to inquire Who would comply with his desire: Who would his anxious wish fulfil, And give him money for his bill.</s> <s id="s1108">An arch young sprig, a banker's clerk, Resolved to hoax the reverend spark, And counselled him to take a range Among the Merchants on the' Change.</s> <s id="s1109">" Some one, perhaps, may want to send A payment to a <enamex sw="w178363" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.762992967">London</enamex> friend; He'll in your wishes gladly join, And take the draft and pay the coin."</s></p>
<p><s id="s1110">The Barber now the Doctor sheared, And soon whipped off his three - days' beard, His wig, which had not felt a comb, Not once since he had quitted home, Was destined now to friz and twirl To be tormented into curl: His coat, which long had ta' en the rust, Was soon deprived of all the dust: His gaiters too, were fresh japanned; Such were the Doctor's stern command:</s> </p><p><s id="s1111">And now with spirits fresh and gay, To the Exchange he took his way, To try in this commercial town A little commerce of his own.</s> <s id="s1112">The Exchange soon met his wondering sight; The structure filled him with delight.</s> <s id="s1113">" Such are the fruits of trading knowledge! Learning," he cried," builds no such college! Indeed, I entertain a notion,( I speak the thought with true devotion,) Though we in Holy Scripture read That <enamex sw="w179236" long="35.19389" lat="33.27333" type="other" gazref="unlock:14211298" name="Tyrus" conf="0.7222346518">Tyre</enamex> and <enamex sw="w179245" long="35.25" lat="33.75" type="other" gazref="unlock:14190994" name="Sidon" conf="0.7496535051">Sidon</enamex> did exceed In wealth, the cities of the world, Where ships their wandering sails unfurled; That even her merchants bore the bell In eating and in drinking well; Were richer than the lordly great, And vyed with princes in their state; Yet, with all their power and rule, I think that they never went to school In such a' Change as <enamex sw="w179584" long="-2.878238320350647" lat="53.5225887298584" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131229" name="Liverpool" conf="2.132021068">Liverpool</enamex>."</s></p>
<p><s id="s1114">He entered now - - and heard within The crowded mart - - a buzzing din - - A sound confused, the serenade Of ardent gain, and busy trade: At length, his penetrating eye Was thrown around him, to descry Some one in whose sleek, smiling face He could the lines of kindness trace: And soon a person he addressed, Whose paunch projected from his breast; Who, looking with good-humour fraught, Appeared the very man he sought: When, with an unassuming grace, To him he thus disclosed his case: - -</s> </p><p><s id="s1115">" I beg this paper you'll peruse; And then, perhaps, you'll not refuse The favour which I ask to grant, And give the money that I want; The draft is good - - and, on my word, It was a present from a Lord,"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1116">Merchant.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1117">" That may be true: but Lords, I fear, Will meet but little credit here:' Tis a fair draft upon the view - - Yes! he's a Lord - - but who are you?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1118">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1119">" Look, and an honest man you'll see - - A Doctor in Divinity, Whose word's his bond; nor ever was known To do a deed he would not own.</s> <s id="s1120">"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1121">Merchant.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1122">" I've nought to say - - all this may be - - But have you no security? Pray, Doctor, ca n't you find a friend To answer for what you pretend?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1123">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1124">" No, I have none; - - I am not known Within the precincts of this town."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1125">Merchant.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1126">" And do you come to <enamex sw="w180884" long="-2.878238320350647" lat="53.5225887298584" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131229" name="Liverpool" conf="2.132021068">Liverpool</enamex> To find a poor good-natured fool? With all your learning and your worth, Pray have you travelled so far north, To think we have so little wit, As by such biters to be bit? To learning we make no pretence: But, Doctor, we have common sense.</s> </p><p><s id="s1127">For learned men we do not seek: And if I may with freedom speak, I take you for a very Greek.''</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1128">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1129">" To know the Greek I do profess - -' Tis my delight and happiness; And Homer's page I oft have read, Through the long night, with aching head, When my wife wanted me in bed."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1130">Merchant.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1131">" Then go to Homer, if you will, And see if he'll discount your bill.</s> <s id="s1132">But the clock strikes.</s> <s id="s1133">- - Good bye, old Sinner!' Tis time for me to go to dinner."</s></p>
<p><s id="s1134">" You want the monies!" said another, A bearded, Israelitish brother.</s> <s id="s1135">"' Tis a suspected bill, I find; But you look poor, and I am kind.</s> <s id="s1136">Well, we must take the chance of trade; For twenty pounds the draft is made, It is too much, as I'm alive, But give it me - - and, here take five."</s></p>
<p><s id="s1137">" Patience, good Heaven!" the Doctor said;" Is this the boast and pride of trade? - - Each man they do not know to treat As an incorrigible cheat; And, when he does his want prefer To play the base extortioner? Commerce, I envy not thy gains, Thy hard-earned wealth, thy golden pains!( For that's hard-earned, though gained with ease Where Honour's sacred functions cease.) The dangers which thy voteries run, Or to undo, or be undone;</s> </p><p><s id="s1138">Whose hungry maws are daily bent On the fine feast of cent.</s> <s id="s1139">per cent.</s> <s id="s1140">; Whose virtue, talents, knowledge, health, Are all combined in that word - - wealth.</s> <s id="s1141">' Tis a proud scene of moneyed strife Forms this magnificence of life: But poor and rich, with all they have, Will find at length a common grave.</s> <s id="s1142">Continue, bounteous Heaven! to me, A feeling heart, and poverty.</s> <s id="s1143">These wights despise me,' cause I'm poor! But yet the wretched seek my door.</s> <s id="s1144">I fear no Duns, I'm not in debt, I tremble not at the Gazette:' Twould to my profit be, and fame, Did but its page display my name, Can these proud merchants say the same?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s1145">More he had said - - but now his bell The Beadle rang aloud, to tell That the good folks should vanish straight, As he must shut the ponderous gate.</s> <s id="s1146">But Syntax did not seem to hear - - So the man rang it in his ear.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1147">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1148">" I pray, my friend, what's all this rout With your fierce bell?"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1149">Beadle.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1150">" To ring you out."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1151">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1152">" I've been used to hear the din Of bells that always rang me in."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1153">Beadle.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1154">" All I've to say, for you to know, I'll shut the gate if you do n't go.</s> </p><p><s id="s1155">I sure shall leave you in the lurch, For now, good Sir, youere not at church."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s1156">Syntax.</s></p>
<p><s id="s1157">" Indeed, my friend, you speak most true: I know all that as well as you.</s> <s id="s1158">This is no temple; for,' tis clear I find no money-changers here; Nor will I say my mind conceives It may be called a den of thieves. However, I'll quit these sons of pelf, And keep my paper to myself: They shall no more at Syntax scoff; - - Grizzle and I will soon be off.</s> <s id="s1159">Thanks to my stars, I've got enough Of that same yellow, useful stuff, As will my every want befriend, And bear me to my journey's end.</s> <s id="s1160">Arrived in town, I'll see my Lord, Who'll welcome me to bed and board;' Twill make the witty Noble sport, When I these trading tricks report - - How near I was to being cheated: And how his Lordship's name was treated."</s></p></text>
</document>