<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1804_b"><p><s id="s1">A</s></p>
<p><s id="s2">Tour</s> </p><p><s id="s3">To The Principal</s></p>
<p><s id="s4">Scotch And English Lakes.</s>
</p><p><s id="s5">By</s></p>
<p><s id="s6">James Denholm,</s></p>
<p><s id="s7">Of the Drawing and Painting Academy, Argyle Steet,</s></p>
<p><s id="s8">Author Of The History Of <enamex sw="w156" long="-4.323445408764941" lat="55.86313234566946" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:9729" name="Glasgow" conf="2.207670132">Glasgow</enamex>,</s></p>
<p><s id="s9">And</s></p>
<p><s id="s10">Member Of The Philosophical And Philotechnical Societies Of That City.</s></p>
<p><s id="s11">" The men" Whom Nature's works can charm, with God himself" <enamex sw="w299" long="-1.203133010685334" lat="51.34037340872234" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11319632" name="Wheat Hold" conf="1.333833972">Hold</enamex> converse-- grow familiar day by day" With his conceptions, act upon his plan," And form to his the relish of their souls."</s> </p>
<p> <s id="s12">Akenside.</s></p>
<p><s id="s13"><enamex sw="w442" long="-4.323445408764941" lat="55.86313234566946" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:9729" name="Glasgow" conf="2.207670132">Glasgow</enamex>:</s></p>
<p><s id="s14">Printed by R. Chapman,</s></p>
<p><s id="s15">For A. Macgoun, Bookseller.</s></p>
<p><s id="s16">1804.</s></p>
<p><s id="s17">Immediately after leaving <enamex sw="w534" long="-2.943736422754175" lat="54.90846320413105" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11291228" name="Stanwix" conf="2.6">Stanwix</enamex>, you cross the Eden by two old narrow bridges, stretching across the two branches into which the river divides itself, having upon the right a level plain, called the Sacery, the scene formerly of many warlike deeds, from its vicinity to the castle and walls of</s></p>
<p><s id="s18"><enamex sw="w804" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex>;</s></p>
<p> <s id="s19"><enamex sw="w816" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> is distant 10 miles from <enamex sw="w850" long="-2.96338204564023" lat="55.0091956888473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:22582" name="Longtown" conf="2.6">Longtown</enamex>, and 101 from <enamex sw="w873" long="-4.323445408764941" lat="55.86313234566946" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:9729" name="Glasgow" conf="2.207670132">Glasgow</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s20">which you now enter, passing through a short suburb, by the Scotch gate, a square fabric of hewn stone, with an arched porch.</s></p>
<p><s id="s21"><enamex sw="w1008" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> is allowed by all writers to be of very great antiquity, having been a place of strength in the time of the Romans, by whom it was called Luguvallam.</s></p>
<p><s id="s22">After the departure of that people from <enamex  sw="w1208" name="Large admin unit">Britain</enamex>, it is said to have been laid waste by the Caledonians, and in this situation it lay, till the reign of Egfrid, who caused it to be rebuilt, and fortified with a wall.</s> <s id="s23">It thereafter was again destroyed by the Danes, who not only burned the town, but put all the inhabitants to the sword.</s></p>
<p><s id="s24">In this situation did it remain for near 200 years, when it was begun to be rebuilt in the time of William the I., by Walter, one of his followers, a priest, and a native of <enamex  sw="w1678" name="Large admin unit">Normandy</enamex>.</s> <s id="s25">By command of William Ruffus, it was surrounded with walls, and a strong fortress at the same time erected for its protection.</s> <s id="s26">Thus did the city continue till the reign of Stephen, when it was taken possession of by David, King of Scotland, who thereafter obtained the whole of <enamex  sw="w1966" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> from the English King, as a reward for assisting him against Henry the Ii.</s> <s id="s27">When this last mentioned monarch got possession of the crown, he had an interview at <enamex sw="w2137" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> relative to the restitution of <enamex  sw="w2177" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, which, however, did not succeed.</s> <s id="s28">Nevertheless, in a short time thereafter, we find it in the possession of the English, for in 1173 it was besieged, though unsuccessfully, by William, the successor of Malcolm, King of Scots.</s></p>
<p><s id="s29"><enamex sw="w2414" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> sustained another siege in the reign of King John, when it was taken possession of by Alexander, King of Scotland, who found himself, however, unable to reduce the castle, which held out, and continued in the hands of the English.</s></p>
<p><s id="s30">The town thereafter was abandoned by the Scotch.</s> <s id="s31">In the year 1296, we are informed, they again attempted to take it by storm, but at this time unsuccessfully; the women shewed, it is said, astonishing valour, pouring boiling water over the walls upon the besiegers, and performing many other intrepid actions for the defence of the city.</s></p>
<p><s id="s32">Another unsuccessful attempt to gain the town was made by the Scots in the 9th year of Edward Ii.; and in the reign of Edward Iii.</s> <s id="s33">they also laid siege to <enamex sw="w3147" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex>, burnt the suburbs, but the city held out.</s></p>
<p><s id="s34">The whole city was taken possession of by the Scots in 1345; shortly after, they were obliged to abandon it, after having reduced the town, or great part of it to ashes.</s></p>
<p><s id="s35">From this period to the time of Aske's rebellion in the 29th of Henry Viii., it does not appear that any formidable attempts were made against <enamex sw="w3512" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex>.</s> <s id="s36">At that time it was besieged by an army of 8000 men.</s> <s id="s37">The garrison, however, found means to discomfit the designs of the besiegers, who were afterwards intercepted by the Duke of Norfolk, and all the leaders ordered for execution, and hung on the city walls.</s></p>
<p><s id="s38">During the reign of Queen Elizabeth, <enamex sw="w3817" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> was visited by a dreadful plague, which carried off about one third of the inhabitants, or 1196 persons.</s></p>
<p><s id="s39">About 60 years thereafter, or in the year 1644, after a siege and blockade of near eight months, it was surrendered to the Parliament forces under Lesly.</s> <s id="s40">During that period the distress of the garrison was so great, that they ate dogs, horses, and rats.</s></p>
<p><s id="s41">From that time, to the rebellion in 1745, nothing remarkable appears to have occurred with respect to this city; at that period it was taken possession of by the rebel army, and shortly thereafter retaken by the Royal forces, under command of the Duke of Cumberland.</s> <s id="s42">This was the last hostile act of which <enamex sw="w4491" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> was the scene, and it is to be hoped, the last that within its walls it will ever witness.</s></p>
<p><s id="s43"><enamex sw="w4591" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> is finely situated upon a gently rising ground, in the midst of an extensive and fertile plain, surrounded by several rivers, the Eden on the north, Caldew on the west, and the Petteril on the east and south.</s> <s id="s44">The walls of the city are still standing, though now in a very ruinous condition; they appear to have been constructed with much scientific knowledge, and are in most situations lofty, and of a great thickness.</s> <s id="s45">These walls have three gates, forming the principal entrances into the city: The English gate upon the south, the Scotch on the north, and the Irish towards the west.</s></p>
<p><s id="s46">The principal street of the city runs north and south, betwixt the Scotch and English gates; it is in general broad and spacious, particularly towards the centre of the town.</s> <s id="s47">The houses are commonly three or four stories in height, and mostly constructed of stone.</s> <s id="s48">From the main street, which is divided into two divisions, Scotch Street and English Street, others branch off, to the west: The finest of these appears to be Abbey Street, many of the houses of which are elegant and beautiful; indeed the whole town has a clean and a - greeable appearance, besides being more regular in its plan than is the case with most other old cities.</s></p>
<p><s id="s49"><enamex sw="w5826" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> contains several public buildings: In the centre of the city are placed the <enamex  sw="w5911" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Town Hall</enamex>, <enamex sw="w5922" long="-2.10089" lat="54.97157" type="other" gazref="unlock:5824963" name="Hexham Moot Hall &amp; Old Gaol" conf="0.84437385">Moot Hall</enamex>, and Council chamber, to which you ascend by a flight of steps.</s> <s id="s50">The last of these is ornamented with a cupola or clock.</s> <s id="s51">The Guildhall is situated at the head of <enamex sw="w6093" long="-90.69732999999999" lat="35.84452" type="other" gazref="unlock:6860697" name="Fisher Street Baptist Church" conf="0.5816582256">Fisher Street</enamex>; it is but a mean building, though to appearance of considerable antiquity.</s></p>
<p><s id="s52">The principal public edifices that are deserving of attention, are the Cathedral and <enamex sw="w6268" long="-0.7334461399619994" lat="52.22650299344568" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11101189" name="Castle, The" conf="1.182092526">the Castle</enamex>.</s> <s id="s53">The Cathedral, which is surrounded with a wall, separating it from the town, is a very ancient structure, having been founded in the reign of William Ruffus, and before the city was erected into a Bishopric.</s> <s id="s54">The eastern part of the edifice, however, appears of a more recent date; it is also the most beautiful part of the fabric.</s> <s id="s55">The choir, with the aisles, is 71 feet in breadth, and has a stately window to the east, 48 feet high and 30 broad, adorned with curious pillars.</s> <s id="s56">The roof is elegantly vaulted with wood, and is embellished with the arms of <enamex  sw="w6834" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w6846" name="Large admin unit">France</enamex>, quartered; as also with Peircy's, Lucy's, Warren's, Moubray's, and many others.</s> <s id="s57">In the choir are monuments of three bishops who are there interred.</s></p>
<p><s id="s58">The castle, which we visited, is another ancient edifice, now, like the walls, falling fast into decay.</s> <s id="s59">It is situated at the western extremity of the city, on an eminence rising considerably above the level of <enamex sw="w7213" long="-2.545503018232447" lat="51.14439493145336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:42065" name="Street On The Fosse" conf="1.419892608">the street</enamex>, and at a great height above the plain to the north and west.</s> <s id="s60">Within its walls it contains a very considerable space, some part of which appears never to have been occupied by buildings.</s> <s id="s61">It seems to have been erected at different periods; its walls are in general lofty, uncommonly strong and massy, and the apartments, which are generally of small dimensions, separated by partitions of stone, and guarded by oaken doors barred with iron.</s> <s id="s62">One of these was shewn us, as the room where the unfortunate Mary Stuart was confined for some time.</s> <s id="s63">It looks to the north, the direction of that country to which she was destined never more to return.</s></p>
<p><s id="s64">From the summit of this fortress, a beautiful and extensive view stretches around, comprehending the greatest part of <enamex  sw="w7984" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>-- the <enamex sw="w8004" long="-3.20953099163933" lat="54.95240084458308" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:39176" name="Bowness-On- Solway" conf="2.6">Solway</enamex> <enamex sw="w8011" long="-2.473993404988601" lat="54.59786031164339" type="water" gazref="unlock:8786658" name="Frith Beck" conf="2.4">Frith</enamex>-- and the more distant coast of <enamex  sw="w8052" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s65">The castle, before the Union of the crowns, like the city adjacent, often changed its masters, having been frequently besieged and taken by the Scots, from whom it was again as often wrested by the English.</s></p>
<p><s id="s66">Amongst the many enterprizes that here took place, the following atchievement is one of the latest, and perhaps not the least daring, that were ever carried into effect.</s></p>
<p><s id="s67">In the latter part of the reign of Elizabeth, the Commissioners of the Borders of both kingdoms having met for the discussion of some matters upon the line of the march, parted thereafter with their followers upon amicable terms.</s> <s id="s68">Amongst the number of those attending the Scotch warden was one of the <enamex  sw="w8740" name="Not a placename">Armstrongs</enamex>, called Will of <enamex sw="w8767" long="-3.351619531121555" lat="56.36053654655679" type="other" gazref="unlock:11187414" name="Kinmonth" conf="0.8268118715">Kinmonth</enamex>, a celebrated freebooter; against him the English held an inveterate hatred, from the many injuries they had received.</s> <s id="s69">After the breaking up of the commission, he was accordingly way-laid, when returning privately home, and carried to the castle of <enamex sw="w9026" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex>, where he was put in irons.</s> <s id="s70">This circumstance coming to the ears of Scot of <enamex  sw="w9111" name="Not a placename">Buccleugh</enamex>, one of the deputy-wardens of the border, he insisted upon restitution from the Governor of <enamex sw="w9213" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex>: Finding his request disregarded, although in time of peace betwixt the nations, he determined to rescue <enamex  sw="w9327" name="Not a placename">Armstrong</enamex> by force, and for this purpose called together a number of his followers, amounting to about 200 horse, the place of rendezvous being the tower of <enamex sw="w9484" long="-1.4946" lat="54.53055" type="other" gazref="unlock:13905913" name="Morton Palms" conf="0.8502522319">Morton</enamex>, about ten miles from <enamex sw="w9513" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex>.</s> <s id="s71">With these, during the night, he crossed the <enamex sw="w9568" long="-3.30009716472156" lat="54.3940525814659" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771979" name="River Esk" conf="2.4">Esk</enamex>, and about two hours before day arrived at the Eden, which was much swollen by some late rains.</s> <s id="s72">This river the party likewise crossed, at the hazard of their lives, and came to the Sacery, a plain under the castle.</s> <s id="s73">Here making a halt at the side of a rivulet, he caused 80 of the company to alight from their horses, with the ladders they had prepared for scaling.</s> <s id="s74">Accompanying them to the foot of the wall, he caused the ladders to be set against it; these, however, being found too short, a breach was ordered to be made with other instruments, nigh the Postern gate.</s> <s id="s75">This, with much labour, was effected, so as to admit a single person, who quickly thereafter broke open the postern for the others.</s> <s id="s76">The noise occasioned by this alarmed some watchmen; who were, quickly secured and taken prisoners.</s> <s id="s77">The other doors that led into the prisoner's apartment were in succession broken open, and <enamex  sw="w10464" name="Not a placename">Armstrong</enamex> in consequence relieved, but no farther damage done, or captives taken, although the whole garrison now lay at their mercy.</s> <s id="s78">Having gained their object, they retreated by sound of trumpet, marching again by the Sacery to the banks of the river.</s> <s id="s79">In the meantime, the town was alarmed, numbers flocked together to oppose the Scots recrossing the river; their ranks were, however, broken, and <enamex  sw="w10863" name="Not a placename">Buccleugh</enamex> and his party plunged into the Eden, landed safely on the opposite bank, and two hours after sun rise, crossed the border into Scottish ground, after having performed one of the most daring and hazardous enterprizes recorded in the history of the two nations-- an enterprize, which had nearly again involved them in war and bloodshed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s80">Besides the cathedral, or St. Mary's church, as it is called, <enamex sw="w11273" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> has another church upon the establishment, <enamex sw="w11325" long="-3.392880350420522" lat="54.81426162231475" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11177650" name="Holme St Cuthbert" conf="2.586940047">St. Cuthbert</enamex>'s, a modern edifice, built upon the situation of the old church of that name, in 1778, with a short spire and dome; 3 protestant dissenting meeting-houses, a quaker meeting-house, one for the methodists, and a Roman catholic chapel.</s></p>
<p><s id="s81">The prison or jail of the city stands near the west end of the town; it is an old fabric, and its apartments dark and gloomy; within its limits, however, a considerable area or open space is included, inclosed with a wall of brick, where the prisoners are allowed to take exercise in the day, contrary to the custom in the Scotch jails, where the benefit of the free air is not allowed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s82">A small part of this area is inclosed by an iron rail; it is appropriated for criminals, many of whom we saw walking up and down with chains, clashing at every step.</s> <s id="s83">One appeared very incommoded by a large clog of wood fixed to his leg: Upon enquiring the cause, we were informed that this was the mode of punishment for such as attempted to make their escape by scaling the wall.</s></p>
<p><s id="s84">In this prison, at the time we were there, was confined a person of the name of <enamex sw="w12419" long="-1.977403080250683" lat="53.46498783270085" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11163147" name="Hadfield" conf="1.468862754">Hadfield</enamex>, who, from some recent criminal acts, of a singular and enterprising nature, had engaged the attention of the whole country, and of consequence had become to most people an object of curiosity.</s> <s id="s85">With the view of seeing this man we visited the jail, alongst with a party, but he very properly would not agree to be shewn. We, however, had a very transient glance of him, in passing the window, with which we were obliged to be satisfied: He appeared to be a middle-sized man, stoutly made, and betwixt 40 and 50 years of age, but without that fine and captivating exterior, which was to be expected in the appearance of one who had gained so many female hearts, and amongst others, the fair and famed Mary of <enamex sw="w13136" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>; his superiority, it is said, consisted in his manner and address, which was said to be remarkably insinuating, polite, and agreeable.</s></p>
<p><s id="s86">With respect to population, <enamex sw="w13310" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> contains, according to the late enumeration by order of Government, 10,221 souls, which is an increase of 1505 since the year 1796, when a preceding account of the inhabitants was taken up.</s></p>
<p><s id="s87">Previous to the middle of the last century, few manufactures of any consequence were carried on in the town.</s> <s id="s88">About that time, a manufacture of woolens was established, but proving unsuccessful, it was given up.</s> <s id="s89">To this succeeded, in the year 1750, a manufacture of osnaburghs, which met with more success.</s> <s id="s90">The cotton manufacture, shortly after this period, began also to be introduced, and this, together with the printing of calicoes, which was begun in 1761, has been the staple ever since.</s> <s id="s91">To such an extent is the calicoe printing carried, that it employs upwards of 1000 people, and yields to the revenue at least L .20, 000 sterling, annually.</s> <s id="s92">The brewing of ales is also carried on to a considerable extent, this branch paying to Government about L .6000 per annum.</s> <s id="s93">A soap-work does also a great deal of business, yielding to the revenue about L .1500 a-year.</s></p>
<p><s id="s94">Leaving <enamex sw="w14380" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> by the English gate, we directed our course southward, alongst the <enamex sw="w14456" long="-0.08573711413610305" lat="51.48768230024373" type="civila" gazref="unlock:13326794" name="Greater London Authority" conf="2.587226271">London</enamex> road, through a beautiful and fertile country, for some miles stretching alongst the banks of the <enamex sw="w14561" long="-2.880368858531455" lat="54.86400004048386" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270823" name="River Petteril" conf="2.4">River Petteril</enamex>, which appears upon the right.</s> <s id="s95">Many seats also adorn this district: The principal of these, after leaving the village of <enamex sw="w14697" long="-1.099086784544633" lat="52.96713222454051" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11098529" name="Carlton" conf="1.326376194">Carlton</enamex>, are <enamex sw="w14710" name="Newbigging Hall">Newbigging Hall</enamex>, the residence of the Rev. Mr Bateman;-- <enamex sw="w14768" long="-77.01997679999999" lat="39.0051099" type="other" gazref="unlock:7119612" name="South Woodside Park" conf="0.8410625753">Woodside</enamex>, the seat of John Losh, Esq;-- <enamex sw="w14809" long="-2.850210856" lat="54.82215178" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00064" name="Barrock Lodge" conf="99992">Barrock Lodge</enamex>, nearly opposite Low <enamex sw="w14844" long="-2.814378231084673" lat="54.79394667307044" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:39070" name="High Hesket" conf="2.6">Hesket</enamex>, the residence of James Graham, Esq; standing on the verge of a high bank, half surrounded with the <enamex sw="w14951" long="-2.880368858531455" lat="54.86400004048386" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270823" name="River Petteril" conf="2.4">River Petteril</enamex>, and looking down a fertile vale, inclosed with wooded banks.</s> <s id="s96">A little farther appears Petteril green, the seat of Robert Collins, Esq;-- <enamex sw="w15105" long="-2.928529867" lat="54.38830822" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00125" name="Calgarth Park" conf="99992">Calthwaite hall</enamex>, Thomas Dixon, Esq;-- <enamex sw="w15144" long="-0.762751906889938" lat="54.30359994744031" type="other" gazref="unlock:11086268" name="Breckonbrough" conf="0.8905977485">Breckonbrough</enamex>, William Wilson, Esq;-- and <enamex sw="w15187" long="-2.784101137171737" lat="54.72085469776" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11246937" name="Plumpton Old Hall" conf="2.2">Plumpton hall</enamex>, the property of John Sanderson, Esq.</s></p>
<p><s id="s97">By degrees as you proceed, the face of the country puts on a more naked appearance, and thus continues till you enter <enamex sw="w15357" long="-2.846762938810356" lat="54.74739707944234" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11182574" name="Inglewood Forest" conf="2.4">Inglewood forest</enamex>, now entirely destitute of trees, and covered partly with a coarse grass, and partly with heath; the view to the east is terminated in this situation by a chain of lumpish hills, covered with heath, running towards the south; to the west a great extent of level country opens to the eye, bounded by the mountains of <enamex sw="w15690" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex> and <enamex sw="w15705" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s98">The prospect to the south is terminated by a ridge of high ground, called <enamex sw="w15788" long="-2.744010531" lat="54.67519654" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00131" name="Penrith Beacon" conf="99992">Penrith Fell</enamex>, crowned by a square building, formerly used as a watch-tower and beacon, to alarm the country upon the incursion of the Scotch.</s> <s id="s99">Upon the left, at a short distance from the road, and nearly equally distant between <enamex sw="w16015" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex> and <enamex sw="w16028" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, we passed a small lake, which we at first fancied to be one of these beautiful sheets of water for which <enamex  sw="w16142" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> is so much celebrated: we were, however, shortly convinced of our error: Its name, we learned, is Wadling Tarn; it is in no respect interesting, either for its extent, or the beauty of the surrounding objects.</s></p>
<p><s id="s100">Continuing still to travel through this extensive common,( which is pastured by sheep, and immense numbers of geese, which roam at large in the day season, and though several miles distant from their home, return punctually to it in the evening) we passed a neat place of worship, called <enamex sw="w16652" name="Salkeld chapel">Salkeld chapel</enamex>, and shortly thereafter, the remains of a Roman station at <enamex sw="w16726" long="-2.784274640403185" lat="54.72984148457152" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11246924" name="Plumpton" conf="2.6">Plumpton</enamex>, still pretty entire, and thought by Camden to be the Petriana of the Romans; it is now called old <enamex sw="w16834" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, and sometimes <enamex sw="w16857" long="-2.751223763214512" lat="54.62219525707822" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11101355" name="Castlesteads" conf="2.2">Castlesteads</enamex>.</s> <s id="s101">The vestiges of this station are very conspicuous.</s> <s id="s102">The vallum and ditch may be traced upon three sides, forming an oblong square, 132 yards, by 120; it lies about 200 yards above the <enamex sw="w17054" long="-2.880368858531455" lat="54.86400004048386" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270823" name="River Petteril" conf="2.4">River Petteril</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s103">The road now begins to ascend, at first gradually, then more quickly, becoming very steep and difficult, and thus it continues for some considerable distance, till you arrive at the summit of the ridge, having <enamex sw="w17280" long="-2.665056498919776" lat="55.03613233380358" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11072261" name="Beacon, The" conf="1.326436227">the beacon</enamex> just now mentioned upon your left.</s> <s id="s104">In this situation we first obtained a view of <enamex sw="w17372" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, situated at the foot or south side of the eminence which we had just ascended.</s> <s id="s105">The character of the country now quickly changes:-- To the south-east particularly, the prospect is rich and beautiful, every where cultivated highly, subdivided by hedge-rows into innumerable parks and closes, and adorned with seats, villas, and cottages.</s> <s id="s106">To the west, the surface is more irregular, at first, gradually swelling from the plain, then rising into hills and mountains of a great altitude, between which are situated these lakes and vales, the principal object of our excursion.</s></p>
<p><s id="s107">We now, after descending the hill, and passing some neat houses, ornamented with small flowerplots, laid out with much taste, arrived at</s></p>
<p><s id="s108"><enamex sw="w18091" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>,</s></p>
<p><s id="s109">18 miles distant from <enamex sw="w18122" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s110">We were much pleased with the appearance of this town, the houses being in general well built, and some of them indeed, lofty and elegant, particularly towards the centre of the main street, which runs in the direction of the great road, north and south.</s> <s id="s111">They are mostly built of a reddish-coloured stone, which gives them a warm and agreeable look, and covered with slate.</s> <s id="s112">Footpaths paved with hewn stone, are likewise laid alongst the sides of the principal street, which contributes to the clean and pleasant appearance of the place.</s></p>
<p><s id="s113"><enamex sw="w18669" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> contains a great number of inns, from being a thoroughfare, not only from the north to the south, but also from <enamex  sw="w18789" name="Large admin unit">Yorkshire</enamex> to the western parts of <enamex  sw="w18823" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s114">These are in general good, and at two in particular, the accommodation and entertainment are excellent; the people who possess them ready to oblige, polite, and hospitable to strangers; the same character, as far as we saw, applied to the other inhabitants, who appeared in general to be in easy and comfortable circumstances.</s></p>
<p><s id="s115">In walking about the town,( which contains about 4000 inhabitants) we visited the church, which is a large and modern fabric, with a square tower.</s> <s id="s116">It is surrounded with a large cemetry, in which we were shewn a remarkable monument of antiquity.</s> <s id="s117">It consists of two upright pillars of stone, about 10 feet in height, and 15 feet asunder, standing in a direction east and west; On each side are two others of a semicircular form, placed edgewise in the ground.</s></p>
<p><s id="s118">This is most likely a sepulchral monument, but whether its origin is to be attributed to the British, <enamex  sw="w19726" name="Not a placename">Romans</enamex>, <enamex sw="w19734" long="-2.185958252289132" lat="52.92544900077839" type="other" gazref="unlock:11278497" name="Saxons' Lowe" conf="0.7732677417">Saxons</enamex>, or <enamex sw="w19745" long="-2.142332971604499" lat="53.23117296826285" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11127139" name="Danes Moss" conf="1.522214582">Danes</enamex>, is not agreed upon by antiquaries.</s> <s id="s119">The common people tell you that these stones inclose the burial place of a giant, 10 or 12 feet in height, who was famous for his feats of valour, and amongst others, for freeing <enamex sw="w19966" long="-2.846762938810356" lat="54.74739707944234" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11182574" name="Inglewood Forest" conf="2.4">Inglewood forest</enamex> from wild boars, with which, previous to his time, it had been much infested; others give you different accounts, and tell a number of traditionary tales respecting it, that do not deserve much attention.</s> <s id="s120">We next took a walk to <enamex sw="w20211" long="-0.7334461399619994" lat="52.22650299344568" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11101189" name="Castle, The" conf="1.182092526">the Castle</enamex> of <enamex sw="w20225" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, situated in the immediate neighbourhood of the town, the property of the Duke of Devonshire.</s> <s id="s121">This fortress is now in ruins, and presents nothing very picturesque or interesting.</s> <s id="s122">It has, however, been a large and strong building, of the form of a parallelogram, fortified with a rampart and deep ditch, the only approach being towards the town, where an opening through the work still appears, formerly occupied, it is supposed, by the drawbridge.</s> <s id="s123">This castle was for a long time the residence of Richard, Duke of Gloucester, who took up his abode here, that he might be nearer at hand to oppose the Scots, and also to keep the adjacent country in awe, the inhabitants being mostly in the interest of the house of <enamex sw="w20947" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s124">Strangers here, when at leisure, likewise often visit <enamex sw="w21012" long="-2.665056498919776" lat="55.03613233380358" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11072261" name="Beacon, The" conf="1.326436227">the beacon</enamex> already noticed, on account of its view, which compensates, by its extent and variety of prospect, for the labour in ascending to procure it, em - bracing a sweep of upwards of 100 miles in circumference.</s></p>
<p><s id="s125">The neighbourhood of <enamex sw="w21248" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> contains many seats: The most beautiful of these, with respect to situation and prospect, is <enamex sw="w21349" long="-2.7191" lat="54.654" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY537290" name="Brougham Castle" conf="99992">Brougham hall</enamex>, about 2 miles to the south, the seat of Henry <enamex sw="w21410" long="-2.670439372771031" lat="54.64677376142333" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403485" name="Brougham CP" conf="2.4">Brougham</enamex>, Esq; father to the ingenious author of the Colonial Policy of the European Powers.</s> <s id="s126">Opposite the front of the house, which is extensive, is a fine terrace, the views from which, for variety and extent, are seldom to be equalled, being rich beyond description.</s></p>
<p><s id="s127">Within the compass of the pleasure-grounds, which are reckoned the first, it is believed, in the north-west of <enamex  sw="w21790" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, are also many delightful situations; in one place you are shewn a sweet retreat, called the <enamex sw="w21891" long="-2.266837360736988" lat="51.54960989590066" type="other" gazref="unlock:11170637" name="Hermit's Cell" conf="0.7551595078">Hermit's Cell</enamex>, being a small circular building, covered with thatch, and lined with mosses of various kinds, the seats matted, and the windows of painted glass.</s> <s id="s128">On the table are painted some appropriate verses, from Il Penseroso of <enamex  sw="w22123" name="Not a placename">Milton</enamex>, and in another part of the building is a scroll, containing these lines:</s></p>
<p><s id="s129">" Beneath this moss-grown roof, this rustic cell," Truth, liberty, content, sequestered dwell," Say, you who dare our hermitage disdain," What drawing-room can boast so fair a train."</s></p>
<p><s id="s130">On the banks of the River <enamex sw="w22413" long="-2.714587092202354" lat="54.60426562927525" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13699" name="Lowther" conf="2.6">Lowther</enamex>, which runs through the grounds, is another small thatched building, which contains a collection of curious prints, and specimens of natural history, with a gallery for the convenience of angling in the river beneath.</s> <s id="s131">A little lower down, upon the <enamex sw="w22669" long="-2.733436339581293" lat="54.64128019629315" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791132" name="River Eamont" conf="2.4">River Eamont</enamex>,( which is also near) stands a spacious and beautiful ruin, <enamex sw="w22742" long="-2.720724891391479" lat="54.64934460899606" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11089698" name="Brougham Castle" conf="2.2">Brougham Castle</enamex>, a place, at one time of great strength, and the residence formerly of the Earls of <enamex  sw="w22842" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s132">In the same neighbourhood, near <enamex sw="w22888" long="-2.739163228840894" lat="54.64897276002622" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31874" name="Eamont Bridge" conf="2.6">Eamont bridge</enamex>, is another antiquity, called Arthur's round table, of an exact circular figure, rising above the plain on which it stands, and surrounded by a trench, about ten paces wide, from which the earth by which it is formed has been taken.</s> <s id="s133">It is thought to have been an ancient tilting ground, where justings had been held-- the circle in the centre the place appropriated for the horsemen to shew their dexterity at these exercises-- and the circus surrounding it, the situation occupied by the spectators assembled at these military feats.</s></p>
<p><s id="s134">Returning to <enamex sw="w23456" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, we obtained a direction to the nearest of the lakes in this neighbourhood, to which we shortly thereafter set out.</s> <s id="s135">Upon leaving the town, the road, for a little way, passes under some beautiful trees, to the <enamex sw="w23673" long="-2.733436339581293" lat="54.64128019629315" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791132" name="River Eamont" conf="2.4">River Eamont</enamex>, in a southerly direction, which it crosses by a bridge, into the <enamex  sw="w23752" name="Large admin unit">county of Westmoreland</enamex>; you then turn more to the west, having Arthur's round table upon the left, and upon the right, a singular looking hill, of no great elevation, rising from the plain, called <enamex sw="w23949" long="-2.746946718" lat="54.64929617" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00126" name="Mayburgh Earthwork" conf="99992">Maybrough</enamex>, upon the top of which are the ruins of some British fortifications, or, according to others, the remains of a Druidical temple.</s></p>
<p><s id="s136">Proceeding in this direction, the face of the country continues, for a mile or two, level and rich; the road passing through shady lanes, in some places, overhung with trees, and in others more open; you then pass the small village of <enamex sw="w24324" long="-2.7438" lat="54.6372" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:13403571" name="Yanwath" conf="99992">Yanwith</enamex>, in the neighbourhood of which is <enamex sw="w24366" long="-2.763943402" lat="54.64658392" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00138" name="Yanwith Hall" conf="99992">Yanwith Hall</enamex>, the property of Joseph Boak, Esq; more to the right, and upon the north side of the Eamont, is <enamex sw="w24475" long="-2.813352976215357" lat="54.63078196381976" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11126513" name="Dalemain" conf="2.2">Dalemain</enamex>, the beautiful and sweetly secluded seat of Edward Hasell, Esq.</s></p>
<p><s id="s137">By degrees, the appearance of the landscape before you begins to vary in its features: You obtain, here and there, peeps, through the trees, of distant blue mountains, towering to a great height; their altitude, as well as colour, changes as you advance, while they seem to stretch, and, as it were, inclose you upon the right and left; you shortly thereafter, enter a delightful vale, and obtain a peep of <enamex sw="w24955" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, now near at hand, at the termination of which, is the small village of <enamex sw="w25037" long="-2.812994518069897" lat="54.61280820901722" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11248058" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley</enamex>, containing a comfortable, though small inn, at which we stopped.</s></p>
<p><s id="s138"><enamex sw="w25110" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s139">This beautiful lake, which, with respect to picturesque and sublime scenery, is perhaps the first in <enamex  sw="w25222" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, is about 9 miles in length, by a mile in breadth, but in some situations, much less.</s> <s id="s140">Its form or outline has not been unaptly compared to the letter Z, but with less acute angles.</s></p>
<p><s id="s141"><enamex sw="w25411" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex> is surrounded upon all sides except the east, by ranges of mountains; these in the neighbourhood of the village just now mentioned, are of no great height, and indeed are mostly cultivated and subdivided into farms; farther to the west, however, they gradually assume a greater height, approach nearer the water, and upon one side, stop all farther passage in that direction; thus they continue to the extremity of the lake in <enamex sw="w25848" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>, where they rear their rocky heads to the clouds, surround <enamex sw="w25918" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, and produce, with the other objects, the grandest and most magnificent scenes.</s></p>
<p><s id="s142">This lake is in general very deep, particularly near to <enamex sw="w26064" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s143">At its eastern termination, where the Eamont branches from it, it is more shallow, and beautifully transparent.</s> <s id="s144">It contains a great number of different kinds of fish, such as char,( so much esteemed) eels and trouts.</s> <s id="s145">The last here have been sometimes taken of such a size, as to weigh 30 pounds.</s></p>
<p><s id="s146">In order to obtain a view of <enamex sw="w26401" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, we left the village of <enamex sw="w26435" long="-2.812994518069897" lat="54.61280820901722" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11248058" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley</enamex>, and immediately crossed a bridge over the Eamont, when we found ourselves at the base of a steep conical hill, though of no great height, and mostly covered with wood, called <enamex sw="w26618" long="-2.8253" lat="54.6137" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY468246" name="Dunmallard Hill" conf="99992">Dunmallet</enamex>.</s> <s id="s147">This we ascended, and obtained at once a prospect of great beauty and softness: The lake lay, as it were, at our feet, having its outline finely broken by numerous capes and retiring bays, particularly to the south.</s> <s id="s148">On all sides it appears, from this point, surrounded with mountains; these upon the left are lofty and craggy, presenting, in several parts, some dreadful and precipitous precipices.</s> <s id="s149">The hills upon the right hand are more humble, and slope gradually into the water.</s> <s id="s150">Near the bases of these hills, many woody copses, cultivated fields, and farms with white cottages thickly strewed around, add much to enliven the prospect.</s> <s id="s151">The view of the lake is terminated, in this situation, by a mountain, called Hallerfell, beyond which, however, appear a cluster of others, beautifully grouped and broken, and which surround scenes, nearer the head of the lake, of still greater sublimity and grandeur.</s></p>
<p><s id="s152">When we first saw <enamex sw="w27555" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, the sun was still high above the horizon, the sky unclouded, and a general glare of light very prevalent throughout, circumstances by no means favourable to shew a scene to much advantage.</s> <s id="s153">We afterwards visited it when the day was farther advanced, the sky dappled with clouds, tinged with the glow of evening, and betwixt which the sun-beams darted with ruddy splendor: The effect was grand, and highly delightful: A strong light hung upon the side of the mountain to the left, shewing its inequalities and broken surface, in the most distinct manner, while the other parts of the landscape were in the shade, and softened by the purplish haze in the air;-- The surface of the lake, in some situations reflected the image of the mountains; in others, disturbed by a breeze, or the shadows of the clouds reflection was interrupted, and variety given to the smooth expanse.</s> <s id="s154">As the evening advanced, the effects shifted, and the warmth of the landscape increased, till such time as the sun set behind the mountains, when objects became gradually more and more indistinct, melting successively, into the purplish, and at length, sable shades of night.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s155">On the summit of <enamex sw="w28735" long="-2.8253" lat="54.6137" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY468246" name="Dunmallard Hill" conf="99992">Dunmallet</enamex> are still to be seen the vestiges of a Roman fort, surrounded by a foss.</s> <s id="s156">Its dimensions are 137 paces by 37.</s> <s id="s157">Care should be taken in what situation you place yourself when admiring the beauties around you from this point, as snakes are often found upon the hill, lying concealed amongst the grass.</s> <s id="s158">My companion in the journey, the Rev. Mr. <enamex  sw="w29085" name="Not a placename">Fleming</enamex>, happened to meet with one of these, which he killed without receiving any injury.</s></p>
<p><s id="s159">In the neighbourhood of the bridge of <enamex sw="w29214" long="-2.812994518069897" lat="54.61280820901722" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11248058" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley</enamex>, and upon the south side of the Eamont, at its eastern extremity, is another view of the lake, stretching out before the eye, to the bottom of Hallenfell.</s> <s id="s160">In this situation, however, much of the beauty of the scene is lost; the water is bounded, to appearance, by right lines, without those indentations which are seen from <enamex sw="w29545" long="-2.8253" lat="54.6137" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY468246" name="Dunmallard Hill" conf="99992">Dunmallet</enamex>; neither are the forms of the mountains so pleasing or beautiful as from that station.</s></p>
<p><s id="s161">On the following day, after arriving at <enamex sw="w29682" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, during the intervals of fair weather, we sauntered about, admiring many other fine scenes: One of these particularly struck us: To get to the point from which this view is obtained, we returned about half a mile upon the <enamex sw="w29914" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> road, then turned to the left, and entered an inclosure, when advancing two or three hundred yards, upon looking west, we were at once struck with a most fascinating and delightful landscape.</s></p>
<p><s id="s162">In this place a considerable space of foreground lies betwixt and the lake, which is seen now at a greater distance, winding its azure waters round the capes and headlands.</s> <s id="s163">This foreground, or rather middle distance, is in itself interesting: It is every where broken by inclosures and hedgerows, copses, farms, and cottages, not disposed in stiff and regular order, but intermixed and distributed in the most pleasing manner.</s></p>
<p><s id="s164">The side screen upon the right is <enamex sw="w30575" long="-2.8253" lat="54.6137" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY468246" name="Dunmallard Hill" conf="99992">Dunmallet</enamex>, towering to a considerable height, with the hills beyond, that bound the lake upon the north.</s> <s id="s165">On the left are another chain, already mentioned as lying to the south, and in the distance, directly in front, is the mountain of Hallenfell, and beyond, lofty Helvellin, rearing his" cloud capt" top on high.</s></p>
<p><s id="s166">To such as wish to make a complete Tour of the Lakes, it will be proper, when at <enamex sw="w30971" long="-2.812994518069897" lat="54.61280820901722" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11248058" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley</enamex>, before proceeding up the banks of <enamex sw="w31013" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, to visit another, at no great distance to the south, called</s></p>
<p><s id="s167"><enamex sw="w31084" long="-2.804508842654697" lat="54.18142154182505" type="water" gazref="unlock:11167631" name="Hawes Water" conf="2.4">Hawes Water</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s168">From <enamex sw="w31102" long="-2.812994518069897" lat="54.61280820901722" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11248058" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley</enamex> a road leads to this lake.</s> <s id="s169">Proceeding alongst it, you first ascend the brow of the hills, which form the southern side of the vale in which <enamex sw="w31249" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex> is situated.</s> <s id="s170">Having gained the summit, you continue south, passing a large barrow of stones, called <enamex sw="w31359" long="-2.7205" lat="54.514" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY53451343" name="White Raise" conf="99992">White Raise</enamex>, near to which are the remains of a small Druidical circle of stones, and farther on, the vestiges of another, somewhat larger, at a place called Moor Dovack.</s> <s id="s171">Continuing on, the vale of <enamex sw="w31558" long="-2.75006695239094" lat="54.55928585398094" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11068932" name="Bampton" conf="2.6">Bampton</enamex> opens to the view, a beautiful rural tract, which conducts you, after a very picturesque approach, between two ridges of mountains, ornamented near their base by inclosures and hedgerows, to <enamex sw="w31757" long="-2.804508842654697" lat="54.18142154182505" type="water" gazref="unlock:11167631" name="Hawes Water" conf="2.4">Hawes Water</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s172">This lake is about 3 miles long, and of very different breadths, in some places half a mile, and in others, not more than a quarter of that space; indeed near the middle it is almost divided into two by promontories from the opposite shores, thereby forming, to appearance, two sheets of water.</s> <s id="s173">Like to <enamex sw="w32073" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, it is surrounded by mountains, some of whom are remarkably precipitous and craggy, dipping their perpendicular sides in the lake, while others are less steep, of a more gradual ascent, having their sides covered with small farms, and neat, but secluded cottages.</s></p>
<p><s id="s174">In the most romantic part of this solitary vale, and near its head, overhung with yews, is placed the little chapel of <enamex sw="w32466" long="-2.82696527422053" lat="54.48836227983379" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788937" name="Mardale Beck" conf="2.4">Mardale</enamex>, beyond which the vale contracts, into an Alpine pass, exhibiting for many miles, to those who chuse to travel this way, the most desert scenes of dread magnificence, from the lofty and overhanging mountains, the immense rocks precipitated from their sides, which threaten destruction to the traveller, and the dashing and foaming cataracts, pouring down on every hand, which only serve to interrupt that gloomy silence that would otherwise hold here its undisturbed reign.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s175">The Pass leads to <enamex sw="w32968" long="-2.745809060481465" lat="54.32561646560368" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185036" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex>, distant 14 miles from the chapel.</s></p>
<p><s id="s176">Instead, however, of proceeding this way, we again retrace the road to <enamex sw="w33081" long="-2.75006695239094" lat="54.55928585398094" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11068932" name="Bampton" conf="2.6">Bampton</enamex>, about 2 miles distant from the lake, and so on, by the objects already mentioned, across the common, descending to the vale of Eamont, and <enamex sw="w33229" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, to <enamex sw="w33243" long="-2.812994518069897" lat="54.61280820901722" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11248058" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s177">After having remained two days at this place, we left it on our way alongst the banks of the lake.</s> <s id="s178">After encompassing the base of a smooth green hill, called Soubyfell, the road continues parallel, and near to the shore; it then recedes, and becomes somewhat more uneven, while the vale to the right opens considerably.</s> <s id="s179">The mountains upon the other hand appear to rise by degrees, with much grandeur; two in particular, called <enamex sw="w33678" long="-2.8507" lat="54.5704" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY451198" name="Swarth Fell" conf="99992">Swarthfell</enamex> and Hallenfell, situated in <enamex sw="w33717" long="-2.8949" lat="54.5395" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY422164" name="Martindale Forest" conf="99992">Martindale forest</enamex>, are beautifully broken by rugged rocks and verdure intermixed.</s> <s id="s180">Those in front, which bound the first stretch of the lake, also increase in altitude, betwixt and which now appears, to great advantage, sweetly embowered in woods, and surrounded with inclosures and hedgerows, <enamex sw="w34010" long="-2.859266517427028" lat="54.5933169397067" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:39919" name="Watermillock" conf="2.6">Watermillock</enamex>, the seat of Colonel Robinson, lying upon a fine swelling bank, stretching into the north side of the lake, which appears winding around the promontory, by the base of Hallenfell.</s></p>
<p><s id="s181">We now passed this beautiful spot, through an avenue of venerable trees, which afforded us, during a hot summer's day, a grateful and cooling shade, continued through hedgerows and lanes, somewhat farther, till we found ourselves near the second reach of <enamex sw="w34459" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>.</s> <s id="s182">To obtain a prospect of it in the most favourable point, you leave the road through a gate to the left, nearly half a mile from <enamex sw="w34598" long="-2.859266517427028" lat="54.5933169397067" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:39919" name="Watermillock" conf="2.6">Watermillock</enamex>, continue to approach the water till within a short distance of the ruins of an old church, when turning around, a view presents itself, still more beautiful, and much more sublime than that from <enamex sw="w34807" long="-2.8253" lat="54.6137" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY468246" name="Dunmallard Hill" conf="99992">Dunmallet</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s183">The lake lies directly in front, part of it being seen through some beautiful trees, near the foreground, stretching for about 3 miles, in a direct line.</s> <s id="s184">Upon the left are the mountains of Hallenfell and <enamex sw="w35022" long="-2.9204" lat="54.5446" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7732640" name="Placefell" conf="99992">Placefell</enamex>, betwixt which, a small slip of cultivated land, finely wooded, stretches to the water's edge.</s> <s id="s185">The mountains are partly rocky and partly verdant, having their summits covered with purple heath, which contrasts finely with the green and yellow tints nearer the lake.</s> <s id="s186">The left screen of this view is also mountainous; here, however, the sweeps which the mountains make are more inclined; that which is nearest is sprinkled in some parts with trees, in others covered with thick woods, variegated with all the different shades of green, amongst which, in a commanding situation, appears a gentleman's seat, equally delightfully placed, with <enamex sw="w35670" long="-2.859266517427028" lat="54.5933169397067" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:39919" name="Watermillock" conf="2.6">Watermillock</enamex>.</s> <s id="s187">Many capes and promontories shoot into the water upon this side, and diversify its outline.</s> <s id="s188">The mountains opposite or in the middle, are Helvellin and his numerous branches, rising in dignity to the clouds, and like Hallenfell, at the termination of the first stretch, appearing to shut up or bound the second.</s></p>
<p><s id="s189">The view of <enamex sw="w36007" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex> in this situation differs much from the prospect at <enamex sw="w36069" long="-2.812994518069897" lat="54.61280820901722" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11248058" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley</enamex>: There the predominant features were softness and beauty;-- here, these are intermixed with grandeur and sublimity.</s> <s id="s190">The mountains on every side being more elevated, nearer each other, more finely broken, and better diversified than in the first station, while the lake also appears to more advantage, not only from these circumstances, but the deeper indentations of its coast, and consequently more picturesque outline, than it presents at the station just now mentioned.</s></p>
<p><s id="s191">We left this charming point with regret, regained the high road, and continued to pass, for some time, through fine woody lanes, overhung with ho - neysuckle, and other flowering shrubs, and catching a glimpse of the smooth expanse, at every opening of the trees.</s> <s id="s192">We then emerged from the shade, and crossed a verdant peninsula, pastured with a numerous herd of cattle, many of whom added much interest to the scenery, from their fine forms and various positions: Some were lying in groupes, under the shade of some thick spreading trees, others were standing far in the lake, to cool the ardent heat, and defend themselves the better from the myriads of flies with which they were surrounded.</s></p>
<p><s id="s193">As we proceeded, the mountains upon the right became more elevated and more precipitous.</s> <s id="s194">Amongst these, one of uncommon height struck us much: Its whole side next the road was composed of rock, shattered into ten thousand forms, in some situations presenting the most romantic and singular appearances; in others, the ruins of old castles, or deserted houses, from the crevices in the walls of which, sprung trees of every form and foliage.</s> <s id="s195">Farther down, immense blocks of stone lay on every hand, at one period or other severed from the mountain above, and scattered in all imaginable positions below.</s></p>
<p><s id="s196">Passing this singular mass, we immediately came in view of an ancient looking building, towering above the trees at the foot of the mountains.</s> <s id="s197">Its name, we learnt, was <enamex sw="w38014" long="-2.9206" lat="54.5761" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11210312" name="Lyulph's Tower" conf="99992">Lyulph</enamex>'s Tower, a hunting-seat of the Duke of Norfolk, and partly erected as an object to the surrounding scenery.</s></p>
<p><s id="s198"><enamex sw="w38129" long="-2.9206" lat="54.5761" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11210312" name="Lyulph's Tower" conf="99992">Lyulph</enamex>'s tower, which we now approached, is situated in a district called Gowbarrow park, which we had entered through a gate about 2 miles below.</s> <s id="s199">It is a square edifice, built of grey stone, in the castelated form, with turreted corners, battlements, and windows in the Gothic style, and has, at a distance, a venerable, and even grand appearance.</s> <s id="s200">The park, within which it stands, contains upwards of 1800 acres, and is pastured by about 600 deer, besides a great number of sheep and black cattle.</s></p>
<p><s id="s201">Proceeding alongst the way, we arrive at the second bend of the lake, which stretches about a mile and a half farther to <enamex sw="w38750" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s202">To obtain this view in perfection, it is likewise necessary to deviate from the road, leaving it to the left, ascending the side of the hill in the opposite direction.</s></p>
<p><s id="s203">If at the last point the scene was picturesque and grand, at this station it is still more so; indeed it is impossible for even the most destitute of taste to look upon the objects before him, without feeling the most exquisite sensations, arising from the presence of beauty, harmony, and the most striking sublimity.</s></p>
<p><s id="s204">The mountains here upon every side, particularly the north, are of a great height.</s> <s id="s205">Upon the opposite sides of the lake their character is essentially different.</s> <s id="s206">To the south arises <enamex sw="w39430" long="-2.9204" lat="54.5446" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7732640" name="Placefell" conf="99992">Placefell</enamex> and Birkfell, around whose base the lake turns; these are entirely barren, without either tree or shrub, or al - most verdure, and are composed of rock and sparry schisters, mixed with gravel, which is continually rolling into the water below.</s> <s id="s207">They are likewise exceedingly steep, and dip their perpendicular sides into the lake, denying all access alongst the shore.</s></p>
<p><s id="s208">Those on the other side of <enamex sw="w39834" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, where the traveller is placed, are, as just now mentioned, of still <enamex sw="w39913" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="1.005768847">superior</enamex> altitude; particularly Helvellin, the rival of <enamex sw="w39969" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, which rears its head to the sky, and stands," proudly pre-eminent."</s> <s id="s209">Their sides are intersected by immense chasms, where numbers of torrents and cascades, deep ingulphed' midst woods and rocks, continually roar.</s> <s id="s210">All alongst the bases of these mountains, and for a considerable way up, they are covered with trees.</s> <s id="s211">Here and there starts from amongst the woods, many dreadful precipices, never hitherto scaled, and where the eagle, and other birds of prey, undisturbed rear their young.</s> <s id="s212">Farther up, the trees are more thinly scattered; at last they give place to heath, and some patches of grass, and to these succeed the region of perpetual cold and sterility.</s> <s id="s213">This appears to be the character of the side-screen to the right, as well as of the other mountains which encircle the lake at its farther extremity.</s> <s id="s214">With respect to the sheet of water itself, it lies in the bosom of this immense amphitheatre, like an embossed mirror, reflecting the surrounding objects upon its surface, which is here decorated with four small islets, that, together with the houses and chapel of <enamex sw="w41053" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex> in the distance, add still farther interest to the scene.</s></p>
<p><s id="s215">To describe, however, in adequate terms, the grandeur of the prospect, is impossible:-- to be enjoyed it must be seen.</s> <s id="s216">Figure to yourself, however, the objects just now mentioned, in the most favourable situation, of the most picturesque form, and varied outline;-- consider the effects resulting from the different distances at which they are placed:-- some shaded with the softer aerial hues-- others, nearer at hand, coloured with the most beautiful tints which such a diversity of trees, of verdure, heath, and rocks will occasion;-- conceive some part of the landscape in the shade, and the sunbeams illuminating the rest;-- add life and motion to the picture: The clouds floating slowly across the top of Helvellin, and some lying upon its breast, like lazy mists, far below its summit;-- the numerous flights of birds continually skimming the air, from rock to rock, or tree to tree;-- the cooing of the wood-pigeon;-- the bleating of numerous herds in the pastures, and a rich and variegated foreground, and then you may have some faint idea of the prospect of <enamex sw="w42202" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, at its farther extremity-- a prospect which art could indeed but feebly imitate:</s></p>
<p><s id="s217">----" For who can paint Like Nature?</s> <s id="s218">Can imagination boast, Amidst its gay creation, hues like her's; Or can it mix them with that matchless skill, And lose them in each other."</s></p>
<p><s id="s219">Having enjoyed this fine landscape, we descended into a lawn, nearer the lake, and obtained another fine view of <enamex sw="w42588" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, looking downwards with <enamex sw="w42622" long="-2.9206" lat="54.5761" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11210312" name="Lyulph's Tower" conf="99992">Lyulph</enamex>'s tower and the mountain behind it, upon the left: At this time, two young ladies were employed in delineating its features with their pencil, and apparently, from the situation they had taken, and other circumstances, with much taste.</s> <s id="s220">We shortly thereafter left Gowbarrow park, and proceeded upwards into <enamex sw="w42935" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>, the road leading still alongst the side of the lake, sometimes level and open, then running through glades and thickets, or rising up the side of a proud promontory, overhanging the lake in a terrific manner, and then descending as before.</s> <s id="s221">In this part of the course, the many glens formed betwixt the mountains display themselves as we proceed, some open and expansive, others narrow and deep, overhung with impending woods, and darkened by the towering hills.</s></p>
<p><s id="s222">After ascending a headland, hanging over the water, in a fearful manner, and which again is overhung with rocks and trees, commanding two stretches of the lake, you descend gradually upon the opposite side, and thus continue, through groves, meadows, and fields, with the water upon the left, till you pass some neat houses, and amongst these, upon the right, a modern elegant mansion, the residence of J. Mounsey, Esq; the principal proprietor of this sequestered district, who, and upon this account, is called the King of Patterdale.</s> <s id="s223">You then pass the church, with a large yew, and immediately arrive at the inn called the King's Arms, a small, but agreeable place of entertainment, situated, with this small village, at the head of the lake, which here is surrounded, and stopped, as it were, by the mountains.</s></p>
<p><s id="s224">The views at <enamex sw="w44237" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex> are many and beautiful, not only of <enamex sw="w44284" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex> and its mountain-screens, but also of particular parts, amongst the deep ravines or gills, as they are called, and the numerous rocks and woods, which in these situations present themselves, in the most picturesque and sublime forms, composing some enchanting close scenes, many of whom, it is believed, have as yet escaped the pencil.</s> <s id="s225">Amongst these recesses, the finest echoes are also to be met with, and in one situation, upon a small eminence, at the back of the inn, the sound is repeated, it is said, no less than seven times.</s></p>
<p><s id="s226">For the purpose of arousing this echo, a small cannon is kept by Mr. Dobson, the landlord, which he discharges for a trifling expence.</s> <s id="s227">We were curious enough to try the experiment, and were much pleased.</s> <s id="s228">At first the report was echoed from the opposite rocks, where, by reverberation, it seemed to roll from cliff to cliff, and return through every valley, till the decreasing tumult gradually died away upon the ear.</s> <s id="s229">The instant it had ceased, the sound of every distant waterfall was heard, but for an instant only, for the momentary stillness was interrupted by the returning echo on the hills, behind where the report was repeated, like a peal of thunder bursting over our heads, continuing for several seconds flying from haunt to haunt, till once more the sound gradually declined.</s> <s id="s230">Again the voice of waterfalls possessed the interval, till, to the right, the more distant thunder arose upon some other mountain, and seemed to take its way up every winding dell and creek, some behind on this side, or on that, in wondrous speed running its dreadful course.</s> <s id="s231">In this manner we heard it three or four times, but not so often as was represented, which may have been owing to the air at the time having been in an unfavourable state, or to some other unknown cause.</s> <s id="s232">From the same situation, where the cannon is placed, the prospect down <enamex sw="w46166" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex> is very fine, composed of the lofty mountains so often mentioned as the side screens, of Gowbarrow park and <enamex sw="w46284" long="-2.9206" lat="54.5761" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11210312" name="Lyulph's Tower" conf="99992">Lyulph</enamex>'s tower in the distance, and in the centre the lake and its islands, betwixt and which is a small and beautiful meadow, watered by a meandering stream, called <enamex sw="w46450" long="-2.939722956" lat="54.54100646" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00143" name="Goldrill Beck" conf="99992">Gold Rill Beck</enamex>, and enlivened by the chapel-inn, and neat houses of <enamex sw="w46518" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s233">A mountainous pass leads from <enamex sw="w46562" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex> to <enamex sw="w46576" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> and <enamex sw="w46590" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>, which some travellers take.</s> <s id="s234">It is truly an Alpine road, winding in a contracted vale, with a high and naked mountain on the left.</s> <s id="s235">Several trees are scattered around in the first part of the road, but which gradually decrease in number as you ascend.</s> <s id="s236">You then pass a small lake called <enamex sw="w46886" long="-77.0127535" lat="38.7415036" type="other" gazref="unlock:7099144" name="Broadwater Estates" conf="0.9376235527">Broadwater</enamex>, from which the small river of <enamex sw="w46928" long="-2.939722956" lat="54.54100646" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00143" name="Goldrill Beck" conf="99992">Gold Rill Beck</enamex> arises, and so proceed through a barren tract, with a steep ascent, till you gain the heights of <enamex sw="w47040" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s237">On every hand lie immense fragments of rocks, which have from time to time been severed from the hills above.</s> <s id="s238">About half way up the mountain we find a passage to the other side, from whence we descend through a dreary and mountainous country to <enamex sw="w47296" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, distant from <enamex sw="w47320" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex> 9 miles.</s></p>
<p><s id="s239">Several boats are kept here for the use of strangers; one of these we hired, after some stay at the inn, and sailed down the lake, enjoying, in a serene afternoon, the fine scenery around us.</s> <s id="s240">We landed at <enamex sw="w47545" long="-2.9206" lat="54.5761" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11210312" name="Lyulph's Tower" conf="99992">Lyulph</enamex>'s tower, and discharged the boat, with the view of proceeding across the mountains to <enamex sw="w47638" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s241">Before setting out, we visited the tower, and obtained permission to walk through <enamex  sw="w47729" name="Too ambigious to allocate">the park</enamex> to the cataract, called the Ayreforce.</s> <s id="s242">It is situated about the eighth of a mile from the lake, upon a rivulet issuing from the high grounds, and embowered in wood; the banks are precipitous and rocky, and the fall, to which we descend by a steep and rugged path, rushes out from betwixt two rocks, through a narrow opening, into the space below.</s> <s id="s243">The scenery is fine and picturesque, particularly from the point of view from which the water is first observed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s244">We left this place at eight o'clock in the evening, it being midsummer, and took the road to <enamex sw="w48291" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, distant, as was said, ten miles.</s> <s id="s245">For a considerable way the ascent was steep and difficult; the road then became more level, on entering a beautiful pastoral valley, called <enamex sw="w48473" long="-2.935358608405132" lat="54.60372737174727" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36869" name="Matterdale End" conf="2.6">Matterdale</enamex>, watered by a rivulet run - ning into <enamex sw="w48521" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, and strewed here and there with cottages and farms, many of the inhabitants of which were, with their children, sitting upon benches at their doors, seemingly comfortable and happy, while enjoying the serenity of the evening.</s> <s id="s246">To our surprise, soon after, the road began again to scale the sides of the mountain, and continued ascending, for nearly two miles, when we arrived, very much fatigued from the days exertions, at a cottage upon the brow of the eminence.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s247">As the road we took should only be ventured upon in the day, and at no time with carriages, another is recommended by the road retracing from <enamex sw="w49139" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex> to <enamex sw="w49153" long="-2.812994518069897" lat="54.61280820901722" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11248058" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley</enamex>; thence a road leads to <enamex sw="w49184" long="-2.84052575158113" lat="54.63029066990679" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:38469" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex>, having <enamex sw="w49198" long="-2.83754" lat="54.63056" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825055" name="Dacre Castle" conf="2">Dacre Castle</enamex> on the right, and so on by an old castle like mansion, called <enamex sw="w49273" long="-2.8695" lat="54.6346" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY43972696" name="Hutton St John" conf="99992">Hutton</enamex> <enamex sw="w49280" long="-1.361732484769859" lat="51.99535612997623" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:22330" name="Barford St John" conf="1.458122252">St. John</enamex>, to <enamex sw="w49293" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, 15 miles.</s></p>
<p><s id="s248">We now entered a dreary common, covered with coarse grass and heath, the road becoming a mere tract, and in some situations, for a considerable space, not to be observed.</s> <s id="s249">We luckily, however, continued in the direction, and soon began to descend, while the night, by advancing upon us, shut out the distinct prospect of all distant objects.</s> <s id="s250">At length we perceived, as we thought, the lake of <enamex sw="w49704" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, to which we eagerly directed our steps, down the steep side of the mountain.</s> <s id="s251">We were, however, much disappointed, when we found, upon inquiry at a house that lay in our way, that we were still distant three miles, and that the illusion had arisen from the fogs of the night, lying in the valleys.</s> <s id="s252">Passing on, the road improved; hedgerows and inclosures lying upon each hand; thus it continued till we arrived at <enamex sw="w50130" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, at one in the morning, having taken about five hours to cross the mountainous tract, a tract which should never be attempted but in the day, or even at that time, without a guide acquainted with the country.</s></p>
<p><s id="s253">On the following morning, after our arrival at <enamex sw="w50395" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, we walked out a short distance from the town, for the purpose of viewing the lake of</s></p>
<p><s id="s254"><enamex sw="w50489" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>,</s></p>
<p><s id="s255">sometimes also, from the name of the town, called <enamex sw="w50553" long="-3.14956" lat="54.584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2651313" name="Derwentwater" conf="99991">Keswick lake</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s256">This sheet of water is about 3 miles in length, by half that space at its greatest breadth, and is of an irregular elliptical figure, stretching north and south.</s> <s id="s257">Its surface is variegated with five beautiful wooded islands, some of which are naked, while others are decorated with wood.</s> <s id="s258">The most remarkable of these is named Pocklington's Island, rising in a spheriodical form from the water, and upon which is a modern built, and neat looking house, the property of Colonel Peachy.</s> <s id="s259">The next may be reckoned Lords' Island, formerly the residence of the Earls of <enamex sw="w51129" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, the ruins of whose seat are still to be seen.</s> <s id="s260"><enamex sw="w51189" long="-3.137379681649069" lat="54.58323023593808" type="other" gazref="unlock:11276541" name="St Herbert's Island" conf="2">St. Herbert's Island</enamex>, more in the middle of the lake, almost entirely covered with trees; and Rampsholm, an island smaller than the three last mentioned, and destitute of wood.</s></p>
<p><s id="s261"><enamex sw="w51366" long="-3.14956" lat="54.584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2651313" name="Derwentwater" conf="99991">Keswick lake</enamex>, like that of <enamex sw="w51393" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, lies in the bosom of a valley, surrounded by mountains.</s> <s id="s262">The vale, in which the former reposes is, however, much wider in its dimensions than that which contains the latter.</s> <s id="s263">A considerable tract of low lands lies also betwixt the base of the mountains and the waters edge, which is not in general the case with respect to the boundaries of <enamex sw="w51743" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s264">The extremities of this valley are open, and communicate with other districts.</s> <s id="s265">The northern is a beautiful, spacious, and fertile plain, watered by the <enamex sw="w51906" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>, which passes through <enamex sw="w51936" long="-3.14956" lat="54.584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2651313" name="Derwentwater" conf="99991">Keswick lake</enamex> and neighbourhood.</s> <s id="s266">The southern leads into a most rugged vale, called <enamex sw="w52019" long="-3.15327" lat="54.52342" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00036" name="Borrowdale" conf="99991">Borrodale</enamex>, abounding with the most romantic and picturesque scenery.</s></p>
<p><s id="s267">The mountains that form the barriers of this lake, are not in general so lofty as those around the upper division of <enamex sw="w52205" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, if we except <enamex sw="w52229" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, the glory of the vale, and whose base lies about a mile from the northern extremity of the lake.</s> <s id="s268">The hills that lie upon the east side of <enamex sw="w52376" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, are in general finely broken in some places, presenting the most dreadful precipices, intermingled with copse-wood and verdure, betwixt the many interstices of which, are some fine cascades.</s> <s id="s269">Those on the opposite side are more smooth and regular in their sur - face, in general verdant, and except near to the waters edge, destitute, or nearly so, of wood.</s> <s id="s270">The town of <enamex sw="w52758" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> lies upon the northern bank of the lake, at an inconsiderable distance, and betwixt and the mountain of <enamex sw="w52870" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, having a fine view of the valley towards the south.</s></p>
<p><s id="s271">The first station we took, as already mentioned, was immediately in the vicinity of the town, at a place called <enamex sw="w53043" long="-0.9883475275881595" lat="53.24494530095355" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11123428" name="Crow Park" conf="1.169975051">Crow Park</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s272">From this place, the surface of <enamex sw="w53086" long="-3.14956" lat="54.584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2651313" name="Derwentwater" conf="99991">Keswick lake</enamex> spreads out in a beautiful sheet before the eye, variegated with the islands upon its surface, and the promontories jutting out from the shore.</s> <s id="s273">The mountains upon each hand run nearly parallel to the waters edge, and as they recede from the eye, tend to a point at the farther extremity of the lake, leaving only a narrow pass, through which we have a view, into the yawning jaws of <enamex sw="w53482" long="-3.15327" lat="54.52342" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00036" name="Borrowdale" conf="99991">Borrodale</enamex>, where mountain appears piled above mountain, in endless form and variety.</s></p>
<p><s id="s274">Leaving this situation, we walked eastward through some inclosures, to a lofty conical eminence, great part of which was covered with wood, and which, from its situation, promised an extensive prospect of the scenery: in this we were not disappointed; the view from its summit is truly fine, embracing the whole extent of the lake and its islands; with the surrounding mountains; the town of <enamex sw="w53959" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> below your feet; with the church of Crossthwaite, the villa of <enamex sw="w54030" long="-3.13838207425008" lat="54.61917439673673" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11237096" name="Ormathwaite" conf="2.6">Ormathwaite</enamex>, the seat of J. Walsh, Esq; and immediately beyond, turning towards the right, the mountain of <enamex sw="w54137" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, rearing his summit on high.</s> <s id="s275">The windings of the <enamex sw="w54194" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>, which flows from the lake into <enamex sw="w54234" long="-3.193601937631324" lat="54.67926476125776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15906" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex>, and the rich and fertile plain, with its numerous seats, villas, and cottages, and part of the last mentioned lake, lying in the direction of, and beyond the town, are also within the scope of this beautiful scene, together with many other objects which it is unnecessary to particularize.</s></p>
<p><s id="s276">Though the view from the top is thus extensive and general, yet in a picturesque point of view, a station farther down the hill is undoubtedly preferable, though the view is more contracted.</s> <s id="s277">In such a situation, the barriers of the lake appear to rise, with magnificence, upon each side; its shores are also more pleasantly indented by capes and headlands, receding behind each other, than in a higher point, and the outline of the islands rises in some situations, so as to break the uniformity of the opposite shore.</s> <s id="s278">A rich and variegated foreground may also here be obtained, composed of rock, bushes, and some beautiful oaks and shrubs, presenting, in their form, colour, and shade, a delightful contrast to the distant objects seen through the openings, or betwixt the branches.</s></p>
<p><s id="s279">Descending from this situation, at the base of the hill you find a road leading from <enamex sw="w55408" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, up the eastern bank of the lake, to its southern extremity, or rather to the village of Grange, somewhat farther on; this road, which winds through level and fertile fields, and in some places groves of trees, is in general nearly level with the water, of which it presents many interesting views.</s> <s id="s280">As you advance, the mountains upon the left increase in height, presenting their craggy fronts to the lake, interspersed in the most romantic manner, with numerous copses, trees, and bushes.</s> <s id="s281">An enormous mass called Wallow Craig, now advances on the left, beyond which, after passing a grove of trees, and near to the gate, a very beautiful view of <enamex sw="w56064" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> lies before the eye, its islands appearing in a different situation, as well as form, than when seen from <enamex sw="w56183" long="-3.8" lat="54.85" type="other" gazref="unlock:4577958" name="Castlehill Point" conf="1.811745902">Castlehill</enamex>, and the other objects, in like manner, much varied.</s> <s id="s282">Upon the opposite shore is <enamex sw="w56274" long="-3.369732073254444" lat="54.5898121897326" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11314285" name="Waterend" conf="2.6">Waterend</enamex>, a seat of Lord William Gordon, rising from the wood, and beyond, the lofty mountains of Causeypike and <enamex sw="w56387" long="-3.200320135150944" lat="54.61857621602921" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11299921" name="Thornthwaite" conf="2.6">Thornthwaite</enamex>, which lie near the entrance of the vale of <enamex sw="w56444" long="-3.185804700514816" lat="54.57418107642148" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790063" name="Newlands Beck" conf="2.4">Newlands</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s283">Continuing southwards, a road strikes off to the left, up a steep ascent, leading to the romantic valley of Watenlah; shortly afterwards you meet with and cross a rivulet, forming here a beautiful cascade, issuing from the mountains, upon the banks of which is Cascade hall, a modern house, the residence of Joseph Pocklington, Esq;.</s> <s id="s284">Passing this place, the sublimity of the scenery increases; the rocks, in some situations, impend over the road, threatening destruction to the traveller, while upon all hands, immense fragments of them lie around, interspersed with bushes, trees, and flowering shrubs.</s></p>
<p><s id="s285">The mountains now incline more to the right, following the outline of the lake, which very quickly contracts; a deep ravine appears cut in the side of the hills, through which is seen the waterfall of <enamex sw="w57259" long="-3.1366" lat="54.5563" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="99992">Lowdore</enamex>, roaring with incessant noise from rock to rock, and presenting, with the projecting crags, the variegated foliage and fantastic branches, stretching from bank to bank; the deep and dark recesses which it has excavated; and the lofty and broken mountains upon each side, a truly grand and picturesque scene.</s> <s id="s286">Immediately after passing this cataract, we fall in with a neat small house, situated betwixt the mountains and the lake, called the inn of <enamex sw="w57715" long="-3.1366" lat="54.5563" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="99992">Lowdore</enamex>, and in its vicinity, the River <enamex sw="w57755" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>, serpentizing through low swampy meadows, into the lake, at the head of which you are now arrived.</s></p>
<p><s id="s287">In this situation, the mountains upon the opposite sides appear to have advanced towards each other, leaving only a vale, betwixt and which, still farther contracts as you proceed, watered by the river just now mentioned.</s> <s id="s288">Into this vale we entered, leaving the lake behind us.</s> <s id="s289">The road became shortly uneven and craggy, and the scenery very wild and sublime; thus we continued for a short space, till we came to the bridge of Grange, crossing the <enamex sw="w58309" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>, to the small village of that name upon the opposite side.</s> <s id="s290">This bridge, the village, and adjacent mountains, have already often afforded a subject for many excellent pencils, and a more striking and romantic scene is not often to be found.</s> <s id="s291">Continuing on, the valley still contracts, while the mountains increase in altitude and barreness.</s> <s id="s292">A singular conical hill rises before you, and appears to shut up, as it were, the vale: Its name is <enamex sw="w58756" long="-3.090245821198284" lat="54.55669882687418" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11100762" name="Castle Crag (Fort)" conf="2.2">Castle Crag</enamex>, upon the top of which, a fine prospect of the lake of <enamex sw="w58823" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, looking downwards, is obtained, bounded by <enamex sw="w58875" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> in the distance, and having the village of Grange, the serpentizing <enamex sw="w58951" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>, and the rocky and broken mountains near the foreground.</s></p>
<p><s id="s293">Turning to the opposite direction, the prospect is awfully sublime, commanding a view of the vale of <enamex sw="w59117" long="-3.15327" lat="54.52342" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00036" name="Borrowdale" conf="99991">Borrodale</enamex>, with its numerous mountains, towering, and piled, as it were, above each other.</s></p>
<p><s id="s294">This singular and secluded valley, at the entrance of which <enamex sw="w59268" long="-3.090245821198284" lat="54.55669882687418" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11100762" name="Castle Crag (Fort)" conf="2.2">Castle Crag</enamex> is situated, differs much in its character from that we have just now left.</s> <s id="s295">It is much more contracted in its dimensions, while the mountains which surround it are far more lofty, and cut into the most romantic shapes, from the numerous projecting rocks which almost every where cover the surface, raising their summits to the sky, particularly one, called the <enamex sw="w59641" long="-3.119691681724922" lat="54.50249902257166" type="other" gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="2">Eagle Crag</enamex>, where these birds rear their young.</s></p>
<p><s id="s296">No trees, and but a scanty portion of verdure, mixed with heath, appear on the mountains, in the distance, instead of these, immense blocks of stone lie thick on every hand, grey with age, and tinted here and there with variegated moss.</s> <s id="s297">Nearer at hand, the mountains, though equally barren, are indeed somewhat more interesting, from some scattered trees which grow from their surface, and by their verdure, contrast finely with the purple heath, and the grey rocks, which jut out from amongst the foliage.</s> <s id="s298">In the middle of this immense amphitheatre lies a small portion of flat land, with some neat looking cottages and inclosures, watered by the <enamex sw="w60337" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>, which rises from the neighbouring mountains.</s></p>
<p><s id="s299">Though upon our approach to <enamex sw="w60419" long="-3.090245821198284" lat="54.55669882687418" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11100762" name="Castle Crag (Fort)" conf="2.2">Castle Crag</enamex> it appears, as has been already mentioned, to block up the valley, yet when still nearer, a passage opens upon the left, which we took, and after a short ascent, arrived at an immense rock, lying on the way, called the <enamex sw="w60650" long="-3.151583904821857" lat="54.53815357559134" type="other" gazref="unlock:11084123" name="Bowder Stone" conf="2">Bowder Stone</enamex>, seemingly precipitated from the mountains upon the left.</s> <s id="s300">This prodigious block is of an irregular form, with a number of angles, upon one of which it rests, resembling somewhat a vessel resting upon her keel, when viewed with the stern in front.</s> <s id="s301">A ladder is placed here, for the convenience of such as chuse to ascend to its top, which is covered with heath, and from whence it is a fine view of <enamex sw="w61060" long="-3.15327" lat="54.52342" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00036" name="Borrowdale" conf="99991">Borrodale</enamex> and the scenery already mentioned.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s302">This singular stone is of the following dimensions: In length, 62 feet; perpendicular height, 36 feet; circumference, 89 feet.</s> <s id="s303">It contains 23,090 solid feet, and its weight is ascertained to be 1771 tons, 13 pounds.</s></p>
<p><s id="s304">In the immediate neighbourhood is a small cottage, where strangers can be supplied with specimens of spars, and the other productions of these romantic mountains, at an easy rate, and where they will find an agreeable shade during the summer's heats.</s></p>
<p><s id="s305">Upon the south side of the <enamex sw="w61601" long="-3.151583904821857" lat="54.53815357559134" type="other" gazref="unlock:11084123" name="Bowder Stone" conf="2">Bowder Stone</enamex>, the road descends into <enamex sw="w61638" long="-3.15327" lat="54.52342" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00036" name="Borrowdale" conf="99991">Borrodale</enamex>, while the vale begins to open, so as to admit a small cultivated spot, which increases in breadth, till you pass the village of <enamex sw="w61777" long="-3.160418408000877" lat="54.30436355899656" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11272960" name="Rosthwaite" conf="2.6">Rosthwaite</enamex>, and a little farther, <enamex sw="w61811" long="-3.147837314" lat="54.51566313" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00120" name="Borrowdale Chapel" conf="99992">Borrodale chapel</enamex>; the road then divides to the right and left, with a narrow road up each valley; that to the left leads to <enamex sw="w61935" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> in <enamex  sw="w61948" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, or <enamex sw="w61965" long="-2.997689462703833" lat="54.37597546544907" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:30241" name="Hawkshead" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex>, near <enamex sw="w61981" long="-3.0765" lat="54.3361" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2653454" name="Coniston Water" conf="99991">Coniston lake</enamex> in <enamex  sw="w61998" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>, over a high mountain, called the <enamex sw="w62043" long="-2.719956334576551" lat="53.72351753550559" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11321004" name="White Stake" conf="1.467709522">Stake</enamex>, exhibiting in its course, the wildest and most barren scenes for about eight miles, after which it becomes more pleasing and agreeable, and so continues to the place just now mentioned.</s></p>
<p><s id="s306">The road to the right leads over Styhead to Wastdale, Wastwater lake, and <enamex sw="w62311" long="-3.406748881310928" lat="54.35437318902203" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:43249" name="Ravenglass" conf="2.6">Ravenglass</enamex>, on the coast of the Irish sea.</s> <s id="s307">In this line of road, a short way above the chapel of <enamex sw="w62408" long="-3.15327" lat="54.52342" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00036" name="Borrowdale" conf="99991">Borrodale</enamex>, you come opposite the celebrated black lead mines, the first and richest in <enamex  sw="w62495" name="Large admin unit">Britain</enamex>, if not in the world; they lie about half way up the mountain upon the right, and are easily discovered from the brown earth cast out by the workings, contrasting with the colour of the surrounding surface.</s></p>
<p><s id="s308">Here there are two workings, as they are called; the lower one is about 340 yards above the level of the sea, the upper one about 390; the perpendicular depth of the lower is about 105 yards, and of the upper between 20 and 30 yards.</s> <s id="s309">There are no certain marks on the surface to direct the miner to the mineral.</s> <s id="s310">The strata of the mountains are very irregular and broken, and the black lead probably was formed in the fissures of the rocks.</s> <s id="s311">There is no regular stratum of this mineral; it is met with in lumps, and irregular masses.</s></p>
<p><s id="s312">The miners generally work through a quantity of earth, mixed with stones of various kinds; then a species of hard granite, and after that, a dark blue stone of a softer nature, where they meet with it.</s> <s id="s313">The rock adjoining is often tinged as black as the mineral itself, to the depth of two or three feet.</s> <s id="s314">The ore is described as lying in the mine, in the form of a tree, having a body or root, from which proceed veins or branches in all directions.</s> <s id="s315">The body is the finest black lead, and the branches the worst.</s> <s id="s316">It is, however, sometimes, though seldom, found in sops or floats, in a body without branches.</s> <s id="s317">A blue rock lies on each side of the mineral, and sometimes a wet sludge, as the miners term it, between the rock and the black lead.</s></p>
<p><s id="s318">From the value of this substance,( which often sells at 3 guineas per pound,) the greatest precautions are used to prevent its being pilfered.</s> <s id="s319">An act of Parliament was obtained for this purpose, in the reign of King George Ii.</s> <s id="s320">inflicting severe punishments against transgressors.</s> <s id="s321">Other measures have also been taken, by building a wall of mason-work, and houses opposite to or over the entrances of the mines, inhabited by the overseers and workmen, so that all access is debarred without their consent.</s></p>
<p><s id="s322">After passing these mines, the vale becomes more contracted, bleak, naked, and less picturesque.</s> <s id="s323">You pass the small village of <enamex sw="w64615" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>, surrounded by the mountains in such a manner, that it is said the sun never shines upon it in the depth of winter.</s> <s id="s324">Farther on, the vale is terminated by a mountain running across, which in general stops the farther progress of visitants.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s325">A road, however, leads over this mountain to the vale of Wastdale, surrounded by lofty hills, and the lake of Wastwater, which measures about 3 miles in length, by one fourth of a mile in breadth.</s></p>
<p><s id="s326">Returning therefore alongst the valley, we have the same scenes already taken notice of, in other, but no less pleasing points of view.</s> <s id="s327">Besides the <enamex sw="w65212" long="-3.119691681724922" lat="54.50249902257166" type="other" gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="2">Eagle Crag</enamex>, formerly mentioned, the principal mountains are called by the names of <enamex sw="w65295" long="-3.165501892757764" lat="54.4840889517741" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11153221" name="Glaramara" conf="2.4">Glaramara</enamex>, <enamex sw="w65306" long="-3.119691681724922" lat="54.50249902257166" type="other" gazref="unlock:11092104" name="Bull Crag" conf="2">Bull Crag</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w65321" long="-66.198852923" lat="45.500146487" type="other" gazref="unlock:5320210" name="Mount Serjeant" conf="0.5355871469">Serjeant</enamex> Crag, presenting the most abrupt and dreadful precipices.</s></p>
<p><s id="s328">The rocks of which they are composed are in general either a blue rag or limestone.</s> <s id="s329">The most prevalent is the former; the mountains formed of this stone are covered with a wet and spongy grass, with great inequalities in its surface, which gives them a disagreeable and barren appearance.</s> <s id="s330">Such of the hills as contain limestone, though in common not so elevated as those just mentioned, are nevertheless more agreeable in their appearance, having a fine verdant dry turf, where they are not broken by the rocks, and afford excellent pasturage.</s></p>
<p><s id="s331">In <enamex sw="w65935" long="-3.15327" lat="54.52342" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00036" name="Borrowdale" conf="99991">Borrodale</enamex>, the moss, which in most other situations is in the valleys, or upon the sides of the hills, lies upon their summit, where it is, in some situations, of a great depth.</s> <s id="s332">As the inhabitants of the vales use a great deal of peat-earth for fuel, they are under the necessity of having recourse to a singular method of procuring it.</s> <s id="s333">After it is dug and dried, a person carries a sledge upon his back to the top of the mountain, from whence, when filled, he conducts it down the most awful descents, by placing himself before it, to diminish the velocity, which would otherwise be too great.</s></p>
<p><s id="s334">In this valley they likewise practise the most dangerous method of bird-catching, by suspending a person with ropes, let down from the top of the rocks, for sometimes 20 fathoms, till opposite the nest, which the person in this situation plunders of its young, though often not without the most furious resistance from the parent birds, should they not previously have been frightened away by the shouting of some of the party, placed at the bottom of the precipice.</s> <s id="s335">This mode of plunder is most commonly directed against the eagle, which here is very destructive to the sheep in the breeding season, often carrying off at the rate of a lamb per day.</s></p>
<p><s id="s336">Leaving <enamex sw="w67189" long="-3.15327" lat="54.52342" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00036" name="Borrowdale" conf="99991">Borrodale</enamex>, you again find yourself near the head of <enamex sw="w67241" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>.</s> <s id="s337">To vary the prospects, the road which leads down the western banks is in general taken by those who have come up the opposite side, otherwise they sail down the lake, as they find mozt agreeable.</s></p>
<p><s id="s338">Crossing the <enamex sw="w67464" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex> by the bridge of Grange, already mentioned, we fall in with the village of that name, whence continue alongst the road, running north by the base of the hills, till near the head of the lake, when you obtain a delightful prospect from a station on a woody rock, near the way, at which it appears in a new and picturesque point of view.</s> <s id="s339">We then shortly enter upon an excellent road, made lately, at the expence of Lord William Gordon, and commanding, from its elevation, a complete view of the water, and its various accompaniments.</s> <s id="s340">We first wind through a wood, to a naked rocky mountain, alongst the side of which, the road ascends gently and regularly, to the corner of <enamex sw="w68144" long="-3.161701326" lat="54.57412879" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00123" name="Brandelhow Park" conf="99992">Brandelow park</enamex>, after running parallel to which, for some length of way, it proceeds alongst the verdant breast of a high and steep mountain, winding into the dells, with a pleasing variety of prospects.</s> <s id="s341">Here, indeed, nothing obstructs our view of the various beauties of the scene.</s> <s id="s342">Above us the mountain on whose skirts we are now treading, rises abruptly into the cloudy regions.</s> <s id="s343">On the opposite side of the lake, the cataract of <enamex sw="w68576" long="-3.1366" lat="54.5563" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="99992">Lowdore</enamex> is distinctly seen, with <enamex sw="w68609" name="Lowdore house">Lowdore house</enamex>, the inn, and other objects, lying at the bottom of the mountains.</s> <s id="s344">On one hand we have <enamex sw="w68710" long="-3.161701326" lat="54.57412879" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00123" name="Brandelhow Park" conf="99992">Brandelow park</enamex>, and on the other, Foe park, with <enamex sw="w68759" long="-3.369732073254444" lat="54.5898121897326" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11314285" name="Waterend" conf="2.6">Waterend</enamex>, the seat of Lord William Gordon, peeping from the wood, at our feet, and lying on the broadest part of <enamex sw="w68872" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, at the extremity of a fine bay, which washes its walls.</s></p>
<p><s id="s345">We now cross the vale of <enamex sw="w68967" long="-3.185804700514816" lat="54.57418107642148" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790063" name="Newlands Beck" conf="2.4">Newlands</enamex>, opening into that of <enamex sw="w68998" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, and winding round Foe park, pass the foot of <enamex sw="w69052" long="-3.168321741791226" lat="54.58293549454491" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11296646" name="Swinside" conf="2.6">Swinside</enamex>, a green sided mountain, which intersects the vale.</s> <s id="s346">Ascending this hill, you obtain a beautiful prospect, not only of <enamex sw="w69179" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, but also <enamex sw="w69202" long="-3.216877183061965" lat="54.65436466085852" type="water" gazref="unlock:11071446" name="Bassenthwaite Lake" conf="2.4">Bassenthwaite lake</enamex>, their rich shores, and encircling mountains.</s> <s id="s347">Farther on, the road passes <enamex sw="w69295" name="Finckle">Finckle</enamex> Street house, the seat of Joseph Pocklington, Esq; and shortly enter the village of <enamex sw="w69387" long="-3.160383346954682" lat="54.60035046101643" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13221" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex>, whence you proceed through a rich and level tract, crossing the <enamex sw="w69464" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex> by a bridge, about two miles, till you again arrive at the town of <enamex sw="w69539" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s348">Before leaving <enamex sw="w69563" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, we hired a boat, with assistants, for sailing upon the lake, and in this excursion, were much pleased with the change of prospect, which our continual shift of situation afforded, by sailing from shore to shore, or island to island, and by the varying altitude or depressions of the different mountains, and the consequent effects which were produced by approaching or receding, nearer or farther off.</s> <s id="s349">In sailing from <enamex sw="w69990" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, you find Pocklington's Island upon your right, and shortly thereafter, after passing a point of land, <enamex sw="w70101" long="-3.137379681649069" lat="54.58323023593808" type="other" gazref="unlock:11206449" name="Lord's Island" conf="2">Lord's Island</enamex>, upon the left, then on the same hand, the small island of Rampsholm.</s> <s id="s350">Nearly opposite, and almost in the middle of the lake, is St. Herbert's island.</s> <s id="s351">This beautiful isle contains about 4 acres, and is the property of Sir Wilfrid Lawson.</s> <s id="s352">It is planted with fir and other trees, and contains an octagonal grotto or cottage, built with unhewn stones, mossed over and thatched, and near to the situation of an ancient hut, said to have been occupied formerly by St. Herbert, the bosom friend of <enamex sw="w70606" long="-3.392880350420522" lat="54.81426162231475" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11177650" name="Holme St Cuthbert" conf="2.586940047">St. Cuthbert</enamex>, another saint of ancient times, famed throughout <enamex  sw="w70669" name="Large admin unit">Britain</enamex> for his sanctity.</s></p>
<p><s id="s353">The water of <enamex sw="w70708" long="-3.14956" lat="54.584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2651313" name="Derwentwater" conf="99991">Keswick lake</enamex> is remarkably transparent, insomuch so, that when unruffled, you can distinctly see the bottom, covered with beautiful pebbles and spars, and the numerous finny tribe, sporting in different directions, at a great depth.</s> <s id="s354">It is, however, subject sometimes to very sudden agitations, even though there is not a breeze of wind, so that from being as smooth as the surface of a mirror, in a short time it will be ruffled, then violently agitated, rising into waves, and tossing the boats violently, which navigate the surface.</s> <s id="s355">The cause of this, as yet is not, it is believed, thoroughly understood; the people tell you it is owing to what they call a bottom wind.</s> <s id="s356">We were not, however, witnesses of this phenomenon.</s></p>
<p><s id="s357">After having proceeded to the farthest extremity of <enamex sw="w71485" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, and stopped some time in the vale at its head, or the Gorge of <enamex sw="w71562" long="-3.15327" lat="54.52342" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00036" name="Borrowdale" conf="99991">Borrodale</enamex>, already mentioned, we again returned in the evening.</s> <s id="s358">The sun was now low in the heavens, and nearly opposite, tinging with ruddy splendour the mountains upon the right, and gilding the summits of the rocks; the hills upon the left were in the shade, as was the mountain of <enamex sw="w71846" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, lying, together with the islands, directly in front.</s> <s id="s359">All was calm and still, no sound caught the ear but that of the distant waterfalls, or of the oars, striking, in alternate succession, the clear expanse;-- the surface of the lake was smooth and unruffled, reflecting the softened shadows of the mountains on its bosom, as well as the glowing hues of the evening sky.</s> <s id="s360">In such a situation, with such a favourable union of circumstances, the effect of the scene was charming: No glaring light, harsh shade, or gaudy colouring offended the eye; all was soft, harmonious, and beautiful, exhibiting a landscape, touched by the pencil of the ablest of Masters.</s></p>
<p><s id="s361">The lake abounds with excellent fish, particularly trout, perch, and eels; fishing parties are therefore often made up by those who visit these scenes, several of whom we passed by in the course of the evening, which still farther enlivened our short voyage.</s></p>
<p><s id="s362"><enamex sw="w72772" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, at which in general all visitants make some stay, is a neat small town, finely situated on the north banks of the lake.</s> <s id="s363">It consist principally of one street, running east and west, having several good houses, and two or three excellent inns, which, in the season of summer, are much frequented by the numerous visitants.</s> <s id="s364">This town lies in the <enamex sw="w73125" long="-2.131634847718615" lat="54.61546597985309" type="other" gazref="unlock:11123276" name="Crossthwaite Common" conf="0.9466598704">parish of Crossthwaite</enamex>, the church of which is at a little distauce, towards the west, and one of the objects which in many situations appears in the prospects.</s> <s id="s365"><enamex sw="w73286" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> has a weekly market upon Saturday, at which considerable quantities of woollen yarn is sold, spun in the adjacent country.</s> <s id="s366">A cotton manufacture has also been some time established, and it is believed, is in a thriving situation.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s367">At these inns guides are procured to the different scenes in this district; they are in general intelligent and well informed with respect to the most remarkable objects around.</s> <s id="s368">One of these we hired at the Queenshead Inn, kept by Mr. Wood.</s></p>
<p><s id="s369">Here are two museums of natural history, for the entertainment of strangers; one kept by Mr. Crossthwaite, the other by Mr. <enamex  sw="w73890" name="Not a placename">Hutton</enamex>.</s> <s id="s370">That which we visited it Mr. Crossthwaite's, which has been long established: It is in an excellent house, upon the south side of <enamex sw="w74028" long="-2.545503018232447" lat="51.14439493145336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:42065" name="Street On The Fosse" conf="1.419892608">the street</enamex>, and consists of an immense number of articles, such as singular monuments of antiquity, curious foreign birds and beasts, in an excellent state of preservation, remarkable productions of nature, petrifactions, shells, fossils, insects,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s371">all arranged with great order, and kept in several apartments, which you are allowed to visit at your leisure, accompanied by himself or his son, either of whom describes in rotation, the several objects.</s></p>
<p><s id="s372">Beside the stations which we have already pointed out, for viewing to advantage the beauties of the vale of <enamex sw="w74593" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, there are some others in the neighbourhood of the town, which are also much visited.</s> <s id="s373">Three of these may be mentioned: The first, though at the greatest distance, is from the top of a smooth verdant hill, called <enamex sw="w74813" long="-3.122649812250939" lat="54.61033292579526" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11192243" name="Latrigg" conf="2.4">Latrigg</enamex>, lying betwixt the mountain of <enamex sw="w74852" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> and the town, ascending by <enamex sw="w74887" long="-3.23935" lat="54.68571" type="other" gazref="unlock:5826134" name="Monks Hall" conf="2">Monks Hall</enamex>, and leaving the villa of <enamex sw="w74924" long="-3.13838207425008" lat="54.61917439673673" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11237096" name="Ormathwaite" conf="2.6">Ormathwaite</enamex> upon the left, then following the road due east, till you approach the gate of an inclosure, which, after entering, you continue ascending, till you gain the brow of the hill.</s> <s id="s374">From this point, the lake and vale of <enamex sw="w75150" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> with the town, and an innumerable number of objects present themselves before you, in a different order from that in which you may have already seen them.</s> <s id="s375">Farther down the side of the hill, at a place called Round <enamex  sw="w75377" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>, is another station, from whence the prospect is extensive and varied.</s> <s id="s376">The third station is in the immediate neighbourhood of the vicarage, to which a road leads from <enamex sw="w75549" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, towards the north-west, crossing the <enamex sw="w75595" long="-1.8674" lat="54.5148" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:41693" name="Greta Bridge" conf="99991">River Greeta</enamex>, and so continuing about half a mile, to the vicinity of the place just now mentioned.</s></p>
<p><s id="s377">After having seen the beauties of <enamex sw="w75729" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, hired horses, and a guide to conduct us to some of the other lakes that lay to the west.</s> <s id="s378">Leaving the town in the morning, we shortly crossed the <enamex sw="w75888" long="-1.8674" lat="54.5148" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:41693" name="Greta Bridge" conf="99991">River Greeta</enamex>, and continued through a beautiful and fertile plain, with Crossthwaite church and <enamex sw="w75984" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> upon the right, and the lake at some short distance upon the left, till we fell in with the River <enamex sw="w76090" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>, connecting, after some beautiful windings, the lake of <enamex sw="w76154" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> with that of <enamex sw="w76175" long="-3.193601937631324" lat="54.67926476125776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15906" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex>.</s> <s id="s379">This we crossed by a bridge, and entered the village of <enamex sw="w76246" long="-3.160383346954682" lat="54.60035046101643" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13221" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex>, containing a number of pleasant houses.</s></p>
<p><s id="s380">Here a road from the left joins that in which you are travelling, leading down the west side of <enamex sw="w76396" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, and which has been already described.</s> <s id="s381">Instead of passing alongst it, we turned more to the right, taking the road to <enamex sw="w76527" long="-2.706787027148595" lat="54.73930575223526" type="other" gazref="unlock:11278629" name="Scalehill" conf="2">Scalehill</enamex> and <enamex sw="w76541" long="-3.360999570010009" lat="54.6624702211972" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10233" name="Cockermouth" conf="2.6">Cockermouth</enamex>, and shortly began to ascend the side of that great range of mountains, that form the western barriers of <enamex sw="w76659" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> and</s></p>
<p><s id="s382"><enamex sw="w76676" long="-3.216877183061965" lat="54.65436466085852" type="water" gazref="unlock:11071446" name="Bassenthwaite Lake" conf="2.4">Bassenthwaite Lake</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s383">Of this sheet of water we shortly obtained a beautiful view, though at some distance, with the vale in which it lies-- the serpentizing <enamex sw="w76835" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>, and the mountain of <enamex sw="w76864" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, upon its eastern side.</s></p>
<p><s id="s384"><enamex sw="w76896" long="-3.216877183061965" lat="54.65436466085852" type="water" gazref="unlock:11071446" name="Bassenthwaite Lake" conf="2.4">Bassenthwaite lake</enamex> is about four miles in length, and generally more than half a mile broad.</s> <s id="s385">Its banks, and the vale in which it lies, are finely cultivated and improved, adorned every where with white farm houses, embosomed in tufts of trees, seats, groves, and woods.</s></p>
<p><s id="s386">The scenery here is of a milder aspect than that of <enamex sw="w77218" long="-3.14956" lat="54.584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2651313" name="Derwentwater" conf="99991">Keswick lake</enamex> or <enamex sw="w77234" long="-2.933353248091587" lat="54.56025302065807" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13477559" name="Ullswater Ward" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>; it is, nevertheless, still pleasing and beautiful, and in many situations, particularly when the vale of <enamex sw="w77350" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> is taken into the distance, highly picturesque.</s></p>
<p><s id="s387">In order to open fully to view the objects around, a road conducts alongst the shores of the lake, which is in general level and in good repair.</s> <s id="s388">Pursuing this road, instead of proceeding first to <enamex sw="w77607" long="-3.160383346954682" lat="54.60035046101643" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13221" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex>, you turn to the right, shortly after leaving <enamex sw="w77665" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, and continue through winding lanes, passing several genteel houses, and making an easy curve round the base of <enamex sw="w77785" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, with the vale and lake of <enamex sw="w77820" long="-3.193601937631324" lat="54.67926476125776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15906" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex> upon our left.</s> <s id="s389">Amongst the seats that you pass is <enamex sw="w77884" long="-3.56844146408483" lat="54.52447723098862" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11220640" name="Mirehouse" conf="2.6">Mirehouse</enamex>, the seat of Thomas Story, Esq; a neat modern building, shaded with groves of young trees, and standing in the vale, nearly of an equal distance, betwixt the base at <enamex sw="w78060" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> and the lake.</s> <s id="s390">In the neighbourhood, but somewhat farther on, a beautiful view of <enamex sw="w78149" long="-3.193601937631324" lat="54.67926476125776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15906" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex> is obtained, by striking down a road leading to a round green hill, called <enamex sw="w78238" long="-3.201379372187576" lat="54.65451935950071" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11088062" name="Broadness Fm" conf="2.2">Broadness</enamex>, jutting out into the lake, and forming, with two other promontories, a large semicircular bay on each side, with <enamex sw="w78362" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex> on the south, and <enamex sw="w78388" long="-3.20164454734032" lat="54.66350510977144" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11278880" name="Scarness" conf="2.6">Scarness</enamex> on the north.</s> <s id="s391">After regaining the road, you recede somewhat farther from the wa - ter, by way of <enamex sw="w78493" long="-3.193601937631324" lat="54.67926476125776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15906" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex> halls, towards Ousebridge.</s> <s id="s392">On an elevated part of this road, to the north of the village, another fine prospect is obtained, of the lake, the north side of <enamex sw="w78663" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, and the opposite shore.</s> <s id="s393">Farther on, you reach <enamex sw="w78718" long="-2.770280882875323" lat="54.81082168905613" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063742" name="Armathwaite" conf="2.6">Armathwaite</enamex>, a small, but finely situated seat, overlooking the water through a grove of trees; here is likewise an excellent situation for seeing in perfection the beauties of <enamex sw="w78895" long="-3.193601937631324" lat="54.67926476125776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15906" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex>, with the objects already mentioned.</s> <s id="s394">Continuing on, you shortly reach the foot of the lake, from whence the <enamex sw="w79017" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex> issues, passing through a stone bridge of three arches, to <enamex sw="w79084" long="-3.360999570010009" lat="54.6624702211972" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10233" name="Cockermouth" conf="2.6">Cockermouth</enamex>, and so on to <enamex sw="w79110" long="-3.551571779176866" lat="54.62740111743355" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11386" name="Workington" conf="3.038851846">Workington</enamex> and the Irish sea.</s></p>
<p><s id="s395">At this place, which is called Ousebridge, there is a good inn, fronting the lake, and commanding some variegated prospects.</s> <s id="s396">Instead of retracing the same road, the taste of the visitant will be better gratified in returning by the north banks of <enamex sw="w79387" long="-3.193601937631324" lat="54.67926476125776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15906" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex>, alongst which a road, passable on horseback, is conducted.</s> <s id="s397">This road is not, however, so level as the former; sometimes it mounts up the side of a mountain, then drops down to the margin of the water, and at other times is hid amongst the woods, or continues through small farms and inclosures.</s> <s id="s398">It thus affords an almost infinite variety of prospects, many of which are highly beautiful, particularly that which is obtained at a place called Beck <enamex sw="w79849" long="-3.2299" lat="54.65" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:18000" name="Wythop Woods" conf="99992">Withop</enamex>, where the view of the lake, the proud promontories of <enamex sw="w79911" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex> and <enamex sw="w79923" long="-3.20164454734032" lat="54.66350510977144" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11278880" name="Scarness" conf="2.6">Scarness</enamex>, on the opposite shore, and the towering heights of <enamex sw="w79984" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, with the chapel of <enamex sw="w80012" long="-3.193601937631324" lat="54.67926476125776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15906" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex>, the house of <enamex sw="w80040" long="-2.770280882875323" lat="54.81082168905613" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063742" name="Armathwaite" conf="2.6">Armathwaite</enamex>, and a rugged and broken foreground, compose a rich and delightful landscape.</s> <s id="s399">Thence you continue, through the same variegated tract, by <enamex sw="w80189" long="-3.200320135150944" lat="54.61857621602921" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11299921" name="Thornthwaite" conf="2.6">Thornthwaite</enamex> to <enamex sw="w80205" long="-3.160383346954682" lat="54.60035046101643" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13221" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex>, already taken notice of.</s></p>
<p><s id="s400">Returning to the situation which we left on our road from <enamex sw="w80301" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, we continued still, for a considerable time, ascending, enjoying some pleasant retrospective views of the lakes of <enamex sw="w80425" long="-3.193601937631324" lat="54.67926476125776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15906" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex> and <enamex sw="w80443" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>, with their numerous capes and bays, the windings of the river betwixt them, and every other object in the vicinity, delineated as it were, upon a map.</s> <s id="s401">The road was now open and uninclosed.</s> <s id="s402">Shortly we entered a long, bleak, and dreary valley, encompassed with lofty, but disagreeable looking mountains, upon the right and left, without inclosures, trees, or the appearance of a human habitation; it is called <enamex sw="w80860" long="-3.215804290008471" lat="54.6184217216403" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11319973" name="Whinlatter Forest Park" conf="2.4">Whinlatter</enamex>, affording nothing either romantic, picturesque, or in any degree interesting.</s></p>
<p><s id="s403">Through this valley runs the great road to <enamex sw="w80993" long="-3.360999570010009" lat="54.6624702211972" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10233" name="Cockermouth" conf="2.6">Cockermouth</enamex>, alongst which we continued for two miles.</s> <s id="s404">We left it, nearly at the beginning of a descent, and took a road to the left, in many places irregular in its direction and much broken, unfit for carriages, and even to be travelled by horses, but such as are acquainted with it daily.</s></p>
<p><s id="s405">Completely wearied with the gloomy uniformity of the objects around us, we at length arrived at its western entrance, where a beautiful prospect of a level and fertile country, stretching to a great distance, and bounded upon the west by the Irish sea, and upon the north by the <enamex sw="w81564" long="-3.576762628834178" lat="54.74010234959695" type="water" gazref="unlock:11286649" name="Solway Firth" conf="2.320007772">Solway Firth</enamex>, with the Scottish hills, spreads upon us.</s> <s id="s406">After enjoying this for some time, and breathing, as it were, the free air, we turned more to the left, through a road descending rapidly into the vale of <enamex sw="w81775" long="-3.308706047209322" lat="54.61745318512404" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11207371" name="Low Lorton" conf="2.6">Lorton</enamex>, watered by the <enamex sw="w81798" long="-3.324481003385194" lat="54.62627021510509" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270131" name="River Cocker" conf="2.4">River Cocker</enamex>, which, like the <enamex sw="w81828" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>, on the other side of the ridge of mountains, connects several lakes with each other.</s> <s id="s407">Shortly after we had got again upon the level of the plain, and passed the village of <enamex sw="w82008" long="-3.097010004524156" lat="54.80830835535834" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084677" name="Brackenthwaite" conf="2.6">Brackenthwaite</enamex>, we turned to the right, and shortly arrived within view of</s></p>
<p><s id="s408">Lowes Water.</s></p>
<p><s id="s409">This beautiful lake, to which we approach by crossing the Cocker at Cocker bridge, near a place called <enamex sw="w82199" long="-0.3439532490138631" lat="51.67312389168163" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11171537" name="High Cross" conf="1.495837815">High Cross</enamex>, is about a mile in length, by half that space in breadth.</s> <s id="s410">It is bounded by a finely variegated shore, of woodlands, inclosures, houses, and cultivated fields, and except towards its southern extremity, is not circumscribed by such lofty guardians, as the lakes already mentioned.</s> <s id="s411">Here, however, several mountains, the most remarkable of which is called <enamex sw="w82564" long="-3.322441248440349" lat="54.5633722472132" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11216937" name="Mellbreak" conf="2.4">Mellbreak</enamex>, bound it in that direction, drooping down with a steep descent towards the water.</s> <s id="s412">From the breast of this mountain is one of the finest views of the lake, as well as of that immedi - ately adjacent, called Crummock water, with their mountain-screens retiring in perspective, and all the rich accompaniments of woods, villages, and rocks.</s></p>
<p><s id="s413">Returning across the bridge to the road which we lately left, we continued southwards, and passed through the small village of <enamex sw="w83039" long="-3.097010004524156" lat="54.80830835535834" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084677" name="Brackenthwaite" conf="2.6">Brackenthwaite</enamex>, having the chain of mountains which we crossed from <enamex sw="w83107" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> upon our left, and on the opposite side of the vale, <enamex sw="w83168" long="-3.322441248440349" lat="54.5633722472132" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11216937" name="Mellbreak" conf="2.4">Mellbreak</enamex>, just now mentioned, and his neighbouring hills.</s> <s id="s414">Of the former, the principal mountains are <enamex sw="w83270" long="-3.168321741791226" lat="54.58293549454491" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11296646" name="Swinside" conf="2.6">Swinside</enamex>, which we first passed; then one still more lofty, at the base of which lies the village of <enamex sw="w83371" long="-3.097010004524156" lat="54.80830835535834" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084677" name="Brackenthwaite" conf="2.6">Brackenthwaite</enamex>, called <enamex sw="w83394" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s415">This mountain, which is of a great height, is conical, and great part of it entirely destitute of verdure, exhibiting from its surface, composed of a crumbling reddish earth and sparry rock, cut into many shapes, the most romantic and singular appearance.</s> <s id="s416">This mountain owes much of its present form to the bursting of a water-spout which fell upon it in the month of September, 1760, and occasioned dreadful devastation in the adjacent plain.</s></p>
<p><s id="s417">This phenomenon took place about midnight, as was conjectured, and nearly at that part of the mountain where three small streams, the principal of which is called the <enamex sw="w84015" long="-3.241525581" lat="54.49775081" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2644203" name="River Liza" conf="99991">Lissa</enamex>, take their rise.</s> <s id="s418">At first it swept the whole side of the hill, and charging itself with all the rubbish it found there, made its way in - to the vale, following chiefly the direction of the <enamex sw="w84211" long="-3.241525581" lat="54.49775081" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2644203" name="River Liza" conf="99991">Lissa</enamex>.</s> <s id="s419">At the foot of the mountain it was received by a piece of arable ground, on which its violence first broke.</s> <s id="s420">Here it tore away trees, soil, and gravel, and laid all bare many feet in depth, to the naked rock.</s> <s id="s421"><enamex sw="w84426" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.4">Over</enamex> the next 10 acres it made an immense roll, covering them with so vast a bed of stones, that no human art can ever again restore the soil.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s422">It was computed, that in many parts the stream must have been 5 or 6 yards deep, and more than 100 broad.</s></p>
<p><s id="s423">The village of <enamex sw="w84691" long="-3.097010004524156" lat="54.80830835535834" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084677" name="Brackenthwaite" conf="2.6">Brackenthwaite</enamex> had a wonderful escape: It stands at the bottom of <enamex sw="w84757" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, rather on a rising ground, and the current, taking its first direction towards them, would have undermined them( for the soil was instantly laid bare) had not a projection of native rock, the interior stratum on which the houses had unknowingly been founded, resisted the current and given it a new direction.</s> <s id="s424">Indeed its force was almost equal to the destruction of any thing: Bridges were thrown down, houses in other situations carried off, and woods rooted up.</s> <s id="s425">But its effects upon a stone causeway were thought the most surprizing. This fabric was of great thickness, and supported on each side by an enormous bank of earth.</s> <s id="s426">The memory of man could trace it, unaltered in any particular, near a hundred years, but by the soundness and firmness of its parts and texture, it seemed as if it had stood for ages.</s> <s id="s427">It was almost a doubt whether it were a work of nature or of art.</s> <s id="s428">This massy mole the deluge not only carried off, but as if it turned it into sport, made its very foundations the channel of its own stream.</s> <s id="s429">Having done all this mischief, not only here, but in many other parts, the <enamex sw="w85863" long="-3.241525581" lat="54.49775081" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2644203" name="River Liza" conf="99991">Lissa</enamex> threw all its waters into the Cocker, which, in consequence, was so much swelled, as to inundate, in its course through a level tract, the country, far and wide.</s></p>
<p><s id="s430">Continuing on our road, we obtained a peep of</s></p>
<p><s id="s431"><enamex sw="w86077" long="-3.30669123730051" lat="54.55455472767663" type="water" gazref="unlock:11124107" name="Crummock Water" conf="2.4">Crummock Water</enamex></s></p>
<p><s id="s432">upon our right, betwixt and the mountain of <enamex sw="w86136" long="-3.322441248440349" lat="54.5633722472132" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11216937" name="Mellbreak" conf="2.4">Mellbreak</enamex>.</s> <s id="s433">In order to see it to more advantage, we turned down a lane, at a place called <enamex sw="w86226" long="-3.303085471" lat="54.5737671" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00174" name="Lanthwaite" conf="99992">Lanthwaite Green</enamex>, crossed over an inclosure-- entered a coppice, jutting out into the lake, from whence this expanse of water appeared to great advantage, bounded by <enamex sw="w86395" long="-3.322441248440349" lat="54.5633722472132" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11216937" name="Mellbreak" conf="2.4">Mellbreak</enamex>, Redpike, Highstile, and some other mountains upon the right; and in front and upon the left, by Honister crag, Whiteless pike, and <enamex sw="w86537" long="-3.2959" lat="54.5521" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY16281820" name="Buttermere Hawse" conf="99992">Buttermere hawse</enamex>; the last a beautiful, broken, and verdant mountain, stretching almost across the vale.</s> <s id="s434">The first mentioned mountains are very precipitous, descending quickly to the water edge, and are partly covered with heath, and partly with verdure; few trees adorn their sides; some broken rocks, however, jut out here and there, and in some degree break that uniformity of surface, which otherwise would be too apparent.</s> <s id="s435">Those that lie opposite, or on the side in which we were placed, are, however, more agreeable and picturesque in their appearance, and equally, if not more lofty and commanding.</s> <s id="s436">At their base, in general, a beautiful plain, mostly cultivated and subdivided, stretches to the water's edge, containing some neat and pleasant farms.</s></p>
<p><s id="s437">This lake is about 4 miles in length, by half a mile broad.</s> <s id="s438">Its surface, near the southern extremity, is decorated by four small islands, none of them, however, of any considerable extent.</s> <s id="s439">It is remarkable for its depth, as well as the clearness of its water, and contains abundance of excellent fish, particularly carp, which is caught here in large quantities, and generally weigh from 6 to 8 ounces each.</s></p>
<p><s id="s440">After passing <enamex sw="w87717" long="-3.303085471" lat="54.5737671" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00174" name="Lanthwaite" conf="99992">Lanthwaite Green</enamex>, the road still continues running southwards, through several gates and inclosures, sometimes approaching the water's edge, and at other times receding to a greater distance, while the vale gradually contracts, and the mountains upon each side become more bleak and savage in their appearance.</s> <s id="s441">Thus you continue, till you arrive at <enamex sw="w88066" long="-3.2959" lat="54.5521" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY16281820" name="Buttermere Hawse" conf="99992">Buttermere hawse</enamex>, already noticed.</s> <s id="s442">Here the road turns suddenly to the right, winding round the side of the mountain, and hanging, as it were, at a great height above the level of the lake, which washes the base of the rocks below.</s></p>
<p><s id="s443">From this point, the upper part of Crummock lake appears in view, surrounded by the mountains, some of whom, particularly that in front, called Honister crag, has a singular and romantic outline.</s> <s id="s444">The others are better broken, and more picturesque, diversified with rocks, rising from the surface, heath, and spots of verdure.</s> <s id="s445">The islands of the lake are here distinctly seen, and contribute much to the beauty of the prospect, as well as several fine wooded knolls beyond the lake, lying in the bottom of the valley, and more upon the left, some variegated banks, partly covered with copses, through which a farm house peeps, in an advantageous point of view.</s></p>
<p><s id="s446">Continuing on, we shortly passed through some of these woods, the road becoming, at the same time, more irregular, while the vale appeared still farther to contract, and to terminate, as it were, in front, at no great distance.</s> <s id="s447">We now approached, after gaining an ascent of no great altitude, the secluded vale and lake of</s></p>
<p><s id="s448"><enamex sw="w89281" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>,</s></p>
<p><s id="s449">surrounded upon all sides, but by that on which you approach it, by an amphitheatre of stupendous and wild mountains, down the sides of whom, in many places, tumble innumerable cascades.</s> <s id="s450">In the lap of this valley lies the lake, and the scattered houses of the village, with some small, but level and fertile fields, divided by hedges and rows of trees, which, together with the woods already men - tioned, affords a pleasing contrast to the bleak surrounding mountains.</s></p>
<p><s id="s451">The lake of <enamex sw="w89774" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, which is about a mile and a half long, by half a mile broad, is in general very deep, and abounds, like Crummock water, with carp, and other species of fish.</s> <s id="s452">The western shores are bounded by those grim looking mountains already taken notice of as lying upon the right, when approaching the vale, and which dip almost perpendicularly into the water.</s> <s id="s453">The eastern shores rise more gently, are wooded, and admit of cultivation, to some distance from the lake.</s> <s id="s454">The north end washes the fine vale of <enamex sw="w90281" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, which is little elevated above the water; and the southern extremity peeps into different recesses, and washes the verdant base of lofty mountains.</s> <s id="s455">The most remarkable of these, and which has been formerly noticed, from the singularity of its outline, when seen at a distance, is Honister crag, presenting a square front to the vale, and towering to a great height.</s></p>
<p><s id="s456">Amongst the many waterfalls which issue in this vicinity from the mountains, is one which is an object of general admiration, it is called <enamex sw="w90798" long="-3.306404041715465" lat="54.54556917612459" type="water" gazref="unlock:11278597" name="Scale Force" conf="2.4">Scale Force</enamex>, and lies about a mile and a half to the west of <enamex sw="w90859" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s457">In visiting it you first cross the vale, and the <enamex sw="w90920" long="-3.324481003385194" lat="54.62627021510509" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270131" name="River Cocker" conf="2.4">River Cocker</enamex>, which connects the lake with that of Crummock, turn to the right, till an opening betwixt the mountains of <enamex sw="w91041" long="-3.322441248440349" lat="54.5633722472132" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11216937" name="Mellbreak" conf="2.4">Mellbreak</enamex> and <enamex sw="w91055" long="-3.134634474412318" lat="54.48438262553012" type="other" gazref="unlock:11080930" name="Blea Crag" conf="2">Blea Crag</enamex>, points out to you the object of your curiosity, situated in a deep chasm cut into the mount - ain, betwixt immense and lofty rocks, crowned with trees, and darkening the scene with their impending boughs.</s> <s id="s458">Here the water falls from a height of upwards of 180 feet, in one unbroken sheet, and with a noise that seems to shake the mountain, and alarms the most intrepid.</s> <s id="s459">Another cascade, opposite to the village, but which is not so often visited, is called, from its colour, the Sour Milk-force.</s> <s id="s460">At a distance it resembles a white line lying upon the side of the mountain, and after heavy rains, is heard a great way off.</s> <s id="s461">It issues from a small lake,( Burtness tarn) singularly placed on top of two adjoining mountains, called <enamex sw="w91790" long="-2.856474599863642" lat="54.26513879014757" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:19637" name="High Crag Wood" conf="2.4">High Crag</enamex> and <enamex sw="w91804" long="-3.290097556376177" lat="54.51877820351508" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11172424" name="High Stile" conf="2.4">High Stile</enamex>, which some imagine, formerly to have been volcanoes.</s></p>
<p><s id="s462">After having seen the vale of <enamex sw="w91899" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, we returned to the inn.</s> <s id="s463">This is a small, but neat and agreeable house, kept by Mr. Robinson.</s> <s id="s464">At the time we were there, and for many months before, the attention of the country around, and indeed, of great part of the kingdom, was engaged by the misfortunes of his daughter, Mary Robinson, called the beauty of <enamex sw="w92222" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s465">This maid had long, from her external charms and agreeable manners, been the admiration of the whole neighbourhood, and the object of the affection of many lovers.</s> <s id="s466">About a year preceding the time of our excursion, amongst the many visitors who came to <enamex sw="w92486" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, was one, who to a graceful exterior added a most insinuating address, and who besides travelled with all the splendor and state of a man of rank and quality.</s></p>
<p><s id="s467">Here he staid a considerable time, amusing himself mostly with fishing and sailing upon the lake, and conducting himself in such a manner, as to secure general respect.</s> <s id="s468">As he lodged at the inn, he frequently saw, and at length became enamoured of Mary, whose heart, pure and sincere, dreaded nothing from the designs of others.</s></p>
<p><s id="s469">Though really a man of no rank, and whose appearance was maintained from his numerous depredations upon the public, and success in gambling, he assumed the name of the brother of a nobleman, and although previously married, paid his addresses to Mary, with all the apparent sincerity of a lover.</s> <s id="s470">She for some time very prudently resisted his entreaties, from the great seeming difference betwixt their situations in life, but at length convinced of his sincerity, and that he was the person he pretended, she yielded to his intreaties, and consented to become his wife.</s> <s id="s471">The day arrived which was fixed upon for the performance of the nuptial ceremony, a day the most unfortunate for Mary she had ever seen.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s472">Earl of Hopeton.</s></p>
<p><s id="s473">For some time after the marriage, which was solemnized in the chapel of <enamex sw="w93782" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, Mary, lived in happiness, grateful to the man who had thus, as she imagined, raised her to a <enamex sw="w93887" long="-80.08477999999999" lat="40.44062" type="other" gazref="unlock:7955193" name="Superior Station" conf="0.6971977293">superior station</enamex> of life, and put it in her power to assist those with whom she was connected.</s> <s id="s474">She was, however, soon undeceived, and all her hopes for ever blasted.</s></p>
<p><s id="s475"><enamex sw="w94053" long="-1.977403080250683" lat="53.46498783270085" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11163147" name="Hadfield" conf="1.468862754">Hadfield</enamex>,( for that was the real name of her deceiver) after the ceremony, continued still about the country, making sometimes excursions from the village, but more frequently amusing himself in angling upon the lake, or sporting in the adjacent fields.</s> <s id="s476">It so happened, that amongst those who came to see <enamex sw="w94358" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, was a person who knew the gentleman whom <enamex sw="w94411" long="-1.977403080250683" lat="53.46498783270085" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11163147" name="Hadfield" conf="1.468862754">Hadfield</enamex> represented, and who was at that time in <enamex  sw="w94461" name="Large admin unit">Germany</enamex>.</s> <s id="s477">Struck with the imposture, upon his return home he mentioned the circumstance, described Hadfield's person, and the situation where he was.</s> <s id="s478">It was then that suspicion fixed upon him, and his name was noised abroad; numbers of fradulent transactions and forgeries were laid to his charge, and warrants issued for arresting him.</s> <s id="s479">These, however, for some time he found means to evade.</s> <s id="s480">At length he was taken into custody, and shortly thereafter removed to <enamex sw="w94923" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex>, as has been formerly noticed, tried there upon a charge of forgery, convicted, and about 6 months ago paid a forfeit for his crimes by his life.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s481">The Honourable Augustus Hope.</s></p>
<p><s id="s482">A few weeks previous to our arrival at <enamex sw="w95148" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, Mary had become a mother;( a name she, however, was shortly in possession of).</s> <s id="s483">By this time she was recovered, and able to attend the concerns of the house, her parents being old and infirm.</s> <s id="s484">Her figure was rather above the middle size, slender, and well proportioned; her face beautiful, and rendered still more engaging, from that air of melancholy and grief which appeared in her features, the consequence of her sad fate.</s> <s id="s485">We conversed with her a considerable time, but avoided her story.</s> <s id="s486">She spoke with feeling, and much information, and behaved with that politeness and affability which is seldom found in such a situation.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s487">There is another road to <enamex sw="w95814" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> besides this, and that which we followed by <enamex sw="w95866" long="-3.308706047209322" lat="54.61745318512404" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11207371" name="Low Lorton" conf="2.6">Lorton</enamex>, leading from <enamex sw="w95887" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, through a romantic and wild vale, called <enamex sw="w95940" long="-3.244032245927692" lat="54.52824948516431" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11151083" name="Gatesgarth" conf="2.6">Gatesgarth</enamex>, encompassed with the most singular, broken, and rocky mountains into <enamex sw="w96021" long="-3.15327" lat="54.52342" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00036" name="Borrowdale" conf="99991">Borrodale</enamex>, thence to <enamex sw="w96042" long="-3.160418408000877" lat="54.30436355899656" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11272960" name="Rosthwaite" conf="2.6">Rosthwaite</enamex>( already mentioned) and <enamex sw="w96077" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s488">Bidding adieu to <enamex sw="w96103" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, we left it on our return to <enamex sw="w96143" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, distant 14 miles, by a road leading through the vale of <enamex sw="w96208" long="-3.185804700514816" lat="54.57418107642148" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790063" name="Newlands Beck" conf="2.4">Newlands</enamex>; passed, upon the left, the small chapel of <enamex sw="w96261" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, looking down upon the village, then began a steep ascent, on an irregular country road, betwixt two mountains.</s> <s id="s489">Thus we continued, winding alongst the breast of the hills, and having, in some situations upon our left, an immense chasm, through which a rivulet run far below.</s> <s id="s490">At length we gained the highest elevation of the road, at the head of the vale, and descended, descended, in the opposite direction, to the lake and vale of <enamex sw="w96704" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, at which we shortly again arrived.</s></p>
<p><s id="s491">In the neighbourhood of <enamex sw="w96777" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, as has been formerly noticed, is <enamex sw="w96819" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, one of the highest of the English hills, and which nearly shuts up, upon the north, the vale of <enamex sw="w96924" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>.</s> <s id="s492">From the top of this mountain, whose perpendicular height is 3228 feet above the level of the sea, and which is easily ascended, an extensive prospect is obtained, comprehending on the south, great part of the counties of <enamex  sw="w97160" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w97175" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>; the Irish sea upon the west; on the east, the mountains separating <enamex  sw="w97256" name="Large admin unit">Northumberland</enamex> from <enamex  sw="w97276" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, and <enamex  sw="w97292" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex> from <enamex  sw="w97310" name="Large admin unit">Yorkshire</enamex>; and upon the north, the <enamex sw="w97345" long="-3.576762628834178" lat="54.74010234959695" type="water" gazref="unlock:11286649" name="Solway Firth" conf="2.320007772">Solway Firth</enamex>, the city of <enamex sw="w97371" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex>, and the distant mountains in <enamex  sw="w97410" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s493">In the neighbourhood of <enamex sw="w97444" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, and to the east, is another lofty mountain, called, from the form of its summit, <enamex sw="w97534" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex>; its height is, however, <enamex sw="w97570" long="-2.421557122390574" lat="53.29060765310844" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13406245" name="Tabley Inferior CP" conf="1.317771257">inferior</enamex> to that of <enamex sw="w97590" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, and consequently it is not so much visited.</s></p>
<p><s id="s494">After having seen the lakes and scenery in the surrounding district, we again left <enamex sw="w97726" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, early in the succeeding day to that of our arrival from <enamex sw="w97791" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, pursuing the road to <enamex sw="w97824" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> lake, <enamex sw="w97839" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, <enamex sw="w97850" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s495">lying to the south.</s> <s id="s496">For about a mile from the town, the road continued on an ascent, presenting in succession a variety of beautiful retrospective views of the scenes we had left.</s> <s id="s497">The finest of these is from the summit of the eminence called <enamex sw="w98108" long="-3.106680651426865" lat="54.59250322469962" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11101332" name="Castlerigg" conf="2.6">Castlerigg</enamex>, where the vale and lake of <enamex sw="w98147" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> and <enamex sw="w98159" long="-3.193601937631324" lat="54.67926476125776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15906" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex>, with the <enamex sw="w98183" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex> connecting them; the mountains, the rich fields, and the town, lie in a beautiful order before the eye.</s> <s id="s498">We then descended, skirting the head of a valley upon the north, called <enamex sw="w98367" name="Naddle Vale">Naddle Vale</enamex>, turned more southwards, and entered the valley of Legberthwaite, bounded by a range of mountains upon each side-- continued alongst it for some miles-- passed the base of the mountain Helvellin upon the left, and came in view of</s></p>
<p><s id="s499"><enamex sw="w98615" long="-3.0667" lat="54.5333" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2636023" name="Leathes Water" conf="99992">Leathes Water</enamex>, Or <enamex sw="w98633" long="-3.0632" lat="54.5346" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY313160" name="Thirlmeer" conf="99992">Thirlmere Lake</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s500">which at first we took for <enamex sw="w98676" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s501">This lake is narrow and unadorned, without the beauties which characterize those already mentioned.</s> <s id="s502">We continued skirting alongst this lake, which stretches about four miles, then passed the chapel and inn of <enamex sw="w98895" long="-3.060646544049678" lat="54.54323368129527" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403099" name="St. John's Castlerigg and Wythburn CP" conf="2.4">Wythburn</enamex>.</s> <s id="s503">From this place a continued ascent carried us to the end of the vale, at a place called <enamex sw="w98993" long="-3.042257566142511" lat="54.49420285694539" type="other" gazref="unlock:11134276" name="Dunmail Raise" conf="2">Dunmail Raise</enamex>, where we again entered <enamex  sw="w99032" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s504">Here an immense heap of stones, called by the name just now mentioned, divide the counties of <enamex  sw="w99140" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w99155" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s505">They are said to have been raised to the memory of the last King of Cumberland, defeated here by <enamex  sw="w99266" name="Not a placename">Edmund</enamex> the Saxon monarch.</s></p>
<p><s id="s506">No sooner had we arrived at this eminence, to which we eagerly pressed, wearied with the uniformity and aspect of the vale we had passed, than a prospect of the sweetest kind presented itself be - fore us.</s> <s id="s507">The vale of <enamex sw="w99509" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> opens itself to view with the lake lying in its bosom, and surrounded by a spacious amphitheatre of mountains, covered in some parts with wood to the water's edge, in other places with verdure, rocks, and moss.</s> <s id="s508">At the north end of the lake, a level plain stretches to the base of the hills, rich and well cultivated, and divided like a garden, by hedgerows, inclosures, and trees.</s> <s id="s509">In this situation is placed the church and white village, rising above the trees, adding still farther to enliven and beautify the landscape.</s></p>
<p><s id="s510">After a continued descent of some length, passing upon the right a singular conical mountain, rearing a broken craggy summit to a great height, and much resembling Ben Artur in Argyleshire, formerly mentioned, with a chain of verdant hills upon the left, we arrived upon the banks of</s></p>
<p><s id="s511"><enamex sw="w100325" long="-3.0216" lat="54.45" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_6956554" name="Grasmere Water" conf="99991">Grasmere Lake</enamex>,</s></p>
<p><s id="s512">which stretches about a mile in length, by half a mile broad, ornamented by the scenery just now noticed, and a small island, decorated by a tuft of trees.</s> <s id="s513">The road which we pursued led upon the east side of the lake, through an agreeable vista of trees and of hedges; in other places, through a more open tract; then passing some neat and pleasant houses, whose fronts were embellished with honeysuckle and jessamine, or with fruit trees, particularly that of the cherry, which was now ripe, and hanging in beautiful clusters around the windows.</s> <s id="s514">We then began to ascend from the banks of the lake, and near the summit of the eminence obtained a retrospective prospect of this paradisical spot, in another and no less pleasing point of view.</s></p>
<p><s id="s515">Scarcely had we left this situation, and gained the greatest elevation of the road, than all at once we were again delighted with another lovely scene, comprehending the small lake of <enamex sw="w101266" long="-2.994852043565142" lat="54.44966001297723" type="water" gazref="unlock:11275811" name="Rydal Water" conf="2.4">Rydal water</enamex>, reposing in a valley, and like <enamex sw="w101310" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, encircled by mountains.</s> <s id="s516">That upon the left, called Rydalhead, is of a great height; in its upper part, craggy and broken, intermixed with trees and bushes.</s> <s id="s517">Farther down, these increase in number, forming thick groves and copses, from amongst which peep out a number of white and picturesque cottages.</s> <s id="s518">On the opposite side of the lake the hills are not so high as Rydalhead, though equally beautiful and engaging; their bases covered with thick and lofty woods to the very margin of the stream.</s> <s id="s519">Beyond these side-screens, the vale makes a sweep from Rydalhead to the left, in a succession of mountains and high grounds, in some places covered with wood, and in others, presenting their verdant fronts to the day.</s></p>
<p><s id="s520">It was still morning when we came thus in sight of <enamex sw="w102083" long="-2.994852043565142" lat="54.44966001297723" type="water" gazref="unlock:11275811" name="Rydal Water" conf="2.4">Rydal water</enamex>; the distance of the scene was tinted with the light blue haze then so prevalent, which softened every object, and shaded it into air.</s> <s id="s521">The other parts of the landscape, though more strongly illuminated, partook also something of this aerial hue, which, blended with the rich and variegated woods hanging from the sides of Rydalhead, the reddish colour of the rocks, and the brilliant green of the banks, had an inexpressible fine effect.</s> <s id="s522">This was still aided by the lustre of the lake, appearing of a brilliant blue, and studded with two small islands covered with trees, which reflected, in a beautiful manner, their softened image in the water.</s></p>
<p><s id="s523">After enjoying this scene, upon which nature has conferred so many beauties, the road descended, nearly to the level of the lake, alongst the banks of which it continued passing a number of houses, some of them venerably mantled with ivy.</s> <s id="s524">Upon our left, at a short distance, and finely situated on a rising ground, surrounded by mountains, we next passed <enamex sw="w103097" long="-2.98" lat="54.4483" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36550632" name="Rydal Hall" conf="99992">Rydal Hall</enamex>, the elegant mansion of Sir Michael Le <enamex  sw="w103147" name="Not a placename">Fleming</enamex>.</s> <s id="s525">Continuing on, under the shade of a long vista of venerable trees, the vale began to open upon every side; we then turned south, and entered the town of</s></p>
<p><s id="s526"><enamex sw="w103309" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>,</s></p>
<p><s id="s527">16 miles from <enamex sw="w103334" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s528"><enamex sw="w103343" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> is a place of great antiquity, and appears to have been of more note formerly than at present.</s> <s id="s529">Near <enamex sw="w103453" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, towards the south-west, at the head of <enamex sw="w103503" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>, are still to be seen the remains of a celebrated Roman station, supposed to be that called the Dietis, where a part of the Cohors Nerviorum Dictentium was stationed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s530">About a mile from <enamex sw="w103700" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> we arrived upon the banks of <enamex sw="w103739" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>, alongst which we rode somewhat farther to <enamex sw="w103793" long="-3.000560623790019" lat="54.24386305141168" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16529" name="Low Wood" conf="2.6">Low Wood</enamex> inn, upon the east side of the lake.</s></p>
<p><s id="s531"><enamex sw="w103839" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>,</s></p>
<p><s id="s532">is the largest of the English lakes, being about ten miles in length, and near a mile in breadth.</s> <s id="s533">It lies partly in <enamex  sw="w103967" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, and partly in <enamex  sw="w103995" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>, and stretches nearly from north to south.</s> <s id="s534">In some places it is of a great depth, particularly opposite to a place called <enamex sw="w104128" long="-2.9429" lat="54.3959" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY38880046" name="Ecclesrig Crag" conf="99992">Ecclesrig</enamex> Crag, where it is said to measure 222 feet; in general, however, about the middle it is not more than 90 feet.</s> <s id="s535">It produces in great abundance the finest kinds of fish, particularly char.</s></p>
<p><s id="s536">Towards the north, <enamex sw="w104344" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex> is surrounded by mountains and high grounds, in the vicinity of <enamex sw="w104419" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>; these gradually decline towards the south, and at last terminate in gentle swells, stretching to the brink of the water, covered with woods and inclosures.</s> <s id="s537">Nearly at an equal distance, betwixt the north and south extremities of the lake, lie several islands,( 10 in number) the largest of which is of an oblong form, and is laid out and planted with much taste by its proprietor, J. C.</s> <s id="s538">Curwen, Esq; who has also here an elegant house, in which he resides.</s></p>
<p><s id="s539">The scenery in the vicinity of <enamex sw="w104917" long="-3.000560623790019" lat="54.24386305141168" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16529" name="Low Wood" conf="2.6">Low Wood</enamex> inn is soft and beautiful.</s> <s id="s540">From it an excellent road stretches down the east side of the lake, passing through some finely variegated grounds, without, however, obtaining a good view of the water, till opposite <enamex sw="w105137" long="-2.928529867" lat="54.38830822" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00125" name="Calgarth Park" conf="99992">Colgarth</enamex>, the seat of the Bishop of Landaff, when it appears to much advantage.</s> <s id="s541">At a short distance from this point is the pleasant village of <enamex sw="w105280" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, about half way down the lake, with a small harbour, and several vessels used for carrying commodities from one district of the coast to the other.</s> <s id="s542">A mile further conducts to the <enamex  sw="w105467" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Ferry Point</enamex>, where <enamex sw="w105486" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex> is very narrow, though it afterwards expands to the south.</s> <s id="s543">Here a boat is kept for conveying you to the opposite shore.</s></p>
<p><s id="s544">From the west banks of the lake, a road conducts, after a short ride, to</s></p>
<p><s id="s545"><enamex sw="w105690" long="-2.977291334332336" lat="54.3599180438576" type="water" gazref="unlock:11140740" name="Esthwaite Water" conf="2.4">Esthwaite Water</enamex>,</s></p>
<p><s id="s546">about two miles in length, and nearly half a mile in breadth, with fine swelling banks, decorated with villages, intermixed with trees and corn fields.</s></p>
<p><s id="s547">Farther on is <enamex sw="w105873" long="-2.997689462703833" lat="54.37597546544907" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:30241" name="Hawkshead" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex>, a market town, with some good inns, finely situated upon the declivity of a mountainous ridge, commanding an extensive prospect of the vale adjacent.</s> <s id="s548">Continuing on, the beautiful lake of</s></p>
<p><s id="s549"><enamex sw="w106071" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex>,</s></p>
<p><s id="s550">with the fells or mountains of <enamex sw="w106112" long="-2.7531" lat="54.6067" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2656903" name="Askham" conf="99991">Furness</enamex>, opens upon the eye.</s> <s id="s551">This lake is six miles in length, and three quarters of a mile in breadth, and exhibits, in different situations, many of the most beautiful and picturesque scenes.</s> <s id="s552">Its outline is finely broken by numerous capes and bays, and its banks, which are more elevated than the boundaries of <enamex sw="w106425" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>, are richly decorated with hedges, woods, and houses, intermixed in the most picturesque and pleasing manner.</s> <s id="s553">A road leads down the east side of the lake, to <enamex sw="w106594" long="-3.222948263035822" lat="54.3397013177194" type="other" gazref="unlock:11207601" name="Low, The" conf="2">the Low</enamex> country, around <enamex sw="w106618" long="-3.065434914086523" lat="54.19737398966196" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11287996" name="South Ulverston" conf="2.6">Ulverston</enamex>; thence you can proceed to visit the magnificent ruins of <enamex sw="w106686" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.169094422">Furness Abbey</enamex>, or to <enamex sw="w106707" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex>, across the sands, and so on, if you think proper, continue to <enamex sw="w106780" long="-2.878238320350647" lat="53.5225887298584" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131229" name="Liverpool" conf="2.338371617">Liverpool</enamex>,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s554">Instead of following this course, however, we returned from <enamex sw="w106855" long="-3.0765" lat="54.3361" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2653454" name="Coniston Water" conf="99991">Coniston lake</enamex>, towards the north, by a road conducting directly to <enamex sw="w106922" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, about eight miles distant, alongst the northern shores of <enamex sw="w106991" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s555">From <enamex sw="w107008" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> we retraced the road to <enamex sw="w107042" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, thence proceeded to <enamex sw="w107071" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, 17 miles, alongst an excellent highway, leading by the village of <enamex sw="w107146" long="-3.050449149478369" lat="54.6193216407524" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:17080" name="Threlkeld" conf="2.6">Threlkeld</enamex>, and the base of <enamex sw="w107173" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex>, and passing an extensive common, about half way betwixt the towns.</s> <s id="s556">From <enamex sw="w107257" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> we returned to <enamex sw="w107280" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.372226797">Carlisle</enamex>, and so on to <enamex sw="w107303" long="-2.96338204564023" lat="55.0091956888473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:22582" name="Longtown" conf="2.6">Longtown</enamex> and <enamex sw="w107316" long="-3.06667" lat="54.98333" type="other" gazref="unlock:4572299" name="Gretna" conf="2">Gretna</enamex>, then turned west to <enamex sw="w107344" long="-3.258165592796878" lat="54.9865068085775" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062586" name="Annan" conf="2.6">Annan</enamex> and <enamex sw="w107354" long="-3.600893412131117" lat="55.06807061840479" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10470" name="Dumfries" conf="1.455766369">Dumfries</enamex>, and continued by <enamex sw="w107381" long="-3.91709548442316" lat="55.36441965065216" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11278101" name="Sanquhar" conf="1.348212154">Sanquhar</enamex> to <enamex sw="w107393" long="-4.492571706278026" lat="55.6078979907687" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11401" name="Kilmarnock" conf="1.983676192">Kilmarnock</enamex> and <enamex sw="w107408" long="-4.323445408764941" lat="55.86313234566946" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:9729" name="Glasgow" conf="2.207670132">Glasgow</enamex>.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s557">Printed by R. Chapman, Trongate, <enamex sw="w107451" long="-4.323445408764941" lat="55.86313234566946" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:9729" name="Glasgow" conf="2.207670132">Glasgow</enamex>.</s></p>
</text>
</document>