<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1968_a"><p><s id="s1">A Journal of a Tour in the Lakes made in 1797 by William Gell</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s2">We[ the doctor and myself] set out on the nineteenth of June from <enamex sw="w141" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="4.593870132">Kendal</enamex> in <enamex  sw="w151" name="Large admin unit">Westmorland</enamex> to join the rest of our party who had arrived some daysbefore us at <enamex sw="w231" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> and had procured a convenient lodging there both for themselves and us.</s> <s id="s3">From <enamex sw="w318" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="4.593870132">Kendal</enamex> to <enamex sw="w328" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> is a stage of eighteen miles and though the first part of the way has nothing in it to attract attention or render it agreeable yet the recollection of it soon ceases on the unexpected sight of <enamex sw="w532" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> from the summit of an hill over which the road lies.</s></p>
<p><s id="s4">At first the lake assumed the appearance of a noble river, in one part almost covered with Islands full of trees and shrubs down to the waters edge, but on a nearerapp-roach the breadth encreased and the lake acquires a majesty which the apparent narrowness had before denied it.</s> <s id="s5">The road passes about 4 miles along the water side through the villages of <enamex sw="w951" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex> and <enamex sw="w963" long="-2.916138691626954" lat="54.37837472794948" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11253232" name="Rayrigg Hall" conf="2.2">Rayrigg</enamex> to <enamex sw="w974" long="-2.931737280270144" lat="54.38724387708846" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11096668" name="Calgarth Hall" conf="2.2">Calgarth</enamex> and <enamex sw="w987" long="-3.005216563799839" lat="54.24283559423841" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11207661" name="Low Wood" conf="2.6">Low wood</enamex> an inn within forty yards of the lake and two miles from <enamex sw="w1053" long="-2.96358681023542" lat="54.4319364520582" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11061737" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>.</s> <s id="s6">We passed through <enamex sw="w1082" long="-2.96358681023542" lat="54.4319364520582" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11061737" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> by <enamex sw="w1095" long="-2.98" lat="54.4483" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36550632" name="Rydal Hall" conf="99992">Rydal Hall</enamex> and water till at a turn of the road we perceived thebeautiful vale of <enamex sw="w1177" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> beneath us.</s> <s id="s7">Here we found our companions on their return from a neighbouring Tarn where they had fished all the morning.</s> <s id="s8">I myself was so impatient ot try my success on the trout, that I could notwait till dinner was over before I took one with my line.</s> <s id="s9">During the first week we visited <enamex sw="w1473" long="-2.98" lat="54.4483" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36550632" name="Rydal Hall" conf="99992">Rydal hall</enamex>, and water and two cascades.</s> <s id="s10">The hall is the seat of Sir Michael leFlemming, a gentleman of a very hospitable disposition, and descended from one of the most ancient families in the Kingdom.</s> <s id="s11">They had formerly largeposessions in the Lordship of <enamex sw="w1728" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>.</s> <s id="s12">The hall on <enamex sw="w1749" long="-3.069150080092114" lat="54.34116196598502" type="water" gazref="unlock:11115206" name="Coniston Water" conf="2.4">Coniston Water</enamex> was the chief seat for many years but on a marriage with the heiress of <enamex sw="w1836" long="-2.113103989239713" lat="53.50988388406682" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11189303" name="Knott Lanes" conf="1.500661056">Knott</enamex> ofRydal they removed it as I take it, and have since remained there.</s> <s id="s13">The house appears handsome and spacious, a little to the left from it, the shrubbery lies, under whichis concealed the lower cascade, and is an artfully contrived as so make what is really nothing in itself at least pleasing if not grand.</s></p>
<p><s id="s14">We passed along a short winding path, closely bordered with young spruce or Silver firs, till we came to the door of a little low summer house, which on opening, presented us through a large square window in the opposite wall with a miniature of as beautiful and romantic a fall of water as the imagination can conceive, within so very limited a compass.</s> <s id="s15">The rocks on each side are covered with moss, or those plants which are usually found in moist situations, trees hang over them, and in the center, the little stream pours itself through a narrow channel into a small bason not more than ten yards in diameter.</s> <s id="s16">The fall may beabout twelve feet, a bridge some yards higher up the stream has a picturesque effect.</s> <s id="s17">The higher cascade though its fall be greater, yet fails in those beauties in whichthe lower excels, though much more retired than the other it wants the accompaniments of trees and gloom to render it so interesting.</s> <s id="s18">The walk to is is good, and at the gate of the wood as we returned we had a sight of <enamex sw="w3167" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s19">The next day we visited <enamex sw="w3203" long="-2.96358681023542" lat="54.4319364520582" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11061737" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, in order to see the <enamex sw="w3234" long="-1.88333" lat="53.05" type="other" gazref="unlock:4559105" name="Waterfall" conf="0.9277336249">Waterfall</enamex> above the town, which we had heard was <enamex sw="w3283" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="1.044099103">superior</enamex> to those of <enamex sw="w3304" long="-2.98206973035289" lat="54.44823197501312" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15013" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex>.</s> <s id="s20">We ascended theh ill for some time, and at length arrived at the spot.</s> <s id="s21">This is far more deserving the name of a waterfall than those of <enamex sw="w3446" long="-2.98206973035289" lat="54.44823197501312" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15013" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex>, descending as we imagined about seventy feet through brokenfragments of rock, and hurried from thence among loose stones, to meet the Rothay in the vale below.</s> <s id="s22">On the 24th while two of our companions went tothe top of <enamex sw="w3671" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169753" name="Helvellyn" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex> two of us went by <enamex sw="w3699" long="-2.96358681023542" lat="54.4319364520582" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11061737" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, across the Rothay and Brathay, along the head of <enamex sw="w3759" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> to <enamex sw="w3773" long="-3.023901654228874" lat="54.37750890240144" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167814" name="Hawkshead Hill" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex>, nine miles from <enamex sw="w3800" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex>; passing throughthe small village of <enamex sw="w3847" long="-2.9786" lat="54.4212" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY366033" name="Clappersgate" conf="99992">Clappers Gate</enamex> in our way, where is a neat and handsome house with a fine view of the lake, the seat of Miss <enamex sw="w3955" long="-122.2631788" lat="47.5295436" type="other" gazref="unlock:8547314" name="Pritchett Island Beach" conf="0.6388266225">Pritchett</enamex> or Pritch Ard.</s> <s id="s23">From this placeperhaps, <enamex sw="w4004" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> is seen to greater advantage than any other situation, for here it cannot be taken for a river as the observer is at the head of the lake and looksonly upon its length.</s> <s id="s24">We passed by the little piece of water called Blellam tarn, which a first we mistook for <enamex sw="w4273" long="-2.977291334332336" lat="54.3599180438576" type="water" gazref="unlock:11140740" name="Esthwaite Water" conf="2.4">Esthwaite water</enamex>, and has nothing to recommend it.</s> <s id="s25">The village of is istuated nearly at the head, about a mile and a half from <enamex sw="w4399" long="-3.023901654228874" lat="54.37750890240144" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167814" name="Hawkshead Hill" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex>, where we soon after arrived after seeing an old house, on the right of the road, called <enamex sw="w4498" long="-2.83895" lat="54.71404" type="other" gazref="unlock:5826154" name="Hutton in the Forest Hall" conf="2">the Hall</enamex> and where we conjectured was formerly the room, in which the author of the history of <enamex sw="w4593" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> says, theabbot of <enamex sw="w4619" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> received his rents from <enamex sw="w4651" long="-3.023901654228874" lat="54.37750890240144" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167814" name="Hawkshead Hill" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex> and kept residence by two or more of his monks.</s></p>
<p><s id="s26">After dinner at the red Lion our Landlord directed us to the ferry at <enamex sw="w4779" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> four miles from the town.</s> <s id="s27">Two miles of it be close to the side of <enamex sw="w4856" long="-2.977291334332336" lat="54.3599180438576" type="water" gazref="unlock:11140740" name="Esthwaite Water" conf="2.4">Esthwaite water</enamex> a lakesaid to be three miles in length the lower end finely border-ed with wood which, climbs almost to the tops of the hills and the upper ornamented with the town of <enamex sw="w5040" long="-3.023901654228874" lat="54.37750890240144" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167814" name="Hawkshead Hill" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex>, <enamex sw="w5050" long="-3.118464887566315" lat="54.45756762847756" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11191353" name="Langdale Pikes" conf="2.4">Langdale Pikes</enamex> at a distance, and a beautiful swelling peninsula surrounded with trees above the tops of which we saw the green corn on its summit.</s></p>
<p><s id="s28">From hence we went to Sawrey a hamlet consisting of a few houses on a little hill, where on enquiring our way it was pointed out to us, by one of the most strapping womenI ever beheld.</s></p>
<p><s id="s29">On the summit of the next hill we saw <enamex sw="w5421" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>, by degrees the whole opened upon us and we saw the island on which stands the house belonging to Mr. Christian, in our descent to the ferry, a small house entirely overhung with trees standing on a peninsulabehind which one of Mr. Christian's vessels lay at anchor.</s> <s id="s30">We got into a boat here in which they usually bring carts and horses across and were conveyed slowly to theother side of the lake which in this place is nom ore than five hundred and ten yards broad.</s></p>
<p><s id="s31">When we were landed we walked about half a mile to <enamex sw="w5950" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex> where is a window in the church taken from the abbey of <enamex sw="w6014" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>.</s> <s id="s32">We hired a boat atthe White Lion and were rowed by two men to <enamex sw="w6085" long="-2.96358681023542" lat="54.4319364520582" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11061737" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, leaving behind us the island which is entirely covered with wood forming the whole into a most delightul open grove.</s></p>
<p><s id="s33">This Island is two miles in circumference being nearly three quarters of a mile long, and lying in a direction neither parallel to the side of thelake nor at right angles to it.</s> <s id="s34">As to the house itself when the observer stands in such a position as not to percieve the portico, it wants only a little green paint ada label of Souchong, or fine <enamex sw="w6556" long="-76.5685782" lat="39.7953804" type="other" gazref="unlock:7308210" name="Hyson Hill" conf="0.7032294368">Hyson</enamex> to make it exactly like a large shop tea canister.</s> <s id="s35">Sir Christopher Philipson lived in the Great island in the beginning of the present century.</s> <s id="s36">How it became the property of the Curwen family I know not.</s> <s id="s37">It contains more than thirty acres and is in the Countyof <enamex  sw="w6824" name="Large admin unit">Westmorland</enamex> though far nearer to the <enamex  sw="w6861" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire side</enamex> it was anciently part of the honour of <enamex sw="w6916" long="-77.48496627807617" lat="37.56164932250977" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131293" name="Richmond" conf="2.080728799">Richmond</enamex> and was held by the Lancasters barons of <enamex sw="w6966" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="4.593870132">Kendal</enamex>.</s> <s id="s38">The whole lake, is ten[ miles] all but 200yds in length, the greatest breadth is not more than 1635 yards, and the smallest not more than five hund-red and ten, where the ferry is situated not far below <enamex sw="w7177" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>.</s> <s id="s39">The greatest depth opposite Graithwaite, is one hundred and thrity-two feet.</s> <s id="s40">Opposite <enamex sw="w7272" long="-2.960645582648914" lat="54.30611996501068" type="other" gazref="unlock:11253130" name="Rawlinson's Intake" conf="2">Rawlinsons</enamex> Nab 132 feet, opposite <enamex sw="w7306" long="-2.9429" lat="54.3959" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY38880046" name="Ecclesrig Crag" conf="99992">Ecclesrig</enamex> Crag 201 feet, and within one hundred yards from the conflux of the Brathay, and the Rothay, the depth is one hundred and sixty six feet.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s41">I have since heard Mr. Curwen bought it of a Mr. English.</s></p>
<p><s id="s42">It is remarkable that in the spawning season, Trout only ascend the Rothay and Char the Brathay.</s> <s id="s43">The fishermen affirm that before any great storm there is a current under water exactly opposite to thedirection in which the storm will appear; this we had not an opportunity of observing though the water was ruffled so violently that we appre-hended an approaching storm. <enamex sw="w7883" long="-2.931737280270144" lat="54.38724387708846" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11096668" name="Calgarth Hall" conf="2.2">Calgarth</enamex> the seat of the Bishop of Llandaff is situated on a gently rising ground on the right, an handsome stone mansion, at a small dis-tance fromthe old hall, where are preserved the famous skulls, of which it is reported, that they have been burnt, ground, powdered and cast into the lake, but nevertheless haveconstantly returned to the window in which they first lay as a perceptual testimony, of the innocence of their original owners, who were executed on suspicion of a murder, which they never committed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s44">After passing <enamex sw="w8412" long="-3.005216563799839" lat="54.24283559423841" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11207661" name="Low Wood" conf="2.6">Low wood</enamex> Inn, we arrived at <enamex sw="w8440" long="-2.96358681023542" lat="54.4319364520582" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11061737" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> and borded not far from the Camp which the Romans formed at the head of <enamex sw="w8522" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> and which commanded a view asfar fown the lake as <enamex sw="w8583" long="-0.5309658453303814" lat="53.90546246268991" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11177640" name="Holme on the Wolds" conf="1.43968422">the holme</enamex>.</s> <s id="s45">The dimensions were 396 feet by 240, no military road has yet been discov-ered leading to it, though many of the learned in Antiq Uities, have taken much trouble, and some have written dissertations on the subject.</s> <s id="s46">The fall at the lower end of this lake, from <enamex sw="w8853" long="-2.959809373549684" lat="54.2701718942731" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11229861" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby bridge</enamex> where it terminates, to <enamex sw="w8889" long="-3.006316758" lat="54.24424243" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00182" name="Low Wood Bridge" conf="99992">Low wood bridge</enamex> is one hundred and five feet, at <enamex sw="w8938" long="-3.006316758" lat="54.24424243" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00182" name="Low Wood Bridge" conf="99992">Low wood bridge</enamex> the die rises some inches or feet.</s></p>
<p><s id="s47">Mr. Curwen the present proprietor of <enamex sw="w9026" long="-0.5309658453303814" lat="53.90546246268991" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11177640" name="Holme on the Wolds" conf="1.43968422">the Holme</enamex>, was formerly a Christian, but having married the heiress of the Curwen family and bringing by her between fifteenand twenty thousand pounds annually into his own changed his name for that of his lady.</s> <s id="s48">( I believe this partly untrue.) The Curwens themselves were originally descendedfrom Gospatric from whm also the <enamex sw="w9351" long="-77.06999999999999" lat="38.9063889" type="other" gazref="unlock:8638876" name="Nevils Building" conf="0.8878621821">Nevils</enamex>' Earls of <enamex  sw="w9368" name="Large admin unit">Westmor</enamex> Land were derived, but on marrying the heiress of the Curwens of <enamex sw="w9441" long="-4.138128091269225" lat="55.07310157832572" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11228877" name="New Galloway" conf="4.409299324">Galloway</enamex> in <enamex  sw="w9453" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex> they took the name whichthey have ever since retained.</s> <s id="s49">They had anciently a seat at <enamex sw="w9546" long="-3.551571779176866" lat="54.62740111743355" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11386" name="Workington" conf="6.027244126">Workington</enamex> near <enamex sw="w9562" long="-3.424036233423147" lat="54.62625233230398" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13331491" name="Cockermouth West ED" conf="5.4">Cockermouth</enamex> and the present Mr. Curwen has made considerable improvements there.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s50">Curwens arms Ar frett Gu a chief az.</s></p>
<p><s id="s51">From <enamex sw="w9686" long="-2.96358681023542" lat="54.4319364520582" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11061737" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> we walked to <enamex sw="w9709" long="-2.98206973035289" lat="54.44823197501312" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15013" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex> a little lake spotted with rocky islands, two or three of which are cloathed with wood but not of sufficient extent to become anobject of attention in a countrey abounding with so many <enamex sw="w9900" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="1.044099103">superior</enamex>: <enamex sw="w9910" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> is but little more than a mile from <enamex sw="w9956" long="-2.98206973035289" lat="54.44823197501312" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15013" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex> and from the hill between the two lakes, is one of the best views of the whole valley Lake annd Island that I haveseen.</s></p>
<p><s id="s52">The lake itself is small, the village is a little way from the head consisting of few houses, and a white church situate close to the bridge over the Rothay which isthe principal feeder of the lake.</s> <s id="s53">We lodged at Robert <enamex sw="w10301" long="-2.630528839144464" lat="53.45348937110084" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11008" name="Newton-Le-Willows" conf="1.511443558">Newton</enamex>'s at the <enamex sw="w10317" long="-2.45814" lat="54.97075" type="other" gazref="unlock:5826225" name="Haltwhistle Red Lion Tower" conf="0.9792643792">Red Lion</enamex> where there is a comfortable house, and we experienced very civil treatment.</s> <s id="s54">We had a boat on the meer at our pleasure.</s> <s id="s55">An island rises gently about the middle of the water, except that on the south west side the shore is rocky andone or two rows of firs contribute to the abruptness of the appearance.</s> <s id="s56">A small barn or perhaps a shelter for cattle is on the extremity, the whole measures about fouracres and an half.</s> <s id="s57">There are a few Rabbits among the rocks.</s></p>
<p><s id="s58">Towards <enamex sw="w10792" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, the piramidal hill called helm Crag, <enamex sw="w10838" long="-3.057695522673377" lat="54.49406878163224" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11291661" name="Steel Fell" conf="2.4">Steel fell</enamex> and <enamex sw="w10853" long="-3.01138127729091" lat="54.49446509482051" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11279836" name="Seat Sandal" conf="2.4">Seat Sandal</enamex>, are the boundaries of this peace-ful valley and shut out all beyond.</s> <s id="s59">The churchwithin is miserable, one or two hatchments as I suppose of <enamex sw="w11004" long="-3.161177376207363" lat="54.33132273053623" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11189311" name="Knott, The" conf="2.4">the Knott</enamex>'s of <enamex sw="w11019" long="-2.98206973035289" lat="54.44823197501312" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15013" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex> hang on the damp green walls.</s> <s id="s60">In the second window from the altar isan oval of stained glass with the same.</s> <s id="s61">On the 27th of June we all four set out from <enamex sw="w11178" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> for <enamex sw="w11192" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> passing the heap of stones in the way called Dunmail raise whichwere piled together by one of the Saxon <enamex sw="w11304" long="0.7175847809662921" lat="52.24697055861436" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094318" name="Bury St Edmunds" conf="1.370307743">Edmunds</enamex> in order to commemorate his victory over Dunmail the last king of <enamex  sw="w11378" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s62">The heap is not largeperhaps 15 yards across over the top is built the wall which divides the Counties of <enamex  sw="w11496" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w11511" name="Large admin unit">Westmorland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s63">From dunmail raise we saw the lake of Leatheswater and as we descended the hill the base of <enamex sw="w11616" long="-3.012269722421011" lat="54.5304112692593" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11169753" name="Helvellyn" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex> stretched along the right of the road.</s> <s id="s64">Leathers water is about two miles and 1/ 2 in length; in breadthno where much more than a quarter as it appeared to me.</s> <s id="s65">After crossing the Greeta the little romantic vale of <enamex sw="w11838" long="-1.683939854346278" lat="54.49795383225262" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35385" name="Aldbrough St John" conf="1.515919673">St. John</enamex> is just caught to the right, but from the villageof Legberthwaite till within one or two miles of <enamex sw="w11945" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> nothing is worthy attention or in the smallest degree inter-esting except <enamex sw="w12027" long="-3.1487" lat="54.6521" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2637715" name="Skiddaw" conf="99992">Skiddow</enamex> and <enamex sw="w12039" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex> at a distance.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s66">Gu a fren Ar crest on a wreath or[ indistinct] knot Az.</s></p>
<p><s id="s67">From <enamex sw="w12127" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> to <enamex sw="w12140" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> is twelve miles.</s> <s id="s68">About half a mile above the latter we had a most delightful view of the vale, the town, the lake of <enamex sw="w12265" long="-3.186667117994916" lat="54.68162943544549" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11071444" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex> and part <enamex sw="w12288" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>.</s> <s id="s69">We lodged at the Queens head, Mr. Woods and were received with every attention we could wish.</s> <s id="s70">We went that evening to Crosthwaites museum.</s></p>
<p><s id="s71">His collection chiefly consists of mineral productions and those indian bows, caps, and ornaments which are to be found in every museum.</s> <s id="s72">He had a collection of coins, which I did not examine, the chair of Ld <enamex sw="w12644" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, a chinese Gong which produced a most thundering sound, and an instrument of the staccato kind, made of stone ofwhich he pretends to have found six notes in the proper musical succession.</s> <s id="s73">He also sells his own maps of the lakes which have the character of thenicest accuracy in every respect.</s> <s id="s74">His daughter seems an elegant woman, and more worth seeing than any thing else in his house, as to himself he is seated in a gouty chairand drums in one corner of the room, like a fool, to the noise of a barrel organ.</s> <s id="s75">While he has mirrors in every direction at the windows, by which he instantly sees every carriage that comes from any of the neighbouring towns, though he sits not near to any of the windows himself.</s> <s id="s76">The organ strikes up if any one passes, and his horrible drum is thumped, at the same time that the old woman runs upstairs and rattles away at the Gong, in a matter that cannot fail to attract the notice of theunfortunate strangers in <enamex sw="w13604" long="-2.550537094982595" lat="51.15293732249635" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11294325" name="Street on the Fosse" conf="1.436673525">the street</enamex>.</s> <s id="s77">He has even attempted to make a larger Gong than that he has already, with which he might astonish strangers but this has not succeeded, probably owing to the too great thick-ness of the brass of which it is formed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s78">On the 28th I rambled by the side of the lake; and fortunately hit on a most advantageous spot for seeing at one view the whole of the lake, its islands and the surrounding mountains.</s> <s id="s79">It is called <enamex sw="w14029" long="-3.137630072408776" lat="54.59221629737263" type="other" gazref="unlock:11148139" name="Friar's Crag" conf="2">Friar's Crag</enamex> where you may place yourself in such a manner as to see most of the beauties of the lake, yet notbe disgusted with the folly and childishness of what is now called <enamex sw="w14206" long="-3.145167855" lat="54.59136241" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00130" name="Pocklington's Island" conf="99992">Pocklingtons</enamex> island, where is an house that appears to have dropped from the clouds, one or two batterieswith pasteboard battlements and a spruceness in the whole, which cannot accord in any degree with the surrounding scenery.</s></p>
<p><s id="s80">Exactly opposite <enamex sw="w14451" long="-2.694991541156079" lat="54.04727200487086" type="other" gazref="unlock:11118597" name="Crag, The" conf="2">the Crag</enamex> is an island called Lord island from having been formerly the occasional residence of the <enamex  sw="w14550" name="Not a placename">Radcliff</enamex>'s Earls of <enamex sw="w14570" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, who took theirtitle from this lake.</s> <s id="s81">The first of this family who appears to have been mentioned in history, was Sir Nicholas Radcliffe of Dilston in the <enamex  sw="w14737" name="Large admin unit">County of NorthumberlandKnight</enamex>, in the time of Edward the first, whose descendant married the heiress of the Derwentwaters in the time of Henry the Sixth, and through her obtained this princely estate.</s> <s id="s82">Francis first Earl of Derwentwater his lineal descendant, became Baron Dilston Viscount <enamex  sw="w15027" name="Not a placename">Langley</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w15039" name="Not a placename">Radcliff</enamex> and Earl of Derwentwater in the time of King Jamesthe second, but his son adhering to the unfortunate family of Stewart, on their attempt to recover the throne in the year 1716, lost at once his titles estate and life.</s> <s id="s83">It is I believe certain that his brother left issue abroad, as to himself, coming over in the late unfortunate and unsuccessful struggleof Prince Charles in the year forty five, he was seized and convicted upon his former attainder, without any enquiry as to his conduct on the latter occasion, but merelyas to the assist-ance he gave to his Brother in 1716.</s> <s id="s84">it is the belief of the vulgar that some years ago a young man of genteel appear-ance came to see this Lake, witha friend who acted as interpreter, as he himself could not speak English.</s> <s id="s85">They enquired for an old man in <enamex sw="w15846" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, who served them as a guide, and desired to see all thatever belonged to the <enamex sw="w15931" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> family, he took them upon one of the neigh-bouring hills and pointed out to them as accurately as he was able every part of the Estatewhich lay before them, the young man burst into tears.</s> <s id="s86">Afterwards having hand-somely rewarded his conductor he turned away from the scene and quitted the kingdom immediately. He is suppos-ed to have been of the <enamex  sw="w16288" name="Not a placename">Radcliff</enamex> family, and probably from the younger brother of the attainted Earl before mentioned.</s> <s id="s87">Camden says this family had ancientlya castle at Castle Rigg and adds that the fine old oaks which surrounded the mansion were cut down by the trustees of the Greenwich hospital to the maintenance of which the forfeited estate was applied.</s> <s id="s88">The presentrepresentative in <enamex  sw="w16652" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> re-ceives at present no more that two thousand five hundreds pounds annually, although the estate amounts to more than 20,000, and it is remarkablethat of the <enamex sw="w16819" long="-122.2261543273926" lat="50.43573570251465" type="water" gazref="unlock:14139049" name="Fraser" conf="0.8630125295">Fraser</enamex>'s and others who were concerned at the same time with Ld <enamex sw="w16883" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> every one has had their property restored except his family.</s> <s id="s89"><enamex sw="w16957" long="-3.145167855" lat="54.59136241" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00130" name="Pocklington's Island" conf="99992">Pocklingtons</enamex> Islandis like all which formerly belonged to the <enamex  sw="w17019" name="Not a placename">Radcliff</enamex>'s let upon long leases to the different tennants.</s> <s id="s90">The taste of Mr. Pocklington in buildings anddecorations, is so remarkable that I cannot omit to mention a few of his singularities.</s> <s id="s91">On making the foundation for his cellars and house at theisland, was found a great stone, this, though the Architect wished it to remain, as an excellent foundation, he resolved to fix up-right before his house and at a greatexpence had is placed there.</s> <s id="s92">A druid temple was the next thing to employ his genius and accordingly he collected a number of large stones, placed them in a circle, and hadthem fixed upright on the southern shore.</s> <s id="s93">Unfortunately for all the lovers of British antiquity a storm arose in the lake, and the waves washed down in one night the labours of some days.</s> <s id="s94">On the other side a venerable whitewashed gothic building rears its august head, in all the pride of pasteboard antiquity.</s> <s id="s95">A church, Faro batteries and four or five cannon painted white make up the whole of this miraculous assemblage of beauties, and surround the enchanted island, I say enchant-ed for tis plain nature never formed in her most sportive moments, such an awkward jumble of gantastic gew gaws.</s></p>
<p><s id="s96">He has just sold this spot to Mr. Peachy and means to retire to Barrow cascade hal, where if possible he has outdone himself in ridiculous fancies. The house is not very particular but a white embattled hermitage is situated on an eminence near it, where he has offered half a crown a day to anyone who will live init, provided the wretch will submit to his conditions, which are these.</s> <s id="s97">The hermit is never to leave the place, or hold conversation with anyone for 7 years during whichtime he is neither to wash himself or cleanse himself in any way whatever, but is to let his hair and nails both on hands and feet, grow as long as nature will permitthem.</s> <s id="s98">Though the reward is certainly great, yet the happiness of the situation is such that he has never yet been able to persuade any one to accept his proposals.</s> <s id="s99">In short all his white buildings and ornaments contribute to diminish the simple beauty of the lake, which is without exception otherwisethe finest piece of water I have yet seen in these parts.</s></p>
<p><s id="s100">While I sat under the rocks of friar crag, and looked at the island, once the seat of hospitality but now deserted and long since covered with wood, the following thoughts came into my head and had I not been interrupted, they would have been written on the rocks which are just opposite to <enamex sw="w19502" long="-3.1366" lat="54.5563" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="99992">Lowdore</enamex>, at that time destitute of water, and remarkable from that distance only... I was suddenly surprized by the sound of a female voice on the crag above me, looking up I saw a gentleman and a lady with whom I soon became acquainted and found that they were Mr. Aufrere and his lady who had known my relations in <enamex  sw="w19820" name="Large admin unit">Derbyshire</enamex>.</s> <s id="s101">I found him a very agreeable and entertaining man, and Mrs. Aufrere an elegant woman.</s> <s id="s102">They gave me much information on the subject of <enamex sw="w19966" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, and its environs.</s></p>
<p><s id="s103">After dinner we took a boat and landed on <enamex sw="w20035" long="-3.145167855" lat="54.59136241" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00130" name="Pocklington's Island" conf="99992">Pocklingtons</enamex> Island, where having laughed sufficiently, we rowed between <enamex sw="w20108" long="-3.137379681649069" lat="54.58323023593808" type="other" gazref="unlock:11206449" name="Lord's Island" conf="2">Lords Island</enamex> and the shore where our rowers informed us though I know not on what grounds there had been a draw bridge to connect it with the mainland.</s> <s id="s104">Not a vestige of the house remains except perhaps a small part of the foundation scarcely visible it was destroyed by the Duke of Cumberland's forces in 1716.</s></p>
<p><s id="s105">There is a tradition among the vulgar, that a chest of gold of great value was thrown into the lake by Ld <enamex sw="w20525" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>'s order before he went to the assistance of the <enamex sw="w20586" long="-79.599636539" lat="45.016801486" type="other" gazref="unlock:5295131" name="Little Stewarts Island" conf="0.7658980605">Stewarts</enamex>, this is probably merely one of the romances which usually attend everything of this kind.</s> <s id="s106">From thence we landed at St. <enamex sw="w20715" long="-3.137379681649069" lat="54.58323023593808" type="other" gazref="unlock:11276541" name="St Herbert's Island" conf="2">Herberts island</enamex> where that saint is reputed to have prayed and obtained his desire to die the same day hour and minute with his former friend and preceptor <enamex sw="w20871" long="-3.392880350420522" lat="54.81426162231475" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11177650" name="Holme St Cuthbert" conf="2.541425337">St. Cuthbert</enamex>, who if I mistake not died at the abbey of <enamex sw="w20927" long="-1.801171527373584" lat="55.68482956596863" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11195202" name="Lindisfarne" conf="0.9604492395">Lindisfarne</enamex> in holy island opposite the mouth of the tyne.</s> <s id="s107">I like it far better than the others; both <enamex sw="w21029" long="-3.145167855" lat="54.59136241" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00130" name="Pocklington's Island" conf="99992">Pocklingtons</enamex> and Lords islands are much too near the shore, while this is but little less than half a mile from the very nearest point of the mainland.</s> <s id="s108">They showed us what they thought or pretended to believe, the remains of St. Herbert's cell, but he had a good notion of building without mortar, if he could make it last from his own time to this, and indeed did not spare either time, or labour, in erecting a building of such an extent, if it were possible the present building could be really his.</s> <s id="s109">The whole is most beautifully covered with trees and a walk to the southern extremity is overhung with lofty pines.</s> <s id="s110">Its only inhabitant is a poor jack ass, who if he has the spirit of contemplation within him may here turn anchorite and enjoy himself in his unenvied solitude.</s> <s id="s111">We next landed at <enamex sw="w21827" long="-3.1366" lat="54.5563" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="99992">Lowdore</enamex> where we had a nearer view of what may sometimes be a most roaring cataract, but when we saw it had not so much water as the little falls of <enamex sw="w21976" long="-2.98206973035289" lat="54.44823197501312" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15013" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex>.</s> <s id="s112">From <enamex sw="w21988" long="-3.1366" lat="54.5563" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="99992">Lowdore</enamex> to Grange is a pleasant walk of two miles, where we endeavoured to procure a lodging at the village, just at the entrance of <enamex sw="w22121" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>, but did not succeed.</s> <s id="s113">We saw the famous <enamex sw="w22172" long="-3.1516" lat="54.5382" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11084123" name="Bowder Stone" conf="99992">Bowdar</enamex> Stone a little farther about 21 yards in length and eleven high a most enormous mass weighing upwards of 1771 tons.</s></p>
<p><s id="s114"><enamex sw="w22295" long="-3.090245821198284" lat="54.55669882687418" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11100762" name="Castle Crag (Fort)" conf="2.2">Castle Crag</enamex>, rises in a piramidal form, on its summit once was a castle, few however if any traces of it now remain.</s> <s id="s115">We determined to proceed along the vale to <enamex sw="w22455" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, although we had nine or ten miles to go, and to use the expression of the countrymen one of the blindest roads we could have chosen.</s></p>
<p><s id="s116">A little after we passed the village of <enamex sw="w22640" long="-3.160418408000877" lat="54.30436355899656" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11272960" name="Rosthwaite" conf="2.6">Rosthwaite</enamex>, we began to ascend a steep hill which with much time and labour we at last overcame.</s> <s id="s117">Hitherto I had seen nothing equal to <enamex sw="w22774" long="-2.949627248591311" lat="54.49496591860104" type="water" gazref="unlock:11131061" name="Dovedale Beck" conf="2.4">Dovedale</enamex>, and here though by far the most romantic part of the country, the hills wanted the spiry rocks and the valley the transparent steam, to render it worthy of comparison.</s> <s id="s118">The account of it in West's guide, though not written by himself is as much overcharged in this subject as it is generally on every other.</s> <s id="s119">From the last ascent, we found a most surprising view down a deep valley, enclosed on either side by lofty crags, and almost covered below with huge fragments of rock that seemed to have been rent from the surrounding heights.</s> <s id="s120">We saw one which we judged might even be one quarter the size of the great <enamex sw="w23393" long="-3.1516" lat="54.5382" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11084123" name="Bowder Stone" conf="99992">Bowdar</enamex> but in this we might probably be deceived as darkness began to overtake us, and the road became so rugged that any attention to the scenery of the country, must have been attended by a stumble over some of the pointed slate of which the way is composed.</s> <s id="s121">A few trifling slips gave us warning of what we had to expect without care, and we afterwards heard that a guide from <enamex sw="w23772" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> had broken his leg there, almost a year before we visited the spot.</s></p>
<p><s id="s122">A short time before we arrived at the top of the fell the road became nothing more than a morass, and it is curious to relate that a dispute ensued, whether a loose line of stones on which we stood was intended for a road or the bed of a torrent at the time when a considerable fall of rain, or the dissolution of winter snows, produces frequent floods in this mountainous region.</s> <s id="s123">At length we saw buttermere; at the head of the lake stand two or three houses, called <enamex sw="w24316" long="-3.244032245927692" lat="54.52824948516431" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11151083" name="Gatesgarth" conf="2.6">Gatesgarth</enamex>, where we learnt from a man who answered our question from his bed, that we only wanted two miles of the village.</s> <s id="s124">We entered the village at eleven, and at the door of the inn, known only by the name of Joseph Robinsons, for there is no sign, we were received by the landlords daughter, the celebrated beauty of those parts.</s> <s id="s125">While our good old hostess, prepared our beds the lovely daughter waited on us at supper, with that good nature and attention which soon determined us as much in favour of her disposition, as we were before captivated by the charms of her person.</s> <s id="s126">Indeed so much attention was paid us, that we all agreed to remain at <enamex sw="w24968" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> some days, though our original intention was to have left it the day after our arrival.</s> <s id="s127">We saw the amazing fall of Scale force in the course of the next day, and it is indeed worthy of notice, falling precipitately from the summit of the hill into a chasm scarce six yards wide enclosed on every side but the outlet, by rocks which in some places start up in perpendicular masses and in others hang over in a manner that joined to the height of one hundred and fifty feet perpendicular render the whole tremendous and unrivalled.</s> <s id="s128">It is indeed worthy the pencil of a <enamex  sw="w25545" name="Not a placename">Rosa</enamex>, the trees covered with moss, the fern starting up in the angles of the rock, and the dashing of the water are highly finished much in his stile.</s> <s id="s129">There are two falls, the lower not more than twelve feet in height, nature has left a kind of staircase by the side of it which seems to have been improved by art in order to give a full view of the higher fall, which otherwise could not have been obtained.</s></p>
<p><s id="s130">Some days after we climbed the steep hill above the village of <enamex sw="w26017" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> and saw the lakes of <enamex sw="w26049" long="-3.322732159981248" lat="54.5723577144906" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209070" name="Loweswater" conf="2.6">Loweswater</enamex> Crommock and <enamex sw="w26073" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> on one side with <enamex sw="w26101" long="-3.145167855" lat="54.59136241" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00130" name="Pocklington's Island" conf="99992">Pocklingtons</enamex> island and <enamex sw="w26125" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, <enamex sw="w26139" long="-3.185804700514816" lat="54.57418107642148" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790063" name="Newlands Beck" conf="2.4">Newlands</enamex> vale, and the rudest assemblage of hills, and rocks, I ever beheld on the other.</s></p>
<p><s id="s131">We even imagined we saw the sea over Mell break, an hill on the side of Crummock.</s> <s id="s132"><enamex sw="w26311" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> is two miles, Crummock about three, and <enamex sw="w26362" long="-3.322732159981248" lat="54.5723577144906" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209070" name="Loweswater" conf="2.6">Loweswater</enamex> just one mile in length, where the hills are softened to rising grounds and the tameness of the scene cannot please, when the eye has been accustomed to the wildness of <enamex sw="w26542" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s133">On Sunday the second of July we went to church and were reconciled to our miserable situation with damp walls and wet soil, for there is no floor, by the sight of a large number of attendants for the size of the place, and the appearance of a respectable preacher.</s> <s id="s134">The daughter of our host was our conductress.</s> <s id="s135">In the night it rained so hard that every little rill became a torrent or waterfall, we wished to re-visit scale force but fishing or other amusements prevented us for sometime.</s></p>
<p><s id="s136">On Tuesday the fourth of July we gave a dance to the villagers of <enamex sw="w27109" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>, our company consisted of five and thirty persons and if it be a pleasure to see merry faces and good humour we had them here in perfection.</s> <s id="s137">We regaled the ladies with queen cakes and punch the rest with ale and porter and for the little expence of perhaps half a guinea on each of us we gave an entertainment unequalled in the annals of <enamex sw="w27458" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s138">We danced from eight in the evening till two the next morning between each country dance, the customary gigs of the country took place for it is usual for every one to ask each of the females to dance a gig though there be thirty in company.</s> <s id="s139">We saw scale force again some days after, my companions thought it improved, by the addition of a considerable flood, for my own part I thought the height appeared so much diminished, as to take away greatly from the effect.</s></p>
<p><s id="s140">We went to <enamex sw="w27948" long="-3.424036233423147" lat="54.62625233230398" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13331491" name="Cockermouth West ED" conf="5.4">Cockermouth</enamex> on the seventh, saw the castle a small and never apparently strong building, founded by Waltheof son of Gospatric, lord of Allerdale.</s> <s id="s141"><enamex sw="w28094" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.4">Over</enamex> the gate are the arms of <enamex sw="w28124" long="-3.83206830771276" lat="51.01396530180237" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11287764" name="South Molton" conf="1.248856475">Molton</enamex>, Humfranville Lucy and <enamex  sw="w28154" name="Not a placename">Percy</enamex> as Camden saws but he forgets to mention the fifth shield, the coat of the Nevill's who married the heiress of Gospatric Earl of Northumberland during the reign of the Conqueror, or soon after.</s> <s id="s142">This Castle is reported to have been built from the ruins of the Roman <enamex sw="w28425" long="-3.387955449709089" lat="54.67050233159707" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11239305" name="Papcastle" conf="2.6">Papcastle</enamex>, by the Britons called Palmcastle, a short distance from <enamex sw="w28492" long="-3.424036233423147" lat="54.62625233230398" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13331491" name="Cockermouth West ED" conf="5.4">Cockermouth</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s143">The town itself is not large, and has little to recommend it.</s> <s id="s144">The name is taken from the situation, standing on the conflux of the Rivers Cocker, and <enamex sw="w28655" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>.</s> <s id="s145">The site of this castle, is now the property of the Earl of Egremont, who derives his title, from another castle in this county, founded by William de Meschines Earl of Chester, whose daughter married William fitz Duncan, of the blood Royal of <enamex  sw="w28908" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>, from whom the title passed through the families of Lucy, <enamex sw="w28975" long="-3.83206830771276" lat="51.01396530180237" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11287764" name="South Molton" conf="1.248856475">Molton</enamex>, and Fitzwalter, till it came to the <enamex  sw="w29019" name="Not a placename">Radcliff</enamex>'s Earls of <enamex sw="w29039" long="0.3720629438757896" lat="50.94554710388184" type="civila" gazref="unlock:14122378" name="East Sussex" conf="1.43613865">Sussex</enamex>.</s> <s id="s146">Thos.</s> <s id="s147"><enamex  sw="w29053" name="Not a placename">Percy</enamex> in the reign of Henry the sixth, was first Lord of <enamex sw="w29110" long="-3.531672049652393" lat="54.48235780155937" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10053" name="Egremont" conf="2.6">Egremont</enamex>, of that family, and I believe the present posessor of <enamex sw="w29174" long="-3.424036233423147" lat="54.62625233230398" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13331491" name="Cockermouth West ED" conf="5.4">Cockermouth</enamex> is his descendant.</s></p>
<p><s id="s148">We returned to <enamex sw="w29220" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> the next day, passing through <enamex sw="w29261" long="-3.308706047209322" lat="54.61745318512404" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11207371" name="Low Lorton" conf="2.6">Lorton</enamex>, where is perhaps the largest school in the country, if that of <enamex sw="w29332" long="-3.582497849760178" lat="54.48833781762206" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11276282" name="St Bees" conf="2.584474174">St. Bees</enamex> be excepted, which is situated on the coast, and so called from St. Bega one of those ladies who came to seek their fortunes here from <enamex  sw="w29476" name="Large admin unit">Ireland</enamex>, which indeed was much the fashion of those days, for we read of St. Winifred and at least a dozen others from that country, doing the same.</s> <s id="s149">This virgin is said to have tamed a wild bull, by her piety, and to have covered the hills and vallies of <enamex  sw="w29731" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> with snow, in the midst of summer but the question of whether she deserved to be canonized for the latter piece of mischief, if left to the good people whose land she injured, would more probably have been determined, in favour of burning her for a witch, than raising her to the skies.</s> <s id="s150">From <enamex sw="w30034" long="-0.7827635783438046" lat="52.02919695365543" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11206671" name="Loughton" conf="1.430930027">Loughton</enamex> to <enamex sw="w30046" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> is about seven miles, the road tolerable to <enamex sw="w30101" long="-3.2959" lat="54.5521" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY16281820" name="Buttermere Hawse" conf="99992">Buttermere hawse</enamex>, a rock jutting out a little way into Crommock, and we were happy to find that our arrival at <enamex sw="w30212" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> was as pleasing as it was unexpected to the inhabitants of the village.</s> <s id="s151">We rowed that evening on the lake of Crummock, a most delightfully glowing sunset, tinged the water, and the surrounding mountains, with the finest purple we had ever seen.</s> <s id="s152">We landed at <enamex sw="w30481" long="-2.75745233250588" lat="54.1983109600986" type="water" gazref="unlock:8787679" name="Holme Beck" conf="2.4">Holme</enamex> island, and afterwards at <enamex sw="w30513" long="0.1944271113636099" lat="51.43944843727217" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084332" name="Bowmans" conf="1.374329257">Bowmans</enamex> island where we sat some time building aerial castles on the rock, while we enjoyed the scene.</s> <s id="s153">It was one of the finest evenings we had seen since the commencement of our tour.</s> <s id="s154">The island we found to be about forty four yards long, perhaps twenty in breadth.</s> <s id="s155">The whole is covered with wood like <enamex sw="w30816" long="-0.5309658453303814" lat="53.90546246268991" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11177640" name="Holme on the Wolds" conf="1.43968422">the Holme</enamex> and bilberries grow plentifully on each.</s> <s id="s156">Some evenings after we rowed two of the village maidens and a friend of theirs whose nicer feelings, for she had been educated at <enamex sw="w30997" long="-3.424036233423147" lat="54.62625233230398" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13331491" name="Cockermouth West ED" conf="5.4">Cockermouth</enamex>, could neither bear the motion of the boat, or the landing on the New island where the grass was not perfectly free from dew.</s> <s id="s157">New island is hardly fifty yards from the shore and somewhat larger than either of the others.</s> <s id="s158"><enamex sw="w31230" name="Wood house island">Wood house island</enamex> is a fourth where we landed, and finding great quantities of bilberries we sat down on the grass and regaled ourselves while the lady in the boat amused herself by her own thoughts on the occasion...</s></p>
<p><s id="s159">The day after we visited <enamex sw="w31473" long="-3.38277023620072" lat="54.51775401071067" type="water" gazref="unlock:11140134" name="Ennerdale Water" conf="2.4">Ennerdale water</enamex> over file miles of fells and bogs.</s> <s id="s160">A mist prevented us from seeing the lake for some time but on clearing up a fine piece of water and a rude fell on the opposite shore rewarded us for our trouble.</s> <s id="s161">There is one small island situated about the middle of the lake.</s> <s id="s162">We left this retired spot on the....... of July, I believe we may without vanity assert that all to whom we were known were not a little sorry at our departure, nor were we on our part insensible to the kindness and hospitality of these our rustic friends.</s> <s id="s163">We passed the lofty Grassmire on the left, scarce ten yards are wanting to make this mountain, equal to <enamex sw="w32114" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> in height, its colour is remarkable being of a tawny hue, without any covering except here and there a speck of heath to diversify its appearance.</s> <s id="s164">On the right just below <enamex sw="w32293" long="-3.236583505" lat="54.54372785" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00202" name="Robinson Crags" conf="99992">Robinsons Crag</enamex> and exactly at the head of <enamex sw="w32335" long="-3.2987" lat="54.5273" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY16051545" name="Newlands Vale" conf="99992">Newlands vale</enamex> is a waterfall, the height of the rock we did not recollect to observe.</s></p>
<p><s id="s165">The author of the guide to the lakes found a beauty and wildness in the valley of <enamex sw="w32503" long="-3.185804700514816" lat="54.57418107642148" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790063" name="Newlands Beck" conf="2.4">Newlands</enamex> which I believe others will scarce imagine with the assistance of the most romantic genius they can summon for the occasion.</s> <s id="s166">The upper end of the valley is poor and if the lower part has any thing particular to attract the attention ours certainly must have been employed another way during our walk.</s> <s id="s167">It was with some difficulty we passed a rapid stream at <enamex sw="w32869" long="-2.89396155055119" lat="54.77402218371541" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11206892" name="Low Braithwaite" conf="2.6">Braithwaite</enamex> where we left the road and crossed a few fields towards <enamex sw="w32937" long="-3.153358511469882" lat="54.60105586584796" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11249032" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex> a village not far from <enamex sw="w32972" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s168">We endeavoured in our way, to catch the sound of <enamex sw="w33030" long="-3.1366" lat="54.5563" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="99992">Lowdore</enamex> from the opposite side of <enamex sw="w33064" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> but a neighbouring river rolling among loose stones prevented us.</s> <s id="s169">At a place called Fincle street in <enamex sw="w33178" long="-3.153358511469882" lat="54.60105586584796" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11249032" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex> Mr. Pocklington has built another of his elegant villas, the situation is good, commanding a view of both <enamex sw="w33296" long="-3.186667117994916" lat="54.68162943544549" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11071444" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex> and Derwentwaters, but all situations may lose much of their effect, by the erection of a tall thin white house, round the angles and windows, of which, runs an elegant border of dirty red, which renders it infinitely more rural and agrees charmingly with the truely romantic, and engaging scenery of <enamex sw="w33611" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex>.</s> <s id="s170">There is however this comfort that his houses are so slightly built that the people think they cannot stand long to be the eye sores of the lake.</s></p>
<p><s id="s171">We had the good fortune to see the effect of the what is called in this country a bottom wind proceeding from some hitherto unknown cause or at least so far uncertain that there are many different opinions on the subject.</s> <s id="s172">The appearance is nearly as I can describe it was this.</s> <s id="s173">One part was agitated violently without the least apparent cause, while another was so smooth as to have scarcely move than a ripple upon its surface, a boat with two men was tossed up and down in a storm in one part while a man at no great distance was fishing quietly with a rod and line from another.</s> <s id="s174">There was little if any wind stirring at the time, and the waves seemed to make more noise than they would if equally agitated in the usual way.</s> <s id="s175">I am not certain whether this phenomenon is peculiar to this lake, at present I have heard of it in no other.</s> <s id="s176">We lodged at our former inn the Queens head, and found every convenience and attention we required.</s></p>
<p><s id="s177">In the morning we set out for <enamex sw="w34733" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex> intending to take <enamex sw="w34761" long="-2.8689" lat="54.6691" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_NY44063079" name="Greystock" conf="99991">Graystoke</enamex> and <enamex sw="w34775" long="-2.844334184103086" lat="54.63056992877543" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11126082" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex> Castles in our way.</s> <s id="s178">Soon after we had passed the first mile stone we got over an hedge to the right and saw the Druids temple, a circle of stones none of which are more than eight feet in height, the diameter of the whole I have forgotten.</s> <s id="s179">We were now on the <enamex sw="w35040" long="-2.749628438755928" lat="54.66475192978902" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11038" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> road and in passing through the vale of <enamex sw="w35088" long="-1.683939854346278" lat="54.49795383225262" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35385" name="Aldbrough St John" conf="1.515919673">St. John</enamex> which in that part has nothing worthy attention, the sun shone with such heat as obliged us to walk but slowly, till we had travelled eight miles of our way.</s> <s id="s180">Not far from the tenth mile stone we turned to the left through the small village of <enamex sw="w35340" long="-2.885528056569588" lat="54.64083215369705" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32942" name="Penruddock" conf="2.6">Penruddock</enamex> to <enamex sw="w35354" long="-2.876952675" lat="54.66990341" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00160" name="Greystoke Castle" conf="99992">Graystock castle</enamex> which we judged to be about four miles from the turnpike road.</s> <s id="s181">While our eggs and bacon were preparing at a small house in <enamex sw="w35494" long="-2.877" lat="54.6699" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY43543089" name="Greystoke" conf="99992">Graystock</enamex> we walked to the castle situated in a park well stocked with deer and the property of the Duke of Norfolk, it is perhaps one of the most retired situations in the kingdom.</s></p>
<p><s id="s182">The dutchess has resided here for more than three years and seldom stirs from the walls of the castle.</s> <s id="s183">The present building is neither new nor is it the ancient castle but was by the appearance probably erected about the begginning of the present century.</s> <s id="s184">The rooms are not large and seem but half finished an handsome oak staircase conducts you to the upper story where on seeing dust curtains hanging from the top of the room, we expected to have found some of the richly worked hangings usually concealed behind them, but I believe our surprize was very visible to the housekeeper who pulling the cover aside discovered nothing but a common cotton bed in the new style from which we immediately turned.</s> <s id="s185">There is one of blue velvet with silver in an adjoining room, the embroidery no doubt executed by some of the noble ladies of the Howard family, this has no cover, though for richness it far surpasses the others and must have cost ten times the sum, at the time it was made.</s> <s id="s186">The front of this building represented in <enamex sw="w36699" long="150.6833333" lat="-33.6" type="other" gazref="unlock:4146803" name="Grose River" conf="0.7071976845">Grose</enamex>, and in a set of engravings by <enamex sw="w36736" long="30.18333" lat="-29.81667" type="other" gazref="unlock:3352098" name="Byrne" conf="0.6336133281">Byrne</enamex> has been taken down by the present duke.</s> <s id="s187">Leaving <enamex sw="w36791" long="-2.877" lat="54.6699" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY43543089" name="Greystoke" conf="99992">Graystock</enamex> we proceeded to <enamex sw="w36817" long="-2.83754" lat="54.63056" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825055" name="Dacre Castle" conf="2">Dacre Castle</enamex> once the seat of the <enamex sw="w36851" long="-2.844334184103086" lat="54.63056992877543" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11126082" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex> family who had great possessions in the north.</s> <s id="s188"><enamex sw="w36904" name="Dumbrough">Dumbrough</enamex> Castle and <enamex sw="w36925" long="-3.052526199324935" lat="54.92333858543775" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35985" name="Burgh By Sands" conf="2.490238884">Burgh</enamex> belonged to them.</s> <s id="s189">The last given by one of the earls of Chester to Robt.</s> <s id="s190">de Trivers from whom it came to the Morvilles one of whom forfeited it by the murder of Thos a Becket in 1170 as well as his castle of <enamex sw="w37139" long="-2.670439372771031" lat="54.64677376142333" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403485" name="Brougham CP" conf="2.4">Brougham</enamex>.</s> <s id="s191"><enamex sw="w37149" long="-2.670439372771031" lat="54.64677376142333" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403485" name="Brougham CP" conf="2.4">Brougham</enamex> is about three miles from <enamex sw="w37184" long="-2.749628438755928" lat="54.66475192978902" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11038" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> and I sincerely regret that our time did not permit us to see the notable ruins.</s> <s id="s192">In the time of the conqueror it belonged to Hugo de Albinois from the Morvilles the Viponts succeeded to it in whose time part was demolished.</s> <s id="s193">The famous Countess of <enamex sw="w37439" long="-4.910528877092794" lat="51.67408287824648" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10999" name="Pembroke" conf="1.189858723">Pembroke</enamex> once possessed it and during a visit here a great part of the <enamex sw="w37510" long="22.25" lat="37.58333" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00046" name="Arcadia" conf="99991">Arcadia</enamex> of Sir <enamex sw="w37525" long="-2.881047976026408" lat="55.56131484815666" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788748" name="Long Philip Burn" conf="1.088274236">Philip</enamex> <enamex  sw="w37532" name="Not a placename">Sydney</enamex> was written.</s> <s id="s194">With respect to the <enamex sw="w37572" long="-2.844334184103086" lat="54.63056992877543" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11126082" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex> family all that I can at present recollect is that by the marriage of Ranulph Lord <enamex sw="w37661" long="-2.844334184103086" lat="54.63056992877543" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11126082" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex> with <enamex  sw="w37672" name="Not a placename">Maud</enamex>, daughter and heir of one of the Multons which family had the representatives of the Morvilles and Vaulx's of Gillesland the title of Gillesland and the great possessions of the three families came to the Dacres.</s> <s id="s195">There were two families one called <enamex sw="w37925" long="-2.844334184103086" lat="54.63056992877543" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11126082" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex> of the north and th other of Gillesland.</s></p>
<p><s id="s196">The part which now remains, I conjecture to have been no more than the keep of the ancient castle.</s> <s id="s197">It is at present the property of the <enamex sw="w38108" long="6.8833333" lat="51.1666667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4378780" name="Hassels" conf="0.2933122042">Hassels</enamex> of <enamex sw="w38119" long="-2.813352976215357" lat="54.63078196381976" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11126513" name="Dalemain" conf="2.2">Dalemain</enamex> about two miles distant.</s> <s id="s198">We had a view of it from the towers of <enamex sw="w38192" long="-2.844334184103086" lat="54.63056992877543" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11126082" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex>.</s> <s id="s199"><enamex sw="w38199" long="-2.813352976215357" lat="54.63078196381976" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11126513" name="Dalemain" conf="2.2">Dalemain</enamex> was anciently part of the barony of <enamex sw="w38244" long="-2.877" lat="54.6699" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY43543089" name="Greystoke" conf="99992">Graystock</enamex> and held as Camden says of that lordship in cornage.</s> <s id="s200">We found the people at the castle civil and obliging and they gave us milk, and one of the fairest married women in the kingdom, conducted us to the top of the building through a narrow stone staircase.</s> <s id="s201">From hence we walked perhaps two miles, to <enamex sw="w38553" long="-2.812994518069897" lat="54.61280820901722" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11248058" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley bridge</enamex> in our way passing by one side of the hill <enamex sw="w38610" long="-2.8253" lat="54.6137" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY468246" name="Dunmallard Hill" conf="99992">Dunmallet</enamex>, till we arrived at the side of Ulleswater where some fishermen who said they belonged to the duke of Norfolk sold us three pounds of their trout and <enamex  sw="w38770" name="Not a placename">Grayling</enamex> which we carried to the inn and dressed for supper.</s> <s id="s202">There are two public housess in the village, we found at Prichardsons a very decent lodging.</s> <s id="s203">We were now on the... side of <enamex sw="w38955" long="-2.8253" lat="54.6137" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY468246" name="Dunmallard Hill" conf="99992">Dunmallet</enamex> and with some difficulty ascended to its summit, not on account of its height but the steepness of the path.</s> <s id="s204">This hill is situated exactly at the lower end of Ulleswater and on one side the... takes its course from the lake on the other the... The view from the summit was beautiful, the scenery round the lake was as rich as a fine sheet of water and woods and fruitful enclosures down to the waters edge could make it.</s> <s id="s205">There was formerly a roman station here, and since the conquest a Benedictine nunnery which once ornamented its brow, must have been a happy and picturesque conclusion to a sail down the lake.</s> <s id="s206">Indeed it is not a little surprising that more of these religious houses are not to be found on these lakes, than which no place could be more suited to the idea of monkish solitude nor could the ruined tower and pointed arch, embosomed in ivy, be found in a place more beautifully calculated to inspire veneration or add thought on other times with greater effect than here.</s> <s id="s207">The next morning we set out from <enamex sw="w39989" long="-2.812994518069897" lat="54.61280820901722" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11248058" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley bridge</enamex> along the side of the lake for <enamex sw="w40034" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s208">The road lies scarcely two hundred yards from the water, the whole of the way indeed till we got near the village of Wattermillock we never left the shore, and in Gowbarrow park the road is washed all the way by the lake on the left.</s> <s id="s209">We admired the situation of Mr. Robinsons house much, situated among trees and commanding a view of two reaches of the lake which here turns to the west having before spread from north west to south east.</s> <s id="s210">The sun shone with all its splendour when we reached the gate of Gowbarrow park, and we sat down by a little rivulet to rest ourselves, for five minutes, the cattle were cooling themselves, in the water, the lake became gently agitated, and the thick woods in <enamex sw="w40745" long="-81.47375" lat="28.58473" type="other" gazref="unlock:10792570" name="The Groves Mobile Home Park" conf="0.6829029094">the park</enamex> were a fine contrast to the naked barrenness of the opposite rock.</s> <s id="s211">As we proceeded we saw three gentlemen whom we had before met at <enamex sw="w40886" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex>, they were fishing from a boat, they acknowledged us, and informed us how far we were distant from <enamex sw="w40995" long="-2.9206" lat="54.5761" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11210312" name="Lyulph's Tower" conf="99992">Lyulph</enamex>'s tower which was they our object.</s></p>
<p><s id="s212">In a short time we saw the turrets peeping over the trees in which they are so concealed that we had very nearly passed the building before we looked up through the trees and discovered our mistake.</s> <s id="s213">We knocked at the door a woman desired us to enter who showed us the inside of the tower consisting of a servants hall a long hall within used as a dining room and beyond a staircase.</s> <s id="s214">On the other side the door we entered, was the room belonging to the family who live there.</s> <s id="s215">Upstairs we had good views of the lake from the windows of the turrets.</s> <s id="s216">The whole is nothing more than a farm house or a gamekeepers lodge where the Duke of Norfolk to whom <enamex sw="w41685" long="-81.47375" lat="28.58473" type="other" gazref="unlock:10792570" name="The Groves Mobile Home Park" conf="0.6829029094">the park</enamex> and parts of the lake belong has two or three rooms for an occasional fishing or shooting party.</s> <s id="s217">The outside nearest to the lake is built of rough stones, the angles are turretted, and though from the form of the battlements and the shape of the windows, the frames of which as well as the doors are painted of a delightful pea green, the place can never be mistaken for an old building, yet at a distance where these little defects are not observed, the whole has an effect that does honour to the taste of the owner.</s> <s id="s218">A very civil fellow who we took to be the gamekeeper coming in and observing us rather warm from our walk insisted on our tasting some rum and new milk which he immediately mixed and presented to us.</s> <s id="s219">He afterwards conducted us to <enamex sw="w42443" long="84.6666667" lat="25.5666667" type="ppl" gazref="geonames:1278483" name="Ara" conf="1.269923878">Ara</enamex> or <enamex sw="w42450" long="-2.936" lat="54.576" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11057415" name="Aira Force" conf="99992">Airey force</enamex>, about a quarter of a mile above the house, a waterfall of about eighty feet and <enamex sw="w42543" long="-2.421557122390574" lat="53.29060765310844" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13406245" name="Tabley Inferior CP" conf="1.310571913">inferior</enamex> to none that we had seen excepting the fall which exceeds all others a little distance from <enamex sw="w42644" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s220">When we had regained the road we rewarded our honest friend for his trouble and he returned his thanks and blessing.</s> <s id="s221">He had an openness about him in every thing he said, or did, that gained much more of our esteem than all the set speeches in the kingdom could have done, and the rusticity of his manner seemed to prove that his kindness and attention to us did not proceed from the hope of gain, but from the benevolence of his heart.</s> <s id="s222">There are few finer deer parks than Gowbarrow, the rocks the woods and the wildness of the place must be well adapted to the preservation of these animals and would naturally be their haunt if left entirely to themselves.</s> <s id="s223">Indeed <enamex sw="w43321" long="-81.47375" lat="28.58473" type="other" gazref="unlock:10792570" name="The Groves Mobile Home Park" conf="0.6829029094">the park</enamex> is overstocked with them and we were informed that it was usual to kill as many fawns as they could catch on account of the difficulty they found in taking them at a more advanced age.</s></p>
<p><s id="s224">The road continued under the foliage of thick trees almost all the way to <enamex sw="w43589" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex> a little past the park gate there is by far the finest view in my opinion that can be found among the lakes.</s> <s id="s225">On the right is a large sweep of the lake adorned with three rocky islands.</s> <s id="s226">Their names are House holm, wall island and Cherry holm, behind them is a rocky and wild assemblage of hills and the beautiful village of <enamex sw="w43923" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex> closes the scene.</s> <s id="s227">On the left are the woods of Gowbarrow and <enamex sw="w43995" long="-81.47375" lat="28.58473" type="other" gazref="unlock:10792570" name="The Groves Mobile Home Park" conf="0.6829029094">the park</enamex>.</s> <s id="s228"><enamex sw="w44005" long="-2.9206" lat="54.5761" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11210312" name="Lyulph's Tower" conf="99992">Lyulph</enamex>'s tower looks nobly from an eminence on the water, over topped by hanging woods that terminate once only by a promontory which hides the remaining part of <enamex sw="w44167" long="-81.47375" lat="28.58473" type="other" gazref="unlock:10792570" name="The Groves Mobile Home Park" conf="0.6829029094">the park</enamex> from the view.</s> <s id="s229">Beyond this are other woods, and fields and hills in the distance, the whole is finished by the <enamex sw="w44287" long="-2.23822" lat="54.53162" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00205" name="Stainmore" conf="99992">Stainmore hills</enamex> in the horizon which compleat the sweetest landscape in the lakes.</s> <s id="s230">From this charming view we passed on the St. Patricks well, which gives name to the valley, there is anually a ceremony observed here on St. Patricks day of drinking a bottle of rum over the spring and on that day dancing and all sorts of merriment go on with great spirit, in honour of the tutelary Saint of this beautiful spot.</s> <s id="s231">We dined at the <enamex sw="w44716" long="-2.804" lat="54.0486" type="other" gazref="unlock:5829745" name="Royal Kings Arms Hotel" conf="2">Kings Arms</enamex> at the head of the lake, the people are very civil and gave us a very good dinner, after which we set out for <enamex sw="w44837" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s232">We passed again by the church, in the yard is an yew tree nine yards in circumference.</s> <s id="s233">The way is one of the most fatiguing that can be conceived running long the side of <enamex sw="w45019" long="-2.981150321058669" lat="54.52167935242581" type="water" gazref="unlock:11161463" name="Grisdale Beck" conf="2.4">Grisdale beck</enamex> for no less than six miles of which at the least four miles and a half are up a steep fell.</s> <s id="s234">We were not a little pleased with the sight of <enamex sw="w45172" long="-3.011603205107465" lat="54.5034516594409" type="water" gazref="unlock:11161476" name="Grisedale Tarn" conf="2.4">Grisedale tarn</enamex>, a small piece of water about three miles from <enamex sw="w45234" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> where we had been on fishing parties before.</s> <s id="s235">From thence the road or rather the track, lies all down hill to <enamex sw="w45353" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> and we found ourselves so thirsty from our long walk up the hill that a little well we met with would have suffered greatly from our attack if prudence had not restrained us in some measure.</s> <s id="s236">At this well there is a report that the old King of Patterdale once emptied an whole bottle of Rum, when on a fishing party the company were not provided with glasses.</s> <s id="s237">Of this Gentleman I forgot to mention that he was called king of <enamex sw="w45787" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex> by hereditary right, having inherited from his ancestors an estate in the valley, upwards of two hundred pounds a year which from the remoteness of the situation is said never to have paid taxes, been disturbed by the rapacity of tyrants or plundered by the incursions of the Scots.</s> <s id="s238">His late majesty lived to a great age.</s> <s id="s239">Her majesty is yet living, and is reported to have lately given up drinking, to which she has formerly been immoderately attached.</s> <s id="s240">The family name is Mounsey, and the present King with a fortune of eight hundred a year, which was partly scraped up by the penurious father, has the character of a gentleman of the most benevolent and charitable disposition.</s> <s id="s241">We arrived at <enamex sw="w46491" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> in the evening where we found another of our party waiting for our return.</s> <s id="s242">As he had never seen <enamex sw="w46597" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> or <enamex sw="w46608" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> he crossed over the fells of <enamex sw="w46648" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex> to the latter.</s> <s id="s243">Two of our former party went with him.</s> <s id="s244">As to myself being not much attracted by the charms of <enamex sw="w46768" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> I went with my only remaining companion to <enamex sw="w46821" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> intending to remains there till the return of the <enamex sw="w46879" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> party.</s> <s id="s245">We took a walk to friar crag, a favourite situation for viewing the Lake.</s> <s id="s246">Some ladies bathing at a distance, certainly more for health than pleasure for it blew a storm might have put me in mind of mermaids or Niads had not the wind been so cold as to chill every effort of the imagination and a shower of rain forced us to retreat to our inn.</s> <s id="s247">I this morning walked about three miles and  to <enamex sw="w47290" long="-3.1366" lat="54.5563" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="99992">Lowdore</enamex> as I saw from friar crag it did not want water.</s> <s id="s248">I cannot say I was much astonished at the fall, after having seen scale force.</s> <s id="s249">Indeed it is no where properly speaking a fall, for there is no part of it where the stream falls two feet perpendicularly but the whole rushes down a bed of rocks, which are not inclined more than five and forty degrees from the horizon.</s> <s id="s250">I cannot think after the wonders that are related of it, that it is ever in perfection during the summer, for among other things the people say the noise can be heard at <enamex sw="w47834" long="0.3389997069709487" lat="52.56983893920285" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11237512" name="Ouse Bridge Fm" conf="0.9801763885">Ouse bridge</enamex> at least ten miles in a direct line from the fall.</s></p>
<p><s id="s251"><enamex sw="w47897" long="-3.186667117994916" lat="54.68162943544549" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11071444" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex> has little beauty when compared to <enamex sw="w47946" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex> there is not one island on the lake it is no where a mile in breadth and the hills except <enamex sw="w48044" long="-3.1487" lat="54.6521" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2637715" name="Skiddaw" conf="99992">Skiddow</enamex> are comparatively nothing.</s> <s id="s252">I believe the length is not much less than five miles but the scenery is unvaried and does not please after <enamex sw="w48187" long="-3.351799651190464" lat="54.57703262453121" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772717" name="River Derwent" conf="2.4">Derwent</enamex> anyone whom I have heard mention it.</s> <s id="s253">In the evening I went up Castle crag above <enamex sw="w48275" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> where from the height of the rock, the whole map of <enamex sw="w48335" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> may be perfectly discovered and eight islands plainly perceived there is a ninth not easily distinguished from this spot and Lords island looks smaller than Vicars from this point.</s></p>
<p><s id="s254">I endeavoured to discover any traces of the Roman fort or <enamex sw="w48587" long="-2.890464102233929" lat="53.18298073394839" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11101187" name="Castle, The" conf="1.177056512">the Castle</enamex> of the Radcliffs but though I ascended the hill with the enthusiastic eye of an antiquary I could find nothing on which to vent my conjectures or the least remnant of a foundation which from its reputed strength I could not have supposed so compleatly destroyed.</s> <s id="s255">The morning after I climbed <enamex sw="w48889" long="-3.1487" lat="54.6521" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2637715" name="Skiddaw" conf="99992">Skiddow</enamex> beginning my ascent from the upper end of <enamex sw="w48939" long="-3.186667117994916" lat="54.68162943544549" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11071444" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex>.</s> <s id="s256">I cannot say I was so much pleased at the views from its summit as I expected from the accounts of others.</s> <s id="s257">The weather was foggy when I began to ascend but before I reached the top, the sun shone and I had an opportunity of seeing all beneath me.</s> <s id="s258">That part of <enamex sw="w49214" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> which I saw, looked mean from such an height and <enamex sw="w49276" long="-3.186667117994916" lat="54.68162943544549" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11071444" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex> was narrow.</s> <s id="s259"><enamex sw="w49302" long="-3.576762628834178" lat="54.74010234959695" type="water" gazref="unlock:11286649" name="Solway Firth" conf="2.312883761">Solway firth</enamex> and the opposite shore of <enamex  sw="w49341" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>, on the one hand, and <enamex sw="w49372" long="-1.500309168183582" lat="54.64543028105785" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13372576" name="Bradbury and the Isle CP" conf="1.234805552">the Isle</enamex> of Man on the other were seen indistinctly through the blue vapour in which they appeared to be enveloped.</s> <s id="s260">I descended by the base of <enamex sw="w49515" long="-3.122649812250939" lat="54.61033292579526" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11192243" name="Latrigg" conf="2.4">Latrigg</enamex> a smaller hill often called <enamex sw="w49551" long="-3.1487" lat="54.6521" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2637715" name="Skiddaw" conf="99992">Skiddow</enamex>'s cub and gained the <enamex sw="w49580" long="-2.749628438755928" lat="54.66475192978902" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11038" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> road about half a mile from <enamex sw="w49616" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> passing over a wooden bridge raised on high rafters which joins the opposite sides of the Greeta.</s> <s id="s261">When I arrived at the Inn I found two of our party returned from <enamex sw="w49787" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> in company with whom I went the next morning on the lake for the second time.</s> <s id="s262">We touched at Lords island and compared a plan I had procured of the old house there with the ruined foundations.</s> <s id="s263">The island is far greater in size than Vicars, the trees flourish greatly.</s> <s id="s264">It is reported that when the trustees of the Greenwich hospital planted the island with young trees there were such numbers of mice on the place that the trees were soon demolished.</s> <s id="s265">To remedy this, numbers of cats were turned loose upon the shore who lessened their numbers so considerably that they themselves had not enough for their subsistence.</s> <s id="s266">Some few were adventurous enough to tempt the waves and gained the nearest land others died on the island and some few remained long in their undisturbed retirement.</s> <s id="s267">Our next object was Barrow cascade the fall was really grand and the walks not ill suited to the place, a most unusual circumstance where Mr. Pocklington is concerned.</s> <s id="s268">We saw <enamex sw="w50755" long="-3.1366" lat="54.5563" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="99992">Lowdore</enamex> again and afterwards as the wind was fair sailed for Lord William Gordons Woods intending to see his house at water end.</s></p>
<p><s id="s269">The situation is the most retired on the Lake, a small bay opens on the west side; and at its extremity, the house, consisting of several rooms on one floor, is overshaded by thick woods, while two promontories guard the north and south aspects, and <enamex sw="w51134" long="-3.168321741791226" lat="54.58293549454491" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11296646" name="Swinside" conf="2.6">Swinside</enamex> shutting up the west leaves only the eastern side of the house exposed to the lake.</s> <s id="s270">Perhaps the view towards the lake may rather incline to the south.</s> <s id="s271">Along the woods are very well preserved walks which as well as the house do honour to the judgement of the owner.</s> <s id="s272">We sailed from thence round Trippat holme a bare and small rock to St. Herberts where we examined the plan of the hermitage if indeed it be the same which St. Herbert saw.</s> <s id="s273">This is indeed a charming spot, when we landed the first time our haste did not permit us to walk along one of the most beautiful walks or rather avenues of firs that I ever saw.</s> <s id="s274">It has all the appearance of the' Long Cathedral Isle' and being split by another row of trees near the further end, has much the effect of those Chantries or small chapels so frequent in our religious houses.</s> <s id="s275">The islands wants but little of two furlongs in length, the breadth is not great, but the thick gloom of the wood prevents the narrowness from being observed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s276">We landed near the town at a little past two in the afternoon and found our appetites improved not a little by our excursion.</s> <s id="s277">We remained till the 23rd at <enamex sw="w52283" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> when we returned to <enamex sw="w52311" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s278">We had still two of our party at <enamex sw="w52355" long="-3.27658381338002" lat="54.54100201454608" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33661" name="Buttermere" conf="2.6">Buttermere</enamex> whom we expected soon to join us at <enamex sw="w52402" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s279">On the twenty 6th we set out for <enamex sw="w52446" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="4.593870132">Kendal</enamex> we passed through <enamex sw="w52471" long="-2.96358681023542" lat="54.4319364520582" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11061737" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> and <enamex sw="w52485" long="-2.977323760699877" lat="54.42251395329949" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33323" name="Clappersgate" conf="2.6">Clappersgate</enamex> along the edge of <enamex sw="w52516" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> to the ferry.</s> <s id="s280">Mr Curwen has planted a border of flowering shrubs along the side of the lake for some way.</s> <s id="s281">I am afraid it will not have a good effect when they are large enough to be distinguished from the wild bushes which surround them.</s> <s id="s282">The border may be a mile or two in length, and scarcely more than ten yards in breadth so that it will have the appearance of a ribband and of various colours, produced by the Liburnum the rose and other flowering shrubs.</s></p>
<p><s id="s283">From the <enamex sw="w52996" long="-126.4119491577148" lat="52.4123592376709" type="water" gazref="unlock:14128088" name="Bella Coola River" conf="0.7507343928">Bella</enamex> Grange side, is by far the best view of the islands of which there are so many as almost divide the lake.</s> <s id="s284">Under the trees which overhang the ferry house we sat down to admire the view for some time.</s> <s id="s285">Two boats deck's in the gayest colours were just gliding gently towards the great island they had each two or three sailors on board in red jackets, and the sun shone on the whole scene in the manner that made me for the time prefer <enamex sw="w53434" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> to <enamex sw="w53448" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex> or <enamex sw="w53462" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s286">Mr. Curwen is said to take great pleasure in his little navy.</s> <s id="s287">I sincerely wish Mr. Pocklington had been more attached to the amusement of sailing, than that of building, indeed the defficiency of sailing boats on the lakes can not fail to strike ever observed to a painter there must be great and striking defect in point of picturesque beauty.</s> <s id="s288"><enamex sw="w53816" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> certainly owes much to Mr. Curwen in this respect and I believe the want of sailing vessels on the other lakes proceeds more from ignorance than the gusts and whirlwinds that come from the mountains.</s> <s id="s289">An island on the right hand as we crossed the ferry is called <enamex sw="w54089" long="-2.9353" lat="54.3487" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD393952" name="Berkshire Island" conf="99992">Berkshire island</enamex>, and belongs to the Countess of <enamex sw="w54138" long="-1.487993728867082" lat="51.21030018478477" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11097" name="Andover" conf="1.847494107">Andover</enamex>.</s> <s id="s290">Rawlingsons nab projects far into the water and from its crown is said to be the finest prospect of the lake.</s></p>
<p><s id="s291">On the left is the great island.</s> <s id="s292">Several vessels were anchored along the shore and they added much to the lively appearance of this beautiful and extensive lake.</s> <s id="s293">We arrived at <enamex sw="w54433" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="4.593870132">Kendal</enamex> about six in the evening, and saw there a miserable museum a most wretched imitation of Crossthwaites.</s> <s id="s294">We ascended to the castle once the residence of the Lancasters Barons of <enamex sw="w54616" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="4.593870132">Kendal</enamex> one of the first families in the country and connected with the Atons Vesu Taillebois and Tysons of <enamex sw="w54723" long="-1.707742202359181" lat="55.41504917197148" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11061307" name="Alnwick" conf="1.352477689">Alnwick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s295">Nothing more than a small part of the shell remains.</s> <s id="s296">The town is neat, in the Church are monuments of the <enamex sw="w54838" long="-75.3396279" lat="41.1034234" type="other" gazref="unlock:7954812" name="Stricklands Wissasset Golf Course" conf="0.6346794834">Stricklands</enamex> of <enamex sw="w54853" long="-2.775715663908865" lat="54.28048529968509" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11284405" name="Sizergh Castle" conf="2.2">Sizergh</enamex>; Parrs of <enamex sw="w54871" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="4.593870132">Kendal</enamex> and Bellinghams.</s> <s id="s297">In the morning of the 27th we set off for Milnthrop passing in our way the hall at <enamex sw="w54978" long="-2.775715663908865" lat="54.28048529968509" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11284405" name="Sizergh Castle" conf="2.2">Sizergh</enamex>, not long since a venerable mansion, now in conformity to the custom of the country daubed with whitewash or plaister, so as to have lost much of its former respectable appearance.</s> <s id="s298">There is a tower here, built in the time of Henry the 3rd or Edward the first by William <enamex sw="w55256" long="-2.67414" lat="54.56738" type="other" gazref="unlock:4568635" name="Little Strickland" conf="2">Strickland</enamex> Knight, who married Elizabeth the heiress of Ralph Lord Deincourt about that time.</s> <s id="s299">This I cannot say I particularly observed as we had not time to see the house.</s> <s id="s300">There are several specimens of oak carving in the hosue as we heard, they were executed under the direction of Walker <enamex sw="w55547" long="-2.67414" lat="54.56738" type="other" gazref="unlock:4568635" name="Little Strickland" conf="2">Strickland</enamex> in the time of Elizabeth or James the first.</s> <s id="s301">We soon after arrived at <enamex sw="w55628" long="-2.790902633561496" lat="54.27139808395574" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11194363" name="Levens" conf="2.6">Levens</enamex>, the ancient and respectable seat of the <enamex sw="w55676" long="-2.790902633561496" lat="54.27139808395574" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11194363" name="Levens" conf="2.6">Levens</enamex> family, from whom this place descended to the <enamex sw="w55729" long="-79.59963669299999" lat="45.15010006" type="other" gazref="unlock:5355971" name="Redman Island" conf="0.8166639876">Redman</enamex>'s from them to the Bellinghams and afterwards to the Graham's.</s> <s id="s302">An heiress of Graham brought this seat to the Suffolk family and the countess of <enamex sw="w55880" long="-1.487993728867082" lat="51.21030018478477" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11097" name="Andover" conf="1.847494107">Andover</enamex> is the present possessor.</s> <s id="s303">We entered in front.</s> <s id="s304">An old hall floored with black oak presented itself, the wainscoat reached about two thirds of the height, above were the arms of Bellingham quartered with another coat all round the room.</s> <s id="s305">The ceiling was covered with plaister mouldings, over the chimney place hung two or three frames containing the genealogy of the family, in another frame I observed a copy of the <enamex sw="w56303" long="0.263708913875448" lat="52.40358557406236" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:9621" name="Ely" conf="1.484726236">Ely</enamex> roll which was drawn in the time of the conqueror.</s> <s id="s306">Under the staircase is a place used as a chapel, above are many lodging rooms.</s> <s id="s307">In one is a handsome state bed at least it has formerly been so.</s> <s id="s308">From the hall a few steps on the left hand conduct you to an handsome apartment, in the windows of which are the arms of the Bellinghams and their matches are painted.</s> <s id="s309">In this room are some of the oak carvings, mentioned by West, as placed here by James Bellingham to imitate the taste of his neighbour Walter <enamex sw="w56812" long="-2.67414" lat="54.56738" type="other" gazref="unlock:4568635" name="Little Strickland" conf="2">Strickland</enamex> of <enamex sw="w56826" long="-2.775715663908865" lat="54.28048529968509" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11284405" name="Sizergh Castle" conf="2.2">Sizergh</enamex>, but if the carvings at <enamex sw="w56858" long="-2.775715663908865" lat="54.28048529968509" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11284405" name="Sizergh Castle" conf="2.2">Sizergh</enamex>, be neither <enamex sw="w56878" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="1.044099103">superior</enamex>, or in greater profusion than here, this is only another instance of the fallacy or Mr. Wests eyesight, who must have possessed a peculiar faculty of magnifying and multiplying whatever came in his way.</s> <s id="s310">The <enamex sw="w57094" long="-2.840631506280864" lat="54.45083129470693" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270576" name="River Kent" conf="2.4">River Kent</enamex> runs through <enamex sw="w57118" long="-81.47375" lat="28.58473" type="other" gazref="unlock:10792570" name="The Groves Mobile Home Park" conf="0.6829029094">the park</enamex> where it falls near twenty feet.</s> <s id="s311">There is much fine timber on the estate and nothing is spoiled by any modern alteration, except the house which is whitewashed all over on the outside.</s> <s id="s312">The garden preserves the same form as it received from a gardener of King James the firsts, who says West, eresided here with the colonel Graham during part of the troubles of his royal master,' Its peculiarity consists in clipped yew trees or cypresses, which distinguish the terraces and gardens of that time, it is laid out in small formal beds bordered with box; the walks are of turf.</s> <s id="s313">We dined at Milnthrop seven miles from <enamex sw="w57741" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="4.593870132">Kendal</enamex> and after dinner went to enquire for the captain of a vessel to whom we had been recommended by a Gentleman of <enamex sw="w57859" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="4.593870132">Kendal</enamex>.</s> <s id="s314">We found him at work in his hay field and he informed us that he meant to sail on the 29th to <enamex sw="w57961" long="-2.878238320350647" lat="53.5225887298584" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131229" name="Liverpool" conf="2.421976433">Liverpool</enamex>.</s> <s id="s315">We returned to Milnthrop to procure provisions, and settle with our Landlady there, and the next morning returned to Mr. Cartwright our captain at whose house we remained till our embarcation.</s> <s id="s316">A very short distance from the house upon the hill that rises gently from the sands is one of the most curious rocks I ever saw and indeed perhaps the only one of the kind.</s> <s id="s317">A large flat surface of rock about an hundred yards each way is intersected with cracks and fissures some of which are three or four yards deep exactly in the stile of clay where after having been wet it is dried by the heat of the sun.</s> <s id="s318">Some little puddles of clay which we found on the rock gave us an opportunity of observing how exactly similar the cracks were in each, the only difference was in size, and softness for the colour is exactly the same.</s> <s id="s319">I believe the fuellists and antifuellists as they are called or in other words, those who refer to the influence of fire, the present appearance of the earth and those who ascribe everything to the universal deluge would find here reason to assent in some degree to the opinions of each other.</s> <s id="s320">We slept at our captains house and were as much pleased with the treatment we experienced, as we were with the modesty of the charge, which was only five shillings for two nights and a day between us both.</s> <s id="s321">Two of our companions were gone to a small village nearer to the vessel.</s> <s id="s322">We went on board about half past ten, after having walked six miles over the wet sand and waded through two rivers, one of which was very rapid.</s> <s id="s323">At about half past four we weighed anchor but we had not been under sail ten minutes before we had the misfortune to hear that we were on a sand bank, and must remain there till about half past two in the next morning in the same situation.</s></p>
<p><s id="s324">We set sail on the return of the tide, the wind was not in our favour, yet not so much against us, as to oblige us to tack, about five in the morning we saw <enamex sw="w59909" long="-4.692535773887674" lat="54.22593372544603" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11241717" name="Peel Castle" conf="0.7830473273">Peel Castle</enamex>, to the right, and the isle of Walney a low flat island, about nine miles in length and not one in breadth.</s> <s id="s325">On the left were two towers of <enamex sw="w60060" long="-2.850475328879767" lat="54.18110576201394" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11141939" name="Far Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex>, and Haslop which as the vulgar believe were built by some great man, together with <enamex sw="w60152" long="0.5192567451091836" lat="52.2248726468138" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:21402" name="Dalham" conf="1.388941766">Dalham</enamex> tower for the residence of his three daughters and coheirs.</s> <s id="s326">The two first in ruins the last inhabited, and entirely rebuilt by a gentleman of the name of Wilson who resides at the tower, within quarter of a mile from Milnthrop.</s> <s id="s327">Not long after we saw <enamex sw="w60409" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> and a miserable flat coast which stretches from thence to <enamex sw="w60477" long="-2.878238320350647" lat="53.5225887298584" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131229" name="Liverpool" conf="2.421976433">Liverpool</enamex> on which is situated <enamex sw="w60508" long="-3.014836311340332" lat="53.83804321289062" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127451" name="Blackpool" conf="2.229733814">Blackpool</enamex>, a place of late much frequented by inhabitants of both towns, as a summer residence.</s> <s id="s328">There is not a single tree near it nor indeed could I perceive one the whole voyage.</s> <s id="s329">About half past two we began to approach <enamex sw="w60730" long="-2.878238320350647" lat="53.5225887298584" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131229" name="Liverpool" conf="2.421976433">Liverpool</enamex> and the tide favouring us we soon arrived at the powder magazine, after we had passed <enamex sw="w60826" long="-2.665056498919776" lat="55.03613233380358" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11072261" name="Beacon, The" conf="1.259895867">the beacon</enamex>.</s> <s id="s330">Here we left our vessel as the Captain was obliged to unload about twenty tonnes of Gunpowder which had been conveyed through a most terrible storm of thunder and lightening all the way from Milnthrop.</s> <s id="s331">The boat landed us at the docks about three miles higher up and on the other side of the river.</s> <s id="s332">We slept at <enamex sw="w61148" long="-2.878238320350647" lat="53.5225887298584" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131229" name="Liverpool" conf="2.421976433">Liverpool</enamex> and in the morning after seeing as much of the town as our time would permit took a passage in the Chester packet for <enamex sw="w61276" long="-2.953511427822022" lat="53.3263358026481" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11137323" name="Eastham Ferry" conf="1.571960876">Eastham</enamex> about seven miles from the <enamex sw="w61311" long="-2.203157052545625" lat="53.41986943988749" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11169238" name="Heaton Mersey" conf="1.534084104">Mersey</enamex>.</s> <s id="s333">The morning was fine a brisk wind sprung up and in about three quarters of an hour we reached the spot where we were to meet the coach which conveyed us to <enamex sw="w61475" long="-2.896921400934089" lat="53.19645216619189" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:9697" name="Chester" conf="2.169065618">Chester</enamex>.</s></p>
</text>
</document>