<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1870_a"><p><s id="s1">July 6th Friday</s> </p><p><s id="s2">The day after my arrival, the door of the Consulate opened, and in came the very sociable personage who had accosted me at the Railway Station, in <enamex sw="w175" long="-1.344933185389088" lat="52.30486014843851" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25552" name="Leamington Hastings" conf="1.930610553">Leamington</enamex>.</s> <s id="s3">He was on his way to <enamex sw="w208" long="-3.284768104553223" lat="55.9251537322998" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131223" name="Edinburgh" conf="2.164809623">Edinburgh</enamex>, to deliver a lecture, or a course of lectures, and had called, he said, to talk with me about spiritualism, being[ 17] desirous of having the judgement of a sincere mind on the subject.</s> <s id="s4">In his own mind, I should suppose, he is past the stage of doubt and enquiry; for he told me that, in every section of his life, he is governed by the councels received from the spiritual world, through a medium.</s> <s id="s5">I did not inquire whether the medium has suggested his visit to me.</s> <s id="s6">The medium is a small boy.</s> <s id="s7">My remarks to him were quite of a sceptical character, in regard to the faith to which he has surrendered himself.</s> <s id="s8">It seems he has lived in <enamex  sw="w853" name="Large admin unit">America</enamex>, in times past, and had a son born there.</s> <s id="s9">He gave me a pamphlet written by himself, on the cure of consumption and other diseases by antiseptic remedies.</s> <s id="s10">The author's name is Dr. Washington Evans.</s> <s id="s11">I hope he will not bore me any more, though he seems to be a very sincere and good man; but these enthusiasts, who adopt such extravagant ideas, appear to me to lack imagination, instead of being misled by it, as they are generally supposed to be.</s></p>
<p><s id="s12">July 8th, Sunday</s> </p><p><s id="s13">At the consulate, yesterday, a queer, stupid, good-natured, fat-faced individual came in, dressed in a sky blue, coarse, cut-away coat, and mixed pantaloons, which( both coat and trousers) seemed rather too small for his goodly size.</s> <s id="s14">He turned out to be the Yankee who came to <enamex  sw="w1600" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, a few weeks ago, to see the Queen, on the strength[ 18] of having sent her his own and his wife's daguerreotype, and having received a note of thanks from her secretary.</s> <s id="s15">Having been swindled by a fellow-passenger, he has loafed about here ever since his arrival, unable to get home - and, indeed, unwilling, until he shall have gone to <enamex sw="w1945" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.652744851">London</enamex> to see the Queen; and, to support himself, he has parted with all the clothes he brought with him, and thrusts himself into the narrow limits of this sky-blue coat and mixed pantaloons.</s> <s id="s16">It is certainly a very odd-looking court-dress; and he hinted, with a melancholy, stupid smile, that he did not look quite fit to see the Queen now.</s> <s id="s17">Of course, he wanted my assistance; but it is marvellous, the pertinacity with which he clings to his idea of going to court, and, though starving, will not think of endeavoring to get home, till that has been effected.</s> <s id="s18">I laid his absurdity before him, in the plainest terms.</s> <s id="s19">" My dear man!" quoth he, with good-natured, simple stubbornness," if you could but enter into my feelings, and see the business from beginning to end, as I see it!" And this he repeated over and over again.</s> <s id="s20">He wished me, if I would not help him myself, to give him the names of some American merchants, to whom he might apply for means to get to <enamex sw="w2909" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.652744851">London</enamex>; but I refused to interfere with his affairs in any way, unless he promised to go back immediately to the <enamex  sw="w3022" name="Large admin unit">United States</enamex>, in case I could get him a passage.</s> <s id="s21">Besides his desire[ 19] to see the Queen, he has likewise( like so many of his countrymen) a fantasy that he is one of the legal heirs of a great English inheritance.</s> <s id="s22">No doubt, this dream about the Queen and his English estate has haunted his poor, foolish mind for years and years; and he deems it the strangest and mournfullest perversity of fate, and awfullest cruelty in me, that now - when he has reached <enamex  sw="w3482" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, and has wealth and royal honors almost within his grasp - he must turn back, a poor, penniless, be-fooled simpleton, merely because I will not lend him thirty shillings to get to <enamex sw="w3670" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.652744851">London</enamex>.</s> <s id="s23">I had never such a perception of a complete booby before, in my life; it made me feel kindly towards him, and yet impatient that such a fool should exist.</s> <s id="s24">Finally( as he had not a penny in his pocket, and no means of getting anything to eat) I gave him a couple of shillings, and told him not to let me see him again, till he had made up his mind to get back to <enamex  sw="w4040" name="Large admin unit">America</enamex> - when I would beg a passage for him if I could.</s> <s id="s25">He thanked me, and went away, half crying, and yet with something like a dull, good-natured smile on his face; still fixed in his inveterate purpose of getting to <enamex sw="w4260" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.652744851">London</enamex> to see the Queen!</s></p>
<p><s id="s26">July 13th( Friday) <enamex sw="w4304" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex></s> </p><p><s id="s27">I left <enamex sw="w4324" long="-2.878238320350647" lat="53.5225887298584" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131229" name="Liverpool" conf="2.278480581">Liverpool</enamex> at ½ past 1 on Saturday last, by the <enamex sw="w4371" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.652744851">London</enamex> and Northwestern railway, for <enamex sw="w4408" long="-1.344933185389088" lat="52.30486014843851" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25552" name="Leamington Hastings" conf="1.930610553">Leamington</enamex>, arrived between 8&amp; 9, P.M.; spent Sunday there, and started at[ 20] about 12 ½ on Monday, for the English lakes, taking the whole family.</s> <s id="s28">We should not have[ taken] this journey, just now; but I had an official engagement, which it was convenient to combine with a pleasure excursion.</s> <s id="s29">The first night, we arrived at <enamex sw="w4737" long="-2.890650344182352" lat="53.19196958316057" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11104567" name="Chester" conf="2.002960116">Chester</enamex>, and put up at the Albion Hotel, where we found ourselves very comfortable.</s> <s id="s30">We took the rail at twelve, next day, and went as far as <enamex sw="w4878" long="-2.749144049" lat="54.22850002" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00190" name="Milnthorpe Station" conf="99992">Milnthorpe station</enamex>, where at five or six o clock we took seats in an old-fashioned English stage-coach, and came to <enamex sw="w4994" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>.</s> <s id="s31">I suppose there are not many of those machines now running on any road in <enamex  sw="w5082" name="Large admin unit">Great Britain</enamex>; but this appears to be the genuine article in all respects, and especially in the round, ruddy coachman, well-moistened with ale, good-natured, courteous, with a proper sense of his dignity and important position.</s> <s id="s32">Una, Julian, and I, mounted on top; Mamma, Nurse, and Rosebud, got inside; and we bowled off merrily up towards the hearts of the hills.</s> <s id="s33">It was more than half - past nine when we arrived at <enamex sw="w5499" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, and alighted at the <enamex sw="w5533" long="-3.0201" lat="54.4655" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828775" name="Macdonald Swan Hotel" conf="2">Swan Hotel</enamex>, where we still are.</s></p>
<p><s id="s34">It is a very agreeable place; not striking as to scenery, but with a pleasant, rural aspect.</s> <s id="s35">A stone bridge, of five arches, crosses the River <enamex sw="w5708" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex>( which is the communication between <enamex sw="w5750" long="-2.93438" lat="54.37296" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_SD402977" name="Winderemere (Lake)" conf="99991">Windermere lake</enamex> and <enamex sw="w5770" long="-2.971573845828191" lat="54.11726758179064" type="water" gazref="unlock:11222778" name="Morecambe Bay" conf="2.377776979">Morecambe bay</enamex>) close to the house, which sits low and well-sheltered in the lap of the hills - an old-fashioned inn, where the landlord and his people have a simple and friendly way of dealing with[ 21] their guests, and yet provide them with all sorts of facilities for being comfortable.</s> <s id="s36">They load our supper and breakfast tables with trout, cold beef, ham, toast muffins, et cetera; and give us three fine courses for dinner, and excellent wine - the cost of which remains to be seen.</s> <s id="s37">This is not one of the celebrated stations among the lakes; but twice a day a stage coach passes from <enamex sw="w6360" long="-2.774704304134491" lat="54.22656024374862" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11220135" name="Milnthorpe" conf="2.553106967">Milnthorpe</enamex> towards <enamex sw="w6379" long="-3.065434914086523" lat="54.19737398966196" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11287996" name="South Ulverston" conf="2.6">Ulverston</enamex>, and twice returns; and three times a little steamer passes to-and-fro between our hotel and the head of the lake.</s> <s id="s38">Yong ladies in broad-brimmed hats stroll about, or row on the river, in the light shallops of which there are abundance; - sportsmen sit on the benches under the windows of the hotel, arranging their fishing-tackle; - phaetons and post chaises,( with postillions in scarlet jackets and white breeches, with one white-topt boot, and the other leathered high in the leg, to guard against friction between the horses) dash up to the door; - morning and night comes the stage-coach, and we inspect the outside passengers, almost face to face with us, from our parlor window, up one pair of stairs; - little boys( and Julian among them) spend hours on hours, fishing in the clear, shallow river, for the perch, chubs and minnows that may be seen flashing, like gleams of light, over the flat stones with which the bottom is paved.</s> <s id="s39">I cannot answer for the other boys; but Julian catches nothing.</s></p>
<p><s id="s40">[ 22] There are a good many trees on the hills and roundabout; and pleasant roads loitering along by the gentle river-side; and it has been so sunny and warm, since we came here, that we shall have quite a genial recollection of the place, if we leave it before the skies have time to frown.</s> <s id="s41">The day after we came, Mamma, with Una, Julian, and myself, climbed a pretty high, and very steep hill, through a path shadowed with trees and shrubbery, up to a tower, from the summit of which we had a wide view of mountain scenery, and the greater part of <enamex sw="w7943" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s42">This lake is a lovely little pool among the hills, long and narrow, beautifully indented with tiny bays and headlands; and when we saw it, it was one smile( as broad a smile as its narrowness allowed) with really brilliant sunshine.</s> <s id="s43">All the scenery we have yet met with is in excellent taste, and keeps itself within very proper bounds - never getting too wild and ragged to shock the sensibilities of cultivated people, as American scenery is apt to do.</s> <s id="s44">On the rudest surfaces of English earth, there is seen the effect of centuries of civilization; so that you do not quite get at naked Nature anywhere.</s> <s id="s45">And then every point of beauty is so well known, and has been described so much, that one must need look through other people's eyes, and feels as if he were looking at a picture rather than a reality.</s> <s id="s46">Man has, in[ 23] short, got entire possession of Nature here; and I think young men might sometimes yearn for a fresher draught.</s> <s id="s47">But an American likes it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s48">Yesterday, we took a phaeton and went to <enamex sw="w8959" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.2">Furness Abbey</enamex> - a ride of about sixteen miles, passing along the course of the <enamex sw="w9038" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex>, to <enamex sw="w9048" long="-2.971573845828191" lat="54.11726758179064" type="water" gazref="unlock:11222778" name="Morecambe Bay" conf="2.377776979">Morecambe bay</enamex>, and through <enamex sw="w9075" long="-3.065434914086523" lat="54.19737398966196" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11287996" name="South Ulverston" conf="2.6">Ulverston</enamex>, and other villages.</s> <s id="s49">These villages all look antique; and the smallest of them generally are formed of such close, contiguous clusters of houses, and have such narrow and crooked streets, that they give you the idea of a metropolis in miniature.</s> <s id="s50">The houses along the road( of which there are not many, except in the villages) are almost invariably old, built of stone, and covered with a light gray plaister[ sic]; generally, they have a little flower garden in front, and, often, honeysuckle, roses, or some other sweet and pretty rustic adornment, is flowering over the porch.</s> <s id="s51">I have hardly had such images of simple, quiet, rustic comfort and beauty, as from the look of these houses; and the whole impression of our winding and undulating road, bordered by hedges, luxuriantly green, and not too closely clipt, accords with this aspect.</s> <s id="s52">There is nothing arid in an English landscape; and one cannot but fancy that the same may be true of English rural[ 24] life.</s> <s id="s53">The people look wholesome and well-to-do - not specimens of hard, dry, sunburnt muscle, like our yeoman - and are kind and civil to strangers, sometimes making a little inclination of the head in passing.</s> <s id="s54">Miss <enamex  sw="w10264" name="Not a placename">Martineau</enamex>, however, does not seem to think well of their mental and moral condition.</s></p>
<p><s id="s55">We reached <enamex sw="w10360" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.2">Furness Abbey</enamex> about 12.</s> <s id="s56">There is a railway-station close by the ruins; and a new hotel stands within the precincts of the Abbey Grounds; and continually there is the shriek, the whiz, the rumble, the bell-ringing, denoting the arrival of the trains, and passengers alight and step at once( as their choice may be) into the refreshment-room to get a glass of ale or cigar, or upon the gravelled paths of <enamex sw="w10763" long="0.6777245875646798" lat="51.58230995227674" type="other" gazref="unlock:11192575" name="Lawn, The" conf="0.9492366003">the lawn</enamex>, leading to the old broken walls and arches of the Abbey.</s> <s id="s57">The ruins are extensive, and the closure of the Abbey is stated to have covered a space of sixty - five acres.</s> <s id="s58">It is impossible to describe them.</s> <s id="s59">The most interesting part is that which was formerly the church, and which, though now roofless, is still surrounded by walls, and has the remnants of the pillars that formerly supported the intermingling curves of the arches.</s> <s id="s60">The floor is all overgrown with grass, strewn with fragments and capitals of pillars.</s> <s id="s61">It was a great and stately edifice, the length and the nave and choir having been nearly three hundred feet,[ 25] and that of the transept more than half as much.</s> <s id="s62">The pillars along the nave were alternately a round, solid one, and a clustered one; now, what remains of some of them is even with the ground; others present a stump just high enough to form a seat, and others are perhaps a man's height from the ground - and all are mossy and with grass and weeds rooted in their chinks, and here and there a tuft of flowers is giving its tender little beauty to their decay.</s> <s id="s63">The material of the edifice is a soft, red stone; and it is now extensively overgrown with a lichen, of a very light gray hue, which at a little distance makes the walls look as if they had long ago been white-washed, and now had partially returned to their original color.</s> <s id="s64">I never saw anything like the immense, the noble arches of the nave and transept; there were four of them together, supporting a tower which has long since disappeared - arches loftier than I ever conceived to have been made by man.</s> <s id="s65">Very possibly, in some cathedral that I have see, or am yet to see, there may be arches as stately as these; but I doubt whether they can ever show to such advantage in a perfect edifice as they do in this ruin - most of them broken - only one, as far as I recollect, still completing its sweep.</s> <s id="s66">In this state, they[ 26] suggest a greater majesty and beauty than any human work can show - the crumbling traces of the half obliterated design producing somewhat of the effect of the first idea of anything admirable, when it dawns upon the mind of an artist or a poet - an idea which, do what he may, he is sure to fall short of.</s></p>
<p><s id="s67">In the middle of the choir is a much dilapidated monument of a cross-legged knight( a crusader, of course) in armor, very rudely executed; and up against the wall lie two or three more bruised and battered warriors, with square helmets on their heads, and visors down.</s> <s id="s68">Nothing can be uglier than these figures; the sculpture of those days seems to have been far behind the architecture.</s> <s id="s69">And yet they knew how to put a grotesque expression into the faces of their images, and we saw some fantastic shapes and heads at the lower points of arches, which would do to copy into Punch.</s> <s id="s70">In the chancel, just at the point below where the high altar stood, was the burial-place of the old barons of <enamex sw="w13686" long="-2.745809060481465" lat="54.32561646560368" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185036" name="Kendal" conf="3.034754691">Kendal</enamex>.</s> <s id="s71">The broken crusader perhaps represents one of them; and some of their stalwart bones might be found, by digging down.</s> <s id="s72">Against the wall of the choir, near the vacant space where the altar was, are some stone seats with canopies richly carved in stone, all quite perfectly preserved; these were where the priest used to sit[ 27] at intervals, during the celebration of mass.</s> <s id="s73">Conceive all these shattered walls, with here and there an arched door, or the great arched vacancy of a window - these broken stones and monuments scattered about - these rows of pillars up and down the nave - these arches, through which a giant might have stept, and not needed to bow his head, unless in reverence to the sanctity of the place - conceive it all with such verdure, and embroidery of flowers, as the gentle, kindly moisture of the English climate procreates on all good things, making them more beautiful old than new - conceive it with the grass for sole pavement of the long and spacious aisle, and the sky above for the only roof.</s> <s id="s74">The sky, to be sure, is more majestic than the tallest of those arches; and yet these latter perhaps make the stronger impression of sublimity, because they translate the sweep of the sky to our finite comprehensions.</s> <s id="s75">It was a most beautiful, warm, sunny day; and the ruins had all the pictoral advantage of bright light and deep shadows.</s> <s id="s76">I must not forget that birds flew in and out of the recesses, and chirped and warbled, and made themselves a home there.</s> <s id="s77">Doubtless, the birds of the present generation are the posterity of those who first settled in the ruins, after the[ 28] Reformation, and perhaps the old monks of a still earlier day may have watched them building about the Abbey, before it was a ruin at all.</s></p>
<p><s id="s78">We had an old description of the Abbey with us, aided by which we traced out the principal parts of the edifice; such as the church, as already mentioned, and contiguous to this the Chapter House, which is better preserved than the church; - also the kitchen, and the room where the monks met to talk, and the range of wall where their cells probably where.</s> <s id="s79">I never before had given myself the trouble to form any distinct idea of what an abbey or monastery was - a place where holy rites were daily and continually to be performed, with places to eat and sleep contiguous and convenient, in order that the monks might always be at hand to perform those rites.</s> <s id="s80">They lived only to worship, and therefore lived under the same contiguity of roof with their place of worship, which, of course, was the principle object in the edifice, and hallowed the whole of it.</s> <s id="s81">We found, too, at one end of the ruins, what is supposed to have been a school-house for the children of the tenantry or villains of the Abbey; all round this room is a bench of stone against the wall, and the pedestal also of the master's seat.</s> <s id="s82">There are likewise the ruins of the mill; and the[ 29] mill-stream, which is just as new as ever it was, still goes murmuring and babbling past the abbey, and passes under two or three old bridges, consisting of a low, gray arch, overgrown with grass and shrubbery.</s> <s id="s83">That stream was the most fleeting and vanishing thing about the ponderous and high-piled Abbey; and yet it has outlasted everything else, and might still outlast another such edifice, and be none the worse for wear.</s></p>
<p><s id="s84">There is not a great deal of ivy upon the walls; and though an ivied wall is a beautiful object, yet it is better not to have too much - else it is but one wall of unbroken verdure, on which you can see none of the sculptured ornaments, nor any of the hieroglyphics of time.</s> <s id="s85">A sweep of ivy here and there, with the gray wall everywhere showing through, makes the better picture; and I think that nothing is so effective as the little bunches of flowers, a mere handful, that grow in spots where their seeds have been carried by the wind, ages ago.</s></p>
<p><s id="s86">I have made a miserable botch of this description; it is no description, but merely an attempt to preserve something of the impression it made on me - and in this I do not seem to have succeeded at all.</s> <s id="s87">I liked the contrast between the sombreness of the walls, and the[ 30] sunshine falling through them and gladdening the grass that floored the aisles; also, I liked the effect of so many idle and cheerful people, strolling into the haunts of the dead monks, and going babbling about and peering into the dark nooks; and listening to catch some idea of what the building was, from a clerical-looking personage who was explaining it to a party of his friends.</s> <s id="s88">I do n't know how well acquainted this gentleman might be with the subject; but he seemed anxious not to impart his knowledge too extensively, and gave a pretty direct rebuff to an honest man who ventured an enquiry of him.</s> <s id="s89">In short, I think that the railway, and the hotel within the abbey-grounds, add to the charm of the place.</s> <s id="s90">A moonlight, solitary visit might be very good, too, in its way; but I believe that one great charm and beauty of antiquity is, that we view it out of the midst of quite another mode of life; - and the more perfectly this can be done, the better.</s> <s id="s91">It can never be done more perfectly than at <enamex sw="w18857" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.2">Furness Abbey</enamex>, which is in itself a very sombre scene, and stands, moreover, in the midst of a melancholy valley, the Saxon name of which mean the Vale of Deadly Night Shade.</s></p>
<p><s id="s92">The entrance to the stable-yard of the hotel is[ 31] beneath an old pointed arch, of Saxon architecture; and on one side of this stands a little old building looking like a chapel, but which may, for aught I know, have been a porter's lodge.</s> <s id="s93">The abbot's residence was in this quarter; and the clerical personage before alluded to spoke of these as the oldest part of the ruins.</s></p>
<p><s id="s94">About half a mile on the hither side of the Abbey stands the village of <enamex sw="w19482" long="-3.177980552513582" lat="54.15480048261493" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11514" name="Dalton-In-Furness" conf="2.6">Dalton</enamex>, in which is a castle built on a Roman foundation, and which was afterwards used by the <enamex sw="w19577" long="-0.4152977401859335" lat="51.70108732572091" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11055259" name="Abbots Langley" conf="1.470122307">Abbots</enamex>( in their capacity as feudal lords) as a prison.</s> <s id="s95"><enamex sw="w19633" long="-3.21196" lat="54.13169" type="other" gazref="unlock:5827283" name="Abbey Park Hospital The" conf="2">The Abbey</enamex> was founded about 1127, by King Stephen, before he came to the throne; and the faces of himself and his queen are still to be seen on one of the walls.</s> <s id="s96">I know not whose property it is now.</s></p>
<p><s id="s97">We had a very agreeable ride home( our ride thither had been uncomfortably sunny and hot) and stopt at <enamex sw="w19935" long="-3.065434914086523" lat="54.19737398966196" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11287996" name="South Ulverston" conf="2.6">Ulverston</enamex> to buy a pair of shoes for Julian, and some drawing-books and stationery.</s> <s id="s98">As we passed through this little town in the morning, it was all alive with the throng and bustle of the weekly market; and though this had ceased, on our return, the streets still looked animated, because the heat of the day drew most of the population, I should imagine, out of doors.</s> <s id="s99">Old men look very antiqua32ted here, in their old fashioned coats and breeches, sunning themselves by the wayside.</s> <s id="s100">We reached home somewhere about eight o sup &gt; clock - home I see I have called it; and it seems as homelike a spot as any we have found in <enamex  sw="w20558" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, the old inn, close by the bridge, beside the clear river, pleasantly overshadowed by trees.</s> <s id="s101">It is entirely English, and like nothing that one sees in <enamex  sw="w20717" name="Large admin unit">America</enamex>; and yet I feel as if I might have lived here a long while ago, and had now come back because I retained pleasant recollections of it.</s> <s id="s102">The children, too, make themselves at home.</s> <s id="s103">Julian spends his time from morning till night, fishing for minnows or trout, and catching nothing at all; and Una and Rosebud have been riding between field and barn, in a hay-cart.</s> <s id="s104">The roads give us beautiful walks along the river-side, or wind away among the gentle hills; and if we had nothing else to look at in these walks, the hedges and stone fences would afford interest enough - so many and pretty are the flowers, roses, honey-suckle, and other sweet things, and so abundantly does the moss and ivy grow among the old stones of the fences, which would never have a single shoot of vegetation on them, in <enamex  sw="w21519" name="Large admin unit">America</enamex>, till the very end of time.</s> <s id="s105">But here, no sooner is a stone fence built, than Nature sets to work to make it a part of herself; she adopts it, and adorns it as if it were her own child.</s> <s id="s106">A little sprig of ivy may be seen creeping up the side, and clinging fast with its many feet;[ 33] a tuft of grass roots itself between two of the stones, where a little dust from the road has been moistened into soil for it; a small bunch of fern grows in another such crevice; a deep, soft, green moss spreads itself over the top and all along the sides of the fence; and wherever nothing else will grow, lichens adhere to the stones and variegate their hues.</s> <s id="s107">Finally, a great deal of shrubbery is sure to cluster along its extent, and take away hall hardness from the outline; and so the whole stone-fence looks as if God had had at least as much to do with it as man.</s> <s id="s108">The trunks of the trees, too, exhibit a similar parasitical vegetation.</s> <s id="s109">Parasitical is an unkind phrase to bestow on this beautiful love and kindred which seems to exist here, between one plant and thing another[ sic]; the strong thing being always ready to give support and sustenance, and the weak thing to repay with beauty, so that both are the richer; - as in the case of ivy and woodbine clustering up the trunk of a tall tree, and adding Corinthian grace to its lofty strength.</s></p>
<p><s id="s110">Mr. White( our landlord) has lent us a splendid work with engravings, illustrating the antiquities of <enamex sw="w22973" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.2">Furness Abbey</enamex>.</s> <s id="s111">I gather from it that the hotel must have been rebuilt or repaired from an old manor house, which was itself built by a family of <enamex sw="w23118" long="0.4797605449134825" lat="51.65861591120929" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159185" name="Great Prestons" conf="0.8867500028">Prestons</enamex>, after the Reformation, and was a renewal from the Abbot's residence.</s> <s id="s112">Much of the edifice, probably, as it exists now, may have[ 34] formed part of the original one; and there are bas-reliefs of scripture-subjects, sculptured in stone, and fixed in the wall of the dining-room, which have been there since the Abbot's time.</s> <s id="s113">This author thinks that what we had supposed to be the school-house( on the authority of an old book) was really the building for the reception of guests, with its chapel.</s> <s id="s114">He says that the tall arches in the church are sixty feet high.</s> <s id="s115">The Earl of Burlington, I believe, is the present proprietor of the Abbey.</s></p>
<p><s id="s116">July 16th( Monday)</s> </p><p><s id="s117">On Saturday, we left <enamex sw="w23802" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, and came by steamboat up <enamex sw="w23841" long="-2.93438" lat="54.37296" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_SD402977" name="Winderemere (Lake)" conf="99991">Windermere lake</enamex> to Lowwood Hotel, where we now are.</s> <s id="s118">The foot of the lake is just above <enamex sw="w23928" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>; and it widens from that point, but never to such a breadth that objects are not pretty distinctly visible from shore.</s> <s id="s119">The little steamer stops at two or three places in the course of its voyage; - the principle being <enamex sw="w24159" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, which has a little bustle and air of business about it, proper to the principle port on the lake.</s> <s id="s120">There were several small yachts on the lake, and many skiffs rowing about.</s> <s id="s121">The banks are everywhere beautiful, and the lake is one portion strewn with little islands, few of which are large enough to be inhabitable, but they all seem to be appropriated and kept in the neatest order.</s> <s id="s122">As yet, I have seen no wildness; everything is perfectly subdued and polished, and imbued with human taste; except, indeed, the outlines of the hills, which continue very much the same as god made them.</s> <s id="s123">As we ap35proached the head of the lake, the congregation of great hills in the distance became very striking.</s> <s id="s124">The shapes of these English mountains are certainly far more picturesque than those which I have seen( as I remember them) in <enamex  sw="w24990" name="Large admin unit">America</enamex>.</s> <s id="s125">There, their summits are almost invariably rounded; they are great hillocks - great bunches of earth, all very similar in their development.</s> <s id="s126">Here, they have great variety of shape, rising into peaks, falling in abrupt precipices stretching along zig-zag in outlines; and thus making the most of their not very gigantic masses to produce a very striking effect.</s></p>
<p><s id="s127">We left <enamex sw="w25368" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, and arrived at the Lowwood Hotel,( which is very near the end of the lake) not long after two o clock.</s> <s id="s128">This house stands almost on the shore of <enamex sw="w25526" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>, with only a green and gravel-walked lawn between; - an extensive hotel, covering a good deal of ground, but low, and rather village-innlike, than lofty with four or five stories, like an American hotel.</s> <s id="s129">We found the house so crowded as to afford us no very comfortable accommodations, either as to parlor or sleeping-rooms; and we find nothing like the home-feeling into which we at once settled down at <enamex sw="w25942" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>.</s> <s id="s130">There is a very pretty vicinity; a fine view of mountains to the north-west, sitting together in a family group, sometimes in full sunshine, sometimes with only a golden gleam in one or two of them, sometimes all in a veil[ 36] of cloud, from which here and there a great dusky head creates itself, while you are looking at a dim obscurity.</s> <s id="s131">Nearer, there are high, green slopes, well-wooded, but with such decent and well-behaved wood as you perceive has grown up under the care of man; still no wildness, no raggedness; - as how should there be, when, every half - mile or so, a porter's lodge, or a gentleman's gateway, indicates that the whole region is used up for villas.</s> <s id="s132">On the opposite shore of the lake, there is a mimic castle( which I suppose I might have mistaken for a real one, two years ago) a great, foolish toy or gray stone.</s></p>
<p><s id="s133">A steamboat comes to the pier as much as six times a day; and stage-coaches and omnibuses[ sic] stop at the door still oftener, communicating with <enamex sw="w26945" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> or the town of <enamex sw="w26970" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>, and with the railway, which opens <enamex sw="w27016" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.652744851">London</enamex> and all the world to us.</s> <s id="s134">We get no knowledge of our fellow guests, all of whom, like ourselves, live in their own circles, and are just as remote from us as if the lake lay between.</s> <s id="s135">The only word I have spoken since arriving here( except to my own family or a waiter) was to one of two young pedestrians, who met me on a walk, and asked me the distance to Lowwood Hotel.</s> <s id="s136">" Just beyond here," said I; and I might stay here for months, no doubt, without occasion to speak again.</s></p>
<p><s id="s137">Yesterday forenoon, Julian and I walked to <enamex sw="w27542" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, distant barely two miles - a little town, chiefly of modern aspect, built on[ 37] a very uneven hillside, and with very irregular streets and lanes, which bewilder the stranger as much as those of a larger city.</s> <s id="s138">Many of the houses, as I remember, look old, and are probably the cottages and farm-houses, which composed the rude hillside village, a century ago; but there are stuccoed shops and dwellings, such as may have been built within a year or two; and three hotels, one of which has the look of the good old village inn, and the others are fashionable or commercial establishments.</s> <s id="s139">Through the midst of the village comes tumbling and rumbling a mountain-streamlet, rushing through a deep, rocky dell, gliding under a stone-arch, and turning( when occasion calls) the great, black wheel of a water-mill.</s> <s id="s140">This is the only very striking feature of the village( and this might very well have escaped my notice) - the stream from the steep hill-side taking its rough pathway to the lake, as it used to do before the poets had made this region fashionable.</s></p>
<p><s id="s141">In the evening, just before eight o clock, I took a walk alone, by a road which goes up the hill back of our hotel, and what I supposed might be the road to the town of <enamex sw="w28780" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s142">But it went up and higher, and, for the mile or two( or two or three) that it led me along, winding up the hillside, I saw no traces of a town; and at last the road turned into what seemed a valley between two high ridges, leading quite away[ 38] from the lake, within view of which the town of <enamex sw="w29087" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> is situated.</s> <s id="s143">It was a very lonely road, though as smooth, hard, and well-kept, as any thoroughfare in the suburbs of a city; hardly a dwelling on either side, except one, half - barn, half farm-house; and one gentleman's gateway near the beginning of the road, and another more than a mile higher up.</s> <s id="s144">At two or three points, there were stone-barns, which are here built with great solidity.</s> <s id="s145">At one place, there was a painted board, announcing that a field of five acres was to be sold, and referring those desirous of purchasing to a solicitor in <enamex sw="w29643" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.652744851">London</enamex>.</s> <s id="s146">The lake-country is but a <enamex sw="w29677" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.652744851">London</enamex> Suburb.</s> <s id="s147">Nevertheless, this walk was lonely and lovely; the copse, and the broad-hillside, the glimpses of the lake, the great, misty company of pikes and fells, beguiled me into a sense of something like solitude; and the bleating of the sheep, remote and near, had a like tendency.</s> <s id="s148">Gaining the summit of the hill, I had the best view of lake <enamex sw="w30027" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> which I have yet obtained; - the best, I should think, that can be had, though, being towards the south, it brings the softer instead of the more striking features of the landscape into view.</s> <s id="s149">But it shows nearly the whole extent of the lake, all the way from Lowwood to just above <enamex sw="w30319" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>; and I think that there can hardly be anything more beautiful in the world.</s> <s id="s150">The water was like a strip and gleam of sky, fitly set among lovely slopes of[ 39] earth.</s> <s id="s151">It was no broader than many a river; and yet you saw at once that it could be no river, its outline being so different from that of a running stream, not straight, nor winding, but stretching to one side or the other, as the shores made room for it; - a thing that could make its own way through the world, but must take what was allowed it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s152">This morning, it is rainy; and we are not very comfortable or contented, being all confined to our little parlor, which has a broken window, against which I have pinned the" Times," to keep out the damp, chill air.</s> <s id="s153">Una has been ill with some kind of humor, resulting from her having been overheated at <enamex sw="w31142" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>.</s> <s id="s154">We have no books( except guide-books) no means of amusement, nothing to do.</s> <s id="s155">There are no newspapers; and I shall remember Lowwood not very agreeably; - as far as we are concerned, it is a scrambling, ill ordered hotel, with insufficient attendance, wretched sleeping accommodations, a pretty fair victualling-department, but German silver forks and spoons.</s> <s id="s156">Nothing that we eat tastes very good; and yet there is no really definite fault to be found.</s></p>
<p><s id="s157">Since writing the above, I have found the first volume( of seven) of Sir Charles Grandison, and two of G. P. R. James's works, in the Coffee Room.</s> <s id="s158">The day pass heavily here, and leave behind them the sense of having answered no very good purpose.</s> <s id="s159">They are long[ 40] enough, at all events; for the sun does not set till after eight o clock, and rises I know not when.</s> <s id="s160">One of the most remarkable distinctions between <enamex  sw="w32021" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> and the <enamex  sw="w32037" name="Large admin unit">United States</enamex> is, the ignorance into which we fall of whatever is going on in the world, the moment we get away from the great thoroughfares and centres of life.</s> <s id="s161">In <enamex sw="w32202" long="-1.344933185389088" lat="52.30486014843851" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25552" name="Leamington Hastings" conf="1.930610553">Leamington</enamex>, we heard no news from week's to week's end, and knew not where to find a newspaper; and here, the case is neither better nor worse.</s> <s id="s162">The rural people really seem to take no interest in public affairs; at all events, they have no intelligence on such subjects.</s> <s id="s163">It is possible that the cheap newspapers may, in time, find their way into the cottages; or, at least, in the country taverns; but it is not the case at all now.</s> <s id="s164">If they generally know that <enamex sw="w32663" long="-121.1210661" lat="39.3626698" type="other" gazref="unlock:8134351" name="Sebastopol" conf="0.6611136253">Sebastopol</enamex> is besieged, that is the extent of their knowledge.</s> <s id="s165">The public life of <enamex  sw="w32745" name="Large admin unit">America</enamex> is lived through the mind and heart of every man in it; here, the people feel that they have nothing to do with what is going forward, and, I suspect, care little or nothing about it.</s> <s id="s166">Such things they permit to be the exclusive affair of the higher classes.</s></p>
<p><s id="s167">The arches of <enamex sw="w33025" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.2">Furness Abbey</enamex> owe their peculiar stateliness and impression of great height, to the tall pillars on which the arch is reared; all other arches, so far as I remember, are all sweep and segment of circles, and have no effect of lofty elevation.</s></p>
<p><s id="s168">[ 41] In front of our hotel, on <enamex sw="w33299" long="0.6777245875646798" lat="51.58230995227674" type="other" gazref="unlock:11192575" name="Lawn, The" conf="0.9492366003">the lawn</enamex> between us and the lake, there are two trees which we have hitherto taken to be yews; but on examining them more closely, I find that they are pine-trees, and quite dead and dry, although they have all the aspect of dark, rich life.</s> <s id="s169">This is the verdure of two great plants of ivy, which have twisted like gigantic snakes round the pine-trees, and clambering up - perhaps throttling the life out of them - have put out branches, and made tops of thick verdure, so that, at a little distance, it is quite impossible not to mistake them for genuine trees.</s> <s id="s170">The trunks of the ivy-plants must be more than a foot in circumference; and the observer feels as if they had stolen the life that belonged to the pines.</s> <s id="s171">The dead branches of the pine stick forth horizontally, through the ivy-boughs, from one of the trees; the other has nothing but the ivy-boughs, and, in shape, a good deal resembles a poplar.</s> <s id="s172">When the pine-trunks shall have quite crumbled away, the ivy-stems will doubtless have gained sufficient strength to sustain themselves independently.</s></p>
<p><s id="s173">July 19th, Thursday</s> </p><p><s id="s174">Yesterday morning, Mamma went down the lake, in the steamboat, to take Una, baby, and Nurse, to <enamex sw="w34474" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, where they are to stay while the three rest of us make a tour through the lake region.</s> <s id="s175">After Mamma's departure, and[ 42] when I had finished some letters, Julian and I set out on a walk which finally brought us - through much delightful shade of woods, and past beautiful rivulets, or brooklets, and over many uphills and down - to <enamex sw="w34820" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>.</s> <s id="s176">This chief harbor of the lakes seemed all alive and bustling with tourists; it being a sunny and pleasant day, so that they were all abroad like summer-insects.</s> <s id="s177">The town is a confused and irregular little place, of very uneven surface; there is an old church in it, and nothing else that I remember particularly, unless it be two or three large hotels.</s> <s id="s178">We staid there perhaps half an hour, and then went to the steamboat pier, where, shortly, a steamer arrived, with music sounding, on the deck of which, with her back to us, sat a lady in a gray travelling-cloak.</s> <s id="s179">Julian cried out" Mamma, Mamma!" - to which the lady deigned no notice; but he repeating it, she turned round, and was as much surprised, no doubt, at seeing her husband and son, as if this little lake had been the great ocean, and we encountering from opposite shores of it.</s> <s id="s180">We soon steamed back to Lowwood, and took a car thence for <enamex sw="w35729" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275806" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex> and <enamex sw="w35739" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, after a cold luncheon.</s> <s id="s181">I forgot to say that, at <enamex sw="w35797" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, I met Miss Charlotte Cushman, who has been staying at the Lowwood hotel with us since Monday, without either party being aware of it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s182">Our road to <enamex sw="w35952" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275806" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex> lay through <enamex sw="w35970" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, which is certainly a very pretty little town, and looks cheerfully in a sunny day.</s> <s id="s183">We saw Miss Martineau's residence, called the Knoll, standing high up on a[ 43] hillock, and having at its foot a Methodist chapel - for which, or whatever place of Christian worship, this good lady can have no great occasion.</s> <s id="s184">We stop a moment in <enamex sw="w36311" long="-2.545503018232447" lat="51.14439493145336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:42065" name="Street On The Fosse" conf="1.363213727">the street</enamex> below her house, and deliberated whether to call on her; but concluded otherwise.</s></p>
<p><s id="s185">After leaving <enamex sw="w36418" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, the road winds in and out among the hills, and soon brings us to a little sheet( or napkin rather than a sheet) of water, which the driver tell us is <enamex sw="w36579" long="-2.999" lat="54.4472" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7288050" name="Rydal Water" conf="99992">Rydal lake</enamex>.</s> <s id="s186">We had already heard it was but three quarters of a mile long, and one quarter broad; still, having an idea of considerable size in our minds, we had inevitably drawn the ideal mass of its physical proportions on a somewhat corresponding scale.</s> <s id="s187">It certainly did look very small; and I said, in my American scorn, that I could carry it away bodily in a porringer.</s> <s id="s188">It is nothing but a little, grassy-bordered pool, among the surrounding hills, which ascend directly from its margin; so that one might fancy it, not a permanent body of water, but a rather extensive accumulation of recent rain.</s> <s id="s189">Moreover, it was rippled with a breeze, as so, as I remember it( though the sun shone) looked dull and sulky, like a child out of humor.</s> <s id="s190">Now, the best thing these little ponds can do, is, to keep perfectly calm and smooth, and not attempt to show off any airs of their own, but to content themselves with serving[ 44] as a mirror for whatever of beautiful or picturesque there may be in the scenery around them.</s> <s id="s191">The hills about <enamex sw="w37611" long="-2.994852043565142" lat="54.44966001297723" type="water" gazref="unlock:11275811" name="Rydal Water" conf="2.4">Rydal Water</enamex> are not very lofty, but are sufficiently so as objects of every day view - objects to live with; - and they are craggier than those we have hitherto seen, and more bare of wood; which, indeed, could hardly grow on some of their precipitous sides.</s></p>
<p><s id="s192">On the roadside, as we reach the foot of the lake( which is the part first reached from <enamex sw="w37958" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>) stands a spruce and rather large house, of modern aspect, but with several gables, and much overgrown with ivy; a most pretty and comfortable house, built, adorned, and seen to, with commendable taste.</s> <s id="s193">We inquired whose it was; and the driver said it was" Mr. W a rdsworth's!" - and that Mrs. W a rdsworth was still residing there.</s> <s id="s194">So we were much delighted to have seen his abode; and as we were to stay the night at <enamex sw="w38387" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, about two miles farther on, we determined to come back and inspect as particularly as should be allowable.</s> <s id="s195">Accordingly, after taking quarters at Brown's Hotel( a very good house, on a retired and picturesque site, with fine mountain-views about it) we got into out return-car, and reaching the head of <enamex sw="w38699" long="-2.993866462466064" lat="54.44746550347175" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796733" name="Rydal Water" conf="2.4">Rydal water</enamex>, alighted to walk through this familiar scene of so many years of Wordsworth's life.</s> <s id="s196">We ought to have seen DeQuincey's former residence and <enamex  sw="w38851" name="Not a placename">Hartley</enamex> <enamex  sw="w38859" name="Not a placename">Coleridge</enamex>'s cottage, I believe, on our way, but we were not aware of it at the time.</s> <s id="s197">Near the lake there is a stone-quarry,[ 45] and a cavern of some extent, artificially formed, no doubt, by taking out the stone.</s> <s id="s198">Above the shore of the lake, not a great way from Wordsworth's residence, there is a flight of steps hewn in a rock, and ascending to a rocky seat whence a good view of <enamex sw="w39242" long="-2.993866462466064" lat="54.44746550347175" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796733" name="Rydal Water" conf="2.4">Rydal water</enamex>, such as it is, may be attained; and as Wordsworth has probably sat there hundreds of times, so did we ascend and sit down, and look at the hills, and at the flags on the lake's shore.</s></p>
<p><s id="s199">Reaching the house that had been pointed out to us as Wordsworth's residence, we began to peer about, at its front and gables, and over the garden-wall, on both sides of the road - quickening up our enthusiasm as much as we could, and meditating to pilfer some flower or ivy-leaf from the house or its vicinity, to be kept as sacred memorials.</s> <s id="s200">At this juncture, a man approached who announced himself as the gardener of the place, and said he could show us Wordsworth's garden; - and said, too, that this was not Wordsworth's house at all, but the residence of Mr. Ball, a Quaker gentleman; - but that his grounds adjoined Wordsworth's, and that he had liberty to take visitors through the latter.</s> <s id="s201">How queer, if we should have carried away ivy-leaves and tender recollections from this domicile of a respectable quaker.</s> <s id="s202">The gardener was an intelligent young man, of pleasant, sociable and respectful[ 46] address; and as we went along, he talked about Wordsworth, whom he had known, and who, he said, was very familiar with the country-people.</s> <s id="s203">He lead us through his master's grounds, up a steep hillside, by winding, gravelled walks, with summer-houses at points favorable for that purpose.</s> <s id="s204">It was a very shady and pleasant spot, containing about an acre of ground, and all turned to much account by the manner of laying out; so that it seemed more than it really is.</s> <s id="s205">In one place( on a little, smooth slab of slate, let into a rock) there is an inscription by Wordsworth, which I think I have read in his works, claiming kindly regards from those who visit the spot, after his departure, because many trees had here been spared, at his intercession.</s> <s id="s206">Wordsworth's own grounds( or rather his ornamental garden) is separated from Mr. Ball's only by a wire fence, or some such barrier; and the gates have no fastening; so that the whole appears like one possession, and doubtless was so as regarded the poet's walks and enjoyments.</s> <s id="s207">We approached by such winding paths that I hardly know how the house stands in relation to the road; but, after much circuitry, we really did see Wordsworth's residence, an old house, with an uneven ridge-pole, built of stone, no doubt, but plaistered[ sic] over of some neutral tint; - a house that would not have been remarkably pretty in itself, but so delightfully situated, so secluded, so hedged about with shrubbery and adorned with flowers, so ivy-grown on one[ 47] side, so beautified with many years of the personal care of him who lived in it and loved it - that it seemed the very place for a poet's residence; and as if, while he lived so long in it, his poetry had manifested itself in flowers, shrubbery and ivy.</s> <s id="s208">I never smelt such a delightful fragrance of flowers as there was all through the garden.</s> <s id="s209">In front of the house, there is a circular terrace, of two ascents, in raising which Wordsworth had himself performed much of the labor; and here there are two seats, from which is obtained a fine view down the valley of the Rothay, and <enamex sw="w42426" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> in the distance - a view of several miles, and which we did not think of seeing, after winding among the hills for far from the lake.</s> <s id="s210">It is very beautiful and picturelike.</s> <s id="s211">While we sat here, Mamma happened to refer to the ballad of little Barbara Lewthwaite; and the gardener said that little Barbara had died not a great while since, an elderly woman, leaving grown up children behind her.</s> <s id="s212">Her marriage name was <enamex sw="w42850" long="-118.613442" lat="37.1429902" type="other" gazref="unlock:8142547" name="Mount Thompson" conf="0.6727227922">Thompson</enamex>; and the gardener believed that there was nothing remarkable in her character.</s></p>
<p><s id="s213">There is a summer house at one extremity of Wordsworth's ground, in deepest shadow, but with glimpses of mountain views through trees which shut it in, and which have spread intercepting boughs since Wordsworth died.</s> <s id="s214">It is lined with pine-cones, in a pretty way enough, but of doubtful taste.</s> <s id="s215">I rather wonder[ 48] that people of real taste should help Nature out, and beautify her( or, perhaps, rather, prettify) so much as they do - opening vistas, showing one thing, hiding another, making a scene picturesque whether or no.</s> <s id="s216">I cannot rid myself of the feeling that there is something false - a kind of humbug - in all this.</s> <s id="s217">At any rate, the traces of it do not contribute to my enjoyment; and, indeed, it ought to be done so exquisitely as to leave no trace.</s> <s id="s218">But I ought not to criticise in any way a spot which gave me so much pleasure, and where it is good to think of Wordsworth, in quiet days past, walking in his home-shadow of trees which he knew, and training flowers, and trimming shrubs, and chaunting in an under-tone his own verses, up and down the undulating walks.</s></p>
<p><s id="s219">The gardener gave Julian a cone, from the summer-house( it had fallen on the seat) and Mamma got some mignionette[ sic], and leaves of laurel and ivy; and we wended our way back to the hotel.</s> <s id="s220">Wordsworth was not the owner of this house; it being the property of Lady <enamex sw="w44287" long="-3.95" lat="51.11667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4579239" name="Bratton Fleming" conf="0.7344722764">Fleming</enamex>.</s> <s id="s221">Mrs Wordsworth still lives there, and is now at home.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s222">5 o clock.</s> <s id="s223">All day it has been cloudy and showery, with now and then thunder; the mists hang low on the surrounding hills, adown which, at various points, we can see the snow-white fall of the little streamlets - forces, they call them here - swollen by the rain.</s> <s id="s224">And overcast day is not so gloomy in a hill-country as in the lowlands; there are[ 49] more breaks, more transfusion of sky-light, through the gloom, as has been the case to-day; and then, too( as I found in <enamex sw="w44823" long="-83.201286" lat="37.957309" type="other" gazref="unlock:7047508" name="Lenox" conf="0.6223098091">Lenox</enamex>) we get better acquainted with clouds by seeing at what height they lie on the hillsides, and find the difference betwixt a fair day and a cloudy and rainy one is very superficial, after all.</s> <s id="s225">Nevertheless, rain is rain, and wets a man just as much among the mountains as anywhere else; so we have been kept within doors all day, till an hour or so ago, when Julian and I went down to the village in quest of the post-office.</s></p>
<p><s id="s226">We took a path that leads from the hotel across the fields, and coming into a road, crosses the Rothay by a one arched bridge, and passes the village church.</s> <s id="s227">The Rothay is very swift and turbulent to-day, and hurries along with foam-specks on its surface, filling its banks from brim to brim, a stream of perhaps twenty feet across.</s> <s id="s228">Perhaps more; for I am willing that the good little river should have all it can fairly claim; it is the <enamex sw="w45692" long="0.83419" lat="51.70374" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563163" name="Saint Lawrence" conf="0.8976172216">Saint Lawrence</enamex> of several of these English lakes, through which it flows, and carries off their superfluous waters.</s> <s id="s229">In its haste, and with its rushing sound, it was pleasant both to see and hear; and it sweeps by one side of the old churchyard where Wordsworth lies buried - the side where his grave is made.</s> <s id="s230">The church of <enamex sw="w46015" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> is a very plain structure, with a low body, on one side of which is a low porch with a pointed arch; the tower is[ 50] square, and look ancient; but the whole is overlaid with plaister[ sic] of a buff or pale yellow hue.</s> <s id="s231">It was originally built, I suppose, of rough, shingly stones, as many of the houses hereabouts are now; and, like many of them, the plaister[ sic] is used to give a sort of finish.</s> <s id="s232">We found the gate of the church-yard wide open; and the grass was lying on the graves, having probably been mowed yesterday.</s> <s id="s233">It is but a small churchyard, and with few monuments of any pretension in it, most of them being slate headstones standing erect.</s> <s id="s234">From the gate at which we entered, a distinct foot track leads to the corner nearest the river-side; and I turned into it by a sort of instinct, the more readily as I saw a tourist-looking man approaching from that point, and a woman looking among the grave stones.</s> <s id="s235">Both of these persons had gone by the time I came up; so that Julian and I were left to find Wordsworth's grave all by ourselves.</s></p>
<p><s id="s236">Right at this corner of the churchyard, there is a hawthorn-bush, or tree, the extremest branches of which stretch as far as where Wordsworth lies.</s> <s id="s237">This whole corner seems to be devoted to himself and his family and friends; and they all lie very closely together, side by side, and head to feet, as room could conveniently be found.</s> <s id="s238"><enamex  sw="w47415" name="Not a placename">Hartley</enamex> <enamex  sw="w47423" name="Not a placename">Coleridge</enamex> lies a little behind, in the direction of the church, his feet being towards Wordsworth's head, who lies in the row of those of his own blood.</s> <s id="s239">I found <enamex  sw="w47584" name="Not a placename">Hartley</enamex> <enamex  sw="w47592" name="Not a placename">Coleridge</enamex>'s grave sooner than[ 51] Wordsworth's; for it is of marble, and, though simple enough, has more of a sculptured device about it - having been erected, as I think the inscription states, by his brother and sister.</s> <s id="s240">Wordsworth has only the very simplest slab of slate with" William Wordsworth," and nothing else upon it.</s> <s id="s241">As I recollect, it is the midmost grave of the row.</s> <s id="s242">It is, or has been, well grass-grown; but the grass s quite worn away from the top, though sufficiently luxuriant at the sides; it looks as if people had stood upon it, and so does the grave next to it, which I believe is one of his children.</s> <s id="s243">I plucked some grass and weeds from it; and as he was buried within so few years, they may fairly be thought to have drawn their nutriment from Wordsworth's mortal remains - and I gathered them from just above his head.</s> <s id="s244">There is no fault to be found with his grave - within view of the hills, within sound of the river murmuring near by - no fault, except that he is packed so closely with his kindred; and, moreover, that, being so old a churchyard, the earth over him must all have been human once.</s> <s id="s245">He might have had fresh earth to himself; but he chose this grave deliberately.</s> <s id="s246">No very stately and broad-based monument can ever be erected over it, without infringing upon, covering, and overshadowing, the graves not only of his family, but of individuals who probably were quite disconnected with him.</s> <s id="s247">[ 52] But it is pleasant to think and know - were it but on the evidence of this choice of a resting-place - that he did not care for a stately monument.</s></p>
<p><s id="s248">After leaving the churchyard, we wandered about in quest of the post-office, and, for a long time, without success.</s> <s id="s249">This little town of <enamex sw="w49310" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> seems to me as pretty a place as ever I met with in my life.</s> <s id="s250">It is quite shut in by hills, that rise up immediately around it, like a neighborhood of kindly giants; these hills descend steeply to the verge of the level on which the village stands, and there they terminate at once, the while site of the little town being as even as a floor.</s> <s id="s251">I call it a village; but it is no village at all, all the dwellings standing apart, each in its own little domain, and each, I believe, with its own little lane leading to it, independently of the rest.</s> <s id="s252">Most of these are old cottages, plaistered[ sic] white, with antique porches, and roses and other shrubbery trained against them, or growing about them; some, too, are ivy-grown.</s> <s id="s253">There are a few edifices of more pretension, and of modern build, but not so strikingly as to put the rest out of countenance.</s> <s id="s254">The post-office, when I found it, proved to be an ivied cottage, with a good deal of shrubbery around it, having its own pathway, like the other cottages.</s> <s id="s255">The whole looks like a real seclusion, shut off from the great world by these encircling hills, on the sides of which, wherever[ 53] they are not too steep, you can see the division lines of property, and tokens of cultivation - taking from their pretensions to savage majesty, but bringing them nearer to the heart of man.</s></p>
<p><s id="s256">Since writing the above, I have been again with Sophia to see Wordsworth's grave; and finding the door of the church open we went in.</s> <s id="s257">A woman and a little girl were sweeping at the farther end; and the woman came towards us out of the little cloud of dust which she had raised.</s> <s id="s258">We were surprised at the extremely antique appearance of the church.</s> <s id="s259">It is paved with bluish gray flag-stones, over which uncounted generations have trodden, leaving the floor as well laid as ever.</s> <s id="s260">The walls are very thick; and the arched windows open through them at a considerable distance above the floor.</s> <s id="s261">There is no middle aisle; but first a row of pews next either wall, and then an aisle on each side of the pews occupying the centre of the church - thus, two side aisles, but no middle one.</s> <s id="s262">And right down through the centre of the church runs a row of five arches, the rudest and the roundest-headed that I ever saw, all of rough stone, supported by rough and massive pillars, or rather, square stone blocks, which stand in the pews, and stood in the same place, probably, long before the wood of those pews began to grow.</s> <s id="s263">Above this row or arches is another row, built upon the same mass of stone, and almost as broad, but lower; and on this upper row rests the frame-work, the oaken[ 54] beams, the black skeleton of the church-roof.</s> <s id="s264">It seems a very clumsy contrivance for supporting the roof; and if it were modern, we should certainly condemn it as very ugly; but being a relic of a simpler age, it comes in well with the antique simplicity of the whole structure.</s> <s id="s265">The roof goes up, barn-like, into its natural angle, and all the rafters and cross-beams are visible.</s> <s id="s266">There is an old font; and in the chancel is a niche, where( judging from a similar one in <enamex sw="w52399" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.2">Furness Abbey</enamex>) the holy water used to be places for the priest's use, while celebrating mass.</s> <s id="s267">Around the inside of the porch is a stone-bench, placed against the wall, narrow and uneasy, but where a great many people have sat, who now have found quieter resting-places.</s></p>
<p><s id="s268">The woman was a very intelligent looking person, not of the usual English ruddiness; but rather thin, and somewhat pale, though bright of aspect.</s> <s id="s269">Her way of talking was very agreeable.</s> <s id="s270">She inquired if we wished to see Wordsworth's monument, and at once showed it to us; - a slab of white marble, fixed against the upper end of the central row of stone arches, with a pretty long inscription, and a profile-bust in bas-relief of his aged countenance.</s> <s id="s271">The monument is placed directly over Wordsworth's pew, and could best be seen and read from the very corner-seat where he used to sit.</s> <s id="s272">The pew is the corner one of those occupying the centre of the church, and is just across the aisle from the pulpit, and is the best in the church for the pur55pose of seeing and hearing the clergyman, and likewise as convenient as any from it neighborhood to the altar.</s> <s id="s273">On the other side of the aisle, beneath the pulpit, is Lady <enamex sw="w53585" long="-3.95" lat="51.11667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4579239" name="Bratton Fleming" conf="0.7344722764">Fleming</enamex>'s pew.</s> <s id="s274">This and one or two other pews are curtained.</s> <s id="s275">Wordsworth's was not.</s> <s id="s276">I think I can bring up his image, in that corner seat of his pew, and of the aisle, a white-headed, tall, spare man, plain in aspect - better than in any other situation.</s> <s id="s277">The woman said that she had known him very well, and that he had made some verses on a sister of hers.</s> <s id="s278">She repeated the first lines( something about a lamb) but neither Sophia nor I remembered them.</s></p>
<p><s id="s279">On the walls of the chancel there are monuments to the <enamex  sw="w54093" name="Not a placename">Flemings</enamex> and other people, and painted escutcheons of some of their arms; and along the side walls, too, and on the square pillars of the row of arches, there are other monuments, generally of white marble, with the letters of the inscriptions blackened.</s> <s id="s280">Along these pillars, likewise, and in many places on thee walls, were hung verses from Scripture, painted on boards.</s> <s id="s281">At one of the doors was a poor box - an elaborately carved little box, of oak - with the date of 1648, and the name of the church( St. Oswald's) upon it.</s> <s id="s282">The whole interior of the edifice was ancient, plain, simple, almost to grimness - or would have been so, only that the foolish churchwardens, or whatever other authority, have washed it over with the same buff or salmon color with which they have overlaid[ 56] the exterior.</s> <s id="s283">It is a pity; it lightens it up and desecrates it horribly - especially as the woman says that there were formerly paintings on the old walls, now obliterated forever.</s> <s id="s284">I could have staid in the church much longer, and could write much more about it; but there must be an end of everything.</s> <s id="s285">Pacing it from the farther end, to the elevation before the altar, I found that it was twenty - five paces long.</s></p>
<p><s id="s286">On looking again at the Rothay, I find I did it some injustice; for, at the bridge, in its present swollen state, it is nearer twenty yards than twenty feet across.</s> <s id="s287">Its waters are very clear, and it rushes along with a speed which is delightful to see, after an acquaintance with the muddy and sluggish <enamex sw="w55599" long="-2.5" lat="51.43333" type="other" gazref="unlock:4581122" name="Avon" conf="0.8696105951">Avon</enamex> and <enamex sw="w55608" long="-1.647250869954262" lat="53.31164472761305" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11193131" name="Leam" conf="1.395513877">Leam</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s288">Since tea, I have taken a stroll from the hotel in a different direction than heretofore, and passed the Swan Inn, where Scott used to go daily to get a draught of liquor, when he was visiting Wordsworth, who had no wine or other inspiriting fluid in his house.</s> <s id="s289">It stands right on the roadside, a small, white-washed house, with an addition in the rear that seems to have been built since Scott's time.</s> <s id="s290"><enamex sw="w56017" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.319331067">Over</enamex> the door is the painted sign of a swan, with" Scott's <enamex sw="w56076" long="-3.0201" lat="54.4655" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828775" name="Macdonald Swan Hotel" conf="2">Swan Hotel</enamex>."</s> <s id="s291">I went a considerable distance beyond it; but a shower coming up, I turned back, entered the inn, and following the mistress into a snug little room, was served[ 57] with a glass of bitter ale.</s> <s id="s292">It is a very plain and homely little inn; and certainly could not have satisfied Scott's wants, if he had required anything very far-fetched or delicate in his potations.</s> <s id="s293">I found two Westmoreland peasants in the room, with liquor before them.</s> <s id="s294">One went away almost immediately; but the other remained, and entering into a conversation with him, he told me that he was going to <enamex  sw="w56659" name="Large admin unit">New Zealand</enamex>, and expected to sail in September.</s> <s id="s295">I announced myself as an American, and he said that a large party had lately gone from hereabouts to <enamex  sw="w56808" name="Large admin unit">America</enamex>; but he seemed not to understand that there was any distinction between <enamex  sw="w56888" name="Large admin unit">Canada</enamex> and the States.</s> <s id="s296">These people had gone to <enamex sw="w56936" long="-71.3492317199707" lat="46.88131141662598" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131345" name="Québec" conf="1.970667809">Quebec</enamex>.</s> <s id="s297">He was a very civil, well-behaved, kindly sort of person, of a simple character, which I took to belong to the class and locality, rather than to himself individually.</s> <s id="s298">I could not very easily understand all that he said, owing to hs provincial dialect; and when he spoke to his own countrymen, or to the women of the house, I really could but just catch a word here and there.</s> <s id="s299">How long it takes to melt <enamex  sw="w57347" name="Large admin unit">England down</enamex> into a homogeneous mass! He told me that there was a public library in <enamex sw="w57431" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, to which he had access, in common with the other inhabitants, and a reading room connected with it, where he reads the" Times" in the evening.</s> <s id="s300">There was no American smartness in his mind.</s> <s id="s301">When I left the Swann[ 58] it was showering smartly; but the drops quite ceased, and the clouds began to break away before I reached my hotel; and I saw the moon over my right shoulder.</s></p>
<p><s id="s302">July 21st Saturday</s> </p><p><s id="s303">We left <enamex sw="w57842" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> yesterday, after breakfast, it being a delightful morning, with some clouds, but the cheerfullest sunshine on great part of the mountainsides and on ourselves.</s> <s id="s304">We returned, in the first place, to <enamex sw="w58047" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, along the border of <enamex sw="w58078" long="-3.0216" lat="54.45" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_6956554" name="Grasmere Water" conf="99991">Grasmere lake</enamex>, which would be a pretty little piece of water, with its steep and high surrounding hills, were it not that a stubborn and straight-lined stone fence, running along the eastern shore, by the roadside, quite spoils its appearance.</s> <s id="s305"><enamex sw="w58322" long="-2.994852043565142" lat="54.44966001297723" type="water" gazref="unlock:11275811" name="Rydal Water" conf="2.4">Rydal Water</enamex>( though nothing can make a lake of it) looked prettier and less diminutive than at first view; and, in fact, I find that it is impossible to know accurately how any prospect or other thing looks, until after at least a second view, which always essentially corrects the first.</s> <s id="s306">This, I think, is especially true in regard to objects which we have heard much about, and exercised our imagination upon; the first view being a vain attempt to reconcile our idea with the reality, and in the second we begin to accept the thing for what it really is.</s> <s id="s307">Wordsworth's situation is really a beautiful one; and <enamex sw="w58934" long="-2.994852043565142" lat="54.44966001297723" type="other" gazref="unlock:11226054" name="Nab Scar" conf="2">Nab Scar</enamex> behind his house rises with a grand, protecting air.</s> <s id="s308">We passed Nab's cottage in which DeQuincey formerly lived, and where <enamex  sw="w59065" name="Not a placename">Hartley</enamex> <enamex  sw="w59073" name="Not a placename">Coleridge</enamex> lived and died.</s> <s id="s309">It is a little, buff-tinted, plastered stone cottage, right on the road[ 59] - side, and originally, I should think, of a very humble class; but it now looks as if persons of taste might sometime or other have sat down in it, and caused flowers to spring up about it.</s> <s id="s310">It is very agreeably situated, under the great, precipitous hill, and with <enamex sw="w59439" long="-2.993866462466064" lat="54.44746550347175" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796733" name="Rydal Water" conf="2.4">Rydal water</enamex> close at hand, on the other side of the road.</s> <s id="s311">An advertisement of lodgings to let was put up on this cottage.</s></p>
<p><s id="s312">I question whether any part of the world looks as beautiful as <enamex  sw="w59624" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> - this part of <enamex  sw="w59647" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, at least - on a fine summer morning.</s> <s id="s313">It makes one think the more cheerfully of human life to see such a bright, universal verdure; such sweet, rural, peaceful, flower-bordered cottages; not cottages of gentility, but real dwellings of the laboring poor.</s> <s id="s314">Such nice villas along the roadside, so tastefully contrived for comfort and beauty, and adorned, more and more, year after year, with the care and after-thought of people who mean to live there a great while, and feel as if their children might live there after them - and so they plant trees to overshadow their walks, and train ivy and whatever beautiful thing will grow there, up against their walls; and so live for the future in another sense than we Americans do.</s> <s id="s315">And the climate helps them out, and makes everything so moist and green, and full of tender life, instead of being dry and arid; as human life and vegetable life is so apt to be with us.</s> <s id="s316">Certainly, <enamex  sw="w60579" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> can present a more attractive face than we can;[ 60] even its humbler modes of life; to say nothing of the beautiful lives that might, one would think, be lead by the higher classes, whose gateways, with broad, smooth, gravelled tracks leading through them( but where none but the owner's carriage, or those of his friends, have a right to enter) you see every mile or two along the road, winding up some proud seclusion.</s> <s id="s317">All this is passing away; and society must assume new relations; but there is no harm in believing that there has been something very good in English life - good for all classes - while the world was in a state out of which these forms naturally grew.</s></p>
<p><s id="s318">Passing through <enamex sw="w61277" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, we turned( that is, our phaeton and pair turned) towards <enamex sw="w61345" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, which we were to reach through the pass of <enamex sw="w61399" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s319">This is some three or four miles from <enamex sw="w61448" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>; and as we approached it, the road kept ascending higher and higher; the hills grew more bare, and the country lost its soft, and delightful verdure.</s> <s id="s320">At last, the road became so steep, that Julian and I alighted to walk.</s> <s id="s321">This is the" aspiring road," which Wordsworth speaks of in his ode; it passes through the gorge of precipitous hills - or almost precipitous - too much so for even the grass to grow on many portions of their declevities, which are covered with gray shingly stones; and I think this pass, in its wilder part, must have looked just the same when the Romans marched through it, as it does now.</s> <s id="s322">No trees could ever have grown on these steep hill-sides, where even the English climate can generate no[ 61] available soil.</s> <s id="s323">I do not know that I have seen anything more impressive than the stern, gray sweep of these naked mountain-sides, with nothing whatever to soften or adorn them.</s> <s id="s324">The notch of the <enamex sw="w62374" long="-71.18091010000001" lat="44.4697806" type="other" gazref="unlock:7830853" name="Northern White Mountains Chamber of Commerce" conf="0.7635402683">White Mountains</enamex>( as I remember it from my youthful days) is more wonderful and richly picturesque, but of a quite different character.</s></p>
<p><s id="s325">About the centre and at the highest point of the pass stands an old stone-house, of mean appearance, with the usual sign of an ale-house(" licensed to retail foreign spirits, ale, and tobacco") over the door; and another little sign, designating it as the highest inhabited house in <enamex  sw="w62792" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s> <s id="s326">It is a chill and desolate place for a residence.</s> <s id="s327">They keep a visitors book here; and we recorded our names, and were not too sorry to leave, the little mean house, smelling as it did of tobacco smoke, and with whatever characterizes the humblest ale-house on the level earth.</s></p>
<p><s id="s328">The <enamex sw="w63082" long="-2.918145377341105" lat="54.46824399504823" type="other" gazref="unlock:11187767" name="Kirk Stone" conf="2">Kirk Stone</enamex>, which gives the pass its name, is not seen in approaching from <enamex sw="w63157" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, until some time after you begin to descend towards Brother's Water.</s> <s id="s329">When the driver first pointed it out, a little way up the hillside on our left, it looked like little more than a boulder of a ton or two in weight, among a hundred others nearly as big; and I saw little or no resemblance to a church or church-spire, to which the fancies of past generation[ s] have likened it.</s> <s id="s330">As we descended the pass, however, and left the stone farther[ 62] and farther behind, it continued to show itself, and assumed a more striking and prominent aspect, standing out clearly relieved against the sky; so that no traveller - where there were so few defined objects to attract notice, amid the naked monotony of the stern hills - could fail to observe it; though, indeed, if I had taken it for any sort of an edifice, it would be rather for a wayside inn or shepherd's hut, than for a church.</s> <s id="s331">We lost sight of this stone, and again beheld it more and more brought out against the sky, by the turns of the road, several times in the course of our descent.</s> <s id="s332">There is a very striking view of Brother's water, shut in by steep hillsides, as we go don <enamex sw="w64303" long="-2.91667" lat="54.45" type="other" gazref="unlock:4569619" name="Kirkstone Pass" conf="2">Kirkstone pass</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s333">At about ½ past twelve, we reached <enamex sw="w64354" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>, at the foot of <enamex sw="w64381" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>, and here had luncheon.</s> <s id="s334">The hotels are mostly very good, all through this region, and this appeared to deserve that character; a black-coated waiter, more gentlemanly than most Englishmen, yet taking a sixpence with as little scruple as a lawyer would his fee; the mistress, in lady like attire, receiving us at the door, and waiting upon us to the carriage-steps; clean, comely house-maids everywhere at hand - all appliances, in short, for being comfortable, and comfortable, too, within one's own circle.</s> <s id="s335">And, on taking leave, everybody who has done anything for you, or who might by possibility have done anything, is to be feed.</s> <s id="s336">You pay the landlord enough in all conscience, and then you pay all his servants, who have been your servants for the time.</s> <s id="s337">But,[ 63] to sat the truth, there is a degree of the same kind of annoyance in an American hotel; although it is not so much an acknowledged custom.</s> <s id="s338">Here, in the house where attendence is not charged in the bill, no wages appear to be paid to those servants - chambermaid, waiter, and boots - who come into immediate contact with travellers.</s> <s id="s339">The drivers of the cars, phaetons, and flies, are likewise unpaid, except by travellers, and claim three pence per mile with the same sense of right as their masters, in charging for the vehicle and horses.</s> <s id="s340">When you come to understand this claim not as an appeal to your generosity, but as an actual and necessary part of the cost of the journey, it is yielded to with a more comfortable feeling; and the traveller has really option enough, as to the amount which he will give, to ensure civility and good behavior on the driver's part.</s></p>
<p><s id="s341"><enamex sw="w66028" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex> is a beautiful lake, with steep hills walling it about; so steep, on the eastern side, that there seems hardly room for a road to run along.</s> <s id="s342">We passed up the western shore; and turned off from it, about midway, I believe, to take the road towards <enamex sw="w66285" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s343">We stopt, however, at <enamex sw="w66316" long="-2.9206" lat="54.5761" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11210312" name="Lyulph's Tower" conf="99992">Lyulph</enamex>'s tower( while the chariot went on, up a hill) and took a guide to show us the way to <enamex sw="w66409" long="-2.936037483005751" lat="54.57596662121968" type="water" gazref="unlock:11057415" name="Aira Force" conf="2.4">Aira Force</enamex>, a little cataract which is claimed as private property, and out of which, no doubt, a pretty little revenue is raised.</s> <s id="s344">I do not think that there can be any[ 64] rightful appropriation, as private property, of objects of natural beauty.</s> <s id="s345">The fruits of the land, I suppose, and whatever human labor can produce from it, belong fairly enough to the person who has a deed or a lease; but the beautiful is the property of him who can gather it and enjoy it.</s> <s id="s346">It is very unsatisfactory to think of a cataract under lock-and-key.</s> <s id="s347">However, we were shown to <enamex sw="w66968" long="-2.936037483005751" lat="54.57596662121968" type="water" gazref="unlock:11057415" name="Aira Force" conf="2.4">Aira Force</enamex> by a tall and graceful mountain-maid, with a healthy cheek, and a step that has no possibility of weariness in it.</s> <s id="s348">The cascade is an irregular streak of foaming water, pouring through a rude, shadowy glen.</s> <s id="s349">I liked well enough to see it; but it is wearisome, on the whole, to go the rounds of what everybody thinks it necessary to see.</s> <s id="s350">It makes one a little ashamed; it is somewhat as if we were drinking out of the same glass and eating from the same dish as a multitude of other people.</s></p>
<p><s id="s351">Within a few miles of <enamex sw="w67489" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, we passed along at the foot of <enamex sw="w67529" long="-3.0502" lat="54.6415" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="99992">Blencathara</enamex>, or <enamex sw="w67545" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex>, and by the entrance of the Vale of <enamex sw="w67592" long="-65.890278" lat="45.316111" type="other" gazref="unlock:5424240" name="Saint John, N. B." conf="1.086013376">Saint John</enamex>; and adown the valley, on the side of one of the slopes, we saw the enchanted castle.</s> <s id="s352">Thence we drove along by the course of the Greta, and soon arrived at <enamex sw="w67759" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, which liew at the base of <enamex sw="w67794" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, and among a brotherhood of picturesque eminences, and is itself a compact little town, with a market-house( built from the old stones of the Earl of Derwentwater's ruined castle) standing in the centre, with the principle street forking into two, as it passes it.</s> <s id="s353">We alighted at the[ 65] King's Head, or King's Arms, or some such sign, and went in search of Southey's residence, which we found easily enough, as it lies just on the outskirts of the town.</s> <s id="s354">We inquired of a group of people, two of whom, I thought, did not seem to know much about the matter; but the third, and elderly man, pointed it out at once - a house surrounded by trees, so as to be seen only partially, and standing on a little eminence, a hundred yards or so from the road.</s></p>
<p><s id="s355">We went up a little private lane that led to the rear of the house, and so penetrated quite into the back-yard without meeting anybody, passing a small kennel in which were two hounds, who gazed at us, but neither growled nor wagged their tails.</s> <s id="s356">The house is three stories high, and seems to have a great deal of room in it, so as not to do discredit to its name of" <enamex sw="w68918" long="-3.139015605" lat="54.603823" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00161" name="Greta Hall" conf="99992">Greta Hall</enamex>"; - a very spacious dwelling for a poet.</s> <s id="s357">The windows, I think, were all closed; there were no signs of occupancy, but a general air of neglect.</s> <s id="s358">Sophia( who is bolder than I, in these matters) ventured through what seemed a back-garden gate; and I soon heard her in conversation with some man, who now presented himself, and proved to be a gardener.</s> <s id="s359">He said that he had formerly acted in that capacity for Southey, although a gardener had not been kept by him as a regular part of his establishment.</s> <s id="s360">This was an old man with an odd crookedness of legs, and strange, disjointed limp.</s> <s id="s361">Sophia told him that we were Americans; and he[ 66] took the idea that we had come this long distance over sea and land, with the sole purpose of seeing Southey's residence; so that he was inclined to do what he could towards exhibiting it.</s> <s id="s362">This was but little; the present occupant( a Mr. Radday, I believe the gardener called him) being away, and the house shut up.</s></p>
<p><s id="s363">But he showed us about the grounds, and let us peep into the windows of what had been Southey's library, and those of another of the front apartments, and showed us the window of the chamber( in the rear of the house) where Southey died.</s> <s id="s364">The apartments into which we peeped looked rather small and low - not particularly so - but enough to indicate rather an old house; they are now handsomely furnished; and we saw over one of the fire-places an inscription about Southey, and in the corner of the same room stood a suit of bright armour.</s> <s id="s365">The front of the house is tall - taller than most gentleman's houses in <enamex  sw="w70491" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> are - and even stately.</s> <s id="s366">All about, in front, beside it, and behind - there is a great profusion of trees, most of which were planted by Southey, who came to live here more than fifty years ago; and they have of course grown much more shadowy than he ever beheld them; for he died as much as fourteen years since.</s> <s id="s367">The grounds are well laid out, and neatly kept, with the usual lawn and gravelled walks, and quaint little devices in the ornamental way.</s> <s id="s368">These may be of later date than Southey's time.</s> <s id="s369">The gardener[ 67] spoke respectfully of Southey, and of his first wife; and observed that it was a" great loss to the neighborhood when that family went down."</s></p>
<p><s id="s370">The house stands right above the Greta, the murmur of which is audible all about it; for the Greta is a swift little river, and goes on its way with a continual sound, which has both depth and breadth in it.</s> <s id="s371">When we had seen the front of the house, the gardener led us to a walk along the bank of the river, close by <enamex sw="w71475" long="-2.83895" lat="54.71404" type="other" gazref="unlock:5826154" name="Hutton in the Forest Hall" conf="1.904510465">the Hall</enamex>, where he said Southey used to walk for hours and hours together.</s> <s id="s372">He might, indeed, get there out of his study in a moment.</s> <s id="s373">There are two paths, one above the other, well laid out on the steep declivity of the high bank; and there is such a very thick shade of oaks and elms( planted by Southey himself) over the bank, that all the ground and grass were moist, although it has been a sunny day.</s> <s id="s374">It is a very sombre walk; not many glimpses of the sky through those dense boughs.</s> <s id="s375">The Greta is here perhaps twenty yards across, and very dark of hue; and it[ s] voice is melancholy, and very suggestive of musings and reveries, but I should question whether it were favorable to any settled scheme of thought.</s> <s id="s376">The gardener told us that there used to be a pebbly beach on the margin of the river; and that it was Southey's habit to sit and write there, using a tree of peculiar[ 68] shape for a table.</s> <s id="s377">An alteration in the current of the river has swept away the beach, and the tree, too, has fallen.</s> <s id="s378">All these things were interesting to me, although <enamex  sw="w72529" name="Not a placename">Southey</enamex> was not, I think, a picturesque man nor one whose personal character takes a strong hold of the imagination.</s> <s id="s379">In these walks, he used to wear a pair of shoes heavily clamped with iron; very ponderous they must have been, from the particularity with which the gardener mentioned them.</s></p>
<p><s id="s380">The gardener dismissed us through the front entrance to the grounds; and returning to the King's Arms, we took a one horse fly for the falls of <enamex sw="w72964" long="-3.13662933748405" lat="54.55627196668239" type="water" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="2.4">Lodore</enamex>.</s> <s id="s381">Our ride thither was along the banks of <enamex sw="w73012" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>; and it is as beautiful a road, I imagine, as can be found in <enamex  sw="w73087" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, or any where else.</s> <s id="s382">I like <enamex sw="w73122" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> the best of all the lakes, so far as I have yet seen them.</s> <s id="s383"><enamex sw="w73194" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> lies at the head of a long even ridge of mountain, rising into several peaks, and one the highest; on the eastern side, there are many noble eminences; and on the west( along which we rode) there is, a part of the way, a lovely wood, and, nearly the whole distance, a precipitous range of lofty cliff, descending sheer down, without any slope except what has been formed, in the lapse of ages, by the fall of fragments and the washing down of smaller stones.</s> <s id="s384">The declivity thus formed, along the base of the cliffs, is in some places covered with[ 69] trees or shrubs; elsewhere it is quite bare and barren.</s> <s id="s385">The precipitous part of the cliffs is very grand; the whole scene indeed might be characterized - without lauding it a great deal too much - as stern grandeur with an embroidery of rich beauty.</s> <s id="s386">All the sternness of it is softened by vegetative beauty, wherever it can possibly be thrown in; and there is not here, so strongly as along <enamex sw="w74145" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>,[ evidence] that human art has been helping out Nature.</s> <s id="s387">I wish it were possible to give any idea of the shapes of the hills; with these, at least, man has had nothing to do, nor ever will.</s> <s id="s388">As we approached the bottom of this lake, and of the beautiful valley in which it lies, we saw one hill that seemed to crouch down, like a Titanic watch-dog, with its rear towards the spectator, guarding the entrance to the valley.</s> <s id="s389">The great superiority of these mountains over those of <enamex sw="w74632" long="0.8543168303199488" lat="51.57184320258142" type="water" gazref="unlock:8792167" name="New England Creek" conf="1.279554775">New England</enamex>( besides the abundance everywhere of water-prospects, which are wanting among our own hills) is their variety and definiteness of shape.</s> <s id="s390">They rise up decidedly; and each is a hill by itself; while ours mingle into one another; and, besides, have such large bases that you can tell neither where they begin nor end.</s> <s id="s391">These <enamex  sw="w74965" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland mountains</enamex> have, many of them, at least, a marked vertebral shape, so that they can often look like a group of huge lions, lying down with their[ 70] rears turned towards each other.</s> <s id="s392">They slope down steeply from narrow ridges; hence these picturesque seclusions of valleys and dales, which subdivide the lake region into so many communities.</s> <s id="s393">Our hills, like apple dumplings in a dish, have no such vallies[ sic] as these.</s></p>
<p><s id="s394">There is a good little inn and <enamex sw="w75430" long="-3.13662933748405" lat="54.55627196668239" type="water" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="2.4">Lodore</enamex>; a small, primitive, country-inn, which has latterly been enlarged and otherwise adapted to meet the convenience of the guests brought thither by the fame of the cascade; but it is still a country-inn, though it takes upon itself the title of a Hotel.</s> <s id="s395">We found pleasant rooms here, and established ourselves for the night.</s> <s id="s396">From this point we have a view up the beautiful lake, and of <enamex sw="w75822" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> at the head of it.</s> <s id="s397">The cascade, too, is within three or four minutes' walk, through the garden-gate, towards the cliff at the base of which the inn stands.</s> <s id="s398">The visitor would need no other guide than its own voice, which is said to be audible, sometimes, to the distance of four miles.</s> <s id="s399">As we were coming from <enamex sw="w76138" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, at some little distance from the inn, we caught glimpses of its white foam, high up on the precipice; and it is only glimpses that can be caught anywhere, because there is no regular sheet of falling water.</s> <s id="s400">Once, I think, it must have fallen right over the edge of the long line of precipice that here extends along, parallel with the[ 71] shore of the lake; but, in the course of time, it has gnawed and sawn its way into the heart of the cliff - this persistent little stream - so that now it has formed a rude gorge, adown which it hurries and tumbles, in the wildest way, over the roughest imaginable staircase.</s> <s id="s401">Standing at the bottom of the fall, you have a far vista, sloping upward to the sky, with the water - everywhere as white as snow - pouring and pouring down, now[ on] one side of the gorge, now on the other, among immense boulders which try to choke its passage.</s> <s id="s402">It does not attempt to leap over these huge rocks, but finds its way in and out among them, and finally gets to the bottom after a hundred tumbles.</s> <s id="s403">It cannot be better described than in Southey's verses, though worthy of better poetry than that.</s> <s id="s404">After all, I do not know that the cascade is anything more than the beautiful fringe to the grandeur of the scene; for it is very grand - this fissure through the cliff, with a steep, lofty precipice on the right hand, sheep up and down, and on the other hand, too, another lofty precipice, with a slope of its own ruin, on which trees and shrubbery have grown.</s> <s id="s405">The right hand precipice, however, has shelves affording sufficient hold for small trees; but nowhere does it slant.</s> <s id="s406">If it were not for the white little stream, tumbling softly downward, and for the[ 72] soft verdure up and down either precipice, and even along the very pathway of the cascade, it would be a very stern vista up that gorge.</s></p>
<p><s id="s407">I shall not try to describe it any more; it has not been praised too much, though it may have been praised amiss.</s> <s id="s408">I went thither again in the morning; and climbed a good way up through the midst of its rocky descent; and I think I could have reached the top in this way.</s> <s id="s409">It is remarkable that the leaps of the water, from one step of its broken staircase to another, gives an impression of softness and gentleness; but there are black, turbulent pools, among the great boulders, where the stream seems angry at the difficulties which it meets with.</s> <s id="s410">Looking upward, in the sunshine, I could see a little rising midst; and I should not wonder if a speck of rainbow were sometimes visible.</s> <s id="s411">I noticed one small oak in the bed of the cascade; and there is a lighter vegetation scattered up and down.</s></p>
<p><s id="s412">About noon, we took a car for <enamex sw="w78800" long="-3.153358511469882" lat="54.60105586584796" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11249032" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex>, and rode thither, back along the road to <enamex sw="w78854" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, through which we passed( stopping to get a package of letters from the Post Office) and reached <enamex sw="w78959" long="-3.153358511469882" lat="54.60105586584796" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11249032" name="Portinscale" conf="2.6">Portinscale</enamex>, which is a mile from <enamex sw="w78993" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s413">After dinner, we walked over a bridge and through a green lane, to the church where Southey is buried.</s> <s id="s414">It is a white church( lime-plastered, I believe) of <enamex  sw="w79157" name="Not a placename">Norman</enamex> architecture, with a low, square tower.</s> <s id="s415">As we approached, we saw two persons entering the porch; and following them[ 73] in, we found the sexton( a tall, thin old man, with white hair, and an intelligent, reverential face) showing the edifice to a stout, red-faced, self-important, good-natured John Bull of a gentleman.</s> <s id="s416">Without any question on our part, the old sexton immediately led us to Southey's monument, which is placed on a side-aisle, where there is not breadth for it to stand free of the walls; neither is it in a very good light.</s> <s id="s417">But it seemed to me a good work of art; - a recumbent figure of white marble, on a couch, the drapery of which he has drawn about him - being quite enveloped in what may be a sheet or a shroud.</s> <s id="s418">The sculptor has not intended to represent death; for the figure lies sidelong, and has a book in its hand, and the face is lifelike, and looks full of expression - a thin, high-featured poetic face, with a finely proportioned head, and abundant hair.</s> <s id="s419">It represents Southey( and rightly, at whatever age he died) in the full maturity of manhood, when he was strongest and richest.</s> <s id="s420">I liked the statue, and wished that it lay in a broad aisle, or in the chancel, where there is an old tomb of a knight and lady of the Ratcliffe family, who have held the place of honor long enough to yield it now to a poet.</s> <s id="s421">Southey's sculptor was <enamex sw="w80530" long="-6.42540431022644" lat="54.61563682556152" type="water" gazref="unlock:14140708" name="Lough Neagh" conf="0.7794157346">Lough</enamex>.</s> <s id="s422">I must not forget to mention that John Bull, climbing on a bench to get a better view of the statue, tumbled off with a racket that resounded irreverently through the church.</s></p>
<p><s id="s423">The old, white headed, thin sexton was a model man of his[ 74] class, and appeared to take a loving and cheerful interest in the church, and those who, from age to age, have worshipped and been buried there.</s> <s id="s424">It is a very ancient and interesting church.</s> <s id="s425">Within a few years, it has been thoroughly repaired, as to the interior; and now looks as if[ it] might endure ten more centuries; and I suppose we see little that is really old, except the double row of <enamex  sw="w81169" name="Not a placename">Norman</enamex> arches, in a light free-stone, that support the oaken beams and rafters of the roof.</s> <s id="s426">All the walls, however, are old, and quite preserve the identity of the edifice.</s> <s id="s427">There is a stained-glass window of modern manufacture; and in one of the side-windows, set amidst plain glass, there is a single pane, five hundred years old, representing <enamex  sw="w81514" name="Not a placename">Saint Anthony</enamex>, very finely executed, though it looks a little faded.</s> <s id="s428">Along the walls, on each side of the church, between the arched windows, there are marble-slabs, affixed, with inscriptions to the memories of those who used to occupy the seats beneath.</s> <s id="s429">I remember none of great antiquity, nor any old monument except that in the chancel, over the knight and lady of the Ratcliffe family.</s> <s id="s430">This consists of a slab of stone, on four small stone pillars about two feet high; the slab is inlaid with a brass-plate, on which is engraved the knight in armor, and the lady in the costume of Elizabeth's time, exceedingly well done and well preserved, and each figure as much a eighteen inches in length.</s> <s id="s431">The sexton produced a rubbing of them, on paper.</s> <s id="s432">Under the slab - which, supported by the low stone pillars, form a canopy for them - lie two sculptured figures of stone, of life-size and at full length,[ 75] representing this same knight and lady; but I think the sculptor was hardly equal in his art to the engraver.</s></p>
<p><s id="s433">The most curious antiquity in the church is the font.</s> <s id="s434">The bowl is very capacious, sufficiently so as to admit of the full immersion of a child of two or three months old.</s> <s id="s435">On the outside, in several compartments, there are bas-reliefs of scriptural and symbolic subjects - such as the Tree of Life - the word proceeding out of God's mouth - <enamex sw="w82872" long="-2.7725" lat="54.8089" type="other" gazref="unlock:5830453" name="The Crown Wetheral Hotel" conf="1.827282639">the Crown</enamex> of Thorns - in the quaintest taste, sculptured by some hand of a thousand years ago, and preserving the fancies of monkish brains in stone.</s> <s id="s436">The sexton was very proud of this font and ts sculptures, and took a kindly personal interest in showing it, as he does whatever is interesting in the church.</s> <s id="s437">And when we had spent as much time as we could, inside, he led us to Southey's grave in the churchyard.</s></p>
<p><s id="s438">The old man told us that he had known Southey long and well,( he being only twenty - nine when he came to <enamex sw="w83389" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> to reside) from early manhood to old age.</s> <s id="s439">He had known Wordsworth, too, and <enamex  sw="w83473" name="Not a placename">Coleridge</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w83488" long="-2.06484" lat="51.18067" type="other" gazref="unlock:13906759" name="Upton Lovell" conf="0.8119365129">Lovell</enamex>; and he has seen Southey and Wordsworth walking arm in arm together, in that churchyard.</s> <s id="s440">He seemed to revere Southey's memory, and said that he had been much lamented, and that there were as many as a hundred people in the churchyard, when he was buried.</s> <s id="s441">He spoke with great praise of Mrs. Southey, his first wife, telling of her charity to the poor, and how she was a blessing to the[ 76] neighborhood; but( for whatever reason) he said nothing in favor of the second Mrs. Southey, and only mentioned her selling the library and other things, after her husband's death, and going to <enamex sw="w84079" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.652744851">London</enamex>.</s> <s id="s442">Yet I think she was probably a good woman, and meets with less than justice, because she took the place of another good woman, and had not time and opportunity to prove herself as good.</s> <s id="s443">As for Southey himself, my idea is, that few better or more blameless men have ever lived, than he; but he seems to lack color, passion, warmth, or something that should enable me to bring him into close relation with myself.</s> <s id="s444">The church-yard, where he lies, is not so rural and picturesque as that where Wordsworth lies buried; although <enamex sw="w84610" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> rises behind it, and the Greta is murmuring at no very great distance away.</s> <s id="s445">But the churchyard itself has a somewhat cold and bare aspect; no shadow of trees, no shrubbery.</s></p>
<p><s id="s446"><enamex sw="w84791" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.319331067">Over</enamex> Southey's grave there is a ponderous, oblong block of slate, a native mineral of this region, as hard as iron, and which will doubtless last quite as long as Southey's works have any vitality in English Literature.</s> <s id="s447">It is not a monument fit for a poet - there is nothing airy or graceful about it - and, indeed, there cannot be many men so solid and matter-of-fact as to deserve a tomb like this.</s> <s id="s448">Wordsworth's grave is much better, with only a simple head-stone, and the grass growing over his mortality - which, for a thousand years, at least, it never can over Southey's.</s> <s id="s449">Most of the monument in the church77yard are of this same black slate; and some( erect head-stones) have curious sculptures, which seem to have been recently erected.</s></p>
<p><s id="s450">We now returned to the hotel, and took a car for the Valley of <enamex sw="w85599" long="-65.890278" lat="45.316111" type="other" gazref="unlock:5424240" name="Saint John, N. B." conf="1.086013376">Saint John</enamex>.</s> <s id="s451">The sky seemed to portend rain in no long time; and <enamex sw="w85663" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> had put on his cap; but the people of the hotel and the driver said that there would be no rain this afternoon - and their opinion proved correct.</s> <s id="s452">After riding a few miles, we again came within sight of the enchanted ruin.</s> <s id="s453">It appears to stand rather more than midway adown the declivity of one of the ridges( to the left, as you go southwards) that form the valley; and its site would have been a good one for a fortress intended to defend the lower entrance of this mountain defile.</s> <s id="s454">At a proper distance, it looks not unlike the gray dilapidation of a Gothic castle, which has been crumbling and crumbling away for ages, until Time might be supposed to have imperceptibly stolen its massive pile away from men, and give it back to Nature; its towers, and battlements, and arched entrances being so much defaced and decayed, that all marks of human labor had nearly been obliterated; and the angles of the hewn stones rounded away; while mosses, and weeds, and bushes, grow over it as freely as over a natural ledge of rocks.</s> <s id="s455">It is conceivable that, in some lights, and in some states of the atmosphere, a traveller, at the entrance of the valley, might really imagine that he be78held a castle here; but, for myself, I must acknowledge that it required a willing fancy, to make me see it.</s> <s id="s456">As we drew nearer, the illusion did not immediately grow less strong; but at length we found ourselves passing at the foot of the declivity, with its mimic towers right above us; and, behold! it was nothing but an enormous ledge of rock, coning squarely out of the hillside, with other parts of the ledge cropping out in its vicinity.</s> <s id="s457">Looking back, after passing, we saw a knoll or hillock, of which the castled rock is the bare face.</s> <s id="s458">There are two or three stone cottages along the road-side, beneath the magic castle, and within the enchanted ground.</s> <s id="s459">Scott, in the Bridal of <enamex sw="w87538" long="-2.633053662208513" lat="54.99136602961568" type="other" gazref="unlock:11306112" name="Triermain" conf="0.7682168932">Triermain</enamex>, locates the castle right in the middle of the valley, and makes King Arthur ride around it; - which any mortal horseman would find great difficulty in doing.</s></p>
<p><s id="s460">This Vale of <enamex sw="w87720" long="-65.890278" lat="45.316111" type="other" gazref="unlock:5424240" name="Saint John, N. B." conf="1.086013376">Saint John</enamex> is a very striking piece of scenery.</s> <s id="s461"><enamex sw="w87768" long="-3.0502" lat="54.6415" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="99992">Blencathara</enamex> shuts it in to the northward, lying right across the entrance; and on either side, there are lofty crags and declivities, those to the west being more broken, as I remember, and better wooded, than the ridge to the eastward, which stretches along for several miles, steep, high, and bare, producing only grass enough for sheep pasture, until is rises into the dark brow of <enamex sw="w88153" long="-3.043402327204126" lat="54.53913510713601" type="water" gazref="unlock:11169754" name="Helvellyn Gill" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex>.</s> <s id="s462">Adown this ridge - seen afar, like a white ribbon - comes here and there a cascade, sending its voice before it, which distance robs of all its fury, and makes it the quietest[ 79] sound in the world; and while you see the foamy leap of its upper course, a mile or two away, you may see and hear the self-same little brook babbling through a field, and passing through the arch of a rustic bridge, beneath your feet.</s> <s id="s463">It is a deep seclusion, with mountains and crags on all sides.</s></p>
<p><s id="s464">About a mile beyond the castle, we stopt at a little wayside inn - the King's Head - and put up for the night.</s> <s id="s465">This, I believe, is the only inn which I have found in <enamex  sw="w88810" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> - the only one, I mean, where I have eaten and slept - that does not call itself a hotel.</s> <s id="s466">It is very primitive in its arrangements; a long, low, white-washed, unadorned, and ugly cottage of two stories.</s> <s id="s467">At one extremity is a barn and cow-house, and next to these the part of the inn devoted to the better class of guests, where we had our parlor and sleeping chambers, contiguous to which is the kitchen, and common room of the ale-house, paved with flag-stones, and lastly another barn and stable - all which departments are not under separate roofs, but under the same long contiguity, and forming parts of the same building.</s> <s id="s468">Our parlor opens immediately upon the roadside, without any vestibule.</s> <s id="s469">The house appears to be of some antiquity, with beams across the low cielings[ sic]; but the people made us pretty comfortable at bed and board, and fed us with ham and eggs, veal-steaks, honey, oat-cakes, gooseberry-tarts, and such cates and dainties - making a moderate charge when we went away.</s> <s id="s470">The parlor was adorned[ 80] with rude engravings( I remember only a plate of the Duke of Wellington, at three stages of his life), and there were minerals, delved doubtless out of the hearts of the mountains, over the mantel-piece.</s> <s id="s471">The chairs were of an old fashion, and had very capacious bottoms.</s> <s id="s472">We were waited upon by two women-folks, who looked and acted not unlike the country-folk of <enamex sw="w90209" long="0.8543168303199488" lat="51.57184320258142" type="water" gazref="unlock:8792167" name="New England Creek" conf="1.279554775">New England</enamex> - say of <enamex sw="w90230" long="-71.63010787963867" lat="44.00276756286621" type="civila" gazref="unlock:14128190" name="New Hampshire" conf="2.427404263">New Hampshire</enamex> - except that they may have been a little more deferential.</s></p>
<p><s id="s473">While we remained there, I took various walks, to get a glimpse of <enamex sw="w90371" long="-3.043402327204126" lat="54.53913510713601" type="water" gazref="unlock:11169754" name="Helvellyn Gill" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex>, and a view of <enamex sw="w90396" long="-3.058857232315457" lat="54.5390008105236" type="water" gazref="unlock:11299411" name="Thirlmere" conf="2.4">Thirlmere</enamex> - which is rather two lakes than one, being so narrow, at one point, as to be crossed by a foot-bridge.</s> <s id="s474">Its shores are very picturesque, coming down abruptly upon it, and broken into crags and prominences, which view their shaggy faces in its mirror; and <enamex sw="w90661" long="-3.043402327204126" lat="54.53913510713601" type="water" gazref="unlock:11169754" name="Helvellyn Gill" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex> slopes steeply upward from its southern shore into the clouds.</s> <s id="s475">On its eastern bank, near the footbridge, stands Armboth House, which Miss <enamex  sw="w90809" name="Not a placename">Martineau</enamex> says is haunted; and I saw a painted board, at the entrance of the road which leads to it, advertising lodgings there.</s> <s id="s476">The ghosts, of course, pay nothing for their accommodations.</s></p>
<p><s id="s477">At noon, on the day after our arrival, Julian and I went to visit the enchanted castle; and we were so venturesome as to turn aside from the road, and ascend the declivity towards its walls - which, indeed, we hoped to surmount.</s> <s id="s478">It proved a very difficult undertaking, the site of the fortress being much higher, and of steeper as81cent, than we had supposed; but we did clamber upon what we took for the most elevated portion of the ruin, when, lo! we found that we had only taken one of the outworks, and that there was a gorge of the hill betwixt us and the main walls, while the citadel rose high above, at more than twice the elevation which we had climbed.</s> <s id="s479">Julian wished to go on; and I let him climb, till he appeared to have reached so steep and lofty a height that he hardly looked bigger than a monkey, and I should not at all have wondered had he come rolling down to the base of the rock were I sat.</s> <s id="s480">But neither did he get actually within the castle; though he might have done so, but for a high stone-fence, too difficult for him to climb, which runs from the rock, along the hillside.</s> <s id="s481">The sheep probably go thither much oftener than any other living thing; and to them we left the castle of <enamex sw="w92204" long="-65.890278" lat="45.316111" type="other" gazref="unlock:5424240" name="Saint John, N. B." conf="1.086013376">Saint John</enamex>, with a shrub waving from its battlements instead of a banner.</s></p>
<p><s id="s482">After dinner, we ordered a car from <enamex sw="w92314" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>; and while it was getting ready, I went to look at the River of <enamex sw="w92388" long="-65.890278" lat="45.316111" type="other" gazref="unlock:5424240" name="Saint John, N. B." conf="1.086013376">Saint John</enamex>, which, indeed, flows beside our inn, only just across the road, though it might well be overlooked, unless you specially looked for it.</s> <s id="s483">It is a brook, brawling over the stones, very much as brooks do in <enamex sw="w92603" long="0.8543168303199488" lat="51.57184320258142" type="water" gazref="unlock:8792167" name="New England Creek" conf="1.279554775">New England</enamex>; only we never think of calling them rivers there.</s> <s id="s484">I could easily have made a leap from shore to shore; and Julian scrambled across on no better footing than a rail.</s> <s id="s485">I believe I have complained of the[ 82] want of books in other parts of <enamex  sw="w92853" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>; but there is no want of them here, and they are always interesting, be they of what size they may.</s></p>
<p><s id="s486">We rode down the valley, and gazed at the vast slope of <enamex sw="w93017" long="-3.043402327204126" lat="54.53913510713601" type="water" gazref="unlock:11169754" name="Helvellyn Gill" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex>, and at <enamex sw="w93035" long="-3.058857232315457" lat="54.5390008105236" type="water" gazref="unlock:11299411" name="Thirlmere" conf="2.4">Thirlmere</enamex> beneath it, and at <enamex sw="w93064" long="-3.1197" lat="54.5025" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11135134" name="Eagle Crag" conf="99991">Eagle's Crag</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w93082" long="-3.1658" lat="54.4931" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11252886" name="Raven Crag" conf="99991">Raven's Crag</enamex>, which beheld themselves in it; and we cast many a look behind, at <enamex sw="w93162" long="-3.0502" lat="54.6415" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="99992">Blencathara</enamex>, and that noble brotherhood of mountains, out of the midst of which we came.</s> <s id="s487">But, to say the truth, I was weary of fine scenery; and it seemed to me that I had eaten a score of mountains, and quaffed down as many lakes, all in the space of two or three days; - and the natural consequence was a surfeit.</s> <s id="s488">There was scarcely a single place in all our tour, where I should not have been glad to spend a month; but, by flitting so quickly from one point to another, I lost all the more recondite beauties, and had come away without retaining even the surface of much that I had seen.</s> <s id="s489">I am slow to feel - slow, I suppose, to comprehend; and, like the anaconda, I need to lubricate any object a great deal, before I can swallow it and actually make it my own.</s> <s id="s490">Yet I shall always be glad of this tour, and shall wonder the more at <enamex  sw="w93998" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, which comprehends so much, such a rich variety, within its little bounds.</s> <s id="s491">If <enamex  sw="w94084" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> were all the world, it still would have been worth while for the Creator to have made it; and mankind would have no cause to[ 83] find fault with their abode - except that there is not room enough for so many as might be happy here.</s></p>
<p><s id="s492">We left the great inverted arch of the Valley behind us, looking back as long as we could at <enamex sw="w94418" long="-3.0502" lat="54.6415" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="99992">Blencathara</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w94435" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> over its shoulder; and the clouds were gathering over them, at our last glimpse.</s> <s id="s493">Passing by <enamex sw="w94535" long="-3.042257566142511" lat="54.49420285694539" type="other" gazref="unlock:11134276" name="Dunmail Raise" conf="2">Dunmail Raise</enamex>( a mound of stones over an old British King) we entered <enamex  sw="w94605" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, and soon had the vale of <enamex sw="w94644" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> before us, with the church where Wordsworth lies, and <enamex sw="w94707" long="-2.994852043565142" lat="54.44966001297723" type="other" gazref="unlock:11226054" name="Nab Scar" conf="2">Nab Scar</enamex> and <enamex sw="w94720" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275806" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex> Water, farther on.</s> <s id="s494">At <enamex sw="w94748" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, we took another car for <enamex sw="w94783" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, whither we drove along the eastern shore of <enamex sw="w94841" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s495">The superb scenery through with e had been passing made what we now saw look tame, although, a week ago, we should have thought it more than commonly interesting.</s> <s id="s496"><enamex sw="w95016" long="-2.993112822792783" lat="54.37776609422815" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167809" name="Hawkshead" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex> is the only village on our road; a little white-washed old town, with a white-washed old <enamex  sw="w95115" name="Not a placename">Norman</enamex> church, low, and with a low tower, on the same pattern with others that we have seen hereabouts.</s> <s id="s497">It was between seven and eight o clock when we reached <enamex sw="w95274" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, and heard Una's voice greeting us, and saw her head, crowned with a wreath of flowers, looking down at us out of the window of our parlour.</s></p>
<p><s id="s498">And to-day( Monday, July 23rd, I believe) I have finished this most incomplete and unsatisfactory record of what we have done and seen since Wednesday last.</s> <s id="s499">I am pretty well con84vinced that all attempts at describing scenery - especially mountain-scenery - are sheer nonsense.</s> <s id="s500">For one thing, the point of view being changed, the whole description which you made up from the previous point of view is immediately falsified.</s> <s id="s501">And when you have done your utmost, such items as those setting forth the scene in a play -" a mountainous country; in the distance a cascade tumbling over a precipice; in front a lake; on one side an ivy-covered cottage" - this dry detail brings the matter before one's mind['s] eye more effectually than all the art of word-painting.</s></p>
<p><s id="s502">July 27th, Friday</s> </p><p><s id="s503">We are still at <enamex sw="w96222" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>; and nothing has occured of remarkable interest; nor have we made any excursions, beyond moderate walks.</s> <s id="s504">Two days - Tuesday and Wednesday - have been rainy; and to-day there is more rain.</s> <s id="s505">We find such weather as tolerable here as it would probably be anywhere; but it passes rather heavily with the children; and, for myself, I should prefer sunshine, though Mr. Whites books afford me some resource, especially an odd volume of Ben Jonson's plays, containing" Volpone,"" The Alchemist,"" Bartholomew Fair," and others.</s> <s id="s506">The Alchemist is certainly a great play.</s> <s id="s507">We watch all arrivals, and other events, from our parlour window; - a stage-coach driving up, four times in the twenty - four hours, with its forlorn outsiders all saturated with rain; - the steamer from the head of the lake, landing a crowd of passengers,[ 85] who stroll up to the hotel, drink a glass of ale, lean over the parapet of the bridge, gaze at the flat stone which pave the bottom of the river, and then hurry back to the steamer again; - cars, phaetons, horsemen, all damped and disconsolate.</s> <s id="s508">There are a number of young men staying at the hotel, some of whom go forth in all the rain, fishing, and come back at nightfall, trudging heavily, but with creels on their backs that do not seem very heavy.</s> <s id="s509">Yesterday was fair, and enlivened us a good deal.</s> <s id="s510">Returning from a walk, in the forenoon, I found a troop of yeomanry Cavalry in the stable-yard of the hotel.</s> <s id="s511">They were the <enamex  sw="w97682" name="Large admin unit">North Lancashire</enamex> regiment, and were on their march to <enamex sw="w97736" long="-2.878238320350647" lat="53.5225887298584" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131229" name="Liverpool" conf="2.278480581">Liverpool</enamex>, for the purpose of drill.</s> <s id="s512">Not being old campaigners, their uniform and accoutrements were in so much the finer order, all bright and looking span-new; and they themselves were a body of handsome and stalwart young men; and it was pleasant to look at their helmets, and red-jackets, and carbines, and steel-scabbarded swords, and gallant steeds - all so martial in aspect - and to know that they were only play-soldiers, after all, and were never likely to do any warlike mischief or suffer any.</s> <s id="s513">By And-by, their bugles sounded, and they trotted away, wheeling over the ivy-grown stone-bridge, and disappearing behind the trees, on the <enamex sw="w98382" long="-2.774704304134491" lat="54.22656024374862" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11220135" name="Milnthorpe" conf="2.553106967">Milnthorpe</enamex>[ 86] road.</s> <s id="s514">Our host comes forth from his bar, with a bill, which he presents to an orderly sergeant, or some such official.</s> <s id="s515">He( the Host) then tells me that he himself once rode many years a trooper in this regiment, and that all his comrades( I think he said all - the greater part, at least) were larger men than himself.</s> <s id="s516">Yet Mr. Thomas White is a good-sized man, and now, at all events, rather over-weight for a dragoon.</s></p>
<p><s id="s517">Yesterday, too, came one of those bands of music that seem to itinerate everywhere about the country.</s> <s id="s518">They consisted of a young woman who played the harp, a bass-violin player, a fiddler, a flutist, and a bugler, besides a little child, of whom, I suppose, the woman was the mother.</s> <s id="s519">They sat down on the bench by the river-side, opposite the house, a played several tunes; and by-and-by, the waiter brought them a large pitcher of ale, which they quaffed with apparent satisfaction; though they seemed to be foreigners by their mustachios and sallow hue, and would perhaps have preferred a vinous potation.</s> <s id="s520">One would like to follow these people through their vagrant-life, and see them at meal-time and bed-time, and overhear their intercourse among themselves.</s> <s id="s521">All vagrants are interesting; and there seems to be a much greater variety of them here, than in <enamex  sw="w99676" name="Large admin unit">America</enamex> - people who cast themselves on fortune, and take whatever she gives, without a certainty of any87thing.</s> <s id="s522">I saw a travelling tinker, yesterday; - a man with a leather-apron, and a string of skewers hung at his girdle, and a pack over his shoulders in which, no doubt, were his tools and materials of trade.</s></p>
<p><s id="s523">It is remarkable what a natural interest everybody feel in fishing.</s> <s id="s524">An angler from the bridge immediately attracts a group to watch his luck; it is the same for Julian fishing for minnows; on the platform near which the steamer lands its passengers.</s> <s id="s525">By The-by, Una caught a minnow, last evening, and immediately after a good-sized perch - her first fish.</s></p>
<p><s id="s526">July 30th, Monday</s>
</p><p><s id="s527">We left <enamex sw="w100371" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, all of us, on Saturday and 12 o clock, and steamed up the river[ lake] to <enamex sw="w100459" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>; a pretty good day, as to weather, but with a little bit of a tendency to shower.</s> <s id="s528">There was nothing new on the lake, and no new impressions, as far as I remember.</s> <s id="s529">At <enamex sw="w100635" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, Mamma and Nurse went shopping; after which we took a carriage to <enamex sw="w100711" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, and established ourself at Browns Hotel there.</s> <s id="s530">I find that my impressions from our from our previous sight of all these scenes do not change on revision.</s> <s id="s531">They are very beautiful; but, if I must say it, I am a little weary of them.</s> <s id="s532">We soon tire of things which we visit merely by way of spectacle, and with which we have no real and permanent connec88tion.</s> <s id="s533">In such cases, we very quickly wish this spectacle to be taken away, and another substituted; - at all events, I do not care about seeing anything more of the English lakes, for at least a year to come.</s> <s id="s534">Besides, a man with children in charge cannot enjoy travelling; he must content himself to be happy with them, for they allow hm no separate and selfish possibility of being happy.</s> <s id="s535">Sophia, however, suffers far less from this impediment than I do, though she has to bear a great deal more of it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s536">Perhaps a part of my weariness of the lakes is owing to the hotel-life which we lead.</s> <s id="s537">At an English hotel, the traveller feels as if everybody, from the landlord downward, were in a joint and individual purpose of fleecing him; because all the attendants, who come in contact with him, are to be separately considered.</s> <s id="s538">So, after paying, in the first instance, a very heavy bill for what would seem to cover the whole indebtedness, there remain divers dues still to be paid, to no trifling amount, to the landlord's servants - dues not to be ascertained, and which you never know whether you have properly satisfied.</s> <s id="s539">You can know, perhaps, when you have less than satisfied them, by the aspect of the waiter, which I wish I could describe; - not disrespectful, in the slightest degree, but a look of profound surprise, a gaze at the offered coin( which he nevertheless pockets) as if[ 89] he either did not see it, or did not know it, or could not believe his eyesight; - all this, however, with the most quiet forbearance, a Christian like non-recognition of an unmerited wrong and insult; - and, finally( all in a moment's space indeed) he quits you and goes about his other business.</s> <s id="s540">If you have given too much, too, you are made sensible of your folly by the extra amount of his gratitude, and the bows with which he salutes you from the door-step.</s> <s id="s541">But, generally, you cannot very decidedly say whether you have been right or wrong; but, in almost all cases, you decidedly feel that you have been fleeced.</s> <s id="s542">Then the living at the best of the English hotels( so far as my travels have brought me acquainted with them) deserves but moderate praise, and is especially lacking in variety.</s> <s id="s543">Nothing but joints, joints, joints; sometimes, perhaps, a meat pie, which, if you eat it, weighs upon your conscience with the idea that you have eaten the scraps and rejected relics of other people's dinners.</s> <s id="s544">At the lake-hotels, the fare( with the exception of trout, which are not always fresh, and which one soon tires of, at any rate) is mutton.</s> <s id="s545">The English seem to have no conception of better living than this.</s> <s id="s546">What must they think of the American hotels!</s></p>
<p><s id="s547">We spent the day, yesterday, at <enamex sw="w103756" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> in little quiet walks about[ 90] the hotel; and at a little past six, in the afternoon, I took my departure in the stage-coach from <enamex sw="w103897" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s548">The coach was awfully overburthened with outside passengers - fifteen, I think, in all.</s> <s id="s549">besides the four insiders - and one of the fifteen formed toe apex of an immense pile of baggage on the top.</s> <s id="s550">It seems to me miraculous that we did not topple over; the road being so hilly and uneven, and the driver, I suspect, none the steadier for his visits to all the tap-rooms along the road from <enamex sw="w104298" long="-3.356649935752379" lat="54.66186838800157" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11111547" name="Cockermouth" conf="2.534248644">Cockermouth</enamex>.</s> <s id="s551">There was a tremendous vibration of the coach, now and then; and I saw that, in case of our gong over, I should be flung headlong against the high stone-fence, that, in English fashion, bordered most of the road.</s> <s id="s552">In view of this, I determined to muffle my head in the folds of my thick shawl, at the moment of over - turn; and as I could do no better for myself, I awaited my fate with equanimity.</s> <s id="s553">As far as apprehension goes, I had rather travel from <enamex sw="w104762" long="-69.02811813354492" lat="45.27190208435059" type="civila" gazref="unlock:14125786" name="Maine" conf="2.121922937">Maine</enamex> to <enamex sw="w104771" long="-83.5001803" lat="32.7504171" type="civila" gazref="geonames:4197000" name="Georgia" conf="2.21637142">Georgia</enamex> by rail, than from <enamex sw="w104798" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> to <enamex sw="w104810" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> by stage-coach.</s></p>
<p><s id="s554">At Lowwood, the landlady espied me from the window, and sent out a large packet that had arrived by mail; but, as it was directed to some person of the Christian name of William, I did not venture to open it.</s> <s id="s555">She said, also, that a gentleman had been here who very earnestly desired to see me;[ 91] and I have since reason to suppose that this was <enamex sw="w105185" long="-84.3404824" lat="36.0275778" type="other" gazref="unlock:7345381" name="Allingham" conf="0.6604224632">Allingham</enamex>, the poet.</s> <s id="s556">We got to <enamex sw="w105216" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> at about half past seven, and waited nearly an hour for the train to start.</s> <s id="s557">I took a ticket for <enamex sw="w105323" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex>, and arrived there at ten; and talked about the war with a gentleman on the Coffee room,( who took me for an Englishman, as most people do, nowadays) and heard from him - as you may from all his countrymen - an expression of weariness and dissatisfaction with the whole business.</s> <s id="s558">These fickle islanders! How differently they talked a year ago! John bull sees, now, that he never was in a worse fix in his life; and yet it would not take much snort as bellicosely as ever.</s> <s id="s559">I went to bed at eleven, and slept unquietly on feathers.</s> <s id="s560">The English know as little how to sleep as to eat.</s></p>
<p><s id="s561">I had purpose to rise betimes, and see the town of <enamex sw="w105965" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> before breakfast.</s> <s id="s562">But here I reckoned without my host; for, in the first place, I had no water for my ablutions, and my boots were not brushed; and so I could not get down stairs till the hour I named for my coffee and chops; - and, secondly, the breakfast was delayed half an hour, though promised every minute.</s> <s id="s563">In fine, I had but just time to take a hasty walk around <enamex sw="w106345" long="-2.80569" lat="54.04996" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825252" name="Lancaster Castle" conf="2">Lancaster Castle</enamex>, and see what[ 92] I could of the town on my way; - a not very remarkable little town, built of stone, with taller houses than in the middle shires of <enamex  sw="w106513" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, modern fronts, narrow streets, up and down an eminence on which <enamex sw="w106586" long="-2.890464102233929" lat="53.18298073394839" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11101187" name="Castle, The" conf="1.020347071">the Castle</enamex> is situated, with the town immediately about it.</s> <s id="s564">The castle is a satisfactory edifice, but so renovated that the walls look almost entirely modern, with the exception of the fine old front, with the statue of an armed warrior( John of Gaunt himself, very likely) in a niche over the <enamex  sw="w106880" name="Not a placename">Norman</enamex> arch of the entrance.</s> <s id="s565">Close beside <enamex sw="w106922" long="-2.890464102233929" lat="53.18298073394839" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11101187" name="Castle, The" conf="1.020347071">the Castle</enamex> stands what looks like an old church.</s></p>
<p><s id="s566">The train left <enamex sw="w106986" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> at half past nine, and reached <enamex sw="w107027" long="-2.878238320350647" lat="53.5225887298584" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131229" name="Liverpool" conf="2.278480581">Liverpool</enamex>( over as flat and uninteresting a country as I ever travelled) at twelve.</s> <s id="s567">I have betaken myself to the Rock Ferry Hotel, where I am as comfortable as I could be anywhere but at home; but it is rather comfortless to think of home as three years off and three thousand miles away.</s> <s id="s568">With what a sense of utter weariness - not fully realized till then - we shall sink down on our threshold, when we reach it.</s> <s id="s569">The moral effect of being without a settled abode is very wearisome.</s></p>
<p><s id="s570">Our coachman from <enamex sw="w107528" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex> to <enamex sw="w107540" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> looked like a great beer-barrel, oozy with his proper liquor.</s> <s id="s571">I suppose such solid soakers never get upset.</s></p>
</text>
</document>