<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1776_a"><p><s id="s1">An Excursion To The Lakes In <enamex  sw="w41" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w58" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>; With A Tour Through Part of the Northern Counties, In the Years 1773 and 1774.</s> </p><p><s id="s2">By W. Hutchinson.</s> </p><p><s id="s3"><enamex sw="w167" long="-0.08573711413610305" lat="51.48768230024373" type="civila" gazref="unlock:13326794" name="Greater London Authority" conf="2.736045777">London</enamex>:</s> </p><p><s id="s4">Printed for J. Wilkie, No. 71, St Paul's Church Yard, and W. Charnley, in <enamex sw="w249" long="-1.66667" lat="55" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00027" name="Newcastle upon Tyne" conf="99991">Newcastle</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s5">Mdcclxxvi.</s></p>
<p><s id="s6">An Excursion,&amp; c.</s> </p><p><s id="s7">Whenever I have read the descriptions given by travellers of foreign countries, in which their beauties and antiquities were lavishly praised, I have always regretted a neglect which has attended the delightful scenes in this island.</s> <s id="s8">The monuments of antiquity, dispersed over this country, are many and curious, some of them arose in the remotest ages, and point out to us the revolutions and history of our own kingdom: a degree of knowledge of the first importance to Englishmen.</s></p>
<p><s id="s9">The rapid progress of cultivation in the northern counties, within this century, threatens the destruction of many of their antique remains;-- the plough share has already in many places gone over them, and perhaps in another age not even their names will remain to denote their site.</s> <s id="s10">-- To preserve their memory to after times, to point out therefore, and describe their strength, form, and magnitude, I humbly presume, are no insignificant pursuits in the traveller, who thereby consigns to posterity the evidence of those circumstances in history, which will be momentous to all ages.</s></p>
<p><s id="s11">Such sentiments gave rise to a summer's excursion, the pleasures of which I have endeavoured to communicate to the reader in the following pages.</s></p>
<p><s id="s12">We were conducted to <enamex sw="w1528" long="-2.011007926764902" lat="54.51739841270697" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33908" name="Bowes" conf="5.1">Bowes</enamex> in <enamex  sw="w1537" name="Large admin unit">Yorkshire</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s13"><enamex sw="w1548" long="-2.011007926764902" lat="54.51739841270697" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33908" name="Bowes" conf="5.1">Bowes</enamex></s> </p><p><s id="s14">Is of great antiquity, in which is its chief consequence.</s> <s id="s15">-- The country around is meanly cultivated, its habitations in general melancholy; and what alone claims the attention of a traveller, is the ruin of a castle, supposed by some of Roman construction; but with greater propriety by others, to be the Turris de Arcubus, built by Alan, first Earl of Richmond, in the time of the Conqueror: It is situate near the old high street, which led from the Cataractonium of the Romans.</s></p>
<p><s id="s16">This castle is fifty three feet in height, built of hewn stone, of excellent workmanship, forming a square of equal sides, eighty one feet each; the windows are irregular; and the walls, which are cemented with lime mixed with small flints, are near five feet in thickness-- it is now much defaced, the outward casing being stript off in many places.</s> <s id="s17">-- This edifice appears to have been divided into several apartments, the principal of which was vaulted, and supported by a central pillar.</s></p>
<p><s id="s18"><enamex sw="w2530" long="-2.01341" lat="54.51663" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825301" name="Bowes Castle" conf="1">Bowes Castle</enamex> is situated on the brink of a hill, declining swiftly to the southward, at whose foot runs the <enamex sw="w2638" long="-3.049780772201727" lat="54.61773088322941" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791217" name="River Greta" conf="2.356355863">River Greta</enamex>;-- it is surrounded with a deep ditch, beyond which, on the southern side, is an open area or platform, extending from the castle-moat ninety paces: and from east to west one hundred paces: the angles are obtuse, and a wide access appears in the centre.</s> <s id="s19">-- On examination, this is indisputably proved to be the remains of the Roman station, the Vallum having formed a strong outwork to the castle, of great height towards the south.</s> <s id="s20">-- This kind of situation was in many places chosen for erecting fortresses, after the departure of the Romans; several castles which we viewed on our tour, are so placed.</s> <s id="s21">-- On the eastern point of the station, we were shewn the site and remains of a <enamex sw="w3336" long="-2.495914459228516" lat="51.34663200378418" type="civila" gazref="unlock:14121725" name="Bath and North East Somerset" conf="2.272743152">Bath</enamex>, with its aqueduct, which are now totally in ruins, and overgrown with weeds and brambles-- the foundations shew the building to have been thirty feet long within, and twenty broad, with a small apartment to the east fifteen feet square; the access from the south.</s></p>
<p><s id="s22">On a late inclosure of some common lands belonging <enamex sw="w3658" long="-2.011007926764902" lat="54.51739841270697" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33908" name="Bowes" conf="5.1">Bowes</enamex>, an ancient aqueduct was discovered, which conveyed the water the distance of two miles from a place called <enamex sw="w3772" long="19.5333333" lat="63.5833333" type="other" gazref="unlock:3962844" name="Levar" conf="0.1456315685">Levar</enamex>, or <enamex sw="w3782" long="-2.054095418374096" lat="54.53463475785163" type="other" gazref="unlock:11194405" name="Levy Pool" conf="1">Levy Pool</enamex>, to the castle, sufficient to supply the garrison and also the baths.</s> <s id="s23">This discovery led me, in the succeeding year, to <enamex sw="w3912" long="19.5333333" lat="63.5833333" type="other" gazref="unlock:3962844" name="Levar" conf="0.1456315685">Levar</enamex> Pool, in hopes I should find, in that sequestered and little-visited place, some remains of Roman Work not known to antiquaries, and fix the site of the baths of Lavatrae, especially as some adjoining lands bear the name of Lavartree, or Laretree; but my expectations were disappointed, nothing but vast works of ancient stone quarries were to be seen; from whence, in all probability, the materials for building the Roman Vallum and the present castle were won.</s></p>
<p><s id="s24">Antiquaries have hithero fixed the ancient Lavatrae at <enamex sw="w4436" long="-2.011007926764902" lat="54.51739841270697" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33908" name="Bowes" conf="5.1">Bowes</enamex>, that place corresponding with the distances set out in the Itinerarie.</s> <s id="s25">-- The antiquity of <enamex sw="w4534" long="-2.011007926764902" lat="54.51739841270697" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33908" name="Bowes" conf="5.1">Bowes</enamex> is confirmed by the great number of Roman coins found there, Plate I. and Ii.</s> <s id="s26">for several of which I am indebted to the Gentlemen of that place; particularly the late Charles <enamex sw="w4715" long="-118.1059034" lat="34.231948" type="other" gazref="unlock:8109099" name="Mount Lowe" conf="0.7531203919">Lowe</enamex> Whytell, Esq; who since the first publication discovered them, in laying the foundations of a summer seat; and forming his garden ground near the old castle.</s></p>
<p><s id="s27">The uppermost coin represented in Plate I. is a consular medallion of Hadrian, of the old mixed brass, supposed to be struck on the first day of January, a day sacred to Janus, and observed by the Romans with great solemnity, as portentive of the felicity or adversity of the new year.</s> <s id="s28">It would be tedious to describe the whole, as they are accurately shewn in the Plate.</s> <s id="s29">The letters placed above each denote the metal.</s></p>
<p><s id="s30">Several parts of earthen vessels have also been dug up here, of the red kind; by placing many of the fragments together, I have been able to form such parts of two of them as are represented in Plate Ii.</s> <s id="s31">One of the vessels, when entire, has been about twelve inches over the brim, the other about ten: the figures are finely relieved, and the red glazing pretty well preserved-- I am inclined to think these have been sacred vessels, the one dedicated to the service of <enamex  sw="w5769" name="Not a placename">Venus</enamex>, the other to Diana; they were used as the Urceus, and held the water with which the people were sprinkled.</s> <s id="s32">-- Mr Addison in his travels, says, that on many altars he perceived the <enamex sw="w5956" long="-119.7829164" lat="34.4411081" type="other" gazref="unlock:8104229" name="La Patera Catholic Cemetery" conf="0.4779098946">Patera</enamex> was formed without any handle: the form of these vessels, and the figures with which they are ornamented, will not allow a conjecture that they were sepulchral:-- the festival of the Roman Hunters, sacred to Diana, and for which service one of the vessels appears to be adapted, was celebrated on the thirteenth day of August.</s></p>
<p><s id="s33">Camden says, he saw an altar to the honour of Hadrian in the church at <enamex sw="w6362" long="-2.011007926764902" lat="54.51739841270697" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33908" name="Bowes" conf="5.1">Bowes</enamex>, with this inscription:</s></p>
<p><s id="s34">Imp Caesari Divi Traiani Parthici maxfilio Divi Nervae Nepoti Traiano Hadria No Aug.</s> <s id="s35"><enamex sw="w6477" long="-3.034677191253732" lat="51.69822667260078" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11247932" name="Pontypool/Pont-y-pwl" conf="1.516659272">Pont</enamex>.</s> <s id="s36">Maxim-- Cos I-- Pp-- Coh.</s> <s id="s37">Iiii F-- Io.</s> <s id="s38"><enamex sw="w6521" long="36.1833333" lat="36.1166667" type="other" gazref="unlock:2240900" name="Sev" conf="0.07882317606">Sev</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s39">From the most diligent search, I could find no such inscription;-- he says the following fragment was also found there:</s></p>
<p><s id="s40">------------ <enamex sw="w6665" long="6.869305" lat="46.029625" type="other" gazref="unlock:5822460" name="Le Gros Nol" conf="0.3840347648">Nol</enamex>. <enamex sw="w6671" long="-2.918380207649255" lat="51.67221587397922" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11095535" name="Cae Cnap" conf="1.4">Cae</enamex>---- Frontinvs-- Coh. I. Thrac.</s></p>
<p><s id="s41">Sir Robert Cotton obtained from thence an altar thus inscribed:</s></p>
<p><s id="s42">Dae Fortvnae-- pro Deae.</s> <s id="s43">-------- Virivs Lvpvs-- Propraetor under Leg.</s> <s id="s44">Aug.</s> <s id="s45">Pr.</s> <s id="s46">Pr.</s> <s id="s47">Severus.</s> <s id="s48">Balinevm Vi-- pro Balneum.</s> <s id="s49">Ignis Exvst Vm.</s> <s id="s50">Coh.</s> <s id="s51">Ithr Acvm Rest Itvit Cvran Teval.</s> <s id="s52">Fron Tone Praef Eq. Alae Vetto-- the Vettones were a people of <enamex  sw="w7015" name="Large admin unit">Spain</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s53">-- He thought this so curious, that he removed it to <enamex sw="w7075" long="-3.0667" lat="54.3667" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2652457" name="Coniston" conf="99991">Connington</enamex>.</s> <s id="s54">From this inscription we may determine, that whilst Virius Lupus ruled as Lieutenant General and Propraetor of <enamex  sw="w7198" name="Large admin unit">Britain</enamex>, under Severus the Emperor, the first cohort of the Thracians lay here in garrison, for whose use he restored the hot baths.</s> <s id="s55">This place was also garrisoned by a Numerus Exploratorum in the time of the Notitia.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s56">Camden's Britannia.</s></p>
<p><s id="s57">The modern name of <enamex sw="w7457" long="-2.011007926764902" lat="54.51739841270697" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33908" name="Bowes" conf="5.1">Bowes</enamex> we may with some degree of propriety derive from the authority of an ancient manuscript belonging the dissolved monastry of St Mary's in <enamex sw="w7600" long="" lat="" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:9659" name="" conf="99991">York</enamex>:</s></p>
<p><s id="s58">" Alanus niger Comes Richmondiae," unus fundatorum hujus monasterii, frater" fuit Ducis Britanniae, intravitq; Angliam" in Exercieu Willielmi Conquestoris;" cui dictus Willielmus contulit," pro servicio suo, Dominium&amp; Comitatum" Richmondiae: et postea idem Alanus" primus Comes Richmondiae, in defensionem" Tenentium suorum Comitatus" praedicti, contra expugnationes hominum" de <enamex  sw="w7996" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex> et <enamex  sw="w8012" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>" rebellantium, contra dictuna Conquestorem," ac cum Gospatricio Duce Northumbriae" adherentium Regi Scotorum," aedificavit sibi Turrim de Arcubus, in" quo constituit Guillermum consanguineum" suum praefectum super 500 sagittarios;" et dedit ei, seutum proprium" cum armis Britanniae, et tres arcus desuper," ac unum bundellum sagittarum," pro capitali insigni suo: ipse Guillermus" exindè nuncupatus fuit, Guillermus de" Arcubus."</s></p>
<p> <s id="s59">He was Ancestor to the famous and knightly family of <enamex sw="w8520" long="-2.011007926764902" lat="54.51739841270697" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33908" name="Bowes" conf="5.1">Bowes</enamex> in the Bishoprie of <enamex sw="w8546" long="-1.799652099609375" lat="54.67715454101562" type="civila" gazref="unlock:14121708" name="Durham" conf="2.246518605">Durham</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s60">The antient custom of Thorotoll is still preserved here, though the fortress is no longer maintained, or of use to the country; which was the original consideration for a tax, now become grievous to the public:-- the right of execution and the ancient power of the <enamex sw="w8820" name="Furca">Furca</enamex> were happily extinguished with the Feudal tenures.</s></p>
<p><s id="s61">From <enamex sw="w8882" long="-2.011007926764902" lat="54.51739841270697" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33908" name="Bowes" conf="5.1">Bowes</enamex> advancing towards <enamex  sw="w8906" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, we were respited from the sad scene of barrenness which we were obliged to pass, by some infant inclosures and attempts towards cultivation;-- the climate, dreary vicinage of mountains, and inclement skies, seemed to deny industry her natural rewards.</s></p>
<p><s id="s62">About two miles from <enamex sw="w9194" long="-2.011007926764902" lat="54.51739841270697" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33908" name="Bowes" conf="5.1">Bowes</enamex> is a singular curiosity, called Gods Bridge, being a natural bridge of limestone rock, where, through a rude arch, sixteen feet in span, the <enamex sw="w9342" long="-3.049780772201727" lat="54.61773088322941" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791217" name="River Greta" conf="2.356355863">River Greta</enamex> precipitates its waters;-- the way formed on the crown of this rock is about twenty feet wide, and the common carriage road over the river.</s> <s id="s63">-- After the Greta has passed this bridge, at a little distance it gains a subterraneous passage for near half a mile; and in a lineal direction breaks out again, through the cavities of the rocks.</s> <s id="s64">A few scanty meadows border the river, and cultivation seems to awake from ignorance over the adjoining lands; where the plough share begins to make the traces of industry on the skirts of the desert.</s></p>
<p><s id="s65">As we proceeded, <enamex sw="w9911" long="-1.048131694698255" lat="54.24543943862314" type="water" gazref="unlock:8773339" name="Spittle Beck" conf="1.232340506">Spittle</enamex> presented its solitary edifice to view; behind which, <enamex sw="w9973" long="-2.255019919860124" lat="54.53437804794765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11233065" name="North Stainmore" conf="2.6">Stainmore</enamex> arises; whose heights feel the fury of both eastern and western storms;-- a dreary prospect extended to the eye, the hills were cloathed in heath, and all around a scene of barrenness and deformity;-- the lower grounds were rent with torrents, which impetuously poured from the steeps in winter; and chasms harrowed on the sides of hills, yawned with ragged rocks, or black and rotten earth.</s> <s id="s66">-- Here and there scattered plots of grass variegated the prospect, where a few sheep found pasturage; and now and then a little rill was seen in the deep dell, which as it flowed in disconsolate meanders, was tinged with the sable soil through which it passed.</s> <s id="s67">-- No habitation for mankind appeared on either side, but all was wilderness and horrid waste, over which the wearied eye travelled with anxiety.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s68">At this place was an ancient Hospital, called Rerecross Hospital, or the <enamex sw="w10859" long="9.79692935943604" lat="48.9067195522402" type="other" gazref="unlock:4299862" name="Spittel hof" conf="0.288570052">Spittel</enamex> upon <enamex sw="w10872" long="-2.255019919860124" lat="54.53437804794765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11233065" name="North Stainmore" conf="2.6">Stainmore</enamex>, which was given to the Nunnery of Maryke before 1171, by Ralph, son of Ralph de Multon, or by Conan Earl of Richmond, and continued parcel of their possessions till dissolution.</s> <s id="s69">It was granted 7 Ed Vi.</s> <s id="s70">to William Buckton and Roger Marshall.</s> <s id="s71">-- Vide Monast.</s> <s id="s72">Vol.</s> <s id="s73">I. p.</s> <s id="s74">485.</s> <s id="s75">-- Dugdale's Baron, Vol.</s> <s id="s76">I. p.</s> <s id="s77">270.</s> <s id="s78">-- <enamex sw="w11195" long="-72.17730450000001" lat="42.6556417" type="other" gazref="unlock:7678470" name="Gale Hill" conf="0.7502958641">Gale</enamex>'s Appendix to Richmond, p.</s> <s id="s79">86.</s></p>
<p><s id="s80">At the turnpike-house on <enamex sw="w11256" long="-2.255019919860124" lat="54.53437804794765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11233065" name="North Stainmore" conf="2.6">Stainmore</enamex> stands a cylindrical stone, which appears to have been a Roman guide post; the inscription has had relation to a Coh.</s> <s id="s81">V. but is in every other part so obliterated that it cannot now be made out.</s> <s id="s82">We approached Roy Cross, which is said to be the boundary stone dividing <enamex  sw="w11535" name="Large admin unit">Yorkshire</enamex> from <enamex  sw="w11550" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s83">-- Hector Boetius has described this to be the meer-stone, erected at the time that William the Conqueror granted <enamex  sw="w11678" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> to the Scots, on condition they should hold it of him by homage, and a compact not to engage in any measures prejudicial to the crown of <enamex  sw="w11826" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s> <s id="s84">-- This cross stands within the remains of a large entrenchment, defended by banks of earth ten paces wide, through which the present turnpike road now passes.</s> <s id="s85">Plate Iii.</s> <s id="s86">fig. I.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s87">Camden's Britannia.</s></p>
<p><s id="s88">Its form is an oblong square, extending from north to south, with two openings on every side of the square, exactly opposite each other, defended by a mound of earth, placed in the front of each pass, rising from the plane about five perpendicular feet, which is near the height of the entrenchment in its highest part.</s></p>
<p><s id="s89">-- The eastern side is two hundred and seventy paces in length, the openings on the sides are ten paces wide, the moles which defend the same thirty - six paces in circumference, and stand ten paces from the outward edge of the entrenchment: the ascent of the adjoining ground on this side is gradual for near half a mile.</s></p>
<p><s id="s90">-- The northern end is two hundred and forty - nine paces in length, with two openings therein, defended by moles of earth, similar to those on the eastern quarter; and as the ground here is flat for a considerable distance, so this part of the entrenchment was by nature rendered inaccessable from the North by a deep morass.</s></p>
<p><s id="s91">-- The western side is similar to those before described, being two hundred and seventy - eight paces in length, standing on a swift descent, which falls without intermission for half a mile or upwards.</s></p>
<p><s id="s92">-- The southern end is in length one hundred and eighty - one paces, has its openings and moles as before described, but stands on the brink of a precipice of considerable height:-- on the highest ground within the entrenchment is a large mound of earth, of a square figure, arising from the plane near three perpendicular feet, and in circumference fifty - three paces.</s></p>
<p><s id="s93">We have little or no account of this entrenchment in history, and are left to conjecture to what people it might belong.</s> <s id="s94">-- As it lies on the Roman road, it strikes one with an apprehension, that it was of Roman original; but the singularity of the passes and mounds which guard them, do not correspond with their usual mode of fortifying a camp, though the interior mound may not improperly be regarded as the Praetorium.</s> <s id="s95">From the conflicts between the northern English and the <enamex sw="w14049" long="-3.335945419297682" lat="50.82184584866096" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25948" name="Norman'S Green" conf="1.27774047">Normans</enamex> after the conquest, and prior to William's ceding <enamex  sw="w14107" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> to the Scots, it may be conceived this was a camp of one of those powers.</s> <s id="s96">I remember to have read in some author whose name I cannot at this instant recollect, that on this ground <enamex  sw="w14298" name="Not a placename">Egbert</enamex> fought a battle with the Picts, and in memory of his victory the Roy Cross was erected.</s></p>
<p><s id="s97">About the year one thousand and sixty - seven William the Conqueror and Malcolm King of <enamex  sw="w14480" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex> concluded a peace at <enamex sw="w14510" long="-1.66667" lat="55" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00027" name="Newcastle upon Tyne" conf="99991">Newcastle</enamex> under these conditions, that King Malcolm should enjoy that part of <enamex  sw="w14588" name="Large admin unit">Northumberland</enamex> which lieth between Tweede, <enamex  sw="w14631" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, and Stainmoor, and to do homage to the King of England for the same.</s> <s id="s98">In the midst of <enamex sw="w14728" name="Stanemore">Stanemore</enamex> there shall be a cross set up, with the King of England's image on the one side, and the King of Scotland's on the other, to signify that one is marche to <enamex  sw="w14893" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, and the other to <enamex  sw="w14919" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s99">-- This cross was called the Recrosse, that is to say, the Crossé of the Kings.</s></p>
<p><s id="s100">Vide Hollinshed's Chronicle of <enamex  sw="w15040" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>, p.</s> <s id="s101">255.</s></p>
<p><s id="s102">As we travelled from thence for several miles, all around was one continued melancholy scene;-- the hills encreasing in height, the vallies in depth and desolation;-- the wind sounded amongst the rocks, whilst a heavy vapour in some parts clouded their summits; in others driving rain was seen streaming along the dales, and shrowding their gloomy recesses:-- the wearied mind of the traveller endeavours to evade such objects, and please itself with the fancied images of verdant plains, purling streams, and happy groves to which we were approaching:-- whilst we were thus engaged, unexpectedly the scene opened, and from such a horrid wild, gave us a prospect as delightful as the other was disgusting.</s></p>
<p><s id="s103"><enamex sw="w15768" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.318660087">Over</enamex> a rugged and rocky foreground, we looked upon <enamex sw="w15819" long="-2.23822" lat="54.53162" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00205" name="Stainmore" conf="99992">Stainmore Dale</enamex> in front; her verdant meadows cheared the eye; her sweet sequestered cottages, her grassy plains, and little shades of sycamores, seemed enchanting, as their beauties were enhanced by the deformity from which they had escaped.</s> <s id="s104">On the right hand a mountain arises, hiding its grey head and naked brow in clouds; the sides are barren rocks, in whose chinks a few shrubs are seen clinging, and cast a teint of green to variegate the grey precipice.</s> <s id="s105">-- On a wild and forlorn situation, in an opening on the side of this mountain, <enamex sw="w16360" name="Hellbeck Hall">Hellbeck Hall</enamex> is descried, covered with trees: the place seems calculated for discontent, and hid from all that's chearful, befitted to a mind full of disappointment and despair; all its prospect, is barrenness; the voice of water-falls, breezes mourning in the branches of the copse, or hissing in the fissures of the rock, its music; the deep shadows render it gloomy; and overhanging vapours, damp and dreary.</s></p>
<p><s id="s106">-- Yet <enamex sw="w16780" long="-2.316841984347655" lat="54.53423192209492" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11169517" name="Helbeck" conf="2.6">Helbeck</enamex> has its beauties;-- it contrasts with the vale beneath, where the extensive plain reaches the very bounds of <enamex  sw="w16898" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, whose lofty mountains we perceived, tinged with blue vapours, and mixing their summits with the sky.</s> <s id="s107">-- In the foreground lay</s></p>
<p><s id="s108"><enamex sw="w17036" long="-2.317311763232068" lat="54.52390316061246" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36930" name="Brough" conf="2.6">Brough</enamex>,</s> </p><p><s id="s109">whose ancient castle, formerly the seat of the <enamex sw="w17091" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex> family, afforded a noble object; around which, rich meadows drest in fresh verdure after mowing, plots of ripening corn, sparkling sheets of water, seen through the trees which decked their margins, the windings of each brook, little groves of ash and sycamore, fantastically dispersed and intermixed with villages and cots, formed the beauties of the vale; on this hand extending towards Kirby Stephen, on that to <enamex sw="w17516" long="-2.487921679387925" lat="54.62354239597875" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11133347" name="Dufton" conf="2.6">Dufton</enamex>, and in front as far as <enamex sw="w17548" long="-2.744010531" lat="54.67519654" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00131" name="Penrith Beacon" conf="99992">Penrith Beacon</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s110">As we began to descend the hill towards <enamex sw="w17604" long="-2.317311763232068" lat="54.52390316061246" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36930" name="Brough" conf="2.6">Brough</enamex>, and leave the deserts of <enamex sw="w17637" long="-2.255019919860124" lat="54.53437804794765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11233065" name="North Stainmore" conf="2.6">Stainmore</enamex>, we passed an antient Roman Fortification, called <enamex sw="w17697" long="-2.859445701781605" lat="54.61248739676893" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11211002" name="Maiden Castle" conf="2.2">Maiden Castle</enamex>-- the Roman road led immediately through it-- its form is square, built of stone, each side forty paces in length;-- it is defended by outworks, the nearest being a small ditch with a breastwork of large stones set erect, and the outward one a ditch and rampart of earth.</s> <s id="s111">This place has been of great strength in former times, from its natural situation, commanding the pass from <enamex sw="w18094" long="-2.317311763232068" lat="54.52390316061246" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36930" name="Brough" conf="2.6">Brough</enamex>.</s> <s id="s112">-- The ascent on the side opposite to <enamex sw="w18140" long="-2.317311763232068" lat="54.52390316061246" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36930" name="Brough" conf="2.6">Brough</enamex>, is very steep for more than a mile; to the South it is inaccessable, by reason of the precipice on whose brink it stands; and towards the North, the ground is every where rugged and mountainous.</s> <s id="s113">-- Camden says, the Roman road led from hence to Cave Vorran, in <enamex  sw="w18409" name="Large admin unit">Northumberland</enamex>. Plate Iii.</s> <s id="s114">fig. 2.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s115">Camden's Britannia.</s></p>
<p><s id="s116"><enamex sw="w18466" long="-2.317311763232068" lat="54.52390316061246" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36930" name="Brough" conf="2.6">Brough</enamex></s> </p><p><s id="s117">Is now divided into two small mean towns, the one called <enamex sw="w18530" long="-2.316702839313971" lat="54.51625634290234" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11106911" name="Church Brough" conf="2.6">Church Brough</enamex>, the other <enamex  sw="w18555" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Market Brough</enamex>, separated by a little brook which falls into the <enamex sw="w18619" long="-2.690643106095647" lat="54.70344735935878" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270317" name="River Eden" conf="2.4">River Eden</enamex>.</s> <s id="s118">-- Husbandry is little advanced here; the management of grass land is the farmer's whole excellence, the meadows being kept in good order, and very rich:-- the inhabitants are ignorant of men and manners, but subtle and crafty.</s></p>
<p><s id="s119">" Roger Lord Clifford, in 4 Edward Iii.</s> <s id="s120">1330," procured the King's charter for a Market upon Thursday" every week at his manor of <enamex sw="w18991" long="-3.052526199324935" lat="54.92333858543775" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35985" name="Burgh By Sands" conf="2.478129693">Burgh</enamex> upon Staynemoor" in <enamex  sw="w19018" name="Large admin unit">Westmerland</enamex>; and a Fair yearly, to begin" two days before the Feast of St Matthew the Apostle, and to continue for the day and morrow after."</s></p>
<p><s id="s121">Dugdale's Baronage, Vol.</s> <s id="s122">I. p.</s> <s id="s123">339.</s></p>
<p><s id="s124">On parties of pleasure, time should never be limited;-- to ride post through a country, is too much the custom of travellers, by which they can reap no more than a superficial idea of it:-- the speculative traveller is never confined to roads, times, or seasons; but as the circumstances exciting his curiosity lie either to the right or left, the pursues the objects of his attention, regardless of every other motive.</s></p>
<p><s id="s125">The pleasantness of the morning called us very early from <enamex sw="w19677" long="-2.317311763232068" lat="54.52390316061246" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36930" name="Brough" conf="2.6">Brough</enamex>;-- the dawn advanced with a deep calm-- the clouds broke from the hills, and drew their grey veil from the face of the morning, revealing her in blushes-- the valley lay wrapped in stillness-- Care and Industry had not departed from their night's recesses-- the ear was hushed, and all around seemed to be the region of tranquility;-- ere long, various sounds grew on the sense, and the living landscape gave us new pleasures; the cottagers being now abroad, busied in the several occupations of the field.</s></p>
<p><s id="s126">As we pursued our journey, at an opening of the road to the left, we viewed the ruins of</s></p>
<p><s id="s127"><enamex sw="w20286" long="-2.32363" lat="54.52177" type="other" gazref="unlock:5824888" name="Brough Castle" conf="2">Brough Castle</enamex>.</s> </p><p><s id="s128">In former times this was a formidable fortress, and of Roman original; its situation on the Roman road leading to Brovonaicum by Aballaba, and its distance from Lavatrae prove, that this was the antient Verteriae mentioned by Antonine and the Book of Notices, where, in the decline of the Roman empire, a band of the Directores were stationed.</s> <s id="s129">-- The name of <enamex sw="w20660" long="-3.052526199324935" lat="54.92333858543775" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35985" name="Burgh By Sands" conf="2.478129693">Burgh</enamex> or <enamex sw="w20669" long="-2.317311763232068" lat="54.52390316061246" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36930" name="Brough" conf="2.6">Brough</enamex> is of Saxon extraction;-- such situations were chosen by that people, for erecting castles, as being already places of strength.</s> <s id="s130">Camden says, but from what authority I know not, that in the time of the later empire, little castles, calculated for defence, and as storehouses for corn, began to be called Burgs.</s> <s id="s131">-- The building to the eastern side is circular, and seems to be of modern architecture, but to the west there remains a noble tower, apparently of great antiquity.</s> <s id="s132">The whole castle stands on a considerable eminence to the north and west, arising swiftly from the plain; to the south and east the access is not so steep, but is guarded by a deep ditch and rampart, which appear to be the remains of the old Roman station, forming an area to the castle.</s> <s id="s133">-- In the beginning of the <enamex  sw="w21468" name="Not a placename">Norman</enamex> government, the northern English conspired here against William the Conqueror.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s134">Camden's Britannia.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s135">Camden's Britannia.</s></p>
<p><s id="s136">In the last century this place was repaired by the Countess of <enamex sw="w21660" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex>, who made it her residence.</s> <s id="s137">-- This appeared by the following inscription which lately stood over the South entrance:" This" castle of <enamex sw="w21806" long="-2.317311763232068" lat="54.52390316061246" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36930" name="Brough" conf="2.6">Brough</enamex> under <enamex sw="w21819" long="-2.255019919860124" lat="54.53437804794765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11233065" name="North Stainmore" conf="2.6">Stainmore</enamex>, and" the great tower of it, were repaired by" the Lady Ann Clifford, Countess Dowager" of <enamex sw="w21923" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex>, <enamex sw="w21933" long="-120.2320052" lat="47.0312395" type="other" gazref="unlock:8532531" name="Dorse Spring" conf="0.4192325981">Dorse</enamex>, and <enamex  sw="w21944" name="Not a placename">Montgomery</enamex>," Baron Clifford, <enamex  sw="w21974" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>," and Vesey, <enamex sw="w22001" long="-0.7394925437662905" lat="51.6365290938372" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11293" name="High Wycombe" conf="1.435207657">High</enamex> Sheriff by inheritance" of the <enamex  sw="w22038" name="Large admin unit">county of Westmoreland</enamex>, and" Lady of the <enamex sw="w22080" long="-0.04965271490377404" lat="51.45275836816165" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11178759" name="Honor Oak" conf="1.53206214">Honor</enamex> of <enamex sw="w22089" long="-2.022863422807434" lat="53.95939075054672" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11284835" name="Skipton" conf="1.534745579">Skipton</enamex> in Craven," in the year of our Lord God 1659," so as she came to lie in it herself for a" little while in September 1661, after it" had laine ruinous without timber or" any covering ever since the year 1521," when it was burnt by a casual fire.</s> <s id="s138">" <enamex sw="w22350" long="73.66666669999999" lat="32.9333333" type="other" gazref="unlock:3201123" name="Chak Īsa" conf="0.259860568">Isa</enamex>.</s> <s id="s139">cha.</s> <s id="s140">lviii.</s> <s id="s141">ver.</s> <s id="s142">12.</s> <s id="s143">-- God's name be" praised."-- The stone which contained this inscription, some few years ago fell down and was destroyed.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s144">This inscription reminds me of one put up on a like occasion by the Countess of <enamex sw="w22581" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex>, on <enamex sw="w22594" long="-2.01474" lat="53.96372" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825280" name="Skipton Castle" conf="0.9436567815">Skipton Castle</enamex>, which runs as follows:" This <enamex sw="w22640" long="-2.01474" lat="53.96372" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825280" name="Skipton Castle" conf="0.9436567815">Skipton Castle</enamex>" was repaired by the Lady Ann Clifford, Countess" Dowager of <enamex sw="w22718" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex>, <enamex sw="w22728" long="-120.2320052" lat="47.0312395" type="other" gazref="unlock:8532531" name="Dorse Spring" conf="0.4192325981">Dorse</enamex>, and <enamex  sw="w22739" name="Not a placename">Montgomery</enamex>," Baroness Clifford, <enamex  sw="w22772" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, and Vesey, Lady" of the <enamex sw="w22811" long="-0.04965271490377404" lat="51.45275836816165" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11178759" name="Honor Oak" conf="1.53206214">Honor</enamex> of <enamex sw="w22820" long="-2.022863422807434" lat="53.95939075054672" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11284835" name="Skipton" conf="1.534745579">Skipton</enamex> in Craven, and <enamex sw="w22843" long="-0.7394925437662905" lat="51.6365290938372" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11293" name="High Wycombe" conf="1.435207657">High</enamex> Sheriffess" by inheritance of the <enamex  sw="w22882" name="Large admin unit">County of Westmoreland</enamex>," in the years 1657 and 1658, after the main part of" it had lain ruinous ever since December 1648 and the" January following, when it was then pulled down" and demolished almost to the ground, by the comand" of the Parliament then sitting at <enamex sw="w23152" long="-0.1341314301907648" lat="51.49910165515224" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11318879" name="Westminster" conf="1.566156802">Westminster</enamex>, because" it had been a garrison in the then civil wars in" <enamex  sw="w23226" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s> <s id="s145">Isaiah, cha.</s> <s id="s146">lviii.</s> <s id="s147">ver.</s> <s id="s148">12.</s> <s id="s149">-- God's name be" praised."</s></p>
<p><s id="s150">As the sun advanced, he gave various beauties to the scene, the beams streaming through the divisions in the mountains, shewed us their due perspective, and striped the plain with gold-- the light falling behind the castle, presented all its parts perfectly to us-- through the broken windows distant objects were discovered;-- the front ground lay in shadows;-- on the left the prospect was shut in by a range of craggy mountains, over whose steeps shrubs and trees were scattered;-- to the right a fertile plain was extended, surmounted by distant hills; over their summits the retiring vapours, as they fled the valley, dragged their watry skirts, and gave a solemn gloom to that part of the scene.</s> <s id="s151">Behind the building, the lofty promontary of <enamex sw="w24044" long="-2.9007" lat="54.3785" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11323643" name="Wildbore Fell" conf="99992">Wilbore</enamex> Fell lifted its peaked brow, tinged with an azure hue, and terminated the prospect.</s></p>
<p><s id="s152">In order to examine this fortress with greater attention, I revisited it the succeeding year.</s> <s id="s153">-- When I attempt to give a reason for my second visit to the Lakes, and beating the same road again, my eyes swim with tears, and my heart-rending sorrow is renewed to me in all its energy, for the inestimable loss I have sustained since my first excursion, in my fellow-traveller, my draughtsman, my friend, my second self, my Brother;-- his virtues were too excellent to be detained from Heaven;-- he departed in the flower of youth, amidst all the fire of genius, in the twenty - third year of his age.</s> <s id="s154">-- Plate Iv.</s></p>
<p><s id="s155">-- With him the unfinished draughts of those admirable views were lost;-- to recover them, though imperfectly, from my great inferiority in that art, I again visited the objects of his admiration, I repassed his lines, trod his steps, and with a melancholy degree of satisfaction viewed the scenes, which were then become to me solemn memorials of him who was not.</s></p>
<p><s id="s156">-- But to return-- half mankind know nothing of the beauties of nature, and waste in indolence and sleep the glorious scene which the morning presents;-- as we passed on, the varied prospect kept attention awake.</s></p>
<p><s id="s157">At the distance of a mile from <enamex sw="w25363" long="-2.317311763232068" lat="54.52390316061246" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36930" name="Brough" conf="2.6">Brough</enamex>, <enamex sw="w25371" long="72.3666667" lat="36.35" type="other" gazref="unlock:3181879" name="Warkup" conf="0.1920078294">Warkup</enamex>, to the left, affords an agreeable view;-- <enamex sw="w25422" name="Warkup Hall">Warkup Hall</enamex>, shrouded with a rich grove of sycamores, overtops the village; the verdure of the meadows, with some extensive fields of yellow corn, contrasted by the hills of pasture ground which lie on the southern side, brown with the summer heat, and tufted with brush-wood, gave a pleasing variety: whilst the morning beam breaking aslant upon the valley, and glistering on the brook, with the blue teints of smoke that arose from the hamlets, painted the rural scene.</s> <s id="s158">-- We were furnished with ideas which still rendered this prospect more pleasing, as they reminded us of the social spirit of the owner of <enamex sw="w26033" long="72.3666667" lat="36.35" type="other" gazref="unlock:3181879" name="Warkup" conf="0.1920078294">Warkup</enamex>, in whose life, hospitality and benevolence are truly characterized.</s></p>
<p><s id="s159">We passed over the ground where <enamex sw="w26141" long="-2.363208136419874" lat="54.53410159444169" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11089664" name="Brough Hill" conf="2.4">Brough Hill</enamex> Fair is annually held on the last day of September;-- a toll is due on this occasion to Lord Thanet, for every head of black cattle,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s160">presented there;-- for several years past the number of cattle exposed to sale, on an average, amounted to eight thousand and upwards, one thousand horses, together with a prodigious quantity of sheep.</s> <s id="s161">-- All kinds of merchandize are brought to this fair.</s></p>
<p><s id="s162">The valley now growing more extensive, encreased in varieties, and pleased us with a new scene of cultivation and husbandry; the large tracts of ground which we passed along, were lately common, but are now dividing and forming into inclosures.</s> <s id="s163">-- Three tumuli of different magnitudes lay on our left, one of which was lately opened at the instance of the Bishop of Carlisle, and some remains of arms, with the ashes of the interred, were discovered.</s> <s id="s164">-- By what was found there, it was apprehended the tumulus was British.</s></p>
<p><s id="s165">At the sixth mile stone we stopped to admire the singularity of the view to the right, where a range of mountains, arising from the extensive plain over which we were travelling, stretched to the westward, and afforded a romantic and noble scene; the nearest hills, with rocky brows and barren cliffs, raised their grey fronts above the humble brush wood, which girt them in the midst, whilst their feet in hasty slopes descended the vale in pasturage: further retiring from theeye, the mountain called <enamex sw="w27574" long="-2.488892044911392" lat="54.70442893932375" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11122882" name="Cross Fell" conf="2.4">Cross Fell</enamex>, with a front of naked rock, overtops the adjoining hills; being said to exceed the mountain <enamex sw="w27679" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.304309865">Skiddaw</enamex>, in <enamex  sw="w27692" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, one hundred and ten perpendicular feet in height:-- further extending westward, the chain of mountains lay in perspective, till they died away upon the sight, and in azure hue seemed to mix with the sky; whilst at the foot of this vast range of hills, three smaller mounts, of an exact conic form, running parallel, beautified the scene, being covered with verdure to their crowns;-- the nearest, called <enamex sw="w28110" long="-2.472536861955642" lat="54.63259127966819" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11133349" name="Dufton Pike" conf="2.4">Dufton Pike</enamex>, was shadowed by a passing cloud, save only the summit of its cone, which was touched by a beam that pointed it with gold;-- the second pike was all enlightened, and gave its verdure to the prospect as if mantled with velvet;-- the third stood shadowed, whilst all the range of hills behind were struck with sunshine, shewing their cliffs, caverns, and dells in grotesque variety, and giving the three pikes a picturesque projection on the landscape:-- nature, as if delighted to charm the eye of man, at this time cast an accidental beauty over the scene;-- the small clouds which chequered the sky, as they passed along, spread their flitting shadows on the distant mountains, and seemed to marble them; a beauty which I do not recollect has struck any painter, and which has not been described even by the bold hand of the immortal Pousin.</s> <s id="s166">The most exquisite fancy of a painter could not have devised more pleasing variety of light and shadow, than what was cast upon this prospect.</s></p>
<p><s id="s167"><enamex sw="w29112" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex>,</s> </p><p><s id="s168">To which we now approached, though placed on an elevated situation, was concealed from our view till we arrived within half a mile; when from the hill which we had ascended, it gave an agreeable surprize.</s> <s id="s169">On the brink of a lofty eminence, fronting towards the East, beneath which runs the <enamex sw="w29410" long="-2.690643106095647" lat="54.70344735935878" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270317" name="River Eden" conf="2.4">River Eden</enamex>, the castle presented itself.</s> <s id="s170">The steep, on whose brow this noble edifice is erected, is richly cloathed with wood; save only where a rugged cliff of red hue breaks through the trees, and gives an agreeable variety to the landscape.</s> <s id="s171">-- The front of the castle is irregular and antique, but loses great share of its beauty, by the joints of the building being whitened and bedaubed with lime.</s> <s id="s172"><enamex sw="w29813" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.318660087">Over</enamex> this front, the top of a fine square tower is discovered, whose corners arise in turrets;-- the landscape to the left is richly wooded;-- to the right it is divided by hanging gardens, which adjoin the town, overtopped with dwellings:-- the pavillions belonging the house of John Robinson, Esq; with the parterres and sloping plots of grass ground, modernize a scene, which condemns all factitiousness of taste; and by the simplicity and elegance nature presents to us on the adjoining lands, reproves the distortions which she receives from dull right lines and angles:-- but whilst I censure fashion, I revere the owner of this mansion, whose excellencies are too eminent to want the traveller's applause.</s></p>
<p><s id="s173">As we approached the bridge, and cast our eyes upon the valley, we were delighted with the happy assemblage of woods and meadows, which form the little vale, where Eden flows; through the thronging branches the water was seen, in many places, reflecting a tremulous beam, and sparkling in the sun's rays;-- over the valley, rude cliffs and hanging rocks, on this hand, appeared projecting through the trees; on that, was seen the lofty front of the castle.</s></p>
<p><s id="s174">The prospect from the terrace, which is under the eastern front of the castle, is very beautiful;-- to the right, the <enamex sw="w31107" long="-2.690643106095647" lat="54.70344735935878" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270317" name="River Eden" conf="2.4">River Eden</enamex> forms a winding lake the distance of half a mile, whose banks are cloathe with lofty hanging woods, descending in a swift but regular sweep to the brink of of the stream.</s> <s id="s175">Below us, the water murmured over a wear, where a mill added to the pleasing sounds.</s> <s id="s176">On the left, lofty cliffs and precipices arise perpendicular from the water, over whose brows, oaks and ashes hanging, render their aspect more romantic by the solemn shade.</s> <s id="s177">-- On the ground above, the public road leading to <enamex sw="w31599" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex>, winds up the hill, on whose side some cottages are scattered; whilst all behind the distant ground is formed by mountains, shadowed with clouds.</s></p>
<p><s id="s178">Whilst here we stayed, enjoying this sweet scene, I could not forbear pointing out to my companion a little tenement which had been remarked to me, standing opposite to us, on the brink of the river, where the fairest maid resides that graces Eden's banks;-- stately and tall, she seems the lily of Eden's garden, whilst she is fair and meek as lilies; in her countenance beauty is graced with intelligence, and in her behaviour innocence is mixed with politeness.</s></p>
<p><s id="s179">The garden grounds around <enamex sw="w32245" long="-2.48863" lat="54.57361" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825254" name="Appleby Castle" conf="2">Appleby Castle</enamex> are without ornament, and calculated for use only.</s></p>
<p><s id="s180">-- On the western side of this castle, detached from the rest of the edifice, is a lofty square, called by the people Caesar's Tower, but whether of Roman construction, is impossible to ascertain:-- I am induced to believe it, from the mode of architecture, to be of <enamex  sw="w32579" name="Not a placename">Norman</enamex> original:-- the corners of the tower form a projection of near a foot from the plane of each front, and rise above the rest of the building in square turrets, now covered with lead, the remaining part of the top being embrasured:-- there are two small windows in each front, near the middle of the building, parallel to each other.</s> <s id="s181">-- This tower is defended by an outward wall, forming a crescent at the distance of about twelve paces, now remaining near twenty feet high, strongly sustained on the outside by buttresses, erected on an eminence thirty paces in ascent, and defended by a deep ditch without.</s> <s id="s182">-- The quarter fronting to the castle lies open to the area, which is enclosed by a wall, continued from the points of the crescent.</s></p>
<p><s id="s183">This was the antient Aballaba, where the Aurelian <enamex sw="w33378" long="6.38333" lat="43.26667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4546029" name="Monts des Maures" conf="0.4031895816">Maures</enamex> kept a station:-- it is almost encompassed by the <enamex sw="w33436" long="-2.690643106095647" lat="54.70344735935878" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270317" name="River Eden" conf="2.4">River Eden</enamex>.</s> <s id="s184">-- William King of <enamex  sw="w33467" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>, in his incursions, surprized this fortress some little time before he was taken prisoner at <enamex sw="w33569" long="-1.699445573634875" lat="55.40948184202175" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10192" name="Alnwick" conf="1.288267511">Alnwick</enamex>, which happened in the year 1174, where, with an army of eighty thousand men, he was overcome by a handful of opponents, under the command of Barnard Baliol.</s> <s id="s185">King John in his northern tour recovered the castle, and gave it to Robert Vipont for his singular services.</s> <s id="s186">-- Camden says the assizes were entirely held there; and it was the common gaol for malefactors.-- It is probable the Roman station was situate on this eminence, and that the present castle stands on the same ground; but the Vallum is totally effaced.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s187">Camden's Britannia.</s></p>
<p><s id="s188">The great Hall is worthy the observation of travellers, there being enclosed in a case in the wainscot, a fine piece of portrait painting, of George Clifford, Earl of Cumberland, his lady, and daughter, afterwards Countess of <enamex sw="w34345" long="-2.321866495142013" lat="50.7948587473371" type="civila" gazref="unlock:13325837" name="Dorset County" conf="1.668881334">Dorset</enamex>, <enamex sw="w34353" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex>, and <enamex  sw="w34367" name="Not a placename">Montgomery</enamex>, ornamented with their pedigree, and historical notes of their lives and atchievements.</s> <s id="s189">-- A stranger is from thence conducted through an adjoining room, where the ragged remains of embroidered furniture, give you a deplorable idea of decaying magnificence, and the vanity of pride;-- the door of a closet being suddenly thrown open, you are startled from your reverie by the shaking of armour, and the sight of a compleat suit, trembling in every joint.</s> <s id="s190">-- This is preserved with great attention, as having been worn by the same George Earl of <enamex  sw="w34924" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, the last Earl of that name, and father of the Countess of <enamex sw="w34994" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex>, by whom great possessions came to the Thanet family.</s> <s id="s191">-- The arms are richly embossed and inlaid with gold, and shew the Earl to have been a man of low stature.</s></p>
<p><s id="s192">In its ichnography, this castle is not much unlike to the ruins of <enamex sw="w35231" long="-2.317311763232068" lat="54.52390316061246" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36930" name="Brough" conf="2.6">Brough</enamex>; the towers of each being detached from the main edifice, and placed to the west.</s></p>
<p><s id="s193"><enamex sw="w35320" long="-2.48863" lat="54.57361" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825254" name="Appleby Castle" conf="2">Appleby castle</enamex> is one of the seats of the Earl of Thanet, but of late years much neglected by the family.</s> <s id="s194">-- Lord Thanet is hereditary Sheriff of the <enamex  sw="w35470" name="Large admin unit">county of Westmoreland</enamex>, and as such intitled to many privileges; some of which, in this age of liberty and cultivation, are rather oppressive; his free-chace in particular.</s></p>
<p><s id="s195">The great possessions of the Countess of <enamex sw="w35684" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex>, in this country, came into the Thanet family in the following manner:-- John Earl of Thanet succeeded his mother, Margaret Countess of Thanet, as Baron of <enamex sw="w35850" long="-1.34557" lat="53.89513" type="other" gazref="unlock:5823748" name="Clifford" conf="0.8810201675">Clifford</enamex>, <enamex  sw="w35860" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, and Vesey, in the year 1676; and in the year 1678 he also succeeded his cousin, the Lady Alathea, sole daughter and heiress of James Earl of <enamex  sw="w36015" long="-0.8812" lat="52.2344" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:4565829" name="Northampton" conf="99992">Northampton</enamex>, by his first wife, the Lady Isabella, his mother's sister: whereby he became possessed of the whole inheritance of his grandmother, the Countess of <enamex sw="w36176" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex>.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s196">Colling's Peerage.</s></p>
<p><s id="s197">The town of <enamex sw="w36219" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex> chiefly consists of one wide continued street, hanging upon the swift decline of a hill, in a direction north and south; the castle terminating it on the summit, the church at the foot.</s> <s id="s198">-- The situation is agreeable in the summer season; but in the winter, cold.</s> <s id="s199">-- The meadow and pasture grounds are beautiful; but there is little tillage; it having been a received opinion for ages past, that grain would not ripen or come to perfection so near the moors and mountains, from whence a continued moist vapour is supposed to be borne into the valley, which blights the corn in its blossom, and prevents its filling or coming to maturity: but this absurdity is declining through experience, which hath taught the inhabitants, that the want of knowledge in agriculture was the chief defect, and the impetuous rains to which a mountainous country is subject, their greatest detriment.</s></p>
<p><s id="s200">This is a very ancient Borough, and by prescription sends two members to parliament.</s> <s id="s201">-- It is the county town, but not blest with a situation for trade.</s> <s id="s202">-- The markets are not populous, the country adjoining, by reason of its extensive wastes and uncultivated lands, being thinly inhabited.-- This is a corporation town, and governed by a mayor, alderman, and common council.</s> <s id="s203">-- The late conflicts in political matters have enriched the inhabitants; the contested elections for this borough having bestowed on the burgage owners many thousands of pounds.</s></p>
<p><s id="s204"><enamex sw="w37665" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex>, antiently Aballaba, was a city in the time of the Romans: had a charter from Henry I. and confirmed by King John.</s> <s id="s205">It continued a place of great account till 1176, when it was utterly destroyed by the Scots, as appears from a stone in the school garden-house.</s> <s id="s206">-- It enjoys the same privileges as <enamex sw="w37969" long="" lat="" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:9659" name="" conf="99991">York</enamex>, by grant from Henry Iii.</s></p>
<p><s id="s207"><enamex sw="w38000" long="-2.48863" lat="54.57361" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825254" name="Appleby Castle" conf="2">Appleby castle</enamex> was granted the 4th of King John, to Robert Vipont, which includes the barony, but not the burrough of <enamex sw="w38118" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex>, that having been granted to the burgesses there by King Henry Ii.</s> <s id="s208">and confirmed by King John, in the second year of his reign; so likewise by Henry Iii.</s> <s id="s209">in the 16th of his reign.</s></p>
<p><s id="s210">Dug.</s> <s id="s211">Baron.</s> <s id="s212">Vol.</s> <s id="s213">I. p.</s> <s id="s214">347.</s></p>
<p><s id="s215">Edward Ii.</s> <s id="s216">in the 5th year of his reign, 1312, took the town of <enamex sw="w38398" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex> into his hands, for the arrearage of their yearly farm.</s> <s id="s217">The town remained in the King's hands a considerable time: the townsmen came and made fine to Edward Iii.</s> <s id="s218">and he restored it to them, to be holden by them in the same plight as they held it before the caption.</s></p>
<p><s id="s219">See Record at full length in Madox Firma Burgi, p.</s> <s id="s220">162, pro Burgensibus de <enamex sw="w38747" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s221">The place where the judges of assize sit in judgment on criminals, is very antique and remarkable:-- by the arms placed on one of the corner pillars, it appears to have been erected by the <enamex sw="w38946" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex> family:-- it is situated in the market place, fronting the north; the sides are opened by a rude balustrade, and in the front supported by pillars; so that it may properly be said, the judge sits dispensing justice in the forum.</s></p>
<p><s id="s222"><enamex sw="w39185" long="-1.503080660637125" lat="52.79868819908115" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11092025" name="Buildings Fm, The" conf="1.029223953">The Buildings</enamex> in this place are chiefly antient; some few modern houses of red free-stone, which have a remarkable fine effect, are interspersed.</s> <s id="s223">-- Near the summit of the hill, stands an obelisk, a pillar of the Ionic order, arising on some few steps; on the base of which is cut this remarkable inscription:--" Preserve your liberties," maintain your rights."-- It seems to be placed there as a public satire on the conduct of the burgage owners, and to imply, hither and no further the conflagration of public virtue advanced.</s> <s id="s224">-- As it had its origin in the contested elections, it excites a smile of derision on the countenance of the traveller, to whose mind it renews the odious ideas of the corruptions of the age.</s> <s id="s225">-- In the midst of the town, to the annoyance of every passenger, stand a filthy slaughter-house and shambles.</s></p>
<p><s id="s226">Here is a School, amply endowed, founded by Robert <enamex sw="w40074" long="-0.9310389472554987" lat="52.5341709994407" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11107146" name="Church Langton" conf="1.436167147">Langton</enamex> and Miles Spence, Doctors of Laws.</s> <s id="s227">-- It was under the conduct of one Reginald Bainbrig, in Camden's time; who speaks of him with great respect.</s> <s id="s228">Before the door of the school-house, some Roman altars are placed, fully treated of by other travellers: amongst which antiquities, Reginald Bainbrig has given a memorial of his folly to posterity, by some inscriptions in antique characters, to celebrate his own memory, in which at least his latin inelegance" Qui Docuit Hic" might have been spared.</s> <s id="s229">Here is also an hospital founded by the Pembrokes, with a stipend for a chaplain:-- the hospital is built on a square, forming an area in the center.</s></p>
<p><s id="s230">In this town was a house of white friars, said to have been founded by the Lord Vesey, Lord Percy, and Lord Clifford, in 1281.</s> <s id="s231">After the dissolution it was granted to Christopher Crakenthorpe, 35 Henry Viii.</s></p>
<p><s id="s232">See Tanner, p.</s> <s id="s233">588.</s></p>
<p><s id="s234">The road we pursued from <enamex sw="w40984" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex>, for several miles, gave us great pleasure: the vallies through which the <enamex sw="w41066" long="-2.690643106095647" lat="54.70344735935878" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270317" name="River Eden" conf="2.4">River Eden</enamex> flows, are singularly beautiful; their woody banks and level meads afford variety of landscapes, particularly below <enamex sw="w41193" long="-2.526151869" lat="54.59294109" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00144" name="Crackenthorpe" conf="99992">Crackenthorp</enamex>. On the opposite shore of the river, surrounded with a thick wood, the ruins of <enamex sw="w41287" name="Buley Castle">Buley Castle</enamex> are seen, now consisting only of one shattered tower.</s> <s id="s235">-- This was an antient retreat of the Bishops of <enamex sw="w41403" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.264248656">Carlisle</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s236">We passed Kirby Thore, where no remains of antient Roman grandeur, spoken of by Camden, are now to be found, except the vestigia of part of the Vallum.</s> <s id="s237">He presumes this was the Gallagum of Ptolomy.</s> <s id="s238">-- The maiden way, a Roman pavement, leads from hence to Caer Vorran, on the Picts wall; along which, it is probable, stood those stations spoken of by Antonine, though now totally effaced.</s> <s id="s239">-- In this neighbourhood were those written rocks, whose inscriptions are preserved by Camden, though obliterated by time, or ignorant workmen</s></p>
<p><s id="s240">Varronivs-- Efectvs Leg.</s> <s id="s241">XX.</s> <s id="s242">W.-- Ael Lvcanvs-- P. Lic.</s> <s id="s243">Ii Avg.</s> <s id="s244">C.</s></p>
<p><s id="s245">which may be read thus: Varronius praefectus Legionis Vicesime valentis Victricis Aelius Lucanus praefectus Legionis Secundae Augustae castrametati sunt.</s> <s id="s246">-- In another place--</s></p>
<p><s id="s247">Cm.</s> <s id="s248">Oct.</s> <s id="s249"><enamex sw="w42201" long="95.3475" lat="5.8513889" type="other" gazref="unlock:2968518" name="Cot Anuraya" conf="0">Cot</enamex>.</s> <s id="s250">Coss.</s></p>
<p><s id="s251">-- The twentieth Legion, called Valens Victrix, kept their residence at <enamex sw="w42284" long="22.91635894775391" lat="45.87808990478516" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132348" name="Deva" conf="1.431295122">Deva</enamex> or <enamex sw="w42292" long="-2.735634538327902" lat="53.1622547368117" type="civila" gazref="unlock:13318455" name="Cheshire West and Chester (B)" conf="1.778291003">West Chester</enamex>, and the second Legion, <enamex  sw="w42329" name="Not a placename">Augusta</enamex>, at <enamex sw="w42341" long="-2.960431199008371" lat="51.6089314755211" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11095832" name="Caerleon or Caerllion/Isca" conf="1.2">Isca</enamex>, that is, Caer Leon, in <enamex  sw="w42370" name="Large admin unit">Wales</enamex>.</s> <s id="s252">-- They probably were employed against the northern powers, and encamped here.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s253">Camden's Britannia.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s254">VV.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s255"><enamex sw="w42483" long="-2.596737456393797" lat="54.65001884181451" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11056445" name="Acorn Bank" conf="2.2">Acorn Bank</enamex>, late the seat of the Dalstons, but now of William Norton, Esq; an elegant modern building, covered with fine plantations, lay in our way; commanding an agreeable, though narrow prospect, over rich meadows to the south, descending to the town of <enamex sw="w42741" long="-2.59660582855903" lat="54.64103158158196" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11298592" name="Temple Sowerby" conf="2.6">Temple Sowerby</enamex>; of which place we were told nothing memorable, but that there remained to this day a pecuniary composition, paid to the <enamex sw="w42878" long="1.381621847413567" lat="51.33922115495494" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11206415" name="Lord of the Manor" conf="0.8127949738">Lord of the Manor</enamex>, in lieu of his custom with each bride within his jurisdiction.</s> <s id="s256">-- It is an extra-parochial place, and from its antient owners, the Knights Templars, enjoyed many privileges which are now obsolete.</s></p>
<p><s id="s257">We then passed <enamex sw="w43109" long="-2.687445" lat="54.652038" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY57350029" name="Whinfell Park" conf="99992">Whinfield Park</enamex>, an extensive forest, the property of the Earl of Thanet, where we had the pleasure of viewing a large tract of ground, lately enclosed from <enamex  sw="w43265" name="Too ambigious to allocate">the park</enamex>, and growing corn.</s> <s id="s258">-- There is not any thing can give greater satisfaction to the eye of the traveller, than to behold cultivation and industry stretching their paces over the heath and waste, the forest and the chace:-- population must follow, and riches ensue.</s> <s id="s259">-- In <enamex sw="w43544" long="-3.141573303591644" lat="54.17869857547983" type="other" gazref="unlock:11319948" name="Whinfield" conf="1.73266923">Whinfield</enamex>, the remains of an antient oak, of prodigious size, is shewn to strangers, called Three Brother Tree, a name arising from the concealment of three brethren within its cavity.</s> <s id="s260">-- On the way side, the shattered trunk of an oak, called White <enamex sw="w43794" long="-1.27629" lat="54.70869" type="other" gazref="unlock:13901529" name="Hart" conf="0.8401302526">Hart</enamex> Tree, is seen, a contemporary perhaps of the other, though <enamex sw="w43859" long="-2.380959059473901" lat="53.26636647649359" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13406367" name="Peover Inferior CP" conf="1.346711395">inferior</enamex> in size-- the monument of elapsed centuries, and the effigy of old age; stretching forth its withered limbs on one side, and on the other, a scanty foliage and poor remnant of life.</s> <s id="s261">-- This tree is nine yards and two feet in circumference.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s262">A stone pillar, erected by the side of the road, next attracted our attention; near to which stands a stone table.</s> <s id="s263">-- The stalk of the pillar is hexagon, the top of it square; on the sides of which are represented, in several quarterings, the arms of the Pembrokes, a south dial, and the following inscription:--</s></p>
<p><s id="s264">" This pillar was erected anno <enamex sw="w44455" long="-118.1236791" lat="33.9091815" type="other" gazref="unlock:8130310" name="Saint Domini Savio School" conf="0.8248638964">Domini</enamex>" 1656, by the Right Honourable Ann" Countess Dowager of <enamex sw="w44520" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex>,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s265">" daughter and sole heiress of the Right" Honourable George Earl of <enamex  sw="w44603" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>," for a memorial of her last parting in" this place, with her good and pious" mother, the Right Honourable Margaret" Countess Dowager of <enamex  sw="w44755" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, the" 2d of April 1616; in memory whereof" she also left an annuity of four pounds" to be distributed to the poor of the parish" of <enamex sw="w44901" long="-2.670439372771031" lat="54.64677376142333" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403485" name="Brougham CP" conf="2.4">Brougham</enamex>, every second day of" April for ever, upon the stone table here" hard by.</s> <s id="s266">Laus Deo.</s></p>
<p><s id="s267">Margaret Countess of <enamex  sw="w45018" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> was the third daughter of Francis Earl of <enamex sw="w45071" long="-0.4614076181314157" lat="52.13560326998379" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10474" name="Bedford" conf="2.086761386">Bedford</enamex>, and married George the third and last Earl of Cumberland.</s></p>
<p><s id="s268">Dugdale's Bar.</s> <s id="s269">Vol.</s> <s id="s270">I. p.</s> <s id="s271">345.</s></p>
<p><s id="s272">She erected a monument in her life time, in <enamex sw="w45213" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex> church, for her burial.</s> <s id="s273">-- She parted with her daughter, Ann Countess Dowager of <enamex sw="w45302" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex>, at the pillar, 2d of April 1616, and died the 24th of May 1616, and was buried at <enamex sw="w45394" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s274">See her Epitaph in Le Neve Monumenta Anglicana, Vol.</s> <s id="s275">Iii.</s> <s id="s276">p.</s> <s id="s277">52, No. 96.</s></p>
<p><s id="s278">Ann Countess Dowager of <enamex sw="w45500" long="-4.914708486060867" lat="51.67560468361661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11241889" name="Pembroke/Penfro" conf="1.365707041">Pembroke</enamex> died the 22d of March 1675, and was buried at <enamex sw="w45555" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s279">See her Epitaph in Le Neve, Vol.</s> <s id="s280">Iv.</s> <s id="s281">p.</s> <s id="s282">168, No. 425.</s></p>
<p><s id="s283">We quitted the high road in order to pass by <enamex sw="w45663" long="-2.720724891391479" lat="54.64934460899606" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11089698" name="Brougham Castle" conf="2.2">Brougham Castle</enamex>, a spacious ruin, situate on the banks of the River <enamex sw="w45731" long="-2.6167" lat="54.6667" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2650566" name="Eamont" conf="99992">Emont</enamex>; that we might enjoy the prospect to advantage, we crossed the river, and made a sweep round the mill, which stands almost opposite to <enamex sw="w45872" long="-2.670439372771031" lat="54.64677376142333" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403485" name="Brougham CP" conf="2.4">Brougham</enamex>; from thence the view opened upon us with an happy effect.</s> <s id="s284">--</s></p>
<p><s id="s285">-- The mill with its streams lay on the left-- a shining canal, formed by the River <enamex sw="w46028" long="-2.6167" lat="54.6667" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2650566" name="Eamont" conf="99992">Emont</enamex>, margined with shrubs, spread a considerable distance to the right-- whilst the streams which fell over a wear made a foaming cascade in front.</s> <s id="s286">On the opposite brink of the channel stands the castle;-- the side next the river is divided by three square towers;-- from thence on either hand a little wing falls back, the one leading to the gate-way, the other connected with the outworks, which extend to a considerable distance along a grassy plane of pasture ground, terminated by a turret, one of the outposts of the castle:-- the centre of the building is a lofty square tower;-- the shattered turrets which form the angles, and the hanging galleries, are grown over with shrubs:-- the sun beams, which struck each gasping loup and bending window, discovered the inward devastation and ruin, and touched the whole with admirable colouring and beauty.</s> <s id="s287">-- To grace the landscape, groups of cattle were dispersed on the pasture, and through the tufts of ash trees, which were irregularly scattered on the back ground, distant mountains were seen, skirting the horizon.</s></p>
<p><s id="s288">The lower apartment in the principal tower still remains intire; being a square of twenty feet, covered with a vaulted roof of stone, consisting of eight arches of light and excellent workmanship.</s> <s id="s289">The groins are ornamented with various grotesque heads, and supported in the centre by an octagon pillar about four feet in circumference, with a capital and base of <enamex  sw="w47472" name="Not a placename">Norman</enamex> architecture.</s> <s id="s290">In the centre of each arch rings are fixed, as if designed for lamps to illuminate the vault.</s></p>
<p><s id="s291">From the construction of this cell, and its situation in the chief tower of the fortress, it is not probable it was formed for a prison, but rather was used at the time of siege and assault, as the retreat of the chief persons of the household.</s></p>
<p><s id="s292">In Mr Grose's ingenious preface to the Antiquities of <enamex  sw="w47886" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w47898" name="Large admin unit">Wales</enamex>, we have the following observations:" On an" eminence in the centre, commonly, though" not always, stood the keep or dungeon:" sometimes, as in the relation of the siege" of <enamex sw="w48082" long="-3.46809" lat="51.41351" type="other" gazref="unlock:5823864" name="Bedford Castle" conf="0.7600721201">Bedford castle</enamex>, emphatically called" the tower; it was the citadel or last retreat" of the garrison, often surrounded" by a ditch, with a draw bridge and" machicolated gate, and occasionally" with an outer wall, garnished with small" towers.</s> <s id="s293">In large castles it was generally" a high square tower, of four or five stories," having turrets at each angle: in" these turrets were the staircases, and" frequently, as in <enamex sw="w48508" long="-75.54095077514648" lat="39.17560577392578" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131479" name="Dover" conf="1.963485344">Dover</enamex> and <enamex sw="w48518" long="0.4795148747608203" lat="51.38878999472801" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11271635" name="Rochester" conf="1.91228826">Rochester</enamex>" castles, a well.</s> <s id="s294">If instead of a square," the keep or dungeon happened to be" round, it was called a julliet, from a" vulgar opinion that large round towers" were built by Julius Caesar.</s></p>
<p><s id="s295">" The walls of this edifice were always" of an extraordinary thickness; which" has enabled them to outlive the other" buildings, and to withstand the united" injuries of time and weather; the keeps" or dungeons being almost the only part" now remaining of our ancient castles.</s> <s id="s296">" Here were the state rooms for the governor,"&amp; c."</s></p>
<p><s id="s297">The approach to this castle is guarded by an outward-vaulted gateway and tower, with a port cullis; and at the distance of about twenty paces, an inward-vaulted gateway of ribbed arches with a port cullis; through which you enter a spacious area, defended by a lofty wall.</s></p>
<p><s id="s298">This castle is situated on the north side of the Roman station Rronovaicum, which has formed an area and outwork one hundred and twenty paces square, defended by the Vallum and an outward ditch; both at this time very discernable.</s> <s id="s299">-- The angles of this camp are obtuse, like most others of that people.</s> <s id="s300">-- This was the station of a band of Defensores, and in the Book of Notices is laid down as being seventeen English miles from <enamex sw="w49760" name="Verterae">Verterae</enamex>.</s> <s id="s301">-- <enamex sw="w49773" long="-2.670439372771031" lat="54.64677376142333" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403485" name="Brougham CP" conf="2.4">Brougham</enamex> was the Lordship and Castle of the Viponts, included in <enamex sw="w49838" long="-2.515050610218439" lat="53.07731370240744" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11298970" name="The Barony" conf="1.475312349">the Barony</enamex> of <enamex sw="w49852" long="-2.487384668217222" lat="54.57860495430396" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062898" name="Appleby-in-Westmorland" conf="2.6">Appleby</enamex> and <enamex sw="w49864" long="-2.317311763232068" lat="54.52390316061246" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36930" name="Brough" conf="2.6">Brough</enamex>, given to Robert de Vipont by King John, from whose family it descended to the Cliffords; but who was the founder is not known.</s> <s id="s302">-- On the outward gate, the remains of the arms of the Vallibus or Vaulx family are to be observed, being chequy Or, and gules; from whence I am led to conjecture they were builders, or great contributors to the works.</s> <s id="s303">-- This castle is now the property of Lord Thanet.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s304">Camden's Britannia.</s></p>
<p><s id="s305">Having now entered the county of <enamex  sw="w50323" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, and passing on behind <enamex sw="w50357" long="-1.099086784544633" lat="52.96713222454051" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11098529" name="Carlton" conf="1.303945565">Carlton</enamex>, the seat of James Wallace, Esq; the eye wandered over a fine cultivated country, from whence we had a distant view of the rich valley of <enamex sw="w50503" long="-2.714587092202354" lat="54.60426562927525" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13699" name="Lowther" conf="2.6">Lowther</enamex>, graced with noble and extensive woods.</s> <s id="s306">-- As we approached <enamex sw="w50571" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, the mountains and piles of rocks, which stand on <enamex sw="w50629" long="-2.89078" lat="54.57564" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00028" name="Ullswater" conf="99992">Uls Water</enamex>, afforded an august scene-- and at the termination of the road the ruins of <enamex sw="w50716" long="-2.75583" lat="54.6603" type="other" gazref="unlock:5824892" name="Penrith Castle" conf="2">Penrith Castle</enamex> presented themselves.</s> <s id="s307">-- The genius, virtue, and industry of the owner of the rich lands which we were then passing, arose to our thoughts;-- the benevolent mind must ever be touched with pleasure, to discern the rewards of prosperity blessing the man of merit.</s></p>
<p><s id="s308"><enamex sw="w50994" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex></s> </p><p><s id="s309">Is an agreeable town, situate on the easy decline of a hill to the southward; it is unchartered, being governed by the Steward of the <enamex sw="w51136" long="-0.04965271490377404" lat="51.45275836816165" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11178759" name="Honor Oak" conf="1.53206214">Honor</enamex>, and a Jury.</s> <s id="s310">-- A considerable manufactory of cotton and linen checks is carried on here, and also a great trade in tanned leather;-- the town house is in ruins, having been destroyed by a fire some few years ago;-- the ornaments mentioned by Camden are in some parts remaining, which prove the ancient patronage of the <enamex sw="w51464" long="-0.7491255850991351" lat="53.73713072981494" type="other" gazref="unlock:11313897" name="Warwicks" conf="0.8270274733">Warwicks</enamex>;-- the houses in general are well built, the inhabitants facetious and polite.</s> <s id="s311">-- The name of this place is derived from the colour of the hills near it, Penroeth being in the ancient British language a red hill.</s></p>
<p><s id="s312">There was formerly in this place a house of <enamex sw="w51731" long="1.628560932278733" lat="52.27643359260463" type="other" gazref="unlock:11161012" name="Grey Friars" conf="0.6142317479">Grey Friars</enamex>, founded before the reign of Edward the Second, but its revenue, to my knowledge, is not mentioned by any author;-- in the 34th of Henry Viii.</s> <s id="s313">it was granted to Robert Tyrwhit, Esq.-- There are two charity schools here, one for boys, and another for girls, well endowed.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s314">Tanner, p.</s> <s id="s315">77.</s></p>
<p><s id="s316">In the year 1385 <enamex sw="w52050" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> suffered severely by the Scots, who taking advantage of the retreat of Richard Ii after he had carried fire and sword into their country, ravaged all the districts on the borders, and laid this town in ashes.</s> <s id="s317">That Monarch's conduct on this occasion was highly reprehensible, and it became one of the principal charges brought against him.</s></p>
<p><s id="s318">Our first excursion from <enamex sw="w52422" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> was to mount the steep hill on which the Beacon is placed, upwards of a mile to the northward of the town;-- the labour was great by which we ascended, but the view amply rewarded out fatigue.</s> <s id="s319">-- The beacon house is a square building of stone, and happily situated for the purpose of alarming the country in times of public danger, as it commands an extensive vale.</s></p>
<p><s id="s320">-- The northern window of <enamex  sw="w52823" name="Too ambigious to allocate">the beacon house</enamex> affords a prospect of <enamex sw="w52862" long="-2.488892044911392" lat="54.70442893932375" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11122882" name="Cross Fell" conf="2.4">Cross Fell</enamex>, with <enamex sw="w52879" long="-2.872764887218234" lat="55.23254273841246" type="other" gazref="unlock:11245240" name="Pikes, The" conf="0.762382697">the Pikes</enamex> of <enamex sw="w52892" long="-2.487921679387925" lat="54.62354239597875" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11133347" name="Dufton" conf="2.6">Dufton</enamex>, together with a chain of mountains extending from east to west near thirty miles; the western point sinking in the spacious plain where the city of <enamex sw="w53048" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.264248656">Carlisle</enamex> lies.</s> <s id="s321">The utmost bounds of this view are formed by a ridge of Scotch mountains.</s> <s id="s322">-- Some faint appearance of St. Mary's church, marks to the eye the site of <enamex sw="w53213" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.264248656">Carlisle</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s323">-- The eastern window presented a view of the country we had passed, bounded by the hills of <enamex sw="w53316" long="-2.255019919860124" lat="54.53437804794765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11233065" name="North Stainmore" conf="2.6">Stainmore</enamex>, and that lofty promontary <enamex sw="w53353" long="-2.9007" lat="54.3785" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11323643" name="Wildbore Fell" conf="99992">Wilbore</enamex> Fell, with its neighbouring mountains above Kirby Stephen.</s></p>
<p><s id="s324">-- The south window presented to us a view of <enamex sw="w53466" long="-2.720724891391479" lat="54.64934460899606" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11089698" name="Brougham Castle" conf="2.2">Brougham Castle</enamex>, with its plains of pasture ground.</s> <s id="s325">-- The spreading woods of <enamex sw="w53544" long="-2.714587092202354" lat="54.60426562927525" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13699" name="Lowther" conf="2.6">Lowther</enamex>, intermixed with rich cultivated lands, formed the rising grounds.</s> <s id="s326">-- Some parts of the lake of <enamex sw="w53648" long="-2.89078" lat="54.57564" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00028" name="Ullswater" conf="99992">Uls Water</enamex> were seen, whilst the mighty rocks and mountains which hemmed in the lake, lifted up their heads in rude confusion, and crowned the scene.</s></p>
<p><s id="s327">-- The western window afforded a new, and not less pleasing prospect;-- the town of <enamex sw="w53882" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> lay before us, and here and there the River <enamex sw="w53934" long="-2.6167" lat="54.6667" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2650566" name="Eamont" conf="99992">Emont</enamex> shewed its windings through the woods.</s> <s id="s328">-- The hill which rises above the town is crowned with the awful remains of a royal fortress;-- time has despoiled its grandeur, but its Honors still survive to its noble owner, the Duke of Portland, who therewith holds the <enamex sw="w54204" long="-0.04965271490377404" lat="51.45275836816165" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11178759" name="Honor Oak" conf="1.53206214">Honor</enamex> of <enamex sw="w54213" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, formerly a royal franchise.</s> <s id="s329">-- Beyond these objects, amidst a range of mountains, at the distance of eighteen miles, <enamex sw="w54339" long="-3.1487" lat="54.6521" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2637715" name="Skiddaw" conf="99992">Skiddow</enamex> is seen, whose majestic front surmounts all the high lands that terminate the view.</s></p>
<p><s id="s330">-- The whole prospect from <enamex  sw="w54458" name="Too ambigious to allocate">the beacon hill</enamex>, as you turn every way, presents you with a vast theatre, upwards of one hundred miles in circumference, circled with stupendous mountains.</s></p>
<p><s id="s331">Common justice requires, that in whatever station of life merit is discovered, it should receive a degree of praise proportioned to its excellence.</s> <s id="s332">-- From this universal principle, which benevolence delights to cherish, I must not pass in silence the deserts of our <enamex sw="w54881" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> host:-- The common conduct of publicans prepossesses the mind of the traveller, when he enters an inn, with the unfavourable idea, that your host is an unfeeling extortioner, impertinent, curious, and imposing;-- whoever visits <enamex sw="w55119" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, either on business or pleasure, will find the keeper of the White Swan the very reverse;-- a man above his rank in sentiments, above his fellows in propriety of manners; his house commodious and clean, his provisions excellent, and his attendance prompt and not impertinent.</s></p>
<p><s id="s333">Our second excursion from <enamex sw="w55430" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> was by <enamex sw="w55445" long="-2.714587092202354" lat="54.60426562927525" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13699" name="Lowther" conf="2.6">Lowther</enamex> to the Lake Of <enamex sw="w55468" long="-2.89078" lat="54.57564" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00028" name="Ullswater" conf="99992">Uls Water</enamex>;-- we passed the village of <enamex sw="w55507" long="-2.7218" lat="54.6297" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_NY535263" name="Clifton" conf="99991">Clifton</enamex>, memorable for the skirmish on the 18th day of December, 1745, between the Duke of Cumberland's forces and the rebels.</s> <s id="s334">-- On the approach to <enamex sw="w55657" long="-2.7218" lat="54.6297" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_NY535263" name="Clifton" conf="99991">Clifton</enamex> from <enamex sw="w55670" long="-2.714587092202354" lat="54.60426562927525" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13699" name="Lowther" conf="2.6">Lowther</enamex>, the way which the Duke's forces advanced, lies <enamex sw="w55726" long="-2.71146" lat="54.62861" type="other" gazref="unlock:9773111" name="Clifton Moor Railway Station" conf="2">Clifton moor</enamex>, a spacious Common, descending with an easy slope towards the village;-- on the western side the road is situate, within twenty yards of the inclosures, which are fenced by hedges and stone walls, from whence the rebels begun firing on the Duke's horse, and made some slaughter;-- to the east, the land descends to some swamps, with small inclosures, at the foot of which is a narrow dark lane, passable for no more than one horseman at a time.</s> <s id="s335">Near this place General Honeywood received those marks of savage barbarity which had almost cost him his life.</s> <s id="s336">-- A little detached from the village stands a cottage, where the rebel Captain, <enamex  sw="w56378" name="Not a placename">Hamilton</enamex>, with some others, had concealed themselves.</s> <s id="s337">This being discovered, one of the Duke's Hussars, with great dexterity, attacked the house, and riding round it, fired several shot in at the window, which did some execution, and obliged <enamex  sw="w56620" name="Not a placename">Hamilton</enamex> to shew himself; when there began a single combat, between two equally expert in horsemanship and the use of arms; in which <enamex  sw="w56753" name="Not a placename">Hamilton</enamex> was taken prisoner, after giving and receiving many wounds.</s></p>
<p><s id="s338">-- A train of melancholy sentiments flowed in upon the mind, on passing the ground rendered famous to posterity by battles and slaughter;-- when rebellion adds its horrid dye to darken the retrospection, the soul recoils at the sad unnatural scene; and tears start from the eye, to weep the sins of fell ambition, and the pride of man.</s></p>
<p><s id="s339">We visited the present works of Sir James <enamex sw="w57201" long="-2.714587092202354" lat="54.60426562927525" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13699" name="Lowther" conf="2.6">Lowther</enamex>, to which he is pleased to give the name of The Village; the buildings are of stone, handsomely sashed, and covered with blue slate.</s> <s id="s340">-- Our approach was at the eastern end, where the work there proceeding formed a crescent, behind which, the other buildings are thrown in squares.</s> <s id="s341">-- The design for which the proprietor is building this beautiful place, is, to entertain a number of linen manufacturers, the erections being calculated for that purpose, with proper apartments for the directors and governors of such a work.</s> <s id="s342">-- By appearance, it seems as if it would be capable of receiving a thousand artists.</s> <s id="s343">The utility and greatness of this project are too manifest to require the traveller's animadversions; enough it is to say, that such works, under the auspices of such men, give the observer infinite pleasure.</s> <s id="s344">The distances between the rich and poor, in this luxurious and proud age, have been too distinctly maintained.</s> <s id="s345">-- The wealth and felicity of this nation depends upon the intimate connection between property and trade.</s> <s id="s346">-- Where opulence is diffused in works to bless the industrious poor, in projects to promote manufactory and arts, panegyric is silenced by that inward approbation and esteem, which leads the mind to regard such virtue, in the character of the rich man, with reverence.</s></p>
<p><s id="s347">-- We passed along from this agreeable scene to a place called the College, from its having been formerly the residence of the preceptors of the Lowther Family: where our admiration was enlarged by the princely works there carried on, at the sole expense of Sir James.</s> <s id="s348">We obtained admission to inspect the carpet manufactory, which is conducted in the manner of the Goblines.</s> <s id="s349">-- It is not possible to convey any competent idea of the beauty of this work by description;-- the shag thrown up on the face of the carpeting is about half an inch in thickness, which renders it so durable, that a new erected mansion would not outstand such furniture.</s> <s id="s350">The colours are disposed with the utmost taste and judgment, in representation of natural flowers; as delicate, easy, and just, as the works of the pencil.</s> <s id="s351">-- We were so fortunate as to see in the looms some carpets of peculiar beauty; the one wrought on a copper-coloured ground, scattered with sprigs of flowers; the other on a violet ground; - the roses and convolvulus, the jesmines and carnations, were exquisite;-- they looked like fresh pulled flowers thrown upon velvet; their disposition was in the happiest taste, and the colours given to form the most agreeable changes and variety.</s> <s id="s352">-- The master of this work, in an open and polite manner, conducted us; not omitting one circumstance which he apprehended could add to our pleasure in the inspection.</s> <s id="s353">-- The spinning for this work is done by children from the foundling hospital.</s> <s id="s354">-- Tears of pleasure gushed from the eye, to behold these poor orphans, who would otherwise perhaps have been totally lost to the world and themselves; thus, by so excellent a charity, saved from the hands of destruction and vice, rendered useful members of society, and happy in their industry and innocence.</s></p>
<p><s id="s355">-- The carpet manufactury is carried on solely for Sir James's pleasure, and not for sale; we were informed that some little time ago a piece of this work was presented to her Majesty.</s></p>
<p><s id="s356">Passing from the college we descended the banks of the River <enamex sw="w60563" long="-2.714587092202354" lat="54.60426562927525" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13699" name="Lowther" conf="2.6">Lowther</enamex>, whose woody scenes are every where picturesque and pleasing:--</s></p>
<p><s id="s357">--" In this path" How long soever the wanderer roves, each step" Shall wake fresh beauties, each short point present" A different picture; new, and yet the same.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s358">Mason's Garden.</s></p>
<p><s id="s359">-- The beauties of the prospect at <enamex sw="w60851" long="-2.7531" lat="54.6067" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2656903" name="Askham" conf="99992">Askam Bridge</enamex> engaged our attention-- the water descending over a rocky channel, fell in irregular and foaming streams;-- the little plain above was dressed in brightest green; the lofty banks on every hand, were cloathed with stately oaks, save only where a bold promontary, which overhung the road we had passed, shewed its rocky brow from out the shade which crowned its threatening front.</s></p>
<p><s id="s360">A gentleman who was so obliging as accompany us in this day's excursion, conducted our rout with great judgment;-- from <enamex sw="w61366" long="-2.714587092202354" lat="54.60426562927525" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13699" name="Lowther" conf="2.6">Lowther</enamex>, he caused us to ascend the hills, which bordered upon <enamex sw="w61429" long="-2.89078" lat="54.57564" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00028" name="Ullswater" conf="99992">Uls Water</enamex>, so that the Lake was totally concealed from us in our approach, till we were just upon it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s361">-- Having attained the summit, with no small degree of patience and fatigue, it opened suddenly upon our view, presenting a sheet of water in the form of an s, nine miles in extent, and above a mile in width;-- as we looked thereon from an eminence, we could discern all its bays, shores and promontaries, and in the extensive landscape take in a variety of objects, thrown together with all that beauty, which wood and water, lawns, rising sweeps of corn, villas, villages, and cots, surmounted by immense mountains and rude cliffs, can form to the eye;-- the country to the right, for many miles, was variegated in the finest manner, by enclosures, woods, and villas; amongst which <enamex sw="w62217" long="-2.877" lat="54.6699" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY43543089" name="Greystoke" conf="99992">Graystock</enamex>, <enamex sw="w62228" long="-2.84052575158113" lat="54.63029066990679" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:38469" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex>, and Delmain were seen, whilst to the left, nothing but stupendous mountains, and rude projecting rocks, presented themselves, vying with each other, for grandeur and eminence.</s></p>
<p><s id="s362">We descended to the village of <enamex sw="w62442" long="-2.817815867535586" lat="54.61151285171987" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36231" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley</enamex>, and from thence, by a winding road on the margin of the Lake, passed on near a mile, to a small inn, where we left out horses.</s></p>
<p><s id="s363">On the water we were accommodated with one of the Duke of Portland's barges, which have been sent there by his Grace for pleasuring;-- a strong south breeze rendered the Lake so rough, that the surf broke over the bow, whilst the swell gave us motion, almost equal to that felt at sea; my companion suffered no small mortification by this accident, as it incommoded him in drawing views of this admirable scene.</s> <s id="s364">-- We were obliged to coast it up the lake, and keep as much under the wind as possible, the labour being great to make any way, with four boat-men at the oars.</s></p>
<p><s id="s365">-- As we took the boat, there stood to our right, a mountain almost circular, covered with verdure to the crown, arising swiftly from the edge of the water many hundred feet in height, and shadowing us from the sun;-- to the left, the lake spread out its agitated bosom, whitened with innumerable breakers, above a mile in breadth; whose opposite shore in one part ascended gradually with cultivated lands from the village of <enamex sw="w63578" long="-2.817815867535586" lat="54.61151285171987" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36231" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley</enamex>, skirting the hills; over which, some scattered wood was happily disposed in irregular groves and winding lines; whilst all above, the brown heath reached the summits.</s> <s id="s366">-- This land adjoined a mountain much superior in height to that on our right, rising almost perpendicular from the lake, with naked cliffs: on its rugged side, through the grey rocks, was torn a passage for a rivulet, whose waters fell precipitate with a mighty noise into the deep below;-- the ground more distant, which was seen still upwards, over an expanse of water not less than four miles, consisted of lofty rocks and bold promontories, here and there shewing naked and storm-bleached cliffs; and in other places, scattered over with the spring of young oaks, arising from the stocks of trees which the ax had lately slain.</s> <s id="s367">-- We could not forbear lamenting the loss of so great an ornament to this romantic scene, as a forest of timber trees hanging on these declivities must have been, from this and every other point of view on the lake.</s></p>
<p><s id="s368">As we passed along, having doubled two small capes, we fell into a bay, under the seat of John Robinson, Esq; of Water Mellock.</s> <s id="s369">-- From the very margin of the lake, in this part, the grass ground ascended gradually in an easy slope, where were dispersed, in agreeable irregularity, pretty groves of ash: there</s></p>
<p><s id="s370">--" Many a glade is found," The haunt of wood gods only, where if art" Ever dared to tread,' twas with unsandaled feet," Printless, as if teh place was holy ground.</s> <s id="s371">"</s></p>
<p> <s id="s372">Mason's Garden.</s></p>
<p><s id="s373">-- Above which, the easy inclining hills shewed us yellow fields of corn, overtopped by the white front of a venerable mansion, more noted for hospitality, than the elegance of its structure.</s></p>
<p><s id="s374">-- The pleasantness of this bay, the verdure of the new-mown meads, with the shade of the grove, induced us there to take our noon-tide repast.</s></p>
<p><s id="s375">-- Whilst we sale to regale, the barge put off from shore, to a station where the finest echoes were to be obtained from the surrounding mountains.</s> <s id="s376">---- The vessel was provided with six brass cannon, mounted on swivels;-- on discharging one of these pieces, the report was echoed from the opposite rocks, where by reverberation it seemed to roll from cliff to cliff, and return through every cave and valley; till the decreasing tumult gradually died away upon the ear.</s></p>
<p><s id="s377">-- The instant it had ceased, the sound of every distant water-fall was heard, but for an instant only; for the momentary stillness was interrupted by the returning echo on the hills behind; where the report was repeated like a peal of thunder bursting over our heads, continuing for several seconds, flying from haunt to haunt, till once more the sound gradually declined;-- again the voice of water-falls possessed the interval,-- till to the right, the more distant thunder arose upon some other mountain, and seemed to take its way up every winding dell and creek, sometimes behind, on this side, or on that, in wonderous speed, running its dreadful course;-- when the echo reached the mountains within the line and channel of the breeze, it was heard at once on the right and left, at the extremities of the lake.</s> <s id="s378">-- In this manner was the report of every discharge re-echoed seven times distinctly.</s></p>
<p><s id="s379">-- At intervals we were relieved from this entertainment, which consisted of a kind of wonderous tumult and grandeur of confusion, by the music of two French horns, whose harmony was repeated from every recess which echo haunted on the borders of the lake;-- here the breathings of the organ were imitated, there the bassoon with clarinets;-- in this place from the harsher sounding cliffs, the cornet;-- in that from the wooded creek, amongst the caverns and the trilling water-falls, we heard the soft-toned lute accompanied with the languishing strains of enamoured nymphs; whilst in the copse and grove was still retained the music of the horns.</s> <s id="s380">All this vast theatre was possessed by inumerable aerial beings, who breathed celestial harmony.</s></p>
<p><s id="s381">-- As we finished our repast, a general discharge of the guns, roused us to new astonishment; although we had heard with great surprize the former echoes, this exceeded them so much that it seemed incredible: for on every hand, the sounds were reverberated and returned from side to side, so as to give the semblance of that confusion and horrid uproar, which the falling of these stupendous rocks would occasion, if by some internal combustion they were rent to pieces, and hurled into the lake.</s></p>
<p><s id="s382">During the time of our repast, the wind was hushed and the lake, which on our first entrance was troubled and foaming, now became a shining mirror, reflecting reversed mountains, rocks, groves, meads, and vales;-- the water was so transparent, that we could perceive the fish and pebbles at the depth of six or eight fathom;---- we now doubled a woody promontary, and passing by the foot of <enamex sw="w68459" long="-2.917469333" lat="54.58251838" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00157" name="Gowbarrow Park" conf="99992">Gobery</enamex> Park, ascended into the narrow part of the lake, leaving the grassy margins and scattered copse, which had bordered the water as we passed by Water Mellock; now all around us being one scene of mountains, which hemmed us in, arising with awful and precipitate fronts;-- here the white cliffs raised their pointed heads, there the shaken and rifted rocks were split and cavated into vast shelves, chasms, and dreary cells, which yawned upon the shadowed lake; whilst other steeps less rugged were decked with shrubs, which grew on every plain and chink, their summits being embrowned with sun-parched moss and scanty herbage.</s></p>
<p><s id="s383">-- The scene was nobly awful as we approached <enamex sw="w69138" name="Starbury">Starbury</enamex> Crag;-- at every winding of our passage, new hills and rocks were seen to overlook those which had but the minute before been new upon our prospect; the clouds hung heavily upon the mountains, rolling in gloomy volumes over their heads, in some places dragging their ragged skirts along the sides of steeps, giving them a deep and melancholy shade; in others, admitting the sun-beams, which illumined the winding dells with a greyish light.</s></p>
<p><s id="s384">Within a little distance of the shore, we were shewn a spring, described to be of sulphurine quality, but neglected by the neighbouring gentlemen, and remaining unanalized: its situation was such, that it was inconvenient to go to view it, so that we only depended on the relation of our attendants for its description.</s> <s id="s385">-- On my second visit to this lake, I enquired industriously after this valuable curiosity, with intention to ascertain its qualities, but could not return to it; and from the assurances given me by Mr Robinson, that he had never heard of such a spring, I am inclined to believe the account given us was erroneous;-- so liable are strangers to be deceived and imposed on by their guides, on whose veracity they are sometimes obliged to rely for the information they obtain.</s> <s id="s386">-- This leads me necessarily to observe, that this kind of writing is subject to the illiberal criticisms and condemnations of every local pedagogue, whose peculiar taste or superficial knowledge, may be piqued by the traveller's inattention to his particular vein, or the objects of his prejudice, which, together with the impositions the traveller is liable to, by the lying talents of those to whose conduct he is obliged to trust, and from whom alone he must receive intelligence, renders the task of describing irksome, and the attempt to communicate the pleasures of a journey disagreeable.</s></p>
<p><s id="s387">-- The fishermen belonging Mr Robinson were so obliging as to make us two draughts; but were not fortunate enough to take any very large fish;-- they drew trout, perch, and skelley,( which last is a species of trout not uncommon in alpine lakes) all which were of excellent flavour.</s> <s id="s388">-- They sometimes take a trout peculiar to this water, of thirty pounds weight and upwards, and eels of eight or nine pounds.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s389">Vide Pennant's Brit.</s> <s id="s390">Zool.</s> <s id="s391">Vol.</s> <s id="s392">Iii.</s> <s id="s393">p.</s> <s id="s394">267, where it is described under the name of Griniad.</s></p>
<p><s id="s395">-- After a voyage upwards of nine miles, we returned down the centre of the lake, and again arrived opposite the woody promontary, which joins the extreme of the cultivated lands of Water Mellock, when the view down the lake opened upon us.</s></p>
<p><s id="s396">-- The meadows, groves, mountains, and rocks, which environed the lake, were disposed in the most picturesque order, bending around the margin of an expanse of water five miles over;-- the lands of Water Mellock now lay at a distance to the left, surmounted by some small conic hills, the heights of <enamex sw="w72029" long="-2.917469333" lat="54.58251838" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00157" name="Gowbarrow Park" conf="99992">Gobery</enamex> Park, that ranged westward, and terminated by the grassy mountain, at whose foot we passed upon our entrance.</s> <s id="s397">-- These sweetly intermingled groves, corn fields and meads, gently inclining to the lake, where they sunk on the grassy margin, or stretched into easy promontaries, now lay in the happiest arrangement;-- to the right were rocky steeps, down which the foaming cataract was hurried; from whence the upstretching inclosures, on gradual declinations, formed the more distant hills; above, from hanging groves that overlooked each other, blue rocks, crowned with brown heath, appeared;-- at the extreme of this fine crescent, stood mount Dunmorlet, of a beautiful conic form, from its skirts to the crown covered with oaks, ashes, and firs, fortunately mingled; at whose foot, the single arch of <enamex sw="w72840" long="-2.812994518069897" lat="54.61280820901722" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11248058" name="Pooley Bridge" conf="2.6">Pooley bridge</enamex>, the outlet of this mighty lake appeared, bending over a little valley, where a few cottages were scattered; over which, at the extremity of the dale, <enamex sw="w73005" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> beacon formed a pleasing obelisk.</s> <s id="s398">-- The beauties of this scene were encreased by the reflection in the water, where the deep green hue was seen to mix with the olive and the grey of the adjoining objects; whilst the back ground seemed to decline in faintest purple, variegated with the deep crimson streaks of an evening sky.</s></p>
<p><s id="s399">-- We lay upon our oars some time, reluctant to quit this prospect, and enjoyed the music of the horns;-- the exquisite softness and harmony which the echoes here produced, were not to be described; the music seemed to issue from some resounding temple, which stood concealed behind the mountains, where the most solemn and delicate symphony was heard, as if reverberated from the brazen dome, or marble colonades; and as the breeze at intervals grew softer, one might imagine the voices of a thousand choristers had filled the lenghtened chorus.</s></p>
<p><s id="s400">-- It happened fortunately for us, that the sun some short time before setting, shone out serene;-- we made a little turn to look back upon the dark and rocky scene we had passed, when the vapour which had for some time almost covered the mountains with a gloomy veil, appeared to roll upon the breeze like a mighty curtain, and withdrew, opening gradually to the eye the pompous theatre.</s> <s id="s401">-- No sooner were these cumbrous volumes lifted above the summits of the western hills, than the horizontal rays broke in upon the mountains; the grass on the heights which was parched and turned of russet hue, received the light in a delicate manner, becoming a rich shade to the bright gold teints with which the sun beams, passing through the evening vapour, struck the cliffs, as the slantway rays pierced each valley and interstice of the mountains; here beaming over a whole hill, there tinging the tops of rocks, and catching the edges of the precipice, with the lustre of burnished gold; whilst the deep shades of every vale, each dell, chasm, and cave, heightened the colouring above.</s> <s id="s402">-- In the water we traced all this picturesque scene inverted, the long and deep shadows thrown from the mountains over the lake, made the objects, which were thus illumined, beautifully reflected on this sable mirror.</s></p>
<p><s id="s403">-- Here the mind was touched with pious and reverential thoughts, which alone delight in silence, whilst contemplation dwells on the mighty author of such wonderous works; to whom it is acceptable, that the heart of man, seeking him in such scenes as these, should pay that adoration which no language can express.</s></p>
<p><s id="s404">-- Approaching night rouzed us from our rhapsodies; the clouds were deeply tinged with crimson, and the whole lake seemed to glow with a fine carnation;-- as the sun descended, the vapours which hung with a grey hue over the hills now assumed a flame colour, and seemed to wind up a multitude of glowing streams in the most grotesque figures; whilst all below was sinking from the eye in solemn confusion;-- the whole range of mountains appearing as on fire, the images of <enamex  sw="w75981" name="Not a placename">Ovid</enamex> immediately occurred to my memory:</s></p>
<p><s id="s405">--" Caucasus ardet" Ossaque cum <enamex sw="w76055" long="30.81667" lat="-28.41667" type="other" gazref="unlock:2779611" name="Pindo" conf="0.3077716265">Pindo</enamex>, marjorq; ambobus Olympus" Aeriaeq; <enamex sw="w76098" long="7.16667" lat="44" type="other" gazref="unlock:5775842" name="Département des Alpes-Maritimes" conf="0.4265164925">Alpes</enamex>,&amp; nubifer Apenninus."</s></p>
<p><s id="s406">We regained the little inn at the foot of Dunmorlet, where our horses waited, and returned towards <enamex sw="w76226" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>, delighted with our voyage, in conversation enumerating the wonderous and enchanting scenes to which we had been present; till we reached Delmain, the seat of J. Hazell, Esq;-- the rich woods which are spread around this mansion, together with its handsome stone-built front, gave us expectation, whilst we saw it in the morning at a distance, that it would be still more pleasing on a nearer view; but we could not forbear turning our eyes away in disappointment, when we perceived the approach kept with a degree of negligence, which disgraced the elegant structure.</s></p>
<p><s id="s407">In my second visit to <enamex sw="w76826" long="-2.89078" lat="54.57564" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00028" name="Ullswater" conf="99992">Uls Water</enamex>, I past by the remains of the castle of <enamex sw="w76876" long="-2.84052575158113" lat="54.63029066990679" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:38469" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex>, which gave the baronial title to the family of Dacres.</s></p>
<p><s id="s408"><enamex sw="w76938" long="-1.477646082829466" lat="52.47082762318331" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13332758" name="Bede ED" conf="1.315359003">Bede</enamex> and William of <enamex sw="w76958" long="-2.100726269953825" lat="51.58387410631619" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11403" name="Malmesbury" conf="1.353158304">Malmesbury</enamex> say that a monastry stood here, but no remains of it appear at this time.</s></p>
<p><s id="s409">This place is famous for the following congress:-- upon the defection of Guthred, Anlaf his brother, and Inguld king of <enamex sw="w77164" long="" lat="" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:9659" name="" conf="99991">York</enamex>, <enamex  sw="w77170" name="Not a placename">Athelstan</enamex> levied a great force, and entered <enamex  sw="w77214" name="Large admin unit">Northumberland</enamex> so unexpectedly, that the malecontents had scarce time to secure themselves by flight.</s> <s id="s410">-- Guthred gained protection from Constantine king of <enamex  sw="w77370" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>, to whom <enamex  sw="w77388" name="Not a placename">Athelstan</enamex> sent deputies, demanding his person, or upon refusal, he threatened to come in quest of him at the head of his army.</s> <s id="s411">Constantine, although greatly piqued at this insolent message, yet afraid of the formidable arms of <enamex  sw="w77615" name="Not a placename">Athelstan</enamex>, consented to meet him at <enamex sw="w77651" long="-2.84052575158113" lat="54.63029066990679" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:38469" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex>; to which place he came attended by the then king of <enamex  sw="w77710" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, where they did homage to <enamex  sw="w77747" name="Not a placename">Athelstan</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s412">In the church-yard of <enamex sw="w77780" long="-2.84052575158113" lat="54.63029066990679" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:38469" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex> are four remarkable monuments, being the effigies of bears in stone, about five feet high, sitting on their haunches, and clasping a rude pillar, or ragged staff, on which two of the figures have their heads rested; the other two carry on their backs the figures of a lynx, the one of which is in an attitude as if endeavouring to rid himself of the animal on his shoulders, with head twisted, and paws cast behind him.</s> <s id="s413">Their position is such, as to form a square, two to the east of the church, and two to the west.</s> <s id="s414">-- There is no traditional account of the occasion on which they were placed there; and it seems probable they are the remains of the decorations of the monastry, to which the <enamex sw="w78479" long="-1.582140134589936" lat="52.28650722319568" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11313882" name="Warwick" conf="1.913858645">Warwick</enamex> family were benefactors.</s> <s id="s415">-- Plate, Fig. I.</s></p>
<p><s id="s416">-- In the church, within the altar-rails, lies the figure of a Knight Templar, much mutilated, and without any inscription.</s></p>
<p><s id="s417"><enamex sw="w78654" long="-2.890464102233929" lat="53.18298073394839" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11101187" name="Castle, The" conf="1.2">The Castle</enamex> of <enamex sw="w78668" long="-2.84052575158113" lat="54.63029066990679" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:38469" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex> is now dismantled, and has little remains of its former strength or grandeur; the moat being filled up, the outworks destroyed, and only three towers standing, one of which is inhabited by peasants-- This was the original seat of the Barons de <enamex sw="w78919" long="-2.84052575158113" lat="54.63029066990679" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:38469" name="Dacre" conf="2.6">Dacre</enamex>, and from thence sprung that illustrious family:-- it continued in the possession of the Dacres till the reign of Queen Elizabeth, when it came by marriage to the Earl of Sussex; the last Earl of which name dying in the reign of Queen Ann without issue male, it was sold to Sir Christopher <enamex sw="w79216" long="-2.37849714175031" lat="54.51607874079329" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11196773" name="Little Musgrave" conf="2.6">Musgrave</enamex>, and from him was transferred to Edward Hazell, Esq.</s></p>
<p><s id="s418">After our arrival at <enamex sw="w79299" long="-2.89078" lat="54.57564" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00028" name="Ullswater" conf="99992">Uls Water</enamex>, we rode along the shore by Water Mellock, to the head of Gobery Park, there to enjoy the prospect of the Lake, with its opposite mountains.</s> <s id="s419">-- In this park, a quarter of a mile from the shore, is a fine water-fall;-- the stream breaks from the summit of of a cliff cloathed with wood, and falls precipitate through a black rocky scene near eighty perpendicular feet in height, and sixteen feet in breadth;-- after it has past about two thirds of its fall, the whole torrent is received into a cleft of the rock, where its passage is impeded by fragments of stone and fallen timber; beneath which the water, through a multitude of small apertures, breaks forth and forms a foaming sheet, which is received into a large bason, worn by the floods, from whence it flows through a thick woody glen, till it sinks into the lake.</s></p>
<p><s id="s420">At the foot of this rivulet we took to the boat, which waited for us;-- a gentle breeze curled upon the water, and afforded the use of our sail;-- this, though it accommodated us with one pleasure, deprived us of another, for the echoes from the discharge of the canon, were not equal to those heard on our former voyage: though the report was returned in six or seven echoes, yet the sound was hurried forward from one end of the lake to the other, without any return from the opposite shore;-- the music of the horns was lost in the vast space, and two German flutes, which were played on by part of our company, were only to be heard under the shelves, and in recesses of the rocks.</s></p>
<p><s id="s421">We ascended the lake, so as to have a view of its upper extremity;-- on the right, the shores are rocky, and cloathed with wood;-- the oak hoes, being fine conic eminences, crowned with timber trees, arise above the cliffs, over which stupendous mountains elevate their fronts, varied with the beautiful colourings of verdant herbage, mingling with grey rocks, and topped with brown heath: whilst, at the feet of these heights, the cultivated vales of Glen Riddin and Glen Coyn, with their scattered cots, most agreeably form the lower landscape;-- the water in this part is ornamented with two beautiful islands.</s> <s id="s422">-- At the head of the lake, the margin is composed of meads, over which the hills called <enamex sw="w81530" long="-2.9533" lat="54.5597" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY38451869" name="Glencoyne" conf="99992">Glencoyn</enamex> Pikes, and a vast amphitheatre of rocky mountains, bound the view;-- to the left, the shore ascends gradually, and is formed of several fine wooded promontaries, easy inclining meadows, and little coppices interspersed amongst the rocks.</s></p>
<p><s id="s423">The slate quarries of Sir James <enamex sw="w81810" long="-2.714587092202354" lat="54.60426562927525" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13699" name="Lowther" conf="2.6">Lowther</enamex> are seen on the brow of the mountains at the head of the lake;-- these slates are of a fine blue colour, and when won are brought down the steeps of these vast hills on horseback, by winding passes, to the lake, where they are received into flat-bottomed boats, and navigated to proper stations for country sale.</s></p>
<p><s id="s424">Travellers should land at Blarvike, from whence, by walking over two rocky eminences, in a truly alpine scene, where nothing but a chaos of rocks is seen impending over the lake, almost without a mark of vegetation, an agreeable view of the upper limb of the lake is gained, with all its beauties, enhanced to the eye by the frightful deformities through which the spectator hath passed to attain the prospect.</s></p>
<p><s id="s425">At the foot of the lake, on the <enamex  sw="w82576" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland side</enamex>, near the summit of one of the mountains, on its southern declination, we viewed an antient fortress called Caerthanock.</s> <s id="s426">-- The country people give it the name of Maiden's Castle.-- It seems to have been calculated more for a place of concealment, than defence, as it is overlooked by two adjoining hills, and lies under a gradual descent from the crown of the eminence on which it is placed.</s> <s id="s427">-- An oblong square is formed on loose stones, twenty paces in length and fifteen in breadth;-- this is surounded with a circular mound of earth eighty paces in diameter, defended on the outside by a ditch, which remains six paces wide.</s> <s id="s428">-- This place is not noticed by Camden, or any other author I have met with.</s> <s id="s429">-- The name expresses it to be a British fortification, though the circular entrenchment is not agreeable to that mode of defence.</s></p>
<p><s id="s430">Mr Hazel, of Delmain, is possessed of the <enamex sw="w83475" long="-0.3002250724362516" lat="51.29477547543581" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11103050" name="Chace Stud Fm" conf="0.9993608622">Chace</enamex> of Markendale, which borders on the lake, and includes most of the heights which lie upon the eastern side.</s> <s id="s431">-- The lands of his manor being customary tenure, are attended with this badge of servility, the tenants are bound to attend their Lord's hunt within this chace once a year, which is called in their court roll a Boon Hunt.-- On this occasion they have each their district allotted on the boundaries of the chace, where they are stationed, to prevent the stag flying beyond the liberty.</s></p>
<p><s id="s432">-- A stag chace was promised the gentlemen of the country, on the marriage of William Hazel, Esq; heir apparent of the House of Delmain, whose excellent character and merit had rendered the occasion a cause of great festivity in the neighbourhood; but as I was not fortunate enough to be present at this diversion, shall beg the reader's attention to a description given me by one who had enjoyed a similar scene.</s> <s id="s433">--</s></p>
<p><s id="s434">--" A stag having been selected from" his herd, the hounds were conducted" to the copse, where he lay inattentive" to the dangers which surrounded him.</s> <s id="s435">"-- On being roused, he stretched his" limbs, advanced his antlers with solemn" dignity, and looked disdainfully upon" the approaching hunters; he quitted the" cover, and in contempt of the threatenings" of his foes, seemed scarce to touch" the ground, as he bounded upon his" springing pasterns, and made his flight" in vaultings and sportive leaps.</s> <s id="s436">---- The cry" of the hounds was singularly melodious," being re-echoed from shore to shore, and" added to the music of the horns.</s> <s id="s437">-- The" hills were cloathed with spectators;-- on" the lake were several barges with colours" displayed, and other boats, crowded" with people.</s> <s id="s438">-- The stag at first took the" heights, where sometimes he was seen" climbing the mountains with incredible" swiftness, whilst the hounds appeared" in a slower train, pursuing, yet losing" ground, so much did he seem to outstrip" them.</s> <s id="s439">-- At other times, the interposing" mountains robbed us of the sight," but indulged us with the music of the" cry; from the melody of which, attention" was not diverted by having the" pack in view.</s> <s id="s440">-- Again they came in" sight;-- the stag flew over every fence" as an arrow from the bow;-- the hounds" appeared to gain ground;-- the various" windings of the fugitive along the steeps" were all in view;-- at length he found" his flight and speed did not avail him;" he meditated to save himself by artifice," submitting to descend into the lower" grounds, and quit the hills.</s> <s id="s441">-- The people" who attended, perceiving the well-known" signal of his declining speed," with their shouts from every quarter" made each cliff and vale resound.</s> <s id="s442">--" Echo deceived our ears in a surprizing" manner; for the shouts were so repeated," as if the whole extensive circus was" crowded with people, and the huzza" given by tens of thousands.</s> <s id="s443">-- Instantly" all the vessels on the lake were put in motion," and the oars were busied in plying" to that quarter to which the stag advanced;" it is their usual custom, when" pressed by the hounds to take the water," to plunge into the lake, and trust to their" swimming.</s> <s id="s444">-- Many of the pack jumped" into the water-- and the chace was continued" even in the lake.</s> <s id="s445">-- The unhappy" stag found, though he escaped his common" enemy, yet other foes, which rendered" all his efforts for safety vain;-- the" boats enclosed him, and brought him again" to shore.</s> <s id="s446">-- To prolong the diversion," his distress was doubled;-- a respite was" given for some moments;-- hope arose" upon his heart, but of short existence!" with looks of terror he soon beheld his" pursuers upon him:-- after many flights" and once more watering, the noble fugitive" was driven to his forlorn hope;"-- his timid nature was changed by necessity," and courage arose from despair;"-- he stood, and with his horns bayed" the approaching hounds-- his last and" sad ineffectual effort;-- he was seized," and by the hunters saved from being" torn piece meal by the dogs."--</s></p>
<p><s id="s447">-- Compassion and the finer feelings have nothing to do with the chace:-- were men to give way to sympathetic sentiments, the distress and misery of the innocent animal which is pursued and hunted down, would overcome the melody of the cry, and the beauty of those artifices which the pursued employs in vain to save his life.</s> <s id="s448">-- Let such men avoid the chace.</s> <s id="s449">-- Men of robust and hardy constitutions, feel the least compassion or sentiment, and trust the least to thought.</s> <s id="s450">-- Such are the heroes of the hunt.</s> <s id="s451">-- I have been told, that after the captive has received his death's wound from the keeper, it is usual for the hunters to compleat their joy, by staining each other's faces with the gore.</s></p>
<p><s id="s452">A little ramble took place on the ensuing morning;-- in our way, we were shewn the tenement, where, in the great tempest some few years ago, Miss <enamex sw="w88400" long="-2.430426782171715" lat="53.57208890145878" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11082597" name="Bolton" conf="2.01495455">Bolton</enamex> and her female friend were overwhelmed in the ruins of their house:-- <enamex sw="w88478" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.318660087">Over</enamex> whose untimely monument even piety lets fall a tear, and resignation bows to heaven with sighs, whilst hope in holy whispers tells, that innocence and virtue called from hence become angelic.</s></p>
<p><s id="s453">We viewed the ruins of <enamex sw="w88698" long="-2.75583" lat="54.6603" type="other" gazref="unlock:5824892" name="Penrith Castle" conf="2">Penrith Castle</enamex>;-- it is said to have arose on the foundations of a Roman fortress.</s> <s id="s454">-- Camden says, in the reign of Henry Vi.</s> <s id="s455">it was repaired out of the ruins of a Roman fort near to it, called Maybourgh: but this opinion is very erroneous, and entirely exploded by the author of Magna Britannia.</s> <s id="s456">-- The buildings form a square, and are situate on a rising ground, surrounded with a ditch;-- the site towards the town is much more elevated than any of the other quarters.</s> <s id="s457">-- If any remains of Roman work is to be found there, it is on this quarter, where the area bears the appearance of the old vallum.</s> <s id="s458">-- This front consists of the remains of an angular tower to the east, which now stands separated from other parts by the falling of the walls;-- the centre, which projects a little from the place of the front, is hastening to decay, presenting to the eye broken chambers, passages, and stairs;-- this part of the building is still connected with the western angular tower, an open gallery forming the communication;-- below this gallery, a large opening is made by the falling of the building, forming a rude arch; through which, and the broken walls to the East, the interior parts of the ruin are perceived in a picturesque manner:-- nothing remains within to attract notice.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s459">If Bishop Nicholson had not corrected Camden in his account, that <enamex sw="w90054" long="-2.75583" lat="54.6603" type="other" gazref="unlock:5824892" name="Penrith Castle" conf="2">Penrith Castle</enamex> was repaired out of the ruins of <enamex sw="w90102" long="-79.19865" lat="41.5934" type="other" gazref="unlock:7940498" name="Mayburg" conf="0.4999986152">Mayburg</enamex>, a bare view of <enamex sw="w90126" long="-0.7334461399619994" lat="52.22650299344568" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11101189" name="Castle, The" conf="1.2">the Castle</enamex> would do it, being intirely built of red hewn stone.</s></p>
<p><s id="s460"><enamex sw="w90190" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex></s>
</p><p><s id="s461">Was formerly a part of the See of <enamex sw="w90232" long="-1.799652099609375" lat="54.67715454101562" type="civila" gazref="unlock:14121708" name="Durham" conf="2.246518605">Durham</enamex>, but in the time of the ambitious Anthony Beck, King Edward I. dismembered it.</s> <s id="s462">-- It is said in a compromise of differences between Henry Iii.</s> <s id="s463">and Alexander the Scottish King, that Henry stipulated to grant to Alexander two hundred librates of land( each librate being four oxgangs, or, as some compute, of twenty pounds yearly value) in <enamex  sw="w90577" name="Large admin unit">Northumberland</enamex> or <enamex  sw="w90595" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, if so much of Henry's land could be found therein, where no castle stood; and that <enamex sw="w90690" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex> was part of this grant.</s> <s id="s464">-- It is not doubted that Henry Vi.</s> <s id="s465">possessed this castle, and restored it.</s> <s id="s466">-- Richard Duke of <enamex sw="w90817" long="-2.207685538427645" lat="51.85760321860896" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:9703" name="Gloucester" conf="1.960175979">Gloucester</enamex>, afterwards Richard Iii.</s> <s id="s467">about the year 1472 married Ann the widow of Edward Prince of Wales, son to Henry Vi.</s> <s id="s468">and daughter and co-heiress of Richard Nevil, Earl of Warwick and Salisbury, by whom( as part of her dowry) he had the <enamex sw="w91058" long="-0.04965271490377404" lat="51.45275836816165" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11178759" name="Honor Oak" conf="1.53206214">Honor</enamex> of <enamex sw="w91067" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>;-- he repaired and beautified this castle, and made it the chief place of his residence; where, from his munificence and noble manner of living, he acquired great popularity and esteem; in so much, that he drew from thence five thousand men to honour or support his coronation.</s> <s id="s469">-- This castle was afterwards dismantled in the time of the Protector Cromwell, and has lain in ruins ever since.</s> <s id="s470">-- In the time of William Iii.</s> <s id="s471">it was granted to William Bentick, Earl of Portland.</s></p>
<p><s id="s472">From thence we went to view a place by the inhabitants called Arthur's round Table, near to <enamex sw="w91645" long="-2.7454" lat="54.6374" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7298091" name="Eamont Bridge" conf="99992">Emont</enamex> Bridge, and about half a mile from <enamex sw="w91686" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.6">Penrith</enamex>.</s> <s id="s473">-- This is said to be of great antiquity, but there is no tradition, when, by whom, or for what purpose it was made.</s> <s id="s474">-- It is cut in a little plain near the river, of an exact circular figure, save to the eastern and western sides an approach is left to the common level of the plain:-- the trench by which it is formed, is near ten paces wide; the soil which has been thrown up on the outward side making a kind of theatre:-- the approaches are ten paces wide, and the whole circle within the ditch is one hundred and sixty paces in circumference.</s> <s id="s475">-- We were induced to believe this was an antient tilting ground, where justings had been held: the approaches seemed to answer for the career, and the circle appears sufficient for the champions to shew their dexterity in the use of the lance and horsemanship; the whole circus being capable of receiving a thousand spectators on the outer side of the ditch.</s> <s id="s476">-- It is not probable that this was an intrenchment or fortified camp, it being too small for such purposes; and more particularly it is overlooked by an adjoining rising ground, from whence it might be annoyed by missile weapons.</s> <s id="s477">Another reason for the same opinion, given by a learned author, is, that the ditch is on the inner side.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s478">Magna Britannia.</s></p>
<p><s id="s479">It is said of the order of Knights of <enamex sw="w92999" long="-2.7407" lat="54.6484" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY523284" name="Arthur's Round Table" conf="99992">the Round Table</enamex>, that it was instituted by King Arthur, to the end there might be no question about precedency, and to teach heroic minds not to be ambitious of place, but merit.</s></p>
<p><s id="s480">At a little distance from the round table, and nearer to <enamex sw="w93235" long="-2.7454" lat="54.6374" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7298091" name="Eamont Bridge" conf="99992">Emont</enamex> Bridge, is another circular ditch, with a very low rampart, but of much greater size, being seventy paces diameter, without any apertures or advances.</s> <s id="s481">-- If we presume the other was intended for feats of chivalry, this may be supposed calculated for pedestrian exercises.</s></p>
<p><s id="s482">At about half a mile's distance we viewed a place called <enamex sw="w93570" long="-2.746946718" lat="54.64929617" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00126" name="Mayburgh Earthwork" conf="99992">Maybrough</enamex>.</s> <s id="s483">-- A hill, which arises gradually on every side about one hundred and forty paces from the level of the lands below, forming the lower section of a regular cone;-- the ascent is on every side grown with oaks and ashes, and seems, from the reliques of the ax, to have been covered in former ages with wood, though no very antient trees now remain standing.</s> <s id="s484">-- The plate fig. I represents an interior view of the place.</s></p>
<p><s id="s485">-- The summit of the hill is fenced round, save only an opening left to the east, twelve paces wide;-- the fence is very singular, being composed of an immense quantity of loose pebble stones, which seem to have been gathered from the river, by their quality, and the similarity there is between them and the gravel of the bed of the <enamex sw="w94335" long="-2.6167" lat="54.6667" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2650566" name="Eamont" conf="99992">Emont</enamex>.</s> <s id="s486">-- No kind of mortar appears to have been used here, the stones lie uncemented, and in a heap, the foot is near twenty paces wide, rising to an edge, in height about eight feet from the level of the interior plain.</s> <s id="s487">-- Here and there, time has scattered a few trees and brush-wood over the pebbles; but in other places, there are loose and naked, both on the out and inside of the fence.</s> <s id="s488">-- The space within, consists of a fine plain of meadow ground, exactly circular, one hundred paces diameter;-- inclining a little to the westward from the centre, a large mass of unhewn stone is standing erect, placed with the smaller end in the earth, on which some little ash trees have taken their growth, by striking their roots into the natural fissures of the stone;-- this stone is in circumference near its middle twenty - two feet and some inches, and in height eleven feet and upwards; it is a species of the free stone, and appears to have been gathered from the surface, and not won in any quarry or bed of stone.</s> <s id="s489">-- The inhabitants in the neighbourhood say, that within the memory of man, two other stones of similar nature, and placed in a kind of angular figure with the stone now remaining, were to be seen there, but as they were hurtful to the ground, were destroyed and removed.</s></p>
</text>
</document>