<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1819_c"><p><s id="s1"><enamex  sw="w12" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Oakwood Hall</enamex>, A Novel; Including A Description Of The Lakes Of <enamex  sw="w75" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> And <enamex  sw="w90" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, And A Part Of <enamex sw="w118" long="-3.051372180157609" lat="51.73782413172798" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13211759" name="South Wales East Assembly ER" conf="1.253482206">South Wales</enamex>.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s2">By Catherine <enamex  sw="w145" name="Not a placename">Hutton</enamex>, Author Of" The Miser Married," And" The Welsh Mountaineer."</s> </p>
<p><s id="s3">In Three Volumes.</s> <s id="s4">Vol.</s> <s id="s5">I.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s6"><enamex sw="w241" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.529267546">London</enamex>: Printed by <enamex sw="w260" long="-90.1009167" lat="30.8296291" type="other" gazref="unlock:7092323" name="Strahan Cemetery" conf="0.5541395544">Strahan</enamex> and <enamex sw="w272" long="-2.613218010003286" lat="55.73737744776889" type="water" gazref="unlock:11289238" name="Spottiswoode Loch" conf="0.9993240664">Spottiswoode</enamex>, Printers Street; For Longman, <enamex sw="w316" long="-1.087943658706903" lat="53.56837944640728" type="water" gazref="unlock:8787294" name="Grumble Hurst" conf="1.248384162">Hurst</enamex>, <enamex sw="w323" long="6.4" lat="51.7666667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4319026" name="Rees" conf="0.8917622899">Rees</enamex>, <enamex sw="w329" long="-3.869865417921439" lat="53.33347365335865" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11159103" name="Great Orme" conf="1.027024574">Orme</enamex>, And Brown, <enamex sw="w346" long="-0.0981" lat="51.5147" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00035" name="Paternoster Row" conf="99991">Paternoster</enamex> Row.</s> <s id="s7">1819.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s8">Letter Xix.</s> <s id="s9">To Miss Freeman.</s>  <s id="s10"><enamex sw="w400" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s11">You will be surprised, my dear Margaret, to see <enamex sw="w460" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> at the top of a letter you expected from <enamex  sw="w511" name="Mythical place">Arrowby</enamex> Lodge.</s> <s id="s12">When we arrived at the house of my friend, Mrs. Douglas, we found it so full of company, that, after staying one night, I determined to take a view of some of the celebrated lakes of <enamex  sw="w709" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w724" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, which have all my life been the objects of my ardent curiosity: and by the time of our return, a large party will have left.</s> <s id="s13">I have taken Millichamp with me, of course.</s> <s id="s14">If I were thirty years younger, I should expect you to be jealous; as it is, I will forgive you, if you are not.</s> <s id="s15">If you should have a rival, it will start up in the form of a mountain, a lake, or a waterfall: of these Millichamp is an enthusiastic admirer; but he does not even see a woman, if he pass her.</s></p>
<p><s id="s16">The streets of <enamex sw="w1229" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> are narrow; but there is something venerable in the appearance of the place.</s> <s id="s17">The houses are of stone, and many of them large.</s> <s id="s18">The county-hall is a noble edifice, with massive pillars.</s> <s id="s19">The church and castle are situated on a magnificent rock, which commands town and country, sea and land.</s> <s id="s20">As we stood in the church-yard, I looked over an expanse of rolling waters, and shuddered to think, that when they had subsided, my horse was to drag me over the space they now covered.</s> <s id="s21">Millichamp's eyes were directed to the eastward, where the majestic <enamex sw="w1782" long="-2.39060829456302" lat="54.16549773629642" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11182520" name="Ingleborough (Fort)" conf="2.030575203">Ingleborough</enamex>, and his attendant mountains, formed the boundary of sight towards his Margaret.</s> <s id="s22">I did not enter the castle, because it is the county prison; and I have such an aversion to see my fellow-creatures struggling under sickness, madness, or captivity, that I never saw the inside of an hospital, a receptacle for lunatics, or a prison, in my life.</s> <s id="s23">If I could restore health to the sick, reason to the deranged, or liberty to the captive; if I could even carry with me an alleviation of their distress; I would conquer my feelings: but I never can go to see misery from curiosity.</s></p>
<p><s id="s24">We crossed the <enamex sw="w2385" long="-2.672622913542797" lat="54.21368667875034" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788892" name="River Lune" conf="2.4">Lune</enamex>, on a handsome modern bridge, on quitting <enamex sw="w2432" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex>, the quay below presenting a busy scene of warehouses and vessels; and pro ceeded about four miles on the great north road, when we turned to the left, to <enamex sw="w2597" long="-2.800813564608896" lat="54.09802913000562" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:20867" name="Hest Bank" conf="2.6">Hest Bank</enamex>, where the sands begin, that we proposed to cross.</s> <s id="s25">The inn here accomodates a very small company of sea-bathers, whose only machine is the landlord's cart.</s> <s id="s26">We stayed all night, and found the situation of the public room so pleasant, that it might well compensate for a few inconveniences.</s> <s id="s27">From its windows are seen the peninsula of <enamex  sw="w2939" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>, running out into the sea; with <enamex sw="w2982" long="-4.692535773887674" lat="54.22593372544603" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11241717" name="Peel Castle" conf="0.7362922312">Peel castle</enamex> at its extremity, and the town of <enamex sw="w3028" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.8476681723">Ulverstone</enamex> farther in; on the north, the two rivers <enamex sw="w3080" long="-3.793494935244656" lat="55.21775011969775" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:23626" name="Keir Mill" conf="1.328459285">Keir</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w3089" name="Large admin unit">Kent</enamex>, divided by a ledge of rocks, empty themselves into the sea; but they are too distant to be distinguished, among the alternate masses of sand and water, left by the receding tide.</s></p>
<p><s id="s28">The sands here are so flat, that the tide advances with rapid strides, and seldom runs off so as to leave them quite dry.</s> <s id="s29">It is said that the <enamex sw="w3416" long="-2.7746" lat="54.2267" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD496815" name="Milnthorpe" conf="99992">Milthrop</enamex> sands, which are the outlet of the <enamex sw="w3460" long="-3.793494935244656" lat="55.21775011969775" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:23626" name="Keir Mill" conf="1.328459285">Keir</enamex>, are sometimes covered as fast as a horse can gallop: and it is certain that a gentleman, crossing them in a gig, found them so unsound, that he was obliged to put his horse on full speed.</s> <s id="s30">He and his wife, who both related the fact to me, compared the motion of the the sands under them to the shaking of a blanket.</s></p>
<p><s id="s31">This story, with a few others which I heard, of men having been obliged to run away from their shoes, and riders from their horses, made me contemplate my approaching journey not very much at my ease.</s></p>
<p><s id="s32">Next morning, when the waters had retired, we set out; the landlord of <enamex sw="w4053" long="-2.800813564608896" lat="54.09802913000562" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:20867" name="Hest Bank" conf="2.6">Hest Bank</enamex>, whom we had engaged for our guide, leading the way, on horseback; Millichamp and I close behind in the gig; and James following with his horse's nose almost leaning over the gig's back; for every one was determined not to be left behind.</s></p>
<p><s id="s33">A road like this, washed twice in the twenty - four hours by a deep sea, must assume a variety of forms.</s> <s id="s34">The one it wore now was awful.</s> <s id="s35">It had rained in the night; and, though the rain had ceased, the clouds hovered low; the sand was every where wet; and we frequently splashed through pools of sea-water.</s> <s id="s36">We soon crossed the <enamex sw="w4626" long="-3.793494935244656" lat="55.21775011969775" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:23626" name="Keir Mill" conf="1.328459285">Keir</enamex>; a rapid river; but now not higher than a man's mid-leg.</s> <s id="s37">The shore on our right was rocky, and formed a large bay, the centre of which, perhaps, was not more than three miles from us.</s> <s id="s38">The distance across is universally allowed to be eleven miles.</s> <s id="s39">I looked at my watch, and when we had trotted half an hour, I asked our guide how far we had come.</s> <s id="s40">" Three miles and a half."</s> <s id="s41">When we had trotted an hour, I repeated my question.</s> <s id="s42">He looked round," Seven miles."</s> <s id="s43">I was glad to hear he measured miles at that rate; for I believe, by the pace of the horses, we had not gone more than five.</s> <s id="s44">I observed he watched very attentively for the track of the stage-coach, which had gone before us.</s> <s id="s45">Once or twice it was obliterated, which gave me some uneasiness; but he had dexterity enough to find it again, and at last brought us to the brink of the <enamex sw="w5466" long="-2.840631506280864" lat="54.45083129470693" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270576" name="River Kent" conf="2.4">River Kent</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s46">Here we were met by a grey-headed old man, called the carter.</s> <s id="s47">He was on horseback, wrapped in a rug coat; and his legs were cased in a pair of huge, thick boots.</s> <s id="s48">To meet with such a being on the brink of a large river, in a vast solitary desart of sand, and to know it was his business to conduct us safely through it, was a comfort you may easily imagine.</s> <s id="s49">I called out to him," Is the river deep?"</s> <s id="s50">He answered," No, shallow water;" and we followed his steps to the other side.</s> <s id="s51">The current was so strong, that it almost made me giddy, and I fancied it was driving us down towards the sea.</s> <s id="s52">It was considerably more than knee-deep.</s></p>
<p><s id="s53">Arrived in safety at the other side, we stopped some time to converse with the carter, who had a dignity of manner above his station.</s> <s id="s54">His grandfather and uncle had successively been carters, the uncle for seventy years; so that the office seems hereditary in his family.</s> <s id="s55">The allowance from government is ten pounds six shillings and eight - pence a year, and as much land for the keep of his horse, as is worth eight or nine pounds more: but his principal revenue arose from the gratuity that every traveller was willing to pay for his services.</s> <s id="s56">Time was, when no person ventured to cross the river without him; now, a post and a stagecoach traverse the sands every day, and other travellers take the opportunity of accompanying them, and withhold the recompence of the poor carter, who complained that his place was not worth having.</s> <s id="s57">He is obliged, by his office, to be on horseback about six hours every tide, and every second week there are two tides in the day.</s> <s id="s58">He says there is seldom a winter's day so bad that he cannot cross.</s> <s id="s59">The worst times are those when the river is obstructed by ice.</s> <s id="s60">His post is at the edge of the water.</s> <s id="s61">If a traveller approach on the same side, he conveys him over; if on the other, he goes through to meet him; if on both, he escorts the nearest first; and, when nobody appears, he frequently rides through the river, to see that the sands are safe.</s> <s id="s62">Millichamp asked him if it were an unhealthful employment.</s> <s id="s63">He said," No; the only difficulty was to stand the cold."</s></p>
<p><s id="s64">When we had crossed the river, I drew a shilling from my purse: while we were talking.</s> <s id="s65">I took out another; and Millichamp and I both repented we had not doubled the reward.</s></p>
<p><s id="s66">" We now soon reached the opposite shore; having been one hour and forty - four minutes on our passage.</s> <s id="s67">We judged the distance to be nine miles; but our road had been tolerably straight: if ever it be made eleven, it must be when the state of the sands or the weather obliges the traveller to keep nearer the shore.</s> <s id="s68">I was glad to see the horses' feet on terra firma, for I like sands so little, that I will not cross them again.</s></p>
<p><s id="s69">We had only three miles to <enamex sw="w8232" long="-2.894482243304862" lat="54.28519073410449" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:22647" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>, a poor neat town, delightfully situated in a valley, skirted by hills; and hills were now becoming mountains.</s> <s id="s70">The church is large and singular.</s> <s id="s71">A high shelving roof rises between two smaller ones, and one tower steeple rises out of another; the angles of the upper against the sides of the lower.</s> <s id="s72">Within, is a choir, with twenty - six stalls.</s> <s id="s73">By some odd chance, or combination of ideas, these are ornamented with vines and bunches of grapes, which are also twining round, and hanging down the pillars.</s> <s id="s74">There wanted only the figure of <enamex sw="w8774" long="-2.724735811120601" lat="53.85142979762715" type="water" gazref="unlock:8781773" name="Bacchus Brook" conf="1.358830307">Bacchus</enamex> to make me determine what deity was worshipped at <enamex sw="w8832" long="-2.894482243304862" lat="54.28519073410449" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:22647" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s75">We took the road to <enamex sw="w8861" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>; but having proceeded about five miles, we quitted it, to sleep at <enamex sw="w8938" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby bridge</enamex>, at the foot of <enamex sw="w8967" long="-2.9344" lat="54.373" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2633852" name="Lake Windermere" conf="99992">Winander</enamex> Mere, which is here called Windthermere Watther.</s> <s id="s76">-- The lake itself is not seen; but the bridge, of five arches, is over the river which issues out of it.</s> <s id="s77">The place is beautiful,-- a narrow dell, embosomed in hills.</s> <s id="s78">The water is fringed with wood; and the bridge, the inn, a gentleman's house, and one or two others of some consideration, enliven the scene.</s> <s id="s79">On a round hill behind it, called <enamex  sw="w9366" name="Too ambigious to allocate">the Knot</enamex>, is a tower that had been our land-mark from <enamex sw="w9420" long="-2.894482243304862" lat="54.28519073410449" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:22647" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>.</s> <s id="s80">The dialect here is something like ours.</s> <s id="s81">An old woman, who looked like one of Macbeth's witches, told me she had a sister, but" hoo was ganged awa;" and then called out to her grandson.</s> <s id="s82">" Ha lang shalta be, before tha cum, Jan?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s83">This morning our road lay across the foot of <enamex sw="w9702" long="-2.9344" lat="54.373" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2633852" name="Lake Windermere" conf="99992">Winander</enamex> Mere, and at <enamex sw="w9724" long="-2.944660290959193" lat="54.27928021981725" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11142885" name="Fell Foot Park" conf="2.2">Fell Foot</enamex>, the seat of Mr. Dixon, we arrived at its banks.</s> <s id="s84">We travelled up it to <enamex sw="w9805" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, which is eight miles from <enamex sw="w9840" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby bridge</enamex>, over steep, round, rocky hills; sometimes wood intercepting our view of the water, and sometimes seeing it stretched at our feet.</s> <s id="s85">At <enamex sw="w9987" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex> we took a boat.</s> <s id="s86">The surface of the water was as smooth as glass, and three beautiful islands, crowned with wood, rose out of it.</s> <s id="s87">I do not include the large island in the beauties of <enamex sw="w10177" long="-2.9344" lat="54.373" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2633852" name="Lake Windermere" conf="99992">Winander</enamex> Mere.</s> <s id="s88">Though in itself beautiful, it is so near the western shore, that it appears like a headland, jutting out, and narrowing, rather than embellishing the lake.</s> <s id="s89">On this island we landed, and made the tour of it, attended by the gardener.</s> <s id="s90">It is of an irregular, oblong form, containing forty - two acres, and the walk round it is a mile and a half.</s> <s id="s91">You have heard of Mr. English, its former possessor, memorable for the cabbages and pot-herbs which flourished under his auspices.</s> <s id="s92">Weary of lake scenery, he sold it to Miss Curwen, a great heiress, who built a house upon it, and gave it, with herself and her name, to Mr. Christian.</s> <s id="s93">They reside there during the summer months; and a more beautiful situation, or one so uncommon, can scarcely be found.</s> <s id="s94">In winter, an old housekeeper, and the gardener and his family, who live in a cottage, are the only inhabitants of the island.</s></p>
<p><s id="s95">The house is circular.</s> <s id="s96">What an idea! Ugly; and inconvenient as ugly.</s> <s id="s97">It looks like a huge overgrown summerhouse; though the gardener told us that it held twenty - six beds, besides those for servants.</s> <s id="s98">To ornament this round house, the architect has added a square portico, which has no fault that I could discover, except that it has no busi ness there.</s> <s id="s99">The house is built of the stone of the country; the portico of very fine stone, brought from <enamex sw="w11508" long="-2.878238320350647" lat="53.5225887298584" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131229" name="Liverpool" conf="2.298451086">Liverpool</enamex> at a great expence.</s> <s id="s100">The inside walls are of bricks, which, by the time they arrived at <enamex sw="w11605" long="-2.9344" lat="54.373" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2633852" name="Lake Windermere" conf="99992">Winander</enamex> Mere island, are said to have cost three - pence each.</s></p>
<p><s id="s101">The gardener has laid out the ground with great taste; planting the middle of the island, which hides its smallness; and diversifying the shores by scattered trees, clumps, and openings to the finest parts of the lake.</s> <s id="s102">His own house is a paltry imitation of a castle; but he has had the good sense to bury it in a wood.</s> <s id="s103">You have heard terrific tales of bottom winds agitating the lakes, when all was calm above.</s> <s id="s104">This man assures me they never existed; except, perhaps, in the imaginations of some travellers of genius.</s></p>
<p><s id="s105">We intended to have visited some other parts of the lake; though I believe none could excel those we had seen; but the distant clouds threatening rain, we doubled the island of <enamex sw="w12363" long="-2.9401" lat="54.3541" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD390958" name="Crow Holm" conf="99992">Crowholm</enamex>, and rowed back to <enamex sw="w12391" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>.</s> <s id="s106">And prudent it was so to do; for the rain came on soon after, and continued five or six hours.</s></p>
<p><s id="s107">At six o'clock the weather cleared up, and we set out for this place, six miles and a half father; our road still on the borders of the water; but it was more frequently hidden from our view.</s> <s id="s108">In one place it went over a steep rock, from the top of which we saw the whole lake at once; a noble sight! At <enamex sw="w12798" long="-3.005216563799839" lat="54.24283559423841" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11207661" name="Low Wood" conf="2.6">Low Wood</enamex>, the most fashionable inn of <enamex sw="w12836" long="-2.9344" lat="54.373" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2633852" name="Lake Windermere" conf="99992">Winander</enamex> Mere, the road runs close to its margin; the water is broad; the waves roll against the shore; and it gives the idea of an arm of the sea.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s109">The lakes of <enamex  sw="w12998" name="Large admin unit">Wales</enamex> are grand and solemn; that of <enamex sw="w13034" long="-2.9344" lat="54.373" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2633852" name="Lake Windermere" conf="99992">Winander</enamex> Mere is gay and beautiful.</s></p>
<p><s id="s110">Adieu, my dear Margaret.</s> <s id="s111">You shall hear of <enamex sw="w13113" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> in your next letter from</s></p>
<p><s id="s112">Jane Oakwood.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s113">Letter XX.</s> <s id="s114">To Miss Freeman.</s>  <s id="s115"><enamex sw="w13192" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s116"><enamex sw="w13202" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> is a poor little town in a recess of the mountains, at the head of Winander Mere.</s> <s id="s117">We climbed about half a mile above the inn, to see a waterfall, which, after the rain, well repaid our pains.</s> <s id="s118">The road to it is a path, not made with hands, but feet; the latter part hanging over the torrent, and more appropriate than commodious.</s> <s id="s119">The cascade is composed of two separate falls, bursting through trees, and seen through trees, uniting in one, and rushing into a deep rocky channel.</s></p>
<p><s id="s120">I had an inclination to cross the mountains immediately above <enamex sw="w13753" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, at the pass called <enamex sw="w13783" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s121">I consulted the people at the inn, who gave the road a dreadful character; though they said they had dragged a post-chaise over it, with four horses.</s> <s id="s122">I am very cautious in believing what people say of their own roads, for I have uniformly found them worse than the description.</s> <s id="s123">To a man who goes often to a place, the shortest way is the best; custom smooths its ruggedness, and lessens its difficulties; but I would no more take such a man for my guide, than I would follow a banker's clerk through the city of <enamex sw="w14306" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.529267546">London</enamex>, and dive into every alley which pointed to my mark, regardless of dirt, dark ness, and ill smells.</s> <s id="s124">Though I am slow in believing the good, I did not doubt the bad report; but I determined to judge for myself.</s></p>
<p><s id="s125">We rode up three quarters of a mile of very steep road; we relieved the poor animal that drew us, by walking; we then rode about half a mile.</s> <s id="s126">By this time we were come to a hollow in the mountain, and saw the last steep, winding before us, to the top of the pass.</s> <s id="s127">" They who make so much of <enamex sw="w14813" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex>," said I to Millichamp," have not travelled in <enamex  sw="w14870" name="Large admin unit">Wales</enamex>."</s> <s id="s128">I found it, however, more than it seemed; a regular steep ascent of about a mile.</s> <s id="s129">I walked the whole, and then boasted I was at the top of <enamex sw="w15017" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s130">We calculated the distance from <enamex sw="w15060" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> to be three miles; though it is there called four, and four and a half.</s> <s id="s131">The top of <enamex sw="w15153" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex> is flat; but moun tains still rose above us on each side.</s> <s id="s132">It is exactly what in <enamex  sw="w15243" name="Large admin unit">Wales</enamex> is called a <enamex sw="w15261" long="-3.233074830285331" lat="51.54343415288282" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11095032" name="Bwlch-y-cwm" conf="1.393449373">Bwlch</enamex>; but higher than any I ever crossed in that country.</s> <s id="s133">Before we descended, the view opened into <enamex sw="w15363" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>, which, I confess, did not answer my expectation.</s> <s id="s134">The descent was horrible: it was steep and rugged; it wound among rocks, and looked down upon a torrent, newly started from the side of the mountain; but the worst of its qualities was the distance to the bottom; at least two miles.</s> <s id="s135">As I had walked more than two - thirds up, for the sake of the horse, I walked the whole way down for my own; but when I arrived at the bottom, I was too weary to boast that I had got over <enamex sw="w15844" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s136">The high end of <enamex sw="w15871" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>, which we now entered, is broken rocky ground, such as frequently grows at the foot of mountains; it affords pasturage.</s> <s id="s137">As we advance, the small lake of <enamex sw="w16035" long="-2.92425" lat="54.50643" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00058" name="Brothers Water" conf="99992">Broader Water</enamex> fills the vale: after which, it expands into beautiful meadows, till it ends in <enamex sw="w16129" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>.</s> <s id="s138">The head of <enamex sw="w16152" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex> is ten miles from <enamex sw="w16180" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>; the larger half of which, for, surely, I cannot say the better, is over <enamex sw="w16263" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s139">We stopped at Dobson's, a small inn in <enamex sw="w16313" long="-2.938607921075117" lat="54.53595761254276" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:37283" name="Patterdale" conf="2.6">Patterdale</enamex>, a little short of <enamex sw="w16343" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>; and, from a rock behind the house, had a fine view of the upper reach.</s> <s id="s140">From a steep rock, called <enamex sw="w16451" long="-2.9509" lat="54.5489" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11295035" name="Stybarrow Crag" conf="99992">Stybray</enamex> Crag, we had afterwards a view of the middle reach; which I think the finest part of the lake.</s> <s id="s141"><enamex sw="w16554" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex> occupies the whole of the vale; <enamex sw="w16596" long="-2.919758694594441" lat="54.54013840748837" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11246208" name="Place Fell" conf="2.4">Place Fell</enamex>, and other lofty mountains, forming the southern boundary, and woods and craggy rocks the northern.</s> <s id="s142">We travelled eight miles and three quarters by its side, which is the whole length of <enamex sw="w16793" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>.</s> <s id="s143">Along the two first reaches, the road never deviated from the lake.</s> <s id="s144">It sometimes ran close to its margin; at others, climbed over rocky promontories, which shoot into it, and then passed through woods on its border.</s> <s id="s145">We found the woods tenanted by myriads of flies, which, as they are seldom disturbed by man, considered us as invaders of their domain, and tormented us as they thought we deserved.</s> <s id="s146">The lower reach of the lake approaches the open country; and its boundaries are not so grand on one side, or so romantic on the other.</s> <s id="s147">From the end of <enamex sw="w17353" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex> we accompanied its outlet, the River Emont, through a rich country of corn and grass, with a chain of mountains in the back ground.</s> <s id="s148">At <enamex sw="w17498" long="-2.813352976215357" lat="54.63078196381976" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11126513" name="Dalemain" conf="2.2">Dalemain</enamex>, the seat of Mr. Hassal, God has given all that man can desire.</s> <s id="s149">At <enamex sw="w17574" long="-2.749628438755928" lat="54.66475192978902" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11038" name="Penrith" conf="2.594563961">Penrith</enamex> we slept.</s> <s id="s150">It appeared a handsome lively town; but I was so much fatigued, that I did not go out of my way to see it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s151">The next morning we came back two miles of our road, and turned to the right for <enamex sw="w17780" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, which is seventeen miles and a half distant from <enamex sw="w17838" long="-2.749628438755928" lat="54.66475192978902" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11038" name="Penrith" conf="2.594563961">Penrith</enamex>.</s> <s id="s152">We passed the villages of <enamex sw="w17873" long="-2.736531989211191" lat="54.24343301354907" type="water" gazref="unlock:8773440" name="Stainton Beck" conf="2.4">Stainton</enamex> and <enamex sw="w17886" long="-2.885528056569588" lat="54.64083215369705" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32942" name="Penruddock" conf="2.6">Penruddock</enamex>, and came to a high uninclosed country, like downs.</s> <s id="s153">We now approached the mountains.</s> <s id="s154">At eight miles, a lofty, lonely, green mountain, called <enamex sw="w18038" long="-2.937068695763348" lat="54.6208997034264" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11159035" name="Great Mell Fell" conf="2.4">Mell Fell</enamex>, rose on the left; and, a little farther, <enamex sw="w18090" long="-2.99945411033648" lat="54.63837728944336" type="other" gazref="unlock:11288239" name="Southerfell" conf="2">Southerfell</enamex>, on the right.</s> <s id="s155">Here we entered a defile, and rode along the foot of the huge and rugged <enamex sw="w18190" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex>.</s> <s id="s156">At fourteen miles, still at the foot of <enamex sw="w18242" long="-3.05017" lat="54.64151" type="other" gazref="unlock:4563283" name="Saddleback" conf="2">Saddleback</enamex>, is the village of <enamex sw="w18272" long="-3.060956395941065" lat="54.61987757675598" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11300453" name="Threlkeld" conf="2.6">Threlkeld</enamex>, and an inn, which afforded us some refreshment.</s> <s id="s157">We then quitted this vale, and came.</s> <s id="s158">in sight of the celebrated Vale of <enamex sw="w18403" long="-1.683939854346278" lat="54.49795383225262" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35385" name="Aldbrough St John" conf="1.39292649">St. John</enamex>, of which more has been said than it appeared to me to deserve.</s> <s id="s159">I got out of the gig to view the Druid temple, on the hill anove <enamex sw="w18541" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>; it is a circle of upright stones, in a field on the left of the road.</s> <s id="s160">The vale of <enamex sw="w18632" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, the lake of <enamex sw="w18653" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, and the mountains which surround them, now burst at once upon our view.</s> <s id="s161">But here, too, expectation had gone before me.</s> <s id="s162">So much has been said on these subjects, that it is difficult for reality to keep pace with imagination.</s></p>
<p><s id="s163">Letter Xxi.</s> <s id="s164">To Miss Freeman, Oakwood.</s>  <s id="s165"><enamex sw="w18930" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s>
</p>
<p><s id="s166">Yesterday morning we hired a boat for six shillings, to carry us round the Lake of <enamex sw="w19023" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>.</s> <s id="s167">On the left appeared <enamex sw="w19058" long="-2.780479631391105" lat="54.53212900095247" type="other" gazref="unlock:11312627" name="Wallow Crag" conf="2">Wallow Crag</enamex>, a perpendicular rock, fifteen hundred feet high, with wood starting out of its crevices; and, farther on, <enamex sw="w19177" long="-2.996161490249542" lat="54.5035798642049" type="other" gazref="unlock:11141693" name="Falcon Crag" conf="2">Falcon Crag</enamex>, full as high, but not so remarkable.</s> <s id="s168">We landed at Barrowgate, and climbed a wood, to see a waterfall above Ashness House, not to be compared with that at <enamex sw="w19344" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>.</s> <s id="s169">From thence we rowed to Lowdoor, where we landed again.</s> <s id="s170">We had the larger cannon fired; and it was curious to hear the rattling peal reverberated from the mountains: as it first sounded in our ears, we almost looked to see if it were visible.</s> <s id="s171">It was silent while it passed the lake, and we believed it over: we started on hearing it from the opposite side: another silence and another peal ensued, each fainter than the last, till it died away.</s></p>
<p><s id="s172">We now entered <enamex sw="w19815" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>; so unlike the <enamex sw="w19841" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex> delineated by <enamex sw="w19866" long="-2.840445358213598" lat="54.30437481328927" type="water" gazref="unlock:8775056" name="River Gilpin" conf="2.4">Gilpin</enamex>, that I looked round in vain for the place I sought.</s> <s id="s173">had been taught to expect enormous concave rocks, that shut out the mid-day sun, and no such could I find.</s> <s id="s174">Rocks there were, towering high, intermixed with wood, and prodigious masses of them broken off, and lying on the ground; but a sun beamed over them which threw me in a fever.</s> <s id="s175">The village of Grange too, in the bottom, presented no other image than a small assemblage of rustic cots, such as I had often seen before.</s> <s id="s176">If ever you mean to visit the lakes, my dear Margaret, burn your books: too much has been said of lake scenery.</s> <s id="s177">Were it possible to come unexpectedly on such objects, they would indeed be striking; but every thing has been described with all the warmth of fancy; every beauty has been pointed out; every spot from which each is to be viewed; till nature has been reduced to a system, examined by rule, and much of its effect is lost.</s></p>
<p><s id="s178">We walked up to <enamex sw="w20799" long="-0.457342812893218" lat="51.31493819256791" type="water" gazref="unlock:11082462" name="Bolder Mere" conf="1.146825509">Bolder</enamex>( pronounced Boodther) Stone; an immense mass of rock fallen from above; though I could not discover the place.</s> <s id="s179">Here description had given me an idea short of truth.</s> <s id="s180">A ladder is reared against it for those who choose to ascend to its top: I thought the place to view it was below.</s></p>
<p><s id="s181">The lake of <enamex sw="w21098" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, on which we again embarked, is three miles and a half long, and one and a half broad.</s> <s id="s182">Our chief boatman told us it was very safe for oars, but not so for a sail, on account of the sudden gusts of wind that came down from the mountains.</s> <s id="s183">The rowers frequently see these gales on the water; when they put the head of the boat to the blast, and lie still till it is over.</s> <s id="s184">A gentleman, who has lately purchased one of the islands of <enamex sw="w21540" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, contrary to the advice of older men, would sail in a small boat on the lake.</s> <s id="s185">He was met by one of these breezes, which laid his vessel on her side in a moment.</s> <s id="s186">He let go the sail, and she righted; but not before his pockets were filled with water.</s></p>
<p><s id="s187">The islands on <enamex sw="w21817" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> are much admired.</s> <s id="s188">There are four large, and four small.</s> <s id="s189">In my opinion, when an island is so large, or so near the shore, as not to leave a considerable space of water all round, it is rather an incumbrance than an ornament, in a general view.</s> <s id="s190">Lord's and Vicar's islands come under this description.</s> <s id="s191">The first is so called from the unfortunate Lord <enamex sw="w22178" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, and was joined to the main land by a drawbridge.</s> <s id="s192">The second, if I may be allowed the expression, is too large for the ground it stands on.</s> <s id="s193">At a distance, it makes a part of the main; and near, it is too bulky to make a part of the lake.</s> <s id="s194">I find another fault with the islands of <enamex sw="w22470" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>.</s> <s id="s195">They are covered with trees, which appear stuck close together, like upright pins on a pin-cushion.</s> <s id="s196">On those of <enamex sw="w22596" long="-2.9344" lat="54.373" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2633852" name="Lake Windermere" conf="99992">Winander</enamex> Mere, both all trees and brushwood spring spontaneously; spreading, fringing the water, and waving with the wind.</s></p>
<p><s id="s197">The fairy palaces of these romantic lakes often change their masters.</s> <s id="s198">Indeed, of the palaces themselves, much good cannot be said.</s> <s id="s199">They remind me of the vulgar saying about meat and cooks: God Almighty made the ground they stand on; the buildings are by another master.</s> <s id="s200">Mr. Pocklington, who purchased Vicar's island, and vainly called it by his own name, has sold it to Colonel Peachy of the Manks Fencibles, and it is become Vicar's island again.</s> <s id="s201">The house upon it is the king of the monsters.</s></p>
<p><s id="s202">Mr. Pocklington instituted a naval fête of so extraordinary a kind, that it would scarcely be credited, if it were not well remembered.</s> <s id="s203">All the boats of the lake assembled annually on a certain day, commanded by Peter Crossthwaite, formerly captain of an Indiaman, now owner and exhibitor of a museum at <enamex sw="w23518" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, and besieged the great island in form.</s> <s id="s204">The islanders, under Governor Pocklington, were prepared for their reception: cannon were fired on both sides; men pretended to drop down dead, and were besmeared with bladders of blood, brought for the purpose.</s> <s id="s205">When the island could hold out no longer, Governor Pocklington appeared in person, dressed in scarley, and armed with a broad-sword, and surrendered the keys of the citadel to Admiral Crossthwaite, who gave it up to be plundered by his sailors.</s> <s id="s206">Then followed the best part of the jest.</s> <s id="s207">A butt of beef, and a barrel of strong beer, had been prepared, on purpose to be stolen; they were born off in triumph by the sailors, and the evening concluded, in the common phrase, with the utmost festivity.</s></p>
<p><s id="s208">The host of strangers who come to visit this mountainous region are termed by the inhabitants lakers, and, immediately on their arrival, they" find each bird a bird of prey."</s> <s id="s209">Even Millichamp and I, a pair of poor lonely pigeons, not worth the plucking, were surrounded by these hawks.</s> <s id="s210">Their system of rapacity made me draw my purse-strings close; perhaps closer than I ought to have done.</s> <s id="s211">Before we entered <enamex sw="w24683" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, a paper was put into my hands, inviting me to visit the museum of Peter Crossthwaite, late naval commander in <enamex  sw="w24802" name="Large admin unit">India</enamex>; and assuring me, that his was the original museum, and the only one worth seeing.</s> <s id="s212">Every time we passed his house, his organ, moved by some invisible agent, serenaded us.</s> <s id="s213">This was great civility; but I kept my shilling in my pocket.</s> <s id="s214">When we went to the lake, another paper was given me, importing that the museum of Thomas <enamex  sw="w25132" name="Not a placename">Hutton</enamex> was particularly well worth seeing, and that it flourished in spite of slander; so I kept two shillings in my pocket.</s> <s id="s215">When we had landed at Barrowgate, the jurisdiction of the boatmen ceased; they consigned us over to a stately old damsel of a housekeeper, who led the way to the cascade, and our shillings went inevitably.</s></p>
<p><s id="s216">At <enamex sw="w25466" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex> we determined to be free.</s> <s id="s217">We left our rowers at the public-house, and began our march alone.</s> <s id="s218">Here crowds of children followed us, and held open every gate; but as we neither wanted their company nor their services, we did not choose to pay for them; and I was in possession of a charm which dispersed them whenever I pleased.</s> <s id="s219">" Do n't trouble yourselves to follow us; we shall not give you any thing."</s> <s id="s220">To one, a tall girl, with a child in her arms, I said," You are old enough to go to service."</s></p>
<p><s id="s221">" Ise at sarvice," she replied.</s></p>
<p><s id="s222">" Then why are you here?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s223">" Ise ganging doon to the hoose."</s></p>
<p><s id="s224">" And what wages have you?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s225">" I wark for meat."</s></p>
<p><s id="s226">" What is your meat?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s227">" Potatoes and sauce."</s></p>
<p><s id="s228">" And what is sauce?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s229">" Butter."</s></p>
<p><s id="s230">You would scarcely suppose that a woman wanted to show us <enamex sw="w26238" long="-0.457342812893218" lat="51.31493819256791" type="water" gazref="unlock:11082462" name="Bolder Mere" conf="1.146825509">Bolder</enamex> Stone, a stupendous mass of rock which we could not avoid seeing, and which astonished us so much, that we could look at nothing else!" Pray, good woman," said I," what could you shew us that we do not see?"</s> <s id="s231">She could shew us how we might shake hands under the stone.</s> <s id="s232">" Very well," said I;" then we will look at the stone where we are, and shake hands when we get home."</s></p>
<p><s id="s233">We had seen the fall of Lowdoor from the Lake, and finding that it was almost dry, we did not choose to go out of our way to see a waterfall without water, and went straight into <enamex sw="w26794" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s234">Returning, we thought we would step and look at the Channel, and were proceeding to a gate for that purpose, when a man followed us, and offered to open it.</s> <s id="s235">We bade him, as we had bidden the children, not trouble himself, and he retired.</s> <s id="s236">But we soon found he had not made the offer without good reason; for he had clapped a padlock on the gate, that nobody might approach the waterfall without his assistance.</s> <s id="s237">We did not call him back, and this is the only one of my economies that I repent.</s></p>
<p><s id="s238">To Day, Millichamp has ascended <enamex sw="w27330" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, and I have visited several of the stations prescribed by law for views of the lake.</s> <s id="s239">The best is from a steep-wooded hill, called <enamex sw="w27468" long="-3.132864841" lat="54.59417441" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00072" name="Castle Head" conf="99992">Castlet</enamex>, from whence the whole water was spread before me, and seen, surrounding every island.</s> <s id="s240">Farther on was the vale of <enamex sw="w27590" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>; beyond that, <enamex sw="w27612" long="-3.2167" lat="54.65" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2656187" name="Basenthwaite" conf="99992">Bassenthwaite water</enamex>; and on my right, <enamex sw="w27650" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>.</s> <s id="s241">I shall here observe, that the family of <enamex sw="w27700" long="-4.094838019916267" lat="53.07251618046283" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:14140710" name="Snowdon" conf="1.021201755">Snowdon</enamex> is called his sons; the progeny of <enamex sw="w27743" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> is only a cub.</s></p>
<p><s id="s242">I wondered, in my walks, to see the prints of so many asses shoes, and some even on causeways, where it would have been difficult for an ass to get: several times, in <enamex sw="w27933" long="-0.5483601002845776" lat="53.40222907213021" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11289047" name="Spital in the Street" conf="1.429350153">the street</enamex>, I turned my head hastily, thinking a horse was at my heels; and, perhaps, saw nothing but an old woman.</s> <s id="s243">The shoes of the common people unravelled these mysteries.</s> <s id="s244">Their soles are of wood, about an inch in thickness, and shod before and behind with iron; or, as they call it, carkered. Besides these, a plate of iron, the depth of the sole, is fastened round the toe, which is called snout-banding. A pair of shoes, thus carkered and snout-banded, will frequently last twelve months, without mending; and it is surprising to see the dexterity with which even old persons and children carry the unwieldy load.</s></p>
<p><s id="s245">In my account of the sharks of <enamex sw="w28586" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, I omit our watermen, and our landlord at the <enamex sw="w28645" long="-2.978329224014967" lat="52.83455433705558" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:38434" name="Queens Head" conf="1.318970736">Queen's Head</enamex>.</s> <s id="s246">The former candidly owned, to James, that they expected no other gratifica tion than the six shillings agreed for: one of which was claimed by the owner of the boat; one spent at the inn which recommended it; and two they each had for rowing.</s> <s id="s247">As they desired no additional reward, I was perverse enough to give them one.</s> <s id="s248">Our landlord added a reasonable bill to great civility and attention; and I shall, at any time, find pleasure in recommending his house to my friends.</s></p>
<p><s id="s249">To Morrow morning, we once more turn our faces towards <enamex  sw="w29186" name="Mythical place">Arrowby</enamex> Lodge.</s> <s id="s250">I say nothing of Millichamp, because he is writing to you himself.</s> <s id="s251">Only I will tell you, for fear he should not, that though he keeps the main body of his garments about him, small detached pieces of apparel, such as nightcaps, gloves, and pocket handkerchiefs, are deserting him daily.</s> <s id="s252">I have some thoughts of taking charge of his purse myself, as it has had one or two good chances of escaping.</s></p>
<p><s id="s253">One set of long letters is enough.-- You will oblige me by putting these in your pocket, and reading them to Mr. Oakwood.</s></p>
<p><s id="s254">Letter Xxii.</s> <s id="s255">To Miss Freeman, Oakwood.</s>  <s id="s256"><enamex sw="w29759" long="-2.7746" lat="54.2267" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD496815" name="Milnthorpe" conf="99992">Milthrop</enamex>.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s257">We quitted <enamex sw="w29781" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> for <enamex sw="w29793" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, from which it is distant sixteen miles, early in the morning.</s> <s id="s258">The boasted view from <enamex sw="w29888" long="-2.50307798537747" lat="54.59651663772429" type="other" gazref="unlock:11101437" name="Castrigg" conf="1.948941464">Castrigg</enamex>, the hill above <enamex sw="w29913" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, I thought <enamex sw="w29932" long="-2.380959059473901" lat="53.26636647649359" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13406367" name="Peover Inferior CP" conf="1.206470001">inferior</enamex> to that from <enamex sw="w29954" long="-3.132864841" lat="54.59417441" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00072" name="Castle Head" conf="99992">Castlet</enamex>; but it is the first which strikes strangers, who generally approach from that side, and I believe they are right in so doing.</s> <s id="s259">From <enamex sw="w30094" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> we should have taken <enamex sw="w30125" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> first, and have returned by <enamex sw="w30161" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex>.</s> <s id="s260">Our road now lay through a narrow dale, with <enamex sw="w30217" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex> behind; and when we lost it, we opened on Helveylin, which appears to me the most stupendous mountain of the country.</s> <s id="s261">The dale became beautiful; rocks, woods, and steep hills rose out of it, and varied with every turn of the road.</s> <s id="s262">Behind one of these, <enamex sw="w30477" long="-3.0667" lat="54.5333" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2636023" name="Leathes Water" conf="99992">Leathes water</enamex> started up; it is about three miles in length, but almost divided in two.</s></p>
<p><s id="s263">At the <enamex sw="w30572" long="-2.522926386172801" lat="53.72453932281032" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11104476" name="Cherry Tree" conf="1.473116417">Cherry Tree</enamex> at <enamex sw="w30587" long="-3.060646544049678" lat="54.54323368129527" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403099" name="St. John's Castlerigg and Wythburn CP" conf="2.4">Wythburn</enamex>, we stopped to breakfast, and desired to have coffee immediately.</s> <s id="s264">After waiting half an hour, I went into the kitchen, and found a slice of bread toasting itself by the fire.</s> <s id="s265">It entered the parlour soon after, exhibiting a stripe of black in the middle, and one of white on each side, the breadth of the bars.</s> <s id="s266">Its texture was so solid, as to be proof against the butter, which was reduced to an oil, and covered the plate.</s> <s id="s267">This was accompanied by three pints of water, made muddy, under the denomination of coffee; which James, who was behind the scenes, told us, afterwards, was made by throwing a very small quantity of coffee into a large teakettle.</s> <s id="s268">We thought we had mistaken our inn, and expressed our doubts to its mistress; but she assured us that her's was the house frequented by the quality; and we were convinced of it, when we found she charged the same for our breakfast that we should have paid at the first inns in <enamex  sw="w31526" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s269">We had now an ascent of a mile and a half to <enamex sw="w31580" long="-3.03068" lat="54.48221" type="other" gazref="unlock:4575087" name="Dunmail Raise" conf="2">Dunmail Raise</enamex>; the top of a pass in the mountains, where Dunmail, the last king of <enamex  sw="w31663" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, who was slain in the tenth century, lies buried under a grass-grown heap of stones.</s> <s id="s270">The wall which divides the counties of <enamex  sw="w31798" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w31813" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, runs over the centre.</s> <s id="s271">The descent is steeper on the <enamex  sw="w31879" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland side</enamex>, and, at the bottom, lies the beautiful little Lake of <enamex sw="w31952" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s272"><enamex sw="w31963" long="-2.993866462466064" lat="54.44746550347175" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796733" name="Rydal Water" conf="2.4">Rydal water</enamex>, which is yet smaller, succeeds it; and has some charming little islands, decorated with wood of nature's own planting.</s> <s id="s273">I could have wished its owner had taken the pains to remove the weeds, which shoot above the surface of the water.</s></p>
<p><s id="s274">Our road from <enamex sw="w32224" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> to <enamex sw="w32235" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, after having ascended to <enamex sw="w32271" long="-2.50307798537747" lat="54.59651663772429" type="other" gazref="unlock:11101437" name="Castrigg" conf="1.948941464">Castrigg</enamex>, has been a continued defile, between two ranges of mountains, divided across by <enamex sw="w32361" long="-3.03068" lat="54.48221" type="other" gazref="unlock:4575087" name="Dunmail Raise" conf="2">Dunmail Raise</enamex>.</s> <s id="s275">The enterprising hand of man seems to have formed three roads over different passes, in the chain of mountains which rise in <enamex  sw="w32501" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w32516" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s276">The western is this, which is not very difficult of access.</s> <s id="s277">The middle is <enamex sw="w32604" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex>, which, I believe, till of late, was considered as impassable.</s> <s id="s278">The eastern is the great road over <enamex sw="w32712" long="-2.78333" lat="54.45" type="other" gazref="unlock:4562539" name="Shap Fells" conf="2">Shap Fells</enamex>, which I have not seen.</s> <s id="s279">The lakes, which occupy the foot of these passes, seem proportioned to the height of the passes themselves.</s> <s id="s280">The large ones of <enamex sw="w32873" long="-2.9344" lat="54.373" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2633852" name="Lake Windermere" conf="99992">Winander</enamex> Mere and <enamex sw="w32891" long="-2.885404073107643" lat="54.57527677327518" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796991" name="Ullswater" conf="2.4">Ullswater</enamex> lie on each side of the lofty <enamex sw="w32931" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex>; the smaller ones of <enamex sw="w32962" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> and <enamex sw="w32976" long="-3.359050759819266" lat="54.73374954392006" type="other" gazref="unlock:11207353" name="Low Leathes" conf="1.895849027">Leathes</enamex> Water on each side <enamex sw="w33003" long="-3.03068" lat="54.48221" type="other" gazref="unlock:4575087" name="Dunmail Raise" conf="2">Dunmail Raise</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s281">In the cool of the evening we walked back a mile and a half to <enamex sw="w33081" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275806" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex>, and, entering a door in <enamex  sw="w33112" name="Too ambigious to allocate">the park</enamex> wall, had half a mile of steep ascent to the waterfall.</s> <s id="s282">The proprietor has had the discretion to let his place alone, wisely supposing he could not mend it: except in the necessary accommodation of a footpath, his hand does not appear in it.</s> <s id="s283">It would be injustice to judge of the fall in this dry season, which has emptied Lowdoor; but the accompaniments surpass all I ever saw.</s> <s id="s284"><enamex sw="w33500" long="-0.457342812893218" lat="51.31493819256791" type="water" gazref="unlock:11082462" name="Bolder Mere" conf="1.146825509">Bolder</enamex> rocks, indeed, I have seen; trees so naturally and beautifully disposed, never.</s></p>
<p><s id="s285">We were conducted out of <enamex  sw="w33612" name="Too ambigious to allocate">the park</enamex> the way we had entered.</s> <s id="s286">" But," said I to our guide," may not we see the small cascade?" for I was too learned not to know all we had to expect.</s> <s id="s287">He made no answer, but opened another door in the wall, which led us into a thick wood, almost excluding daylight.</s> <s id="s288">I did not think it possible for trees to have spread so deep a gloom.</s> <s id="s289">Emerging from this, we passed an open <enamex sw="w33988" long="-76.33690369999999" lat="39.5181632" type="other" gazref="unlock:7104850" name="Forest Lawn" conf="0.7763783873">lawn</enamex>, and entered another dark embowering shade.</s> <s id="s290">Here our guide opened the door of a mean-looking building; and though I knew what it was to offer to our view, I stood motionless when I entered it.</s> <s id="s291">Neither description nor fancy could paint any thing so beautiful; magic, alone, seemed equal to the effect: how, then, can I convey an idea of it to you! I can but say that we looked through a window, without either frame or glass, and saw, at a few yards distance, the water-fall, environed by trees, which shut out heaven above, and earth around.</s> <s id="s292"><enamex sw="w34535" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.358341971">Over</enamex> the top is thrown a bridge, that is less picturesque than it has been, since humanity has added parapet walls; but, if I had not been told the circumstance, I should not have imagined it could be more so than it is.</s> <s id="s293">A servant, riding over it, on a dark night, fell, with his horse, into the pool of the cascade below.</s> <s id="s294">They had neither of them any bones broken, and, though much hurt, they both recovered; but parapet walls were immediately raised on the bridge, to prevent the possibi lity of such an accident in future.</s> <s id="s295">There are trout in the pool, and one may fish out of the window; but a party of lakers, a few weeks ago, did much better.</s> <s id="s296">They dined in this enchanting retreat, and the poor trout dined with them.</s></p>
<p><s id="s297">Our road lay now by <enamex sw="w35279" long="-2.745809060481465" lat="54.32561646560368" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185036" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex> and <enamex sw="w35290" long="-0.5532341705220136" lat="53.25843959634453" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094187" name="Burton-by-Lincoln" conf="1.409295811">Burton</enamex>, to <enamex sw="w35301" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex>; but, not choosing to go the beaten track, we yesterday morning crossed the head of Winander Mere, and breakfasted at the little town of Hawkeshead, five miles from <enamex sw="w35476" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>.</s> <s id="s298">Before we reached it, we had a charming view of the vale in which it stands, including <enamex sw="w35574" long="-2.977291334332336" lat="54.3599180438576" type="water" gazref="unlock:11140740" name="Esthwaite Water" conf="2.4">Esthwaite water</enamex>, about two miles in length.</s> <s id="s299">From Hawkeshead, our road lay on the border of the water: and, on quitting the vale, we passed through light woods, and by gentlemen's houses, till we came into the woods which skirt <enamex sw="w35801" long="-2.9344" lat="54.373" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2633852" name="Lake Windermere" conf="99992">Winander</enamex> Mere, of which we now and then caught a glance.</s> <s id="s300">At nine miles from <enamex sw="w35877" long="-3.023901654228874" lat="54.37750890240144" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167814" name="Hawkshead Hill" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex>, we arrived again at <enamex sw="w35908" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, having made the circuit of the banks of <enamex sw="w35962" long="-2.9344" lat="54.373" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2633852" name="Lake Windermere" conf="99992">Winander</enamex> Mere.</s></p>
<p><s id="s301">From <enamex sw="w35982" long="-2.96495694909774" lat="54.26698463408014" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:32206" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, I chose rather to encounter rocks I did not know, than sands I did; and we have come fourteen miles to <enamex sw="w36099" long="-2.7746" lat="54.2267" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD496815" name="Milnthorpe" conf="99992">Milthrop</enamex>, over scars and mosses almost frightful.</s> <s id="s302">After a long and gradual ascent, we found ourselves on the top of a hill called Tawtop.</s> <s id="s303">Possibly, if the orthography adhered to the original meaning, it might be Talltop.</s> <s id="s304">From hence we looked, over a turbury below, to <enamex sw="w36367" long="-2.870270619568472" lat="54.24800657671408" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:42588" name="Witherslack" conf="2.6">Witherslack</enamex> <enamex sw="w36379" long="-2.629961755372798" lat="53.7869491367909" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11253825" name="Red Scar" conf="1.533209047">Scar</enamex>, which rose beyond, so destitute of verdure, that at the first glance Millichamp took the ash-coloured rock for ploughed fields.</s> <s id="s305">The descent from Tawtop was about half a mile: steeper than <enamex sw="w36573" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex>; steeper than any thing I ever saw; except the old Welsh road from <enamex sw="w36650" long="-3.034677191253732" lat="51.69822667260078" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11247932" name="Pontypool/Pont-y-pwl" conf="1.474538951">Pont</enamex> Aber Glaslyn, to Tan y bwlch.</s> <s id="s306">I felt the same sensation here as there; fear lest the horses should not be able to keep on four legs, as they walked slowly over such unequal ground.</s> <s id="s307">You may be assured we walked too.</s></p>
<p><s id="s308">Having crossed the vale, which is a mixture of rock and peat, we ascended <enamex sw="w36944" long="-2.870270619568472" lat="54.24800657671408" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:42588" name="Witherslack" conf="2.6">Witherslack</enamex> <enamex sw="w36956" long="-2.629961755372798" lat="53.7869491367909" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11253825" name="Red Scar" conf="1.533209047">Scar</enamex>, as high as it is cultivated, and then went along its side; leaving the enormous ploughed rocks above.</s> <s id="s309">To this scar succeeded one still higher, called <enamex sw="w37112" long="-2.852510210721162" lat="54.27996687258928" type="other" gazref="unlock:11320167" name="Whitbarrow Scar" conf="2">Whitbarrow Scar</enamex>, the rocky summit of which had exactly the appearance of a ruined castle.</s> <s id="s310">As I looked up, I fancied I could distinguish walls and towers.</s> <s id="s311">Below us was <enamex sw="w37279" long="-2.820899591577965" lat="54.23524310022309" type="other" gazref="unlock:11147208" name="Foulshaw Moss" conf="2">Foulshaw</enamex> <enamex  sw="w37288" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Moss</enamex>, with our road, which is called the Long <enamex sw="w37334" long="-3.00543510534219" lat="54.25182255148098" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11101916" name="Causeway End" conf="2.6">Causeway</enamex>, running across it, like a white thread; and beyond this a better country.</s> <s id="s312">The moss affords a passage to two small rivers, which join the <enamex  sw="w37481" name="Large admin unit">Kent</enamex> a little farther down; and as nature, in complaisance to these, has given them a valley as level as their own waters, she has made herself amends, by raising a barrier of huge rocky fells on one side, and not very small rocks on the other.</s> <s id="s313">At <enamex sw="w37729" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex>'s bridge we crossed the <enamex  sw="w37759" name="Large admin unit">Kent</enamex>, and got into another world.</s> <s id="s314">No more mosses or rocks, but the finest verdure and the noblest trees.</s> <s id="s315">The scenery about the bridge is uncommonly beautiful.</s> <s id="s316"><enamex sw="w37918" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex>'s park is the seat of the Earl of Suffolk.</s></p>
<p><s id="s317">We did not arrive at <enamex sw="w37988" long="-2.7746" lat="54.2267" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD496815" name="Milnthorpe" conf="99992">Milthrop</enamex> till late last night; and we shall not leave it till evening, on account of the heat.</s> <s id="s318"><enamex sw="w38083" long="-2.894482243304862" lat="54.28519073410449" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:22647" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>, Hawkeshead, and <enamex sw="w38108" long="-2.7746" lat="54.2267" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD496815" name="Milnthorpe" conf="99992">Milthrop</enamex>, please me much; three pleasant, poor, and quiet towns, that do not, all to gether, afford one post-chaise.</s> <s id="s319">There is only one inn in each, and these are rather mean; but the people are civil, the provisions good, and the charges so moderate, that one would not think the same country supplied the food which furnishes the neighbouring inns on the great roads.</s></p>
<p><s id="s320">I was sitting to-day, after dinner, with Millichamp, when, his shirt bosom being a little open, I espied a black ribband.</s> <s id="s321">" Millichamp," said I," what have you hanging to that ribband?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s322">He hesitated, and replied," A remembrance of Margaret."</s></p>
<p><s id="s323">" A picture?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s324">" No."</s></p>
<p><s id="s325">" A lock of hair?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s326">" No."</s></p>
<p><s id="s327">" What then?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s328">" I will tell you," he answered," because you will not laugh at me; but I should be afraid to tell any other person."</s></p>
<p><s id="s329">He then drew from his bosom a bit of folded writing-paper, which contained-- what?-- A darn in a piece of diaper, in which the threads were as exactly laid, as they had been at first by the shuttle of the weaver.</s> <s id="s330">I contradicted his good opinion of me; for I could not help laughing, and exclaiming," What a remembrance! and by the fair one's own hand!"</s></p>
<p><s id="s331">" You may laugh," said Millichamp;" but a picture would only have reminded me of my Margaret's beauty, and a lock of hair could only have attached my ideas to her person; but this is an emblem of her virtues.</s> <s id="s332">This, as I will prove to you, proclaims her affection, industry, modesty, and ta lents.</s> <s id="s333">If she had not loved me, she would not have darned my night-cap.</s> <s id="s334">If she had not been industrious, she would not have darned it.</s> <s id="s335">If she had not been modest, she would have told me she had done it.</s> <s id="s336">And if she had not been ingenious and correct, she could not have done it so well."</s></p>
<p><s id="s337">" And so, as a proof of your Margaret's virtues, you cut it out of your night-cap?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s338">" I did; and determined to wear the hole in it for her sake; but, when it came from washing, it was mended again, though not so neatly as before; and I believe it was done in a coarser manner, that the hand of the workwoman might not be suspected."</s></p>
<p><s id="s339">Dear Margaret, how fortunate that such a profound reasoner should come to your door! How many young women might live to be wrinkled before they met with a logician who could deduce all these consequences from a darn in a night-cap!</s></p>
<p><s id="s340">End Of The First Volume.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s341">Printed by <enamex sw="w40419" long="-90.1009167" lat="30.8296291" type="other" gazref="unlock:7092323" name="Strahan Cemetery" conf="0.5541395544">Strahan</enamex> and <enamex sw="w40431" long="-2.613218010003286" lat="55.73737744776889" type="water" gazref="unlock:11289238" name="Spottiswoode Loch" conf="0.9993240664">Spottiswoode</enamex>, Printers Street, <enamex sw="w40462" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.529267546">London</enamex>.</s>
</p>
</text>
</document>