<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1771_a"><p><s id="s1">A Tour In <enamex  sw="w23" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s2">Mdcclxix.</s> <s id="s3">Tros Tyriusque mihi nullo discrimine agetur <enamex sw="w87" long="-2.890650344182352" lat="53.19196958316057" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11104567" name="Chester" conf="1.941508663">Chester</enamex>: Printed By John Monk.</s> <s id="s4">Mdcclxxi.</s>
</p><p><s id="s5">The country between <enamex sw="w148" long="-3.436251929794801" lat="55.33411155755289" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10241" name="Moffat" conf="1.300146437">Moffat</enamex> and <enamex sw="w159" long="-3.3563" lat="55.123" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2643791" name="Lockerby" conf="99991">Lockerby</enamex> is very good, a mixture of downs and corn-land, with a few small woods: the country grows quite flat and very unpleasant.</s> <s id="s6">Cross a fmall river called the <enamex sw="w321" long="-3.043771324289254" lat="55.04440166485178" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772028" name="River Sark" conf="2.326720681">Sark</enamex>, which divides the two kingdoms, and enter <enamex  sw="w370" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s7">About three miles farther cross the <enamex sw="w418" long="-3.30009716472156" lat="54.3940525814659" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771979" name="River Esk" conf="2.166983059">Esk</enamex> over a handsome stone-bridge, and lie at the small village of <enamex sw="w484" long="-2.96338204564023" lat="55.0091956888473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:22582" name="Longtown" conf="2.559097225">Longtown</enamex>. The country is very rich in corn, but quite bare of trees, and very flat.</s> <s id="s8">Near this village, at <enamex sw="w591" long="-2.946690997669673" lat="55.03426776775118" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11227952" name="Netherby" conf="2.55386423">Netherby</enamex> are the ruins of a Roman sta -, tion, where statues, weapons and coins are often dug up.</s></p>
<p><s id="s9">Cross the Eden to <enamex sw="w706" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.25967798">Carlisle</enamex> a pleasant city, surrounded with walls, like <enamex sw="w760" long="-2.890650344182352" lat="53.19196958316057" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11104567" name="Chester" conf="1.941508663">Chester</enamex>, but they are very dirty, and kept in very bad repair.</s> <s id="s10">The castle is antient, but makes a good appearance at a distance: the view from it is fine, of rich meadows, at this time covered with thousands of cattle, it being fair-day.</s> <s id="s11">The Eden here forms two branches, and infulates the ground; over one is a bridge of four, over the other one of nine arches.</s> <s id="s12">There is besides a prospect of a rich country, and a distant view of Cold Fells, Cross Fells, <enamex sw="w1220" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.188894326">Skiddaw</enamex>, and other mountains.</s></p>
<p><s id="s13">The cathedral is very imperfect, <enamex  sw="w1284" name="Not a placename">Cromwell</enamex> having pulled down part to build barracks with the materials.</s> <s id="s14">There remains some portion that was built in the Saxon times, with very massy pillars and round arches.</s> <s id="s15">The rest is more modern, said to have been built in the reign of Edward Iii.</s> <s id="s16">who had in one part an apartment to lodge in.</s> <s id="s17">The arches in this latter building are sharp-pointed: the cast window remarkably fine.</s></p>
<p><s id="s18">The manufactures of <enamex sw="w1689" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.25967798">Carlisle</enamex> are chiefly of printed linnens, for which near 3000l.</s> <s id="s19">per ann. is paid in duties.</s> <s id="s20">It is also noted for a great manufacture of whips, which employs numbers of children.</s></p>
<p><s id="s21">Salmons appear in the Eden in numbers so early as the months of December and January; and the <enamex sw="w1962" long="-0.08573711413610305" lat="51.48768230024373" type="civila" gazref="unlock:13326794" name="Greater London Authority" conf="2.319473095">London</enamex> and even <enamex sw="w1978" long="-1.66667" lat="55" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00027" name="Newcastle upon Tyne" conf="99991">Newcastle</enamex> markets, are supplied with early fish from this river: but it is remarkable, that they do not visit the <enamex sw="w2092" long="-3.30009716472156" lat="54.3940525814659" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771979" name="River Esk" conf="2.166983059">Esk</enamex> in any quantity till April, notwithstanding the mouths of both these waters are at a small distance from each other.</s> <s id="s22">I omitted in its proper place an account of the <enamex sw="w2262" long="-1.66667" lat="55" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00027" name="Newcastle upon Tyne" conf="99991">Newcastle</enamex> fishery, therefore insert here the little I could collect relating to it: the fish seldom appear in the <enamex sw="w2376" long="-2.12294" lat="54.98234" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00186" name="River Tyne" conf="99992">Tyne</enamex> till February: there are about 24 fisheries on the river, besides a very considerable were, and the whole annual capture amounts to about 36,000 fish.</s> <s id="s23">I was informed that once the fish were brought from <enamex sw="w2584" long="-2.726444260973307" lat="56.05602135232765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11348" name="North Berwick" conf="1.170978549">Berwick</enamex> and cured at <enamex sw="w2605" long="-1.66667" lat="55" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00027" name="Newcastle upon Tyne" conf="99991">Newcastle</enamex>; but at present, notwithstanding all goes under the name of Newcafstle Salmon, very little is taken there, in companion of what is caught in the Tweed.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s24">Begun by Walter, deputy of these parts, under William Rufus; but the new choir was not founded till about 1354.</s></p>
<p><s id="s25">The country near <enamex sw="w2901" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.25967798">Carlisle</enamex> consists of small enclosures; but a little farther on, towards <enamex sw="w2973" long="-2.749628438755928" lat="54.66475192978902" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11038" name="Penrith" conf="2.513101145">Penrith</enamex>, changes into coarse downs.</s> <s id="s26">On the east, at a distance, are ridges of high hills running parallel to the road, with a good inclosed country in the intervening space.</s> <s id="s27">Above <enamex sw="w3154" long="-2.749628438755928" lat="54.66475192978902" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11038" name="Penrith" conf="2.513101145">Penrith</enamex> is a rich inclosed tract, mixed with hedge-row trees and woods.</s> <s id="s28">On the south-west, a prospect of high and craggy mountains.</s> <s id="s29">After I left <enamex sw="w3299" long="-3.3563" lat="55.123" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2643791" name="Lockerby" conf="99991">Lockerby</enamex>, Nature, as if exhausted with her labors in the lofty hills of <enamex  sw="w3372" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>, seemed to have lain down and reposed herself for a considerable space; but here began to rise again with all the sublimity of alpine majesty.</s></p>
<p><s id="s30"><enamex sw="w3525" long="-2.749628438755928" lat="54.66475192978902" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11038" name="Penrith" conf="2.513101145">Penrith</enamex> is an antient town, seated at the foot of a hill: is a great thoroughfare for travellers; but has little other trade, except a small one of checks.</s> <s id="s31">The church is very neat, the gallery supported by large columns, each formed of a single stone.</s> <s id="s32">In the church-yard is a monument of great antiquity, consisting of two stone pillars eleven feet six inches high, and five in circumference in the lower part, which is rounded; the upper is square, and tapers to a point: in the square part is some fret-work, and the relievo of a cross.</s> <s id="s33">Both these stones are mortised at their lower part into a round one: they are about fifteen feet asunder; the space between them is inclosed on each side with two very large but thin semicircular stones, so that there is left a walk between pillar and pillar of two feet in breadth.</s> <s id="s34">Two of these lesser stones are plain, the other two have certain figures at present scarce intelligible.</s></p>
<p><s id="s35">Cross the Emot, a small river, and soon after the <enamex sw="w4503" long="-2.714587092202354" lat="54.60426562927525" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:13699" name="Lowther" conf="2.57156978">Lowther</enamex>, over Yeoman's Bridge, near which I enter</s></p>
<p><s id="s36"><enamex  sw="w4554" name="Large admin unit">Westmorland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s37">About four miles farther cross <enamex sw="w4598" long="-2.71146" lat="54.62861" type="other" gazref="unlock:9773111" name="Clifton Moor Railway Station" conf="1.957718979">Clifton Moor</enamex>, where the Rebels made a short stand in 1745, and sacrificed a few men to save the rest of their army.</s> <s id="s38">Pass over <enamex sw="w4724" long="-2.70213192148222" lat="54.46969187537132" type="other" gazref="unlock:11281530" name="Shap Fells" conf="1.949115606">Shap Fells</enamex>, more black, dreary, and melancholy, than any of the Highland hills, being not only very barren but destitute of every picturesque beauty.</s> <s id="s39">This barren scene continued till within a small diftance of</s></p>
<p><s id="s40"><enamex sw="w4934" long="-2.745809060481465" lat="54.32561646560368" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185036" name="Kendal" conf="3.059913068">Kendal</enamex>, a large town on the <enamex sw="w4962" long="-2.745484042987077" lat="54.30764151236711" type="water" gazref="unlock:11270577" name="River Kent" conf="2.384693845">River Kent</enamex>, in a rich and beautifull vale, well cultivated, and prettily wooded.</s> <s id="s41">Here is a very great trade in knit worsted-stockings, some linsies, and a coarse sort of cloth, called cottons, for the <enamex  sw="w5164" name="Large admin unit">Guinea</enamex> trade.</s></p>
<p><s id="s42">Near <enamex sw="w5183" long="-0.6855457191527591" lat="52.36085754462765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094145" name="Burton Latimer" conf="1.188437871">Burton</enamex> enter <enamex  sw="w5196" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>.</s> <s id="s43">Reach its capital, <enamex sw="w5227" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.017181404">Lancaster</enamex>, a large and well-built town, seated on the <enamex sw="w5282" long="-2.672622913542797" lat="54.21368667875034" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788892" name="River Lune" conf="2.36746325">Lune</enamex>, a river navigable for ships of 250 tuns as high as the bridge.</s> <s id="s44">The custom-house is a small but most elegant building, with a portico supported by four ionic pillars, ona beautifull plain pediment.</s> <s id="s45">There is a double slight of steps, a rustic surbase and coins; a work that does much redit to Mr. Gillar, the architect, an inhabitant of this town.</s></p>
<p><s id="s46">The church is seated on an eminence, and commands an extensive but not pleasing view.</s> <s id="s47">The castle is entire, the courts of justice are held in it; and is also the county jail.</s> <s id="s48">The front is very handsome, consists of two large angular towers, with a handsome gateway between.</s></p>
<p><s id="s49">Hastened through <enamex sw="w5927" long="-2.705402502615134" lat="53.75956131118807" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11249845" name="Preston" conf="2.025835855">Preston</enamex>, <enamex sw="w5937" long="-2.6381" lat="53.5685" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:13224553" name="Wigan" conf="99991">Wiggan</enamex>, <enamex sw="w5946" long="-2.554683566093445" lat="53.38736343383789" type="civila" gazref="unlock:14126032" name="Warrington" conf="2.179248536">Warrington</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w5963" long="-2.890650344182352" lat="53.19196958316057" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11104567" name="Chester" conf="1.941508663">Chester</enamex>, and finished my journey with a rapture of which no fond parent can be ignorant, that of being again restored to two innocent prattlers after an absence eqully regretted by all parties.</s></p>
</text>
</document>