<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1893_a"><p><s id="s1">Down The <enamex sw="w21" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> With Wordsworth By Herbert Rix, B.A.</s>
</p><p><s id="s2">" Careless of flowers that in perennial blow Round the moist marge of Persian fountains cling; Heedless of Alpin torrents thundering <enamex sw="w197" long="-2.721001163485692" lat="54.03201649694773" type="water" gazref="unlock:8774117" name="Trough Brook" conf="2.366413158">Trough</enamex> ice-built arches radiant as heaven's bow; I seek the birth-place of a native stream."</s></p>
<p><s id="s3">The admirer of Wordsworth's <enamex sw="w318" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> Sonnets will perhaps do the same.</s> <s id="s4">If so, he will probably be a good deal puzzled by the large number of birthplaces which this particular" native stream" seems to possess.</s> <s id="s5">Countless rills ooze from mossy beds in all directions, and there seems no particular reason why any one should be chosen more than any other.</s></p>
<p><s id="s6">For my own part, so bent was I upon doing my duty to the full, that for two mortal hours I tore about those fells, tracking stream after stream to its fountain head with a copy of Thorne's" Rambles by Rivers" open in my hand at page 11, where there is a picture purporting to represent" The Source of the <enamex sw="w946" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>."</s> <s id="s7">Alas! each stream that I ascended led me at length to a place with a crag, a stone or two, and a tiny brook, just like James Thorne's picture and so soon as I had decided upon one, I was sure to find half a dozen others which answered just as well.</s></p>
<p><s id="s8">The stream, however, upon which I finally fixed as the one which, from its beauty, the poet is most likely to have followed, may be thus identified.</s> <s id="s9">As soon as the traveller from Landale reaches the" <enamex sw="w1404" long="-3.117241463264904" lat="54.41263588064015" type="other" gazref="unlock:11300399" name="Three Shire Stone" conf="2">Three Shire Stone</enamex>," let him turn sharply to the right and at a distance of about two hundred yards he will come to a deep cleft hung with a tapestry of bracken and parsley fern, and roofed by the interwoven branches of two mountain ashes springing from the rock on either hand.</s> <s id="s10">Just above this grotto the stream divides, the right-hand branch leading to the highest, the farthest, and therefore, geographically speaking, the source of the <enamex sw="w1843" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>, while the left-hand branch leads to a spot more nearly answering to the description in the Sonnets, which we may therefore call the poetic source.</s> <s id="s11">At this point there is no open prospect; nothing but bare crags, scattered boulders, ling, and moss.</s> <s id="s12">The very Spirit of Desolation seems to brood around, and the blast goes ever moaning through the pass beneath.</s> <s id="s13">Here we find the" gleam of brilliant moss" which the poet notes - a patch of bog-moss showing up brightly amid the dark heather - and here we note the" trembling eyebright," the" purple thyme," and those" sundry flowers" of hardy constitution for which the tiniest gully forms a sufficient shelter even on this bleak mountain.</s></p>
<p><s id="s14">Tripping musically down from stone to stone the little rill soon reaches the more level ground of <enamex sw="w2636" long="-3.117241463264904" lat="54.41263588064015" type="other" gazref="unlock:11327716" name="Wrynose Pass" conf="2">Wrynose</enamex> <enamex  sw="w2644" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Gap</enamex>, and then goes</s></p>
<p><s id="s15">" Thridding with sinuous lapse the rushes, through Dwarf willows gliding, and by ferny brake,"</s></p>
<p><s id="s16">till at length, its volume having grown at every step, it reaches the brow of the hill with its infancy behind it and its fate at hand.</s> <s id="s17">Like some poetic nature living unnoticed and solitary, but ever gaining strength for the crisis of life, this river has hitherto meandered through desert places; but now the crisis is come, and with one bold plunge <enamex sw="w3109" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> leaps into life, hurls himself headlong from the precipice, and so, by a series of cascades, foams his way down to the foot of <enamex sw="w3243" long="-3.1156" lat="54.4146" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY27700270" name="Wrynose" conf="99992">Wyrnose</enamex> Fell.</s></p>
<p><s id="s18">A less perilous path conducts the traveller to the same position, and he finds himself in that most barren and forbidding region known as <enamex sw="w3395" long="-3.147804138495237" lat="54.40336061293446" type="other" gazref="unlock:11327713" name="Wrynose Bottom" conf="2">Wrynose Bottom</enamex>.</s> <s id="s19">On either hand hangs a dark mountain, so steep that the vast blocks of stone which cover it look as though they might at any moment come slipping in a deadly avalanche upon the wayfarer.</s></p>
<p><s id="s20">The first sign of human life is the little house at <enamex sw="w3650" long="-3.163207410991242" lat="54.40321322882879" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11111654" name="Cockley Beck" conf="2.6">Cockley Beck</enamex> - that" cottage rude and grey" of which Wordsworth sang in one of the sweetest of his sonnets.</s> <s id="s21">It is situated just at the bend of the stream, where <enamex sw="w3811" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> emerges from <enamex sw="w3831" long="-3.147804138495237" lat="54.40336061293446" type="other" gazref="unlock:11327713" name="Wrynose Bottom" conf="2">Wrynose Bottom</enamex>, and turns to pursue a southerly course between the counties of <enamex  sw="w3910" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w3925" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>.</s> <s id="s22">As we round the corner, the green trees clustered about the cottage break with a sense of relief upon the eye, and almost involuntarily we look for those" ruddy children," whom the poet paused to watch at their sport.</s> <s id="s23">Alas! where are they?</s> <s id="s24">They are grey and wrinkled, or lying perhaps in <enamex sw="w4225" long="-3.192710108182777" lat="54.35798160812438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279852" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex> churchyard.</s> <s id="s25">And yet, as I stood there upon <enamex sw="w4279" long="-3.159574454108297" lat="54.4027762361785" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:14206" name="Cockley Beck" conf="2.6">Cockley</enamex> Brig and gazed at the little cottage, so literally was the poet's picture reproduced, that the young mother actually came forth from the door, the" ruddy children" of another generation playing merrily beside her.</s> <s id="s26">So" one generation passeth away, and another generation cometh."</s></p>
<p><s id="s27">And now we find ourselves in a more generous region, as we pursue the course of the stream through vagrant meadows.</s> <s id="s28">" I shall never forget," says Mr. Rawnsley, in a note to Professor Knight's edition of Wordsworth," the beauty or the size of the golden feathery spikes of sweet scented gallium, lady's bedstrawm or the wonderful odour of the selfheal, and the glory of the harebells, as I saw them carpeting the meadows near <enamex sw="w4990" long="-3.163207410991242" lat="54.40321322882879" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11111654" name="Cockley Beck" conf="2.6">Cockley Beck</enamex>."</s> <s id="s29">Through such meadows I pursued the stream for half a mile, and found myself at length nearing a solitary farmhouse; but long before I reached it a hound came rushing across the fields, leaping wall after wall, and barking furiously all the way.</s> <s id="s30">Fortunately he was muzzled, an unusual precaution where strangers are so few and far between, but one which was soon explained.</s> <s id="s31">There was a" clippin'" going on; the farmer's care was for fell-lambs, not for chance travellers.</s></p>
<p><s id="s32">And here let me advise the reader by all means to go to a north-country" clipping," if he ever gets the chance.</s> <s id="s33">It was a quaint and characteristic sight.</s> <s id="s34">With the dalesman down the <enamex sw="w5657" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> it is quite a grand occasion, for their fellow-dalesmen come from far and near to give a helping hand, and, while the men are busy in the byre, the good wife bustles to and fro to provide the needful refreshment.</s> <s id="s35">Things are managed here on the give-and-take principle.</s> <s id="s36">The yeomen of the <enamex sw="w5951" long="-3.193494016" lat="54.37016091" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00146" name="Duddon Valley" conf="99992">Duddon Valley</enamex> keep no staff of labourers, but Tom o' <enamex sw="w6004" long="-3.095966416155546" lat="54.31489886282274" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:25489" name="Thrang Crag Wood" conf="2.4">Thrang</enamex> helps Reuben o' <enamex sw="w6027" long="-3.295888062240946" lat="54.2130936327904" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11191747" name="Langthwaite Fm" conf="2.2">Langthwaite</enamex>, and Reuben helps Tom when his turn comes; and so each man goes the round of all the" clippings," the" clippings" at different farms being, of course, arranged to fall on different days.</s></p>
<p><s id="s37">I begged leave to watch the operation, and was invited to stay as long as I chose, the farmer's wife hospitably bringing out currant cake and gooseberry wine for the stranger's refreshment.</s> <s id="s38">The men were mostly tall, and somewhat gaunt, with big bushy beards.</s> <s id="s39">They wore leather leggings, and blue cotton jackets reaching just to the waist and drawn in like a" garibaldi."</s> <s id="s40">Each shearer is provided with a" par sheears" and a" sheep-stool"-- the latter being a kind of bench, across one end of which he straddles.</s> <s id="s41">When he is ready for work, the lad whose business it is to keep the shearers provided with sheep brings the animal with its head towards the operator, and by a dexterous twist throws it on its back upon the stool.</s> <s id="s42">The fleece is cut away underneath, and then the four legs are tied with a" sthring" and the shearer clips the back, working lengthwise from head to tail, and bringing away the fleece in one piece.</s> <s id="s43">As he nears the end of the operation he cries" Sheep!" and another sheep is then ready for him by the time that he has finished.</s></p>
<p><s id="s44">Before I took my leave one of the shearers invited me to go to his clippin on the morrow, which was at the highest house anywhere upon these fells, remarking that I could there" spy oot t' nakedness o' t' laand."</s> <s id="s45">I declined with thanks, though I was glad to have seen one clipping.</s> <s id="s46">I could not but regret that I was too late for the sheep-washing, especially as Wordsworth has devoted one of <enamex sw="w7670" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> sonnets to the subject; but, as one of the farm-boys explained to me," They mostly wesh three weeks an' a month afore they clips."</s></p>
<p><s id="s47">For the next mile or two the river flows along a tolerably level bed, troubled only here and there, where the stream is shallow and the stones are large.</s> <s id="s48">The first considerable break occurs at <enamex sw="w8001" long="-2.530420621975364" lat="54.31776717193408" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11077784" name="Birks" conf="2.485680374">Birks</enamex> Brig, where the river is precipitated to a lower level, and at the same time forced into a much narrower channel, being churned into a mass of foam in the process.</s> <s id="s49">From this point the country becomes increasingly wild and rugged, and the river presently plunges into a fissure between two towering crags, the Faery Chasm of Wordsworth's eleventh sonnet, entitled" Hints for the Fancy."</s></p>
<p><s id="s50">Seen even from the road, the crags by which the river is imprisoned are exceedingly picturesque.</s> <s id="s51">Here a rock crowned with a group of pines, and there one whose top is bright with verdure; here an unbroken wall of grey, and yonder a great cleft choked with brushwood; while behind and above all rises the sombre head of <enamex sw="w8712" long="-3.208887855126327" lat="54.38478705157009" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11166663" name="Harter Fell" conf="2.4">Harter Fell</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s52">Such were the romantic scenes through which I wandered that July afternoon.</s> <s id="s53">Every sight and sound told of nature's wildest life and man's most primitive pursuits.</s> <s id="s54">The musical bleating of lambs mingled sweetly with the muffled roar of the torrent, and from the shepherd's cot perched quaintly on a rocky shelf came a whiff of peat-smoke through the open door.</s> <s id="s55">Then the crags became lower, and <enamex sw="w9117" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> came into sight again, banked now by grassy slopes blue with orchids, and crossed" The Fiddle Stones" where the path to <enamex sw="w9244" long="-3.323474574274605" lat="54.38973821999076" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:39694" name="Eskdale Green" conf="2.6">Eskdale</enamex> struck across the stream.</s> <s id="s56">And when a second time he hid himself from view I did not follow him, but chose instead to climb one of the crags that walled him in-- a rock bearing the ancient British name of" <enamex sw="w9458" long="-2.811921514610853" lat="54.55888661396433" type="other" gazref="unlock:11242002" name="Pen, The" conf="1.969138012">The Pen</enamex>."</s> <s id="s57">The ascent was gradual, but it ended abruptly on the verge of a precipice, and it was with a thrill of surprise that I found myself suddenly in view of far-famed Donnerdale.</s></p>
<p><s id="s58">" Hail to the fields-- with dwellings sprinkled over, And one small hamlet under a green hill Clustering, with barn and byre, and spouting mill!"</s></p>
<p><s id="s59">To that" one small hamlet" I now descended, for evening was falling, and as it was still a good step to <enamex sw="w9894" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex> it behoved me to inquire whether I could perchance get accommodation here in <enamex sw="w9977" long="-3.192710108182777" lat="54.35798160812438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279852" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>.</s> <s id="s60">Luckily I got into the good graces of some people at a farmhouse very near at hand, and there I slept, reserving for the morrow a detailed examination of this classic ground.</s></p>
<p><s id="s61">The next day was Sunday, and proved to be the very sweetest day of all the summer-- a tender spring-like day, as though May had come back to see how July was getting on.</s></p>
<p><s id="s62">It seemed appropriate to spend my Sunday here, in a place whose beauties and memories had inspired the sonnet to Religion--" Sacred Religion! Mother of form and fear!" It was a" means of grace" to wander in lanes and fields which had been looked upon and loved by the" priest" of <enamex sw="w10620" long="-3.192710108182777" lat="54.35798160812438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279852" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>--" Wonderful Walker," as he is admiringly called to this day.</s></p>
<p><s id="s63">Every one knows his story-- how he reared and educated a family of ten children on a living amounting at first to thirteen pounds a year and a cottage, and at last to something under fifty pounds; and how with this mighty income he refused the additional living of <enamex sw="w10964" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>, for fear he should be deemed covetous! how he tilled his own garden, span and wove and fashioned his own garments, tanned his own leather, dug his own peat, and dipped his own rushlights; and how, with all his frugality, he was so far from being niggardly, that he would often expend his whole weekly allowance of fresh meat in making broth on Sunday for those of his parishoners who came from afar.</s> <s id="s64">There are men still living whose fathers worked side by side with him at the" clipping" and the" haying"; and I have been told by such a one how he kept by him a hay-cloth, such as is still sometimes used in that district for gathering and carrying the shorter grass, and how, after helping some neighbour at his haying, he would be seen trudging homeward in his wooden clogs, with the sheet of hay slung over his shoulder-- his guerdon for the day's work.</s></p>
<p><s id="s65">A humorous story, too, I learnt from a native of the valley concerning his frugality.</s> <s id="s66">The old parson( or" priest," as they were then called) would occasionally have a merry-making at the parsonage, on which occasion the cards would be brought out.</s> <s id="s67">Whist was played, and also round games.</s> <s id="s68">Walker's sight not being very good, he would have a rushlight to himself besides that in the centre of the table.</s> <s id="s69">When he was" cut out" of the game he would blow out his rushlight, and as soon as he" cut in," he would re-light it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s70">A quaint figure truly! but a character which has left its impress to this hour, and a memory still green, though a century has passed above his tomb--</s> </p>
<p><s id="s71">" A pastor such as Chaucer's verse portrays; Such as the heaven-taught skill of Herbert drew; And tender Goldsmith crowned with deathly praise!"</s></p>
<p><s id="s72">I strolled up the road in the fresh morning, my heart overflowing with a sense of the tenderness and brightness and delicious grace of the scene.</s> <s id="s73">I stood before the parsonage-- the same low white cottage in which Robert Walker lived and died.</s> <s id="s74">It was covered to the very chimneys with ivy, barbary, and white roses, and through the open door came the" mimic notes" of the cuckoo-clock.</s></p>
<p><s id="s75">Close by is the little school-house.</s> <s id="s76">There was no school-house in Robert Walker's time.</s> <s id="s77">He used to sit in the chancel of the church with his spinning-wheel, and hear the children their lessons while he span.</s> <s id="s78">But the simple little building which now stands here is quite in keeping with his memory and with the surrounding scene.</s></p>
<p><s id="s79"><enamex sw="w13365" long="-3.187972142" lat="54.35484638" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00087" name="Seathwaite Chapel" conf="99992">Seathwaite Chapel</enamex>, which lies a few steps further on, is not the <enamex sw="w13430" long="-3.187972142" lat="54.35484638" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00087" name="Seathwaite Chapel" conf="99992">Seathwaite Chapel</enamex> which Robert Walker knew-- that has vanished, and in its place has arisen this little grey church with its three lancet lights.</s> <s id="s80">It is simple and appropriate enough, but yet I must confess to a regret that the lowly pile in which the venerable patriarch enchained the hearers with his rugged eloquence has gone, and that the place which knew it shall know it no more.</s></p>
<p><s id="s81">Then I crossed <enamex sw="w13833" long="-3.1306" lat="54.3924" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:8773738" name="Tarn Beck" conf="99992">the Tarn Beck</enamex>-- that" tributary stream" of which the poet sang--" the fairest, softest, liveliest of them all."</s> <s id="s82">On the further bank stands a ruined mill-- a structure which in Wordsworth's day was in full work, and which he tels us called to his mind" the momentous changes wrought by such inventions in the frame of society."</s> <s id="s83">But the little old mill spins no yarn now, and te machinery which once stood within its roofless walls, and which was so full of moment in the poet's mind, would raise a smile on the face of a modern manufacturer.</s> <s id="s84">Sic transit.</s> <s id="s85">Then I crossed a stretch of boggy ground covered with rushes, cotton-grass, and light blue orchids, and a bit of pasture land with deep rich turf, and a rock cropping up in the middle, and then, squeezing myself through a slit in the wall( a kind of gangway much in vogue here), I came to a strip of copse and a fringe of feathery larches marking the river bank.</s> <s id="s86">For at this point we come to the <enamex sw="w14791" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> again-- a broad, shallow stream just here-- and, peering through the bushes,</s></p>
<p><s id="s87">" Lo! what might seem a zone Chosen for ornament-- stone matched with stone In studied symmetry, with interspace For the clear waters to pursue their race Without restraint."</s></p>
<p><s id="s88">These may be" The <enamex  sw="w15076" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Stepping Stones</enamex>" with which tradition associates the name of Wordsworth, though I am inclined to think that the true" stones" are further up the valley, near" <enamex sw="w15235" long="-3.178610543749578" lat="54.40306388059761" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11078541" name="Black Hall" conf="2.2">Black Hall</enamex>."</s></p>
<p><s id="s89">Standing half way across the stones and looking up a stream you see a perfect chaos of rocks-- great fragments of which have been torn from the impending crags by storm and frost, and tossed here and there in titanic heaps.</s> <s id="s90">The water comes through them, and under them, and over them, and round them, forcing its way just as it can down the stony wilderness.</s> <s id="s91">A most lovely and romantic spot! well fitted for the rustic courtship of the" shepherd lass" and her lover.</s> <s id="s92">And when Silvius and PhOEbe have safely crossed the stones, there awaits them on them on the further side a delicious woodland path, with here and there a lover's seat in the shape of a boulder, or an old tree-stump bowered among the bushes and cushioned with the softest moss.</s></p>
<p><s id="s93">In these woods I wandered for a while-- lost myself in the tunnels of hazel and leafy oaklings, but found my way back to the stepping-stones at last, and there sat listening to the music of the <enamex sw="w16193" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> till I fell into a long reverie, from which I was awakened only by the sound of the church-bells coming up from <enamex sw="w16312" long="-3.192710108182777" lat="54.35798160812438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279852" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex> and calling me to morning prayer.</s></p>
<p><s id="s94">I obeyed the summons, and, entering the churchyard, found the dalesmen standing about in groups awaiting the arrival of the parson.</s> <s id="s95">He came, and his flock trooped after him into the little church.</s> <s id="s96">It was a goodly sight that array of bronzed faces and clean smocks.</s> <s id="s97">These men, who daily come in contact with reality, who lead no life of dreams or theories, but live face to face with nature, have something impressive in their presence.</s> <s id="s98">And to see them gathered for the worship of that God whose presence they have never learned to doubt, is to have one's own faith confirmed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s99">When service was ended I looked around for the relics of Robert Walker.</s> <s id="s100">They are unfortunately few.</s> <s id="s101">The pulpit is gone, and so is the pew lined with cloth of his own weaving.</s> <s id="s102">There is a brass affixed to the wall of the church, originally fastened to his tomb.</s> <s id="s103">It bears the inscription" In memory of the Rev. Robert Walker, who Died on the 25th June 1802, in the 93rd yera of his Age An 67th of his Curacy at <enamex sw="w17341" long="-3.192710108182777" lat="54.35798160812438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279852" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>."</s> <s id="s104">His tombstone, a simple slab of mountain slate, bears the same words.</s> <s id="s105">The little sun-dial still stands in the kirk-yard upon its whitened post, and the yew tree( more than 200 years old, they say) looks gravely down, pensive with the memories of bygone generations.</s></p>
<p><s id="s106">All through the bright hours of that peaceful day I hovered round this sacred spot, climbed the Pen to look down upon the village, or sat and pondered in some quiet nook by the banks of <enamex sw="w17806" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>, till the sun went down lighting the hilltops with a golden glory, and the shadows came stealing up Donnerdale.</s> <s id="s107">It was a Sunday long to be remembered.</s> <s id="s108">In such a place one needs no books of meditation.</s></p>
<p><s id="s109">" Each cloud-capped mountain is a holy altar; An organ breathes in every grove; And the full heart's a psalter Rich in deep hymns of gratitude and love!'</s></p>
<p><s id="s110">The next morning I bade good-bye to my hostess and took the road to <enamex sw="w18235" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>.</s> <s id="s111">The sun was not yet high.</s> <s id="s112">A maiden, with a can in one hand and a rake in the other, was just going to the hayfield.</s> <s id="s113">Six little girls in cotton hoods and pinafors of blue and white were trotting merrily along on some important mission; they could not be going to school, for it was holiday time and the school-house was shut.</s> <s id="s114">Rich masss of foliage, and rocks streaked with white spar, adorned the roadside till, at the distance of a mile from <enamex sw="w18684" long="-3.192710108182777" lat="54.35798160812438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279852" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>, the hamlet of <enamex sw="w18710" long="-3.206612762061802" lat="54.34921400477799" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:40402" name="Hall Dunnerdale" conf="2.6">Hall Dunnerdale</enamex> was reached.</s></p>
<p><s id="s115">One is struck here by the sudden change in the appearance of the river.</s> <s id="s116">A deep pool, with surface absolutely unbroken, lies above and below the bridge, and even further down the stream the water is but slightly ruffled, and goes wimpling donw with" liquid lapse serene" between banks thickly wooded with oak, ash, beech, larch, and plane-trees.</s> <s id="s117">The mountains, too, have lost their rugged peaks, and the valley is set amidst lower and greener hills, more like Surrey Downs than the crags of the rugged North.</s> <s id="s118">The whole scene corresponds well to the twentieth of the <enamex sw="w19304" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> Sonnets.</s></p>
<p><s id="s119">I did not cross the bridge, as the road upon the right of the stream is separated from it by intervening fields, and I desired to have as close a companionship with the little river as possible.</s> <s id="s120">Keeping down the left bank, therefore, I chose a longer but a prettier route to <enamex sw="w19595" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>.</s> <s id="s121">On the way we pass a set of eighteen stepping-stones-- the fourth set since leaving <enamex sw="w19689" long="-3.163207410991242" lat="54.40321322882879" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11111654" name="Cockley Beck" conf="2.6">Cockley Beck</enamex>.</s> <s id="s122">Here the stream again freshens into life, and is very turbulent from this point all the way to <enamex sw="w19798" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>.</s> <s id="s123">The banks, too, are rocky, and often of considerable height, and at one point they form a vista which is somewhat remarkable.</s> <s id="s124">The stream takes a sudden and unexpected turn to the right, and, as if by magin, opens up a view down a long straight channel walled in on each side by slabs and pillars of slate.</s> <s id="s125">Half way down this corridor, which is known to the natives by the name of Long Dub, is a somewhat noteworthy spot.</s> <s id="s126">The forst, or some other of Nature's agents, has here split off a quantity of slate in thin slabs, and these slabs have got themselves jammed together at all sorts of angles, the interstices being filled with luxuriant growth of feathery fern.</s> <s id="s127">Here a rill trickles down and falls into the river by a miniature cascade, and just beyond it is a cliff of rock, some twelve or fifteen feet in height, overhanging a deep sullen pool, where the thick foliage of oak and beech casts a black shadow on the waters.</s> <s id="s128">This pool, I cannot doubt, is the scene of Wordworth's twenty - second sonnet; there is no other which answers so well to the description.</s> <s id="s129">Hither came the poor broken-hearted girl, seeking to solace herself with the beauty of the spring flowers, and here, by some slip of the foot or some failing of the heart or brain, she fell, and the cold waves of <enamex sw="w21082" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> closed over her.</s></p>
<p><s id="s130">" Upon the steep rock's breast The lonely primrose yet renews its bloom, Untouched memento of her hapless doom!"</s></p>
<p><s id="s131">There is but one other spot worthy of note before we come to <enamex sw="w21279" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>, and that is the ancient burial-place at <enamex sw="w21326" long="-3.170943449740977" lat="54.13347128285491" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11228642" name="New Close Fm" conf="2.112241297">New Close</enamex>.</s> <s id="s132">I had often wondered what might be the scene of Wordsworth''s twenty ninth sonnet, and why two sonnets so near together in the series should be devoted to burial-places, when I chanced to find mention in some country history of a Quaker burial-place near <enamex sw="w21592" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>, and immediately the lines sprang to mind with a flash of new meaning,</s></p>
<p><s id="s133">" No record tells of lance opposed to lance, Horse charging horse,' mid these retired domains."</s></p>
<p><s id="s134">Accordingly, on a visit to this region, which I paid in 1883, I set to work to discover the whereabouts of this Quaker graveyard.</s></p>
<p><s id="s135">" Can you tell me of any burial-place near here besides the kirkyard at <enamex sw="w21965" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>?"</s> <s id="s136">I asked of an old labourer who was hoeing turnips.</s></p>
<p><s id="s137">" <enamex sw="w22025" long="70.04715" lat="37.17255" type="other" gazref="unlock:2923619" name="Kōh-e Sang Wāl" conf="0">Wal</enamex>," he slowly replied, tilting his hat over his eyes and scratching the back of his head," there is a pleace they calls' the se pul chre,' but I never heard tell o' onybody being buried there."</s></p>
<p><s id="s138">And no wonder, for it is now 130 years or thereabout since any" friend" was interred here.</s> <s id="s139">The little square enclosure contains two old fir-trees and a mass of laurels and tangled grass.</s> <s id="s140">All trace of the graves is hidden, nor can so much as one epitaph be read.</s> <s id="s141">The very picture of oblivion is this lonely spot upon the mountain slope.</s> <s id="s142">Far away the busy world pursues its own ambitions, nor gives a thought to those who here are sleeping:</s></p>
<p><s id="s143">" Yet to the loyal and brave, who lie In the blank earth, neglected and forlorn, The passing winds memorial tribute pay; The torrents chant their praise."</s></p>
<p><s id="s144">I regarded this as a discovery, for the sonnet loses half its point unless interpreted by its locality, and I am not aware that this had ever before been identified.</s></p>
<p><s id="s145">Leaving the" <enamex sw="w22993" long="-3.44507137652138" lat="54.70426049023622" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771355" name="Sepulchre Beck" conf="2.1643335">Sepulchre</enamex>," we pass through a copse, and then across some low-lying fields where the little white Kirk of <enamex sw="w23099" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>, perched high upon its rock, comes clearly into sight, hanging literally</s></p>
<p><s id="s146">" like a star, that doth present Its shining forehead through the peaceful rent Of a black cloud diffused over half the sky."</s></p>
<p><s id="s147">Thence we may climb the fells upon the right, and visit the old castle of the Lords of <enamex sw="w23390" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>, though there is little enough now left of it, what with the tooth of time and the still more destructive hands of the dalesman who have used its old stones to build new barns,</s></p>
<p><s id="s148">" Fallen, and diffused into a shapeless heap, Or quietly self-buried in earth's mould, Is that embattled house, whose massy keep Flung from yon cliff a shadow large and cold.</s> <s id="s149">There dwelt the gay, the bountiful, the bold; Till nightly lamentations, like the sweep Of winds-- though winds were silent-- struck a deep And lasting terror through that ancient <enamex sw="w23933" long="-1.203133010685334" lat="51.34037340872234" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11319632" name="Wheat Hold" conf="1.105183597">Hold</enamex>."</s></p>
<p><s id="s150">By the bye, Wordsworth tells us in another place that the tradition here alluded to belongs in reality to quite a different locality, and is introduced here only by poetic licence.</s> <s id="s151">But the old castle does not need to borrow, for it has a tradition of its own.</s> <s id="s152">At least, the natives tell a vague story of a lady being killed here by a wolf close to a well, which is on that account called to this day" The Lady's Dub( i.e. pool);" and some say that this incident gave the palce is name of <enamex sw="w24429" long="-2.721840156330559" lat="54.71225348846785" type="other" gazref="unlock:11324883" name="Wolfa" conf="1.857159573">Wolfa</enamex> or <enamex sw="w24438" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>.</s> <s id="s153">In all probability, however, the" Wolf," after which the place was really named, was <enamex  sw="w24530" name="Not a placename">Ulf</enamex>, the son of Evard, to whom the lordship was originally granted, and whose posterity enjoyed it till the time of Henry Iii.</s></p>
<p><s id="s154">Thence it will be best to descend again and follow the right bank of the stream through the thick woods of <enamex sw="w24764" long="-3.238328544" lat="54.29475077" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00147" name="Duddon Grove" conf="99992">Duddon Grove</enamex>.</s> <s id="s155">As I continued my journey by this path the sky darkened, and as good luck would have it a rain-storm swept the valley.</s> <s id="s156">And it is not in irony that I speak of this as good luck, for nothing else could have lent such beauty to this part of my journey.</s> <s id="s157">The fine feathery grass, which ws very abundant, was soon bedewed with sparkling drops, and the larches were a sight for fairy-land.</s> <s id="s158">But that which especially owed its beauty to this downpour was the Dunnon.</s> <s id="s159">The bed below <enamex sw="w25250" long="-3.238057281238421" lat="54.33055836482416" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11309242" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex> is strewn with blocks of stone of some size, and the river, swelled by the rain, rushed impetuously over these, and was thrown into billows which curled backwards and fell foaming in a direction opposite to that in which the stream was flowing.</s> <s id="s160">The tributary torrents came roaring down the hills on either hand, and in one place I skirted a copse through which the water swept in one broad flood, rooting up the saplings and beating itself into a sheet of foam among the tangled underwood.</s></p>
<p><s id="s161">Half way through <enamex sw="w25763" long="-3.238328544" lat="54.29475077" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00147" name="Duddon Grove" conf="99992">Duddon Grove</enamex> I fell in with a gamekeeper trampling unconcernedly through the pouring rain, and in the course of conversation he assured me that often the streams will suddenly come rushing down the fells when there has not been a drop of water in the valley, and that they will even pour down the hills on one side of <enamex sw="w26081" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> while those upon the other side are almost dry-- so abrupt and so partial are these mountain storms!</s></p>
<p><s id="s162">The way here lies amidst beautiful woods, with noble specimens of beech and fir, and a carpet of rich green moss stretching far away beneath the covert.</s> <s id="s163"><enamex sw="w26345" long="-3.236978659407915" lat="54.2946137796413" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11133275" name="Duddon Hall" conf="2.2">Duddon Hall</enamex> lies upon the left, with white front and outspread lawns-- a very pleasant sight, yet striking one somewhat strangely after the grey farmhouses of the upper valley nestling beneath their homely sycamores.</s> <s id="s164">Everything, however, bespeaks our approach to a town.</s> <s id="s165">There are multiplied wheel-tracks, and passers-by become less rare.</s> <s id="s166">Another mile or so and the road turns to the left, crossing the <enamex sw="w26751" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> and the Lickle, and then rising by a short steep hill to the town of <enamex sw="w26827" long="-2.73333" lat="53.81667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4578882" name="Broughton" conf="0.8481712074">Broughton</enamex> In-Furness.</s></p>
<p><s id="s167">The rain had now held a bit, and down this hill came one ghostly figure after another in long grey robes, their hands grasping mysterious wands.</s> <s id="s168">A nearer approach resolved the robes into mackintoshes, and revealed clogs and short pipes, and the wands proved to be fishing-rods.</s> <s id="s169">They were the natives of <enamex sw="w27152" long="-2.73333" lat="53.81667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4578882" name="Broughton" conf="0.8481712074">Broughton</enamex> going to their favourite sport---- trout-fishing in the <enamex sw="w27223" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s170">I was rather weary as I entered the town and accosted the first lad whom I saw:</s></p>
<p><s id="s171">" Is there any hotel in <enamex sw="w27334" long="-2.73333" lat="53.81667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4578882" name="Broughton" conf="0.8481712074">Broughton</enamex>?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s172">" I dooan't think there is."</s></p>
<p><s id="s173">" Is there an inn?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s174">The boy looked puzzled, as though he had never heard the term" inn" before.</s> <s id="s175">Presently, however, he brightened as a thought struck him--</s> </p>
<p><s id="s176">" It's a pooblic house happen ye mean?"</s></p>
<p><s id="s177">I explained that I wanted a decent resting-place, no matter by what name it was called.</s> <s id="s178">And a decent resting-place I found-- an inn of good old-fashioned type, hight" The Old King's Head."</s></p>
<p><s id="s179">Here I got a good meal.</s> <s id="s180">But I was not yet content with the labours of the day; I could not go to rest till I had finished the <enamex sw="w27888" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>.</s> <s id="s181">So in the evening I sallied forth once more.</s> <s id="s182">The rain was over, it was a clear, calm evening.</s> <s id="s183">I retraced my steps as far as <enamex sw="w28020" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon Bridge</enamex>, then climbed a hill-side through a copse, and came out upon the open fells.</s> <s id="s184">Stretched out before me, radiant in the glow of sunset, was</s></p>
<p><s id="s185">" Majestic <enamex sw="w28181" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>, over smooth flat sands, Gliding in silence with unfettered sweep!"</s></p>
<p><s id="s186">I thought, as I viewed it from this point, that the poet's comparison with" Sovereign Thames" was not so far-fetched as some have felt it, and the low rounded hills on the farther shore are not unlike the <enamex sw="w28461" long="0.6429" lat="51.2677" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2646748" name="Kentish Downs" conf="99992">Kentish Downs</enamex>.</s> <s id="s187">But, let <enamex sw="w28485" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> be himself, and it suffices.</s> <s id="s188">It was wonderful what affection I had gained for this little river in so short a time.</s> <s id="s189">But, indeed, I have seen few streams so varied in beauty-- here thrown into rude commotion, and there entranced in slumber; here flowing through broad, sunny fields, and there plunged into some dark and impenetrable cleft, and finally, when all the troubled scenes of life are past, gliding like a human spirit to its rest.</s></p>
<p><s id="s190">Like a human spirit it appeared to me-- a glorious symbol of the immortal life-- as I stood there and watched it radiant with the setting sun.</s> <s id="s191">I stood and watched it still coming, ever coming down from the distant hills; still flowing, ever flowing to its rest in the bosom of the ocean; and, grateful for its guidance through so many lovely scenes, so many homes of quiet rural life, and so many spots hallowed by pious memories, I could not but address the calm waters in the words of the poet's last and noblest sonnet:</s></p>
<p><s id="s192">" I thought of thee, my partner and my guide, As being past away.</s>  <s id="s193">-- Vain sympathies! For, backward, <enamex sw="w29566" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>, as I cast my eyes, I see what was, and is, and will abide; Still glides the stream, and shall for ever glide; The form remains, the function never dies; While we, the brave, the mighty, and the wise, We men, who in our morn of youth defied The elements, must vanish;-- be it so! Enough, if something from our hands have power To live, and act, and serve the future hour; And if, as toward the silent tomb we go, Through love, through hope, and faith's transcendent dower, We feel that we are greater than we know."</s></p>
</text>
</document>