<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1813_a"><p><s id="s1">Journal Of A Tour To The Northern Parts Of <enamex  sw="w55" name="Large admin unit">Great Britain</enamex></s> </p><p><s id="s2">Non ut me miretur turba laboro, Contentus paucis lectoribus.</s> </p><p><s id="s3"><enamex sw="w130" long="-0.08573711413610305" lat="51.48768230024373" type="civila" gazref="unlock:13326794" name="Greater London Authority" conf="2.363794438">London</enamex></s> </p><p><s id="s4">Printed For J. Triphook, No. 38, St. James's Street.</s></p>
<p><s id="s5">1813.</s></p>
<p><s id="s6">1796.</s> <s id="s7">Oct. 12.</s> <s id="s8">Wednesday</s> </p><p><s id="s9">We took leave of our respectable host this morning, and set out for <enamex sw="w288" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.290362121">Carlisle</enamex>, which is 12 miles distant from <enamex sw="w329" long="-2.946690997669673" lat="55.03426776775118" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11227952" name="Netherby" conf="2.430544879">Netherby</enamex>.</s> <s id="s10">Mr. Hayes accompanied me in the post chaise; Mr. Smith drove his own curricle; and Messrs. King and Carlyle travelled on horseback.</s> <s id="s11">The morning was fine, but cold.</s> <s id="s12">In three miles we passed through <enamex sw="w536" long="-70.149492" lat="43.6889715" type="other" gazref="unlock:7711291" name="Town of Long Island" conf="0.5157355458">Long Town</enamex>, a place of some size.</s> <s id="s13">The road was frequently blocked up by droves of oxen travelling towards the South.</s> <s id="s14">There was nothing striking in the approach to <enamex sw="w698" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.290362121">Carlisle</enamex>.</s> <s id="s15">We drove through some spacious streets to the <enamex sw="w754" long="-71.3758971" lat="42.7517558" type="other" gazref="unlock:7824376" name="Bush Hill" conf="0.6841059313">Bush</enamex> Inn, whence, after writing letters, we proceeded to view the city.</s> <s id="s16">In our walk we met Mr. Farish, of Magdalen College, <enamex sw="w878" long="0.126108942553401" lat="52.22885322570801" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14125569" name="Cambridge" conf="2.010322875">Cambridge</enamex>, who led us to the Cathedral.</s> <s id="s17">It is an old, but plain, building; the choir is neat and worthy of observation.</s> <s id="s18">We passed from the cathedral to the castle, round which we were conducted by an artillery man.</s> <s id="s19">In former times, when civil war desolated the land, it was a place of some importance, but every appearance or form of fortification has long since disappeared.</s> <s id="s20">We made but a short stay in <enamex sw="w1282" long="-2.923743724822998" lat="54.89435005187988" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14127466" name="Carlisle" conf="3.290362121">Carlisle</enamex>, and proceeded on our route to <enamex sw="w1322" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.43477318">Penrith</enamex>, a stage of 18 miles; and we added an additional pair of horses to the carriage, in consequence of the severe hills which we were told to expect.</s> <s id="s21">Our intention was to visit Nunnery and <enamex sw="w1515" long="-2.81841325837126" lat="54.8824087507624" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11116064" name="Corby Castle" conf="2.108636898">Corby Castle</enamex>, the seat of Mr. Howard, on our road, but rain obliged us to relinquish that scheme.</s> <s id="s22">The way was rough and stony, but we reached <enamex sw="w1657" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.43477318">Penrith</enamex> at four o'clock.</s> <s id="s23">The last ten miles miles lay through <enamex sw="w1719" long="-2.909305014501532" lat="54.76492021101333" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11182573" name="Inglewood Forest" conf="2.298381023">Inglewood Forest</enamex>, an uncultivated and barren waste.</s> <s id="s24">Near <enamex sw="w1776" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.43477318">Penrith</enamex> a beacon is erected on the summit of a hill, a monument of those tumultuous times which now exist only in the page of history.</s> <s id="s25">It was on this spot that the <enamex  sw="w1940" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> Militia, in 1715, attempted to oppose the rebels, but ineffectually, for they fled almost as soon as their opponents came in sight.</s> <s id="s26">While dinner was preparing at <enamex sw="w2113" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.43477318">Penrith</enamex>, we lounged into a subscription coffee-room, where strangers are admitted upon enrolling their names in a book.</s> <s id="s27">In the evening we had the satisfaction of paying our respects, during half an hour, to Lady William Gordon, who was passing from Lady Irvine's house near <enamex sw="w2387" long="-1.475695967674255" lat="53.75947761535645" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14126330" name="Leeds" conf="2.280361451">Leeds</enamex>, to her own residence on <enamex sw="w2418" long="-3.14956" lat="54.584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2651313" name="Derwentwater" conf="99991">Keswick Lake</enamex>.</s> <s id="s28">We had travelled 30 miles to day.</s></p>
<p><s id="s29">1796.</s> <s id="s30">Oct. 13.</s> <s id="s31">Thursday.</s> </p><p><s id="s32"><enamex sw="w2491" long="-2.75205279814005" lat="54.66713013349954" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11243307" name="Penrith" conf="2.43477318">Penrith</enamex> is a neat town, and is prettily situated under mountains of no inconsiderable height.</s> <s id="s33">We left it this morning, and rode to <enamex sw="w2622" long="-2.89078" lat="54.57564" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00028" name="Ullswater" conf="99992">Ulleswater</enamex> Lake, which is only four miles distant.</s> <s id="s34">It is one of the largest of the lakes, being eight miles long, and in its widest part, two miles broad.</s> <s id="s35">The scenery is exceedingly beautiful, for the course of the lake winds in easy curves, and is well broken by promontories.</s> <s id="s36">The southern side is mountainous, while a great variety of rocky and woody scenes offer themselves on the other sides.</s> <s id="s37">We passed a most agreeable day in visiting its different parts, and continued our journey afterwards to <enamex sw="w3123" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.524277534">Keswick</enamex>, a distance of 10 miles from the point where where we quitted <enamex sw="w3193" long="-2.89078" lat="54.57564" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00028" name="Ullswater" conf="99992">Ulleswater</enamex> Lake.</s> <s id="s38">We dined and slept at <enamex sw="w3232" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.524277534">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s39">( 14 miles.)</s></p>
<p><s id="s40">1796.</s> <s id="s41">Oct. 14.</s> <s id="s42">Friday.</s> </p><p><s id="s43">To day we went out upon <enamex sw="w3300" long="-3.14956" lat="54.584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2651313" name="Derwentwater" conf="99991">Keswick Lake</enamex>, which forms an oblong of about ten miles in circumference.</s> <s id="s44">It is variegated by several islands, and finely set off by a screen of mountains which surround it; but at the base of which there is a margin of meadow, spreading to the water's edge.</s> <s id="s45">Lord and Lady William Gordon inhabit a beautiful spot on the banks of <enamex sw="w3628" long="-3.14956" lat="54.584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2651313" name="Derwentwater" conf="99991">Keswick Lake</enamex>, and we landed from our boat and visited them.</s> <s id="s46">We remained there for nearly an hour, and after partaking of some refreshments, and walking through the plantations, which are carried down to the lake itself, we re-embarked, and proceeded to view and to admire the beautiful scenery which was presented to us on every side.</s> <s id="s47">Towards the head of the lake is the waterfall of <enamex sw="w4012" long="-3.13662933748405" lat="54.55627196668239" type="water" gazref="unlock:11204948" name="Lodore Falls" conf="2.331462598">Lodore</enamex>.</s> <s id="s48">The stream which forms it, falls through a chasm between two perpendicular rocks, which are broken into large shelves, on which there is soil sufficient for the growth of trees.</s> <s id="s49">Amidst these broken rocks the stream rushes down a descent of nearly a hundred feet; but we had too lately visited the <enamex sw="w4317" long="-3.772267416685592" lat="55.65422188032782" type="water" gazref="unlock:11141791" name="Falls of Clyde" conf="0.980821379">Falls of Clyde</enamex>, to experience either the pleasure or the surprise which we should otherwise have felt.</s> <s id="s50">Further on, we saw an enormous stone, known in the country by the name of the <enamex sw="w4498" long="-3.1516" lat="54.5382" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11084123" name="Bowder Stone" conf="99992">Boudar Stone</enamex>: it is an enormous mass of insulated rock, covering a considerable space of ground.</s> <s id="s51">Towards Towards evening we left the lake, and joining the turnpike road in about four miles, proceeded straight to <enamex sw="w4710" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, and thence two miles further, to <enamex sw="w4754" long="-3.000560623790019" lat="54.24386305141168" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16529" name="Low Wood" conf="2.535397618">Low Wood</enamex>.</s> <s id="s52">This ride was particularly striking.</s> <s id="s53">A more clear, still, beautiful autumnal evening I never knew; and as we journeyed along, the scenery about <enamex sw="w4908" long="-3.0216" lat="54.45" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_6956554" name="Grasmere Water" conf="99991">Grasmere Lake</enamex> and a little village on its margin, was peculiarly romantic.</s> <s id="s54">We called to mind the description of it in Gray, who was so enchanted with it, that he expressed a wish to have retraced his steps from <enamex sw="w5119" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>.</s> <s id="s55">Of all inland rides, either in <enamex  sw="w5161" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, <enamex  sw="w5170" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>, or <enamex  sw="w5183" name="Large admin unit">Wales</enamex>, this may almost be pronounced the most delightful.</s> <s id="s56">Mr. King lingered behind us, in order to enjoy, at his own pace, the singular serenity of the evening, and the alternate grandeur and beauty of the prospects.</s> <s id="s57"><enamex sw="w5400" long="-3.000560623790019" lat="54.24386305141168" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16529" name="Low Wood" conf="2.535397618">Low Wood</enamex> is situated close to <enamex sw="w5430" long="-2.93438" lat="54.37296" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_SD402977" name="Winderemere (Lake)" conf="99991">Windermere Lake</enamex>.</s> <s id="s58">We arrived there late in the evening, and united the meals of dinner and supper.</s> <s id="s59">We had made our journey from <enamex sw="w5557" long="-3.125370693283439" lat="54.60160037173823" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10824" name="Keswick" conf="2.524277534">Keswick</enamex> altogether about 20 miles.</s></p>
<p><s id="s60">1796.</s> <s id="s61">Oct. 15.</s> <s id="s62">Saturday.</s> </p><p><s id="s63">Early this morning we received a visit from the Bishop of Landaff, who, having retired from the busy scenes of life, has occupied himself in creating a place in the immediate neighbourhood of <enamex sw="w5809" long="-2.93438" lat="54.37296" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_SD402977" name="Winderemere (Lake)" conf="99991">Windermere Lake</enamex>, which he calls <enamex sw="w5841" long="-2.928529867" lat="54.38830822" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00125" name="Calgarth Park" conf="99992">Calgarth Park</enamex>.</s> <s id="s64">After accepting an invitation with which his lordship honoured our party, we set out upon a voyage on the lake.</s> <s id="s65"><enamex sw="w5968" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> may be considered as the chief of the <enamex  sw="w6017" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland Lakes</enamex>.</s> <s id="s66">Its length is is about twelve miles, and it is frequently two in breadth, seldom narrower than one.</s> <s id="s67">Part of its coasts are wild and mountainous, others more flat and cultivated.</s> <s id="s68">There is also a sufficiency of wood to complete the beauty and variety of the scenery.</s> <s id="s69">In the centre there are several islands; on one of which( in size of about thirty acres,) we landed, and walked over the grounds and mansion of Mr. Curwen, who has here fixed his sequestered habitation.</s> <s id="s70">On our return to <enamex sw="w6520" long="-3.000560623790019" lat="54.24386305141168" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16529" name="Low Wood" conf="2.535397618">Low Wood</enamex>, we dressed, and afterwards moved our quarters to <enamex sw="w6579" long="-2.928529867" lat="54.38830822" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00125" name="Calgarth Park" conf="99992">Calgarth Park</enamex>, where we dined and passed a most agreeable evening, under the hospitable roof of our worthy friend, the Bishop and his numerous family.</s></p>
<p><s id="s71">1796.</s> <s id="s72">Oct. 16.</s> <s id="s73">Sunday.</s>
</p><p><s id="s74">We accompanied the Bishop to church at <enamex sw="w6792" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, which place may be called the capital town of the lake.</s> <s id="s75">On our return to <enamex sw="w6874" long="-2.931737280270144" lat="54.38724387708846" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11096668" name="Calgarth Hall" conf="2.2">Calgarth</enamex>, the Bishop allowed us the convenience of an early dinner, in order that we might fulfil our intention of proceeding in the evening to <enamex sw="w7018" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="2.905412405">Lancaster</enamex>.</s> <s id="s76">Our first stage was to <enamex sw="w7052" long="-2.745809060481465" lat="54.32561646560368" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185036" name="Kendal" conf="3.037989587">Kendal</enamex>, which is nine miles distant from <enamex sw="w7093" long="-2.931737280270144" lat="54.38724387708846" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11096668" name="Calgarth Hall" conf="2.2">Calgarth</enamex>.</s> <s id="s77">There is but little worthy of observation here, and we passed on through a very long stage of twenty - one miles, to <enamex sw="w7218" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="2.905412405">Lancaster</enamex>.</s> <s id="s78">About half way we passed through a town called <enamex sw="w7276" long="-0.6855457191527591" lat="52.36085754462765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11094145" name="Burton Latimer" conf="1.209406968">Burton</enamex>; hence, we had, on our right, a view of the <enamex sw="w7327" long="-3.01901097221647" lat="54.17979785752691" type="other" gazref="unlock:11100387" name="Cartmel Sands" conf="1.878165386">Cartmel Sands</enamex>, which at low water are passable, though sometimes not without difficulty.</s> <s id="s79">We arrived at <enamex sw="w7430" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="2.905412405">Lancaster</enamex> late in the evening, after a journey of thirty miles.</s></p>
</text>
</document>