<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1804_c"><p><s id="s1"><enamex sw="w12" long="-2.9382" lat="54.8951" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2653775" name="Carlisle" conf="99991">Carlisle</enamex></s> </p><p><s id="s2">The view of the castle, on entering the city is fine; the town is large, the upper street wide and well paved, and the <enamex  sw="w141" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Bush</enamex> inn a very comfortable one, at least we found it so.</s></p>
<p><s id="s3">Mr. P. Brown, who dined and passed the evening with me, advised me to alter my intended route, and go by <enamex sw="w304" long="-3.1611" lat="54.8248" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2633933" name="Wigton" conf="99991">Wigton</enamex>, which advice I determined to follow.</s> <s id="s4">The claret we found excellent, but the stock small.</s></p>
<p><s id="s5">October 24.</s> <s id="s6">- Morning, a very sharp frost; indeed I never knew one so severe at this time of the year, which prevented my making many observations on the town, though it well deserves, from its antiquity and other circumstances, to be noticed by the traveller.</s></p>
<p><s id="s7">It is surrounded by a wall, thirty feet high, which is going fast to decay.</s> <s id="s8">The castle stands at the north end, and, though very well when viewed at a distance, I found, on examination, the rudest heap of stones ever piled together by the industry of men.</s> <s id="s9">There are four old invalids who take care of the ammunition kept in it, of which there is a considerable quantity, and five hundred stand of arms.</s> <s id="s10">On the walls are mounted thirty guns, from six to twenty - four pounders, and, among these, the guns with which the town was reduced, in the year 1745, by the Duke of Cumberland.</s> <s id="s11">The ditch around the castle is a filthy stagnated pool; and this character of filthiness is equally applicable to the walks around the city walls and the general avenues.</s> <s id="s12">Beyond the old citadel or castle, and the walls and moat, by which it is separated from the town, is a declining bank, on which there is a row of trees, planted by the hands of the unfortunate Mary, queen of Scots, when a prisoner in <enamex sw="w1647" long="-2.9382" lat="54.8951" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2653775" name="Carlisle" conf="99991">Carlisle</enamex>.</s> <s id="s13">There are many good houses in this town, though, in general, it is very ill built, and, as before observed, excessively dirty, from the circumstance of its being surrounded with a wall, and having only a few outlets.</s> <s id="s14">Over the river, which is pretty large, are thrown two very elegant bridges.</s></p>
<p><s id="s15">The cathedral, which consists merely of the choir and transepts of the old church, is built of a stone, in colour resembling brick-dust, which has but an ill effect.</s> <s id="s16">Its architecture, in general, is the later species of the pointed order, light and extremely elegant; but other parts appear of a much earlier date.</s> <s id="s17">The eastern window may vie with that in any church for its beautiful shape, and the delicacy of its fine ramifications.</s> <s id="s18">The western end is altogether as deformed, and exhibits the ravages and violence it has undergone.</s></p>
<p><s id="s19">The inside is chiefly remarkable for some singular legendary paintings, of remote antiquity, and extremely well preserved, each of which has an uncouth rhyming distich over it, written in the old black letter.</s> <s id="s20">These paintings are certainly curious, though many of the subjects are hideous, as they show what progress our ancestors had made in the art of design.</s></p>
<p><s id="s21">A curious monumental brass plate, to the memory of Bishop Robinson, containing his effigy kneeling, and surrounded by a great number of emblematical devices, is well worthy notice, as are the elegant stalls of the choir and the bishop's throne.</s></p>
<p><s id="s22">Near the cathedral there is a very modern church, which looks on the outside more like a ball-room than a place of worship.</s></p>
<p><s id="s23">The wind continued frosty during the day; but the sun, fortunately for us, shone most powerfully.</s> <s id="s24">Reached <enamex sw="w3321" long="-3.1611" lat="54.8248" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2633933" name="Wigton" conf="99991">Wigton</enamex>, after an uninteresting ride of ten miles, on a bad road.</s></p>
<p><s id="s25"><enamex sw="w3386" long="-3.162105902218126" lat="54.82423915205727" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:34118" name="Wigton" conf="2.553270067">Wigton</enamex> is a small wretched town, the inn not extraordinary: here I heard there were some famous pointers.</s> <s id="s26">I looked at a brace, and tried them on my road to <enamex sw="w3542" long="0.3389997069709487" lat="52.56983893920285" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11237512" name="Ouse Bridge Fm" conf="0.8150490768">Ouse Bridge</enamex>, but did not approve of them.</s> <s id="s27">From the three to the seven mile stone, I think I never saw a more cold, unpleasant country.</s> <s id="s28">Had <enamex sw="w3681" long="-72.8667674" lat="41.6295428" type="other" gazref="unlock:8024327" name="Churchill Hill" conf="0.9536838347">Churchill</enamex> said of this place,</s></p>
<p> <s id="s29">I scarcely ever found one pointer in fifty answer my expectations, either for shape, bone, or action, and the different modes of breaking, if they are not whelps, make them irreclaimable; but it only costs a little time and a little money, at least to see such as are well recommended, and the greater opportunity the greater chance of success; if well-shaped dogs or bitches, they can be bred soon, and they may make game-keepers' dogs, any thing being good enough for people that do not shoot for pleasure.</s></p>
<p><s id="s30">' Far as the eye could reach,&amp; c.'</s></p>
<p><s id="s31">it would have been at least as well applied as to any part of <enamex  sw="w4317" name="Large admin unit">North Britain</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s32">At the bridge there is a very neat, pleasant-looking inn, where we asked some directions for <enamex sw="w4425" long="0.3389997069709487" lat="52.56983893920285" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11237512" name="Ouse Bridge Fm" conf="0.8150490768">Ouse Bridge</enamex>, and found that our landlord at <enamex sw="w4469" long="-3.1611" lat="54.8248" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2633933" name="Wigton" conf="99991">Wigton</enamex> had deceived himself in the distance, it being fourteen miles instead of ten: a horrid road! About the nine mile stone there is a view of <enamex sw="w4615" long="-3.6667" lat="54.75" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2637542" name="Solway Firth" conf="99991">the Frith</enamex> of <enamex sw="w4628" long="-3.6667" lat="54.75" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2637542" name="Solway Firth" conf="99991">Solway</enamex>, bounded by the bold shore of <enamex sw="w4665" long="-3.258165592796878" lat="54.9865068085775" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11062586" name="Annan" conf="2.488970708">Annan</enamex>, with the Scottish mountains in the distance.</s> <s id="s33">In the flat stands, apparent, Sir Gilbert Lawton's, a large white mansion, with some trees, the first I had seen for many miles.</s> <s id="s34">As we approached <enamex sw="w4863" long="0.3389997069709487" lat="52.56983893920285" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11237512" name="Ouse Bridge Fm" conf="0.8150490768">Ouse Bridge</enamex>, we passed, to our right, Mrs. Spedding's, a neat house.</s> <s id="s35">The inn stands about half a mile out of the <enamex sw="w4976" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> road, at the foot of the lake of <enamex sw="w5017" long="-3.193601937631324" lat="54.67926476125776" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:15906" name="Bassenthwaite" conf="2.6">Bassenthwaite</enamex>.</s> <s id="s36">Here the scene becomes more interesting: the lake is pretty, but small; an epitome of those in the Highlands; and above it, to the east, rises <enamex sw="w5175" long="-3.123888158550623" lat="54.65526311800171" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11284755" name="Skiddaw Forest" conf="2.4">Skiddaw</enamex>, at this time covered with snow.</s> <s id="s37">Mr. Gerrard took a view of this lake, and, after a slight dinner, we proceeded for <enamex sw="w5299" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s38">The road very bad indeed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s39">I had not rode above a mile, when I came up to one of the most beautiful and innocent country girls I ever saw: I wished much to get into conversation with her; but found her as coy as handsome.</s> <s id="s40">Mr. Gerrard, perceiving her distress, left us and trotted on, when her coyness by degrees diminished, and we became more familiar.</s> <s id="s41">She permitted me to accompany her five miles, which added much to the pleasure I received in this ride, and gave me every intelligence I wished for, answering all my enquiries concerning the gentlemen's seats,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s42">And I flatter myself we were so well pleased with each other, during this short intercourse, as to feel a mutual inconveniency in parting.</s></p>
<p><s id="s43">Trotted on briskly, and soon overtook Mr. Gerrard, when we made the best of our way to <enamex sw="w6100" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, as it grew late; and, by the glimmering of the moon, observed several neat gentlemen's houses, on both sides the road, as we approached the town, which merit the attention of the traveller who has leisure to visit them.</s> <s id="s44">Arrived at our inn at <enamex sw="w6351" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, which we found <enamex sw="w6375" long="-2.380959059473901" lat="53.26636647649359" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13406367" name="Peover Inferior CP" conf="1.193464888">inferior</enamex> to most of the Highland inns, a circumstance unpardonable in a country much more frequented.</s></p>
<p><s id="s45"><enamex sw="w6477" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex></s> </p><p><s id="s46">October 25.</s> <s id="s47">- Morning, a white frost.</s> <s id="s48">- The sun shone very warm, which made me decline going out so early as I could have wished, not chusing to be wet; but, in the course of the morning, took a view of the town, a small one, and of little note, except for its lake, though the buildings have a pretty appearance, from being covered with blue slates, so much <enamex sw="w6845" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="0.9717482139">superior</enamex> to the glare of red tile; and the same pleasing effect is produced in the vale, from the farms and other houses being likewise covered with the same material.</s> <s id="s49">In the neighbourhood are manufactures of carpets, flannels, linsies, and yarn, the last sold to people from <enamex sw="w7121" long="-3.356649935752379" lat="54.66186838800157" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11111547" name="Cockermouth" conf="2.579484949">Cockermouth</enamex>, who come for it every market day.</s></p>
<p><s id="s50">Being informed that a cabinet of natural curiosities, generally admired by strangers, was to be seen at Mr. Crossthwaite's, paid a visit to that gentleman.</s> <s id="s51">We found the commodore at home, for so he is called, from having been formerly a sea-faring man, and being appointed to superintend the annual regattas, held on the lake of <enamex sw="w7497" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s52">After passing some time with him, we took a walk to the side of the lake: it is named after the town; but is likewise called <enamex sw="w7631" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> from the ancient and noble family of that name, who had a castle on it, and a very considerable estate around it, which was forfeited to the crown in 1715, by the last earl, who was concerned in the Scotch rebellion of that year against George I. and was beheaded on <enamex sw="w7911" long="-3.949957705475076" lat="55.39086524892649" type="other" gazref="unlock:11303624" name="Towerhill" conf="0.682486065">Towerhill</enamex> for high treason.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s53">When the act passed for restoring the forfeited estates, great expectations were formed by Lord Newburgh, the present heir to that unfortunate earl, that the property, belonging to the family, would be recovered, and claims were preferred for that purpose; but very strong reasons operated with government to exclude the forfeitures incurred in 1715; and, in particular, the appropriation of the estate at <enamex sw="w8347" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex> to the support of that noble and useful charity, Greenwich Hospital: besides which, in order to secure this revenue permanently to the above foundation, a considerable sum of money was given some years since to the family, to give up all claim whatever to this estate, that might hereafter arise from any collateral branch of it, found not to have incurred the forfeiture.</s></p>
<p><s id="s54"><enamex sw="w8728" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, certainly, for its extent, which is about three miles from north to south, is as charming a scene as can be imagined; but I am sorry to add, that the original simplicity, which, in my opinion, constitutes its chief beauty, is, in a great measure, destroyed by several inelegant houses and offices, as formal as numerous, on one of the islands: this circumstance displeased us so much that we returned, after having admired some points of view, equal, if not <enamex sw="w9200" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="0.9717482139">superior</enamex>, to the stations, usually described by authors, as the only proper places from whence all strangers should see the beauties of the lakes.</s> <s id="s55">It may be necessary to point out stations to persons who are totally destitute of taste and judgment, but, in general, such directions are useless; for every person, of the least discernment, will readily judge for himself.</s></p>
<p><s id="s56">One of the beautiful islands on the Lake of <enamex sw="w9615" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, called Vicar's Isle, is distinguished, above the rest, for a valuable discovery, made some years since, of a mineral, called black lead, which is the produce of <enamex  sw="w9787" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> solely, not being to be met with in any other part of <enamex  sw="w9849" name="Large admin unit">Europe</enamex>.</s> <s id="s57">It is found in great abundance on the shore of the Vicar's Isle, incorporated with the sand and soil of the beach, from which it is afterwards separated for use: but in what manner it has been deposited there, whether by occasional floods, or by any natural cause, is uncertain; however, such was the importance of the discovery, that soon after it was made, it became an object of serious speculation, by what methods the whole lake might be drained, an idea being formed, that the profits arising from such an acquisition, would be prodigious; and the following account, given by Dr. Campbell, in his Political Survey of <enamex  sw="w10480" name="Large admin unit">Great Britain</enamex>, of this useful mineral, will serve not only to illustrate the subject, but to account for laying aside the project.</s></p>
<p><s id="s58">' Black lead is what some have supposed, with very little reason, to be the molybdena, or galena, of <enamex  sw="w10713" name="Not a placename">Pliny</enamex>; others style it plumbago. Our judicious Camden, in whose days it was a new thing, would not venture to give it a Latin name, but calls it a metallic earth, or hard, shining, stony substance, which, whether it was the pingites or melanteria of Dioscorides, or an ochre burnt to blackness, and so unknown to the ancients, he left others to enquire.</s> <s id="s59">Dr. Merret, from the use to which it was first applied, named it ingrica fabrilis. The learned <enamex  sw="w11164" name="Not a placename">Boyle</enamex> is of opinion, that it has not anything metallic in its nature; relying upon which, we have ventured to give it a place here.</s> <s id="s60">It is, indeed, a very singular substance; but, being common, and, consequently, well known, it would be needless to describe it.</s> <s id="s61">It is found, but in very trivial quantities in several mines here, by itself is on <enamex sw="w11508" long="-3.15327" lat="54.52342" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00036" name="Borrowdale" conf="99992">Barrowdale</enamex>, about six miles from <enamex sw="w11541" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, in the county of <enamex  sw="w11567" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s62">It is there called wadd, and those who are best acquainted with it, style it a black, pinguid, shining earth, which they suppose to be impregnated with lead and antimony.</s> <s id="s63">When it was first discovered, the people used it to mark their sheep: it was afterwards introduced into medicine, and taken in powder for the cure of the cholic and gravel; but it has since been applied to many other purposes.</s> <s id="s64">It serves to scour, clean, and give a lustre to wrought iron, and defends it from rust: it is applied in the varnishing crucibles, and other earthen vessels that are to be exposed to the fiercest fire, which end it answers effectually: but, after all, the great consumption of it is in two articles; in dying, to fix blues, so that they may never change their colour, and in pencils.</s> <s id="s65">The latter articles, being confined to this country, is so well known and as universally allowed, that they are from thence styled abroad, crayons d' Angleterre. It arises from hence, that this substance is little known to foreigners, the most learned of whom speak of it very confusedly, and with much uncertainty.</s> <s id="s66">These farther particulars we may venture to affirm concerning it, without any danger of misleading our readers; that the mine before mentioned is private property, is opened but once in seven years, and the quantity known to be equal to the consumption in that space sold at once: and, as it is used without any preparation, it is more valuable than the ore of any metal found in this island.</s> <s id="s67">But there is nothing improbable, much less impossible, in supporting that other, and it may be many other uses, will be discovered in medicine, painting, dying, varnishing, or pottery, which would certainly contribute to raise the value of a mineral peculiar to this country, and, with the nature of which, though so long in our possession, we are still so imperfectly acquainted.'</s></p>
<p><s id="s68">Bidding adieu to <enamex sw="w13470" long="-3.137880601359804" lat="54.60120234465001" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11185565" name="Keswick" conf="2.6">Keswick</enamex>, we proceeded for <enamex sw="w13496" long="-2.98" lat="54.4483" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36550632" name="Rydal Hall" conf="99992">Rydal Hall</enamex>, sending a servant forward to inform my worthy friend, Sir Michael <enamex  sw="w13574" name="Not a placename">Fleming</enamex>, that I should pass a few hours with him in my way to <enamex sw="w13636" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s69">The road becomes very hilly, immediately on leaving the town, and, at the one mile stone, we stopped to admire a most beautiful view, comprising the whole valley, and a circuit of twenty miles, bounded by stupendous mountains.</s> <s id="s70">About half a mile from this charming prospect, to the left, is the famous Druid Temple, so much celebrated by all our antiquaries; and of which so many descriptions have been published, that we regretted the less our want of time to repair to it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s71">Pursuing the road, we passed by <enamex sw="w14153" long="-3.0667" lat="54.5333" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2636023" name="Leathes Water" conf="99992">Leathes Water</enamex>, a narrow, uninteresting lake, black and gloomy, not owing to its depth, but to the strata through which it runs, which is of the colour of slate, and to the dark rocks which hang over, and seem as if falling into it, and which deprive it of that fine effect of light and shade universally to be found in the Highland lakes, <enamex sw="w14492" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="0.9717482139">superior</enamex> to any I have seen elsewhere.</s></p>
<p><s id="s72">The road winds through these prodigious crags, and, descending, we saw before us <enamex sw="w14612" long="-3.0216" lat="54.45" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_6956554" name="Grasmere Water" conf="99992">Grassmere Water</enamex>, which we thought far <enamex sw="w14650" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="0.9717482139">superior</enamex>, in the composition of its parts, to any of the lakes we had passed.</s> <s id="s73">It is considerably enlivened by the neat village of <enamex sw="w14780" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex>, consisting of white houses covered with slate, and the parish church rising in the centre: but still it is much colder in its appearance than <enamex sw="w14933" long="-4.615916061663459" lat="56.15797993037354" type="water" gazref="unlock:8794433" name="Loch Lomond" conf="1.068794524">Loch Lomond</enamex>, <enamex sw="w14946" long="-4.137659732571856" lat="56.5202340278469" type="water" gazref="unlock:11203033" name="Loch Tay" conf="1.039052762">Loch Tay</enamex>, or any of the more northern lakes; and this appeared to me to be occasioned not by the want of wood, for it is well provided with trees, hedges, and inclosures on its verge, but to the changed state of agriculture around it.</s> <s id="s74">The farmers, finding the soil and climate unfavourable for corn, have diminished the quantity of arable land, and converted it into pasturage, which has hurt the beauty of the scenery, as the meanest corn-fields certainly enrich the view, and the poverty of the crops can only be discovered on a near inspection.</s></p>
<p><s id="s75">The road passes over <enamex sw="w15515" long="-3.0117" lat="54.4506" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY345066" name="Grasmere Hill" conf="99992">Grassmere Hill</enamex>, and, descending into a vale, we came to <enamex sw="w15571" long="-2.993866462466064" lat="54.44746550347175" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796733" name="Rydal Water" conf="2.4">Rydal Water</enamex>, a pretty little lake, taking its name from <enamex sw="w15628" long="-2.98" lat="54.4483" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36550632" name="Rydal Hall" conf="99992">Rydal hall</enamex>, which we soon approached.</s></p>
<p><s id="s76">This is the ancient mansion of the respectable family of Le <enamex  sw="w15726" name="Not a placename">Fleming</enamex>, who have been resident in the North of <enamex  sw="w15774" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> from the time of the Conquest; and this beautiful seat came into their possession in the reign of Henry Iv.</s> <s id="s77">by the marriage of an ancestor of the present proprietor with an heiress, the daughter of Sir John <enamex sw="w15989" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s78">Mr. Gerrard, as I proposed only to stay an hour or two, proceeded forward to <enamex sw="w16077" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, wishing, while I waited for and with Sir Michael, to amuse himself with examining accurately the splendour of <enamex sw="w16198" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s79">He took the gig, and left me Sardonix, my black mare.</s></p>
<p><s id="s80">On our arrival, I found that Sir Michael was gone to fish for char; but had taken proper care to prevent my proceeding without seeing him: by his desire I went after him, attended by his groom with his horses.</s> <s id="s81">We joined the party, all busy in drawing a pool in the river: it consisted of ladies and gentlemen.</s> <s id="s82">They were so engaged, that I came upon them unexpectedly.</s> <s id="s83">As their cavalry were in the highest condition, and the group perfectly well dressed, they added much to the beauty of the situation, by the elegant pastime they were following.</s> <s id="s84">Nets, from the simple forms they take, have a most picturesque appearance; and the fish and some wicker baskets that were dispersed; some horses loose and grazing, and the vale itself small, but, in composition, not to be surpassed, made me lament Mr. Gerrard's absence.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s85">The sardonix is one of the largest and most durable stones we are acquainted with; and this mare being possessed of all those requisites in a hackney, we had her christened as above.</s></p>
<p><s id="s86">I was discovered contemplating the company, and marking them on paper for Mr. Gerrard's approbation.</s> <s id="s87">They advanced, and being introduced by my old friend to the ladies and the party, we were, as all fashionable people are in such parties, very easy.</s></p>
<p><s id="s88">Sir Michael very much admired the horse I rode, I offered readily to sell him, and we had nearly agreed, before I discovered to him, that it was one of his own.</s> <s id="s89">He paid me some compliments on my seat as a Yorkshire man, and we all laughed most immoderately.</s> <s id="s90">Returned, amply provided with very fine char, some of them weighing near two pounds.</s> <s id="s91">I had never seen one above the size of a small herring before: they were much fatter than any I had seen in the Highlands.</s></p>
<p><s id="s92">It was in vain now to think of departing; for the baronet kindly pressed me to pass a few days with him, and an agreeable party of his friends, then on a visit.</s> <s id="s93">Accepting, therefore his cordial invitation, it gave me opportunity to examine the various beauties of this inchanting spot.</s></p>
<p><s id="s94">October 26.</s> <s id="s95">- Morning frosty; but clear and fine.</s></p>
<p><s id="s96"><enamex sw="w18318" long="-74.7223827" lat="40.3673286" type="other" gazref="unlock:7843883" name="Mount Rose" conf="0.6577746711">Rose</enamex> early, and resolved to devote it to a full contemplation of the magnificent and delightful scenes around the house.</s></p>
<p><s id="s97">I well knew my friend was not an early riser; I also knew that he was the best soul in the world; and conceiving that such merits were equally dispensed to the females of the same family, if the beauties of the scenery should make me a little exceed the hour of breakfast, I was certain I should be forgiven.</s></p>
<p><s id="s98">I had, with Mr. Gerrard, taken a slight view of the cascade above, and of the smaller one below the house.</s> <s id="s99">I now examined them again, and found that, though <enamex sw="w18905" long="-2.380959059473901" lat="53.26636647649359" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13406367" name="Peover Inferior CP" conf="1.193464888">inferior</enamex> in size, and not so tremendous as the great Fall of Fiers, <enamex sw="w18973" name="Thornton Falls">Thornton Falls</enamex>, and some others, they are peculiarly well adapted for a picture; and a very justly admired one has been painted by M.G. Gerrard, of which an elegant print has been executed by Middiman.</s></p>
<p><s id="s100">I now returned, and found I was just in time for breakfast, and Sir Michael requested me to desire Mr. Gerrard to follow, whom he undertook to wait on; but as I knew it would interfere with his schemes, I politely excused him, and wrote word, that I would wish him to amuse himself and go on to <enamex sw="w19470" long="-1.305390746711617" lat="53.98579406467463" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13432081" name="Thornville CP" conf="1.21010721">Thornville</enamex> at his leisure, as it might be a day or two before I should leave my generous landlord; he accordingly proceeded, returning me the gig.</s></p>
<p><s id="s101">October 27.</s> <s id="s102">- Morning frosty; but day delightful.</s></p>
<p><s id="s103">We had agreed the night before to rise early, in order to take the hill-road to <enamex sw="w19747" long="-3.457115296600183" lat="54.43598051808319" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11247683" name="Ponsonby" conf="2.6">Ponsonby</enamex>, by which twenty - five miles are saved; but Sir Michael being engaged in justice business, and other similarly pleasant avocations for a young gentleman, the forenoon passed away insensibly; and finding the day so much advanced, I had the honour to set out with Miss <enamex  sw="w20022" name="Not a placename">Fleming</enamex>, leaving the gentlemen to follow.</s></p>
<p><s id="s104">The sun shone most delightfully, and, as we passed <enamex sw="w20115" long="-85.48329320000001" lat="38.7472812" type="other" gazref="unlock:7013324" name="Rider Lake" conf="0.533644836">Rider Lake</enamex>, a small piece of water, the property of Sir Michael, about three miles in circumference, the picturesque islands, with which it was studded, and the fertility of its variegated banks, clothed with a happy mixture of hollies, oaks,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s105">made the country appear quite beautiful.</s></p>
<p><s id="s106">The road being narrow, as well as hilly, was, consequently, except in some parts, very unsociable.</s> <s id="s107">In this ride, I found we had by far the best view of <enamex sw="w20556" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s108">The church, with the road winding over the hill beyond it, and the scene bounded by the valley, gave the lake a most delightful appearance.</s></p>
<p><s id="s109">Proceeded as fast as the road would admit.</s> <s id="s110">The gentlemen, we had been obliged to leave at <enamex sw="w20797" long="-2.98" lat="54.4483" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36550632" name="Rydal Hall" conf="99992">Rydal Hall</enamex>, overtook us, as I was contemplating the wild situation eround Hard <enamex  sw="w20876" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>, a vale which forms a junction of the three countries of <enamex  sw="w20938" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, <enamex  sw="w20950" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, and <enamex  sw="w20968" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>.</s> <s id="s111">Should three of the most enthusiastic provincialists meet here, I think they would not dispute about the luxuriancy of their respective counties.</s></p>
<p><s id="s112">The road is really more deplorable than Glen <enamex  sw="w21171" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Crow</enamex>, Glen Ammon, or Sluick Muich, which I fancy no Scotchman would expect to find here.</s> <s id="s113">It climbs over the very tops of the mountains, now grizzled with snow, and over continued heaps of loose, angular stones, which makes it very dangerous riding.</s> <s id="s114">I really should have been greatly distressed for any other lady; but Miss F's accomplishments, as a horsewoman, joined to the goodness of the animal she rode, made all anxiety, on her account, needless.</s></p>
<p><s id="s115">After a ride of fourteen miles, which appeared short, from the lively sallies and bon mots of our party, we arrived at <enamex sw="w21742" long="-2.877519181888596" lat="55.44819880730391" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11140437" name="Esdale Law" conf="1.102529425">Esdale</enamex>, an absolute Highland inn, affording nothing but bad corn, and some tolerable ale, a liquor I never drink; but our provident friend, Sir M. had sent forward an excellent dinner, and I never passed my time more agreeably.</s> <s id="s116">Fearing, however, that night should overtake us, and having still eleven miles to <enamex sw="w22052" long="-3.457115296600183" lat="54.43598051808319" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11247683" name="Ponsonby" conf="2.6">Ponsonby</enamex>, we were obliged to proceed, and, when we arrived, it was too dark to see its beauties.</s></p>
<p><s id="s117">Weather the same the proceeding day.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s118">Ponsonby House, the seat of Mr. Stanley, is a large, new edifice, not quite finished, built under the direction of that eminent architect, Mr. Paine.</s> <s id="s119">The plan is both elegant and commodious.</s> <s id="s120">It consists of three fronts; the principal, which is the north-east, commands a fine view of <enamex sw="w22472" long="-3.472851292970033" lat="54.44477869607492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11096504" name="Calder Abbey" conf="2.2">Calder Abbey</enamex>, situated in a beautiful but narrow vale, the banks very steep, and clothed with different woods, above which rise the gently-sloping <enamex sw="w22619" long="-3.457115296600183" lat="54.43598051808319" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11247683" name="Ponsonby" conf="2.6">Ponsonby</enamex> Fells, and <enamex sw="w22640" long="-3.21333" lat="54.45583" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00026" name="Scafell" conf="99991">Scaw Fell</enamex>, rather too naked at present, but regularly inclosed.</s> <s id="s121">To the north, the eye surveys a very fine glen, beautifully shaded with ancient oaks and infant firs, and crowded with every flowering shrub.</s> <s id="s122">Fortunately this valley runs in such a manner, that little of its beauty is lost; nor does it interrupt the view of a larger tract of well-improved, flat country, at the extremity of which is indistinctly seen the thriving and rich town of <enamex sw="w23086" long="-3.574638671553102" lat="54.54261524067765" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063" name="Whitehaven" conf="3.020606813">Whitehaven</enamex>.</s> <s id="s123">This spot also affords a noble view of the sea, with the island and <enamex sw="w23166" long="-2.5" lat="54.35" type="other" gazref="unlock:4578383" name="The Calf" conf="1.900584718">Calf</enamex> of Man; and not less than two hundred sail of shipping appeared in sight.</s> <s id="s124">The west front looks down the valley, takes in another view of the sea, and, in a favourable day, you may discern, at the same time, <enamex sw="w23378" long="-4.396781741780916" lat="54.68171071241343" type="other" gazref="unlock:11093947" name="Burrow Head" conf="0.644976026">Burrow Head</enamex>, in <enamex  sw="w23394" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>, the <enamex sw="w23408" long="-4.890646320949005" lat="54.6439542567576" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11224974" name="Mull of Galloway Fm" conf="0.7854120233">Mull of Galloway</enamex>, and <enamex  sw="w23430" name="Large admin unit">Flintshire</enamex>.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s125">The common appellation in the North of <enamex  sw="w23482" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> for bills and crags.</s></p>
<p><s id="s126">From the calmness of the day, the sea appeared like a sheet of glass, and the vessels, some tacking, others sailing before the wind, seemed white as silver, and made this scene, so different from any I had lately beheld, perfectly beautiful.</s></p>
<p><s id="s127">After breakfast our company divided, some on shooting parties, others for coursing. I chose the latter, having an opportunity, while pursuing it, of admiring some delightful prospects.</s></p>
<p><s id="s128">We tried for some cocks in the above-mentioned beautiful glen, where it was said, a brace and a half had been seen the day before, but had no success: I was, however, sufficiently repaid for my walk, by having it in my power to contemplate the beauties of a venerable, old, stinted oak, forming a long, fantastic, and wide arch over the river beneath it, which is full of salmon and trout.</s></p>
<p><s id="s129">I understood from Mr. Stanley, that salmon taken from the sea are far <enamex sw="w24399" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="0.9717482139">superior</enamex> to those caught in the river; and as he has every opportunity of judging, I make no doubt but his remark is well founded.</s></p>
<p><s id="s130">I had a salmon sent me by Mr. <enamex sw="w24560" long="-6.311646370745557" lat="49.91484128104226" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10838" name="Hugh Town" conf="0.9268417345">Hugh</enamex> Todd, of Rutheven, whose snout was similar to that of a hawk, which I understood is not uncommon, when they have been in fresh water; I therefore did not trouble Mr. Gerrard to paint it.</s></p>
<p><s id="s131">I have given myself the trouble to attend to the cause of this, and it appears to me, that probably it is owing to their turning up the gravel with their snouts, to deposit their spawn, which they always do in rivers.</s> <s id="s132">Minnows have been said not to inhabit the Spey; and on examining a small lake, adjoining a larger one, called Craglochy, and very near the Spey, I found the accounts accurate; I have no doubt, but in those parts of the Spey that are not too rapid for their nature, there are plenty.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s133">I cannot say much in favour of my friend's greyhounds; indeed, his only idea of goodness in the dogs, is of those that kill most, which lurchers, from their cunning; frequently do.</s> <s id="s134">I am confident he may have reason to be satisfied; but they are not dogs to my goût, nor did I quite please him, when I recommended a barber.</s></p>
<p><s id="s135">Returns of the day; a brace of hares; Sir Michael's shooting, quite harmless.</s></p>
<p><s id="s136">Morning, a severe white frost; day charming.</s></p>
<p><s id="s137">I went with my friend to see <enamex sw="w25730" long="-3.472851292970033" lat="54.44477869607492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11096504" name="Calder Abbey" conf="2.2">Calder Abbey</enamex>, and elegant, neat, and simple piece of antiquity.</s> <s id="s138">As an abbey it is small, but in the highest preservation: and its situation is truly charming.</s> <s id="s139">The verdure around, and its pretty river, the <enamex sw="w25936" long="-3.4725" lat="54.4358" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11096506" name="Calder Bridge" conf="99991">Calder</enamex>, meandering through the vale in an amphitheatre of venerable oaks, while the eye commanding as favourable view of <enamex sw="w26057" long="-3.457115296600183" lat="54.43598051808319" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11247683" name="Ponsonby" conf="2.6">Ponsonby</enamex> as in return, it receives from the abbey, render the whole a most enchanting scene.</s> <s id="s140">In this truly happy situation, I understood, Mr. J. intends to build.</s></p>
<p><s id="s141">Unwilling to lose the opportunity so favourable a day afforded, of seeing places to advantage, we trotted on to Mr. Lutwich's, about four miles from <enamex sw="w26369" long="-3.4725" lat="54.4358" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11096506" name="Calder Bridge" conf="99991">Calder</enamex>.</s> <s id="s142">The house is small, neat, and whimsical; but too much crowded with wood at the entrance, which excludes the rays of the sun, and makes the rooms gloomy and damp.</s> <s id="s143">To the north-east, it stands on the brink of a verdant precipice, chequered with different forest and fruit trees, that alternately vary the scene, the beauties of which are greatly heightened by the River <enamex sw="w26745" long="-3.4725" lat="54.4358" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:11096506" name="Calder Bridge" conf="99991">Calder</enamex>, at this place quite crystalline, from the beautiful bed it runs through.</s> <s id="s144">On the opposite banks are regular, rich pastures, neatly kept, and presenting several glances of little, spouting cascades.</s> <s id="s145">The back ground is bounded, at the distance of about four miles, by the infinitely wild mountains of Wesdal, broken and rocky to a degree.</s> <s id="s146">These circumstances altogether make this one of the most romantic and beautiful Highland views I ever beheld.</s></p>
<p><s id="s147">Above the house is seen a stupendous rock, called Adam's Crag, which might, with great propriety, be denominated <enamex sw="w27313" long="-3.090245821198284" lat="54.55669882687418" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11100762" name="Castle Crag (Fort)" conf="2.2">Castle Crag</enamex>, as it happily assumes the form of an elegant, large castle, when viewed at a proper distance; and, upon a nearer inspection, is a singularly magnificent, natural curiosity.</s></p>
<p><s id="s148">Returned by an excellent road to <enamex sw="w27533" long="-3.457115296600183" lat="54.43598051808319" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11247683" name="Ponsonby" conf="2.6">Ponsonby</enamex>, and overtook Sir M.F. who had seen plenty of game, but had been unsuccessful, which he attributed to his gun being crooked.</s></p>
<p><s id="s149">Sir James Graham and his brother dined with us at <enamex sw="w27717" long="-3.457115296600183" lat="54.43598051808319" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11247683" name="Ponsonby" conf="2.6">Ponsonby</enamex>, and politely expressed their concern at not being at <enamex sw="w27780" long="-3.497793983934793" lat="54.70514895041604" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11228154" name="Netherton" conf="2.502279671">Netherton</enamex> when I passed it, upon which I promised to pay my respects to Sir James in my next excursion, and to examine his museum of Roman antiquities, so universally known and admired by the literati.</s></p>
<p><s id="s150">Day delightful and no frost.</s> <s id="s151">Our whole party went to see Lord <enamex sw="w28044" long="-3.354050022188986" lat="54.35854835143625" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13402588" name="Muncaster CP" conf="2.354163856">Muncaster</enamex>'s; the road, like most others in this country, was better supplied with materials than any I know of elsewhere; and they are not injudiciously applied.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s152">Mulcaster House is a very large, old, irregular building, fitted up in the best Gothic style: I think I scarcely ever saw a greater number, or more elegantly furnished, rooms in any house whatever.</s></p>
<p><s id="s153">It stands boldly on the verge of a very steep precipice, the south-west, or principal front, overlooking a pretty small <enamex  sw="w28525" name="Too ambigious to allocate">lawn</enamex>, embossomed by a hill, clothed to the top with different forest trees; these shelter the house from the north wind, which blows here impetuously.</s> <s id="s154">In this prospect without suffering any inconvenience from the wood, you have an advantageous view of the sea, at the distance of about a mile.</s></p>
<p><s id="s155">To the south, beyond another fine hanging wood, is seen the river, branching off into several arms, and running rapidly along the flats, where it falls into a fine salt-water lake; the whole bounded by beautiful, smooth, sloping hills, covered with sheep.</s></p>
<p><s id="s156">The view to the east differs very materially from either of the other two.</s> <s id="s157">Adjoining to the house is a very ancient hanging bank of venerable oaks, mixed with other trees, sheltering the building from the wind, and at the same time receiving such protection from it themselves, that they grown wonderfully large.</s> <s id="s158">Looking up the valley the river again is seen, bubbling as it passes; its chequered banks formed into little coppices, the receptacle of a great number of woodcocks, while beyond, at the distance of three or four miles, appear immensely wild rocks, exhibiting their rugged, weather-beaten fronts, and their heads lost in the clouds.</s> <s id="s159">In short, I never saw any place more fortunately situated.</s></p>
<p><s id="s160">Having had the honour to know Lord <enamex sw="w29815" long="-76.049367735" lat="44.350114941" type="other" gazref="unlock:5321559" name="Mulcaster Island" conf="0.5327903498">Mulcaster</enamex> some years past, his lordship now pressed me very much to stay with him a few days, assuring me that he had seen plenty of woodcocks the day before; and adding many other kind inducements, which had I not been engaged as I was, would most readily have prevailed with me.</s></p>
<p><s id="s161">We were so much struck with the elegance of the inside of this mansion, and the beautiful prospects about it, that we staid till we found it very difficult to pass the Dudden Sands; these are narrow, and the tide running in very fast, and not attending properly to my guide, Sir M.F. but contemplating the views, if I had not been roused by the gentlemen who were farther on the shore, I should certainly have shown my mare's abilities as a swimmer.</s></p>
<p><s id="s162">The road from <enamex sw="w30560" long="-76.049367735" lat="44.350114941" type="other" gazref="unlock:5321559" name="Mulcaster Island" conf="0.5327903498">Mulcaster</enamex> House to <enamex sw="w30579" long="-2.08333" lat="53.95" type="other" gazref="unlock:4578881" name="Broughton" conf="1">Broughton</enamex>, which is about eight miles, for the first six passes over dreary moors; but, within a mile of <enamex sw="w30684" long="-2.08333" lat="53.95" type="other" gazref="unlock:4578881" name="Broughton" conf="1">Broughton</enamex>, the hanging banks, little cottages, and a prospect, through the valley, of the sea forming itself into a lake, interspersed with islands, relieved the eye after so solitary a ride.</s></p>
<p><s id="s163">We had sent a servant forward to order dinner, and found, on our arrival, a neat, small inn, where we had excellent fish, and were, in every respect, well accommodated.</s></p>
<p><s id="s164">After dinner we proceeded for <enamex sw="w31075" long="-3.069850309407378" lat="54.36812180953843" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11115199" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex>, passing by <enamex sw="w31096" long="-2.690971739658283" lat="53.80459153862378" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11089758" name="Broughton Hall" conf="1.152962201">Broughton Hall</enamex>, which, in my opinion, is by no means well situated.</s> <s id="s165">Night came on so fast, and the road was sometimes so steep, that it was twilight before we reached the banks of <enamex sw="w31276" long="-3.0765" lat="54.3361" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2653454" name="Coniston Water" conf="99991">Coniston Lake</enamex>, which I lamented, as both the lake and the country round it are beautifully picturesque, and finely variegated.</s></p>
<p><s id="s166">Drank tea at Mrs. <enamex sw="w31421" long="-2.662537985499308" lat="54.88335881243914" type="rgn" gazref="unlock:11189330" name="Knotts Wood" conf="2.184109939">Knotts</enamex>.</s> <s id="s167">These ladies, who have a seat likewise in the Highlands, turned the conversation upon the superiority of those scenes, in which we perfectly agreed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s168">Miss F. with much solicitation, was prevailed upon to stay the evening, which was the mildest imaginable, and we set off for <enamex sw="w31703" long="-2.98" lat="54.4483" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36550632" name="Rydal Hall" conf="99992">Rydal Hall</enamex>; the murmuring of water-falls heard at a distance, and the romantic scenes advantageously discovered by the clear light of the moon, as we passed, made our ride seem very short, and we reached home sooner than we expected.</s></p>
<p><s id="s169">October 28.</s> <s id="s170">- Day warm and pleasant.</s></p>
<p><s id="s171">The morning passed away so agreeably, that, though we had determined to try for woodcocks early, we did not get fairly out of doors till twelve o'clock; and after beating about for some time, without success, I joined the gamekeeper, who had been ordered to procure for me some char, the best he could get.</s></p>
<p><s id="s172">Had a very good sport, killing about six dozen of these fish, some still larger than those I had seen, and some trout.</s> <s id="s173">He informed me that in <enamex sw="w32423" long="-2.993866462466064" lat="54.44746550347175" type="water" gazref="unlock:8796733" name="Rydal Water" conf="2.4">Rydal water</enamex>, I mean the river, where he was fishing, fourteen dozen of large char have been taken with a net, at one draught.</s></p>
<p><s id="s174">On our return, we met with some woodcocks and a snipe, and killed two brace and a half.</s></p>
<p><s id="s175">They are very plentiful in this part of the country during the season, and are publicly sold in great numbers at <enamex sw="w32750" long="-3.023901654228874" lat="54.37750890240144" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167814" name="Hawkshead Hill" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex>, in the vicinity of <enamex sw="w32780" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275806" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex>, formerly for six - pence each, but now the Fly's from <enamex sw="w32839" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex> take them south; they are as much encreased in value as other articles of luxury.</s></p>
<p><s id="s176">Returns; killed five woodcocks, one snipe.</s></p>
<p><s id="s177">October 29.</s> <s id="s178">- Day gloomy, but in other respects fine.</s></p>
<p><s id="s179">As I had a desire, previous to my quitting, to examine <enamex sw="w33080" long="-3.0765" lat="54.3361" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2653454" name="Coniston Water" conf="99991">Coniston lake</enamex>, and this morning being highly favourable for the purpose, I took a ride towards that charming spot.</s></p>
<p><s id="s180">The road we found but indifferent; its defects, however, were amply compensated by the surrounding scenery, which was in the highest degree interesting.</s> <s id="s181">After a short ride, we ascended to the top of a neighbouring hill, from whence the full extent of the lake may be seen to the greatest advantage.</s></p>
<p><s id="s182"><enamex sw="w33494" long="-3.0765" lat="54.3361" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2653454" name="Coniston Water" conf="99991">Coniston Lake</enamex> is certainly a beautiful sheet of water, and the fertility of the rich meadows, which surround it, heightens the effect, as do the lower parts of the adjacent mountains, which are well covered with wood.</s> <s id="s183">In point of variety, however, the scenery, though beautiful, by no means equals <enamex sw="w33792" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s184">The bills assume a more regular appearance in their summits, and reach, in general, the water's edge with a more gentle descent.</s> <s id="s185">The want of islands too is a great deficiency, and upon the whole, though it possesses great beauties, as they must be considerably lessened by a comparison with <enamex sw="w34095" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>, that lake should by all means be seen last.</s></p>
<p><s id="s186">The north end of <enamex sw="w34168" long="-3.0765" lat="54.3361" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2653454" name="Coniston Water" conf="99991">Coniston Lake</enamex> has a bold and striking appearance; and here we admire the situation of <enamex sw="w34254" long="-3.07188" lat="54.35783" type="other" gazref="unlock:5826053" name="Coniston Hall" conf="2">Coniston Hall</enamex> on an eminence, and surrounded with fine hanging woods, with rich pasture lands below, reaching to the edge of the lake.</s> <s id="s187">Behind and above the hall, several mountains rise with tremendous majesty, craggy, bleak, and barren; from the bosom of which a cataract issues, which in wet weather must add considerably to the grandeur of the scene.</s></p>
<p><s id="s188">I now bid adieu, with regret, to all the beauties of <enamex sw="w34661" long="-2.98" lat="54.4483" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY36550632" name="Rydal Hall" conf="99992">Rydal Hall</enamex>, but had the satisfaction of enjoying the company of the worthy family, in my progress to <enamex sw="w34762" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex>, to which town they were likewise going on a visit.</s></p>
<p><s id="s189">Passed <enamex sw="w34828" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, a place much noticed by Camden, <enamex sw="w34871" long="-1.850403559283775" lat="54.98733981747228" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:27770" name="Horsley" conf="1.368067533">Horsley</enamex>, and other writers, as having been a Roman station; but there are now only small remains of its antiquity; and a good inn is perhaps the only object worth the traveller's attention: all the variegated beauties of the country, however, surround it, and may be visited in walks and short rides.</s> <s id="s190">Roman coins, arms, and urns have been found here at different times; and it is evident, that the ancient Roman road took the same direction as the present turnpike road through <enamex sw="w35349" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275806" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex>.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s191">Some of the trees here are of prodigious size, as will be seen by the following memorandum:</s></p>
<p> <s id="s192"><enamex sw="w35450" long="-2.97943049851992" lat="54.44978599662359" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11275806" name="Rydal" conf="2.6">Rydal</enamex>, October 26, 1784.</s></p>
<p><s id="s193">Memorandum.</s> <s id="s194">- That in March last a cluster pine was cut down at <enamex sw="w35540" long="-3.069850309407378" lat="54.36812180953843" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11115199" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> demesne, in <enamex  sw="w35561" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>, the property of Sir Michael Le <enamex  sw="w35604" name="Not a placename">Fleming</enamex>, Bart.</s> <s id="s195">which was one hundred years old; had two hundred feet of useful timber in it, and eleven feet in length at the but of the tree, contained sixty feet of timber.</s> <s id="s196">The large sound oak tree, by the sheep-house, is nineteen feet in circumference.</s></p>
<p><s id="s197">The inhabitants of these parts are very industrious, and are much employed in knitting stockings for <enamex sw="w35961" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex> market; in spinning woollen yarn, and making thread to weave their linsies.</s> <s id="s198">The countenances of the people may be perceived here to differ considerably from their southern neighbours, especially in the tender sex; and the square face, and the high cheek bone, are strong indications of their proximity to <enamex  sw="w36273" name="Large admin unit">North Britain</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s199">Below <enamex sw="w36294" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>, in a meadow near the <enamex sw="w36326" long="-2.994198939372259" lat="54.42269989843945" type="water" gazref="unlock:11256639" name="River Brathay" conf="2.4">River Brathay</enamex>, is a Roman camp, the outline of which is still very visible, and extends one way four hundred feet, and three hundred the other.</s> <s id="s200">It is supposed by Mr. Pennant to be the Dictis of the Notitia, and was the station of part of the cohort of the Numerus Nerviorum Dictensium. It was placed very conveniently to command several passes.</s> <s id="s201">Coins, bricks, and other antiquities are often found on this sport.</s></p>
<p><s id="s202">We followed the banks of the charming, justly-celebrated, Lake of <enamex sw="w36807" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>, a beautiful epitome of the great Highland lake; fortunately, the sun peeping out occasionally, gave us that advantageous view of its beauties, which we apprehended we should be deprived of by the gloominess of the morning.</s> <s id="s203">Many stations are pointed out as the most advantageous for viewing this lake, in the same manner as at <enamex sw="w37145" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex>, and the particular descriptions of such situations may serve to swell volumes of guides and tours to the lakes; but, after all, every one will judge for himself on the spot, as I did, conceiving that, in our way to <enamex sw="w37374" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex>, we had as favourable a view of <enamex sw="w37413" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex> as we could wish for.</s></p>
<p><s id="s204">Our road continuing for about five miles by the side of the lake, brought us nearly to the Horse Ferry, which crosses the lake to the village of Sawrey; and this being about the centre, we had a fine view, not only across, but almost of the whole extent of the lake, including the islands and the injudicious erections on them.</s></p>
<p><s id="s205">So many, and such ample descriptions have been given of <enamex sw="w37830" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>, and it is so foreign to my purpose to expatiate on the subject, that I shall content myself with simply pointing out the difference between this admired lake and others.</s></p>
<p><s id="s206">Each of the lakes, no doubt, has its own particular features; <enamex sw="w38074" long="-3.0252" lat="54.4584" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2648201" name="Grasmere" conf="99991">Grassmere</enamex> is characterized by mildness; <enamex sw="w38114" long="-3.1588" lat="54.6018" type="other" gazref="unlock:5828527" name="Derwentwater Hotel" conf="2">Derwentwater</enamex> by grandeur; <enamex sw="w38140" long="-3.069850309407378" lat="54.36812180953843" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11115199" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> is elegant, romantic, and sublime; but <enamex sw="w38188" long="-2.907933804199639" lat="54.37599546506077" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="2.6">Windermere</enamex>, from its immensity and variety of prospect, may justly claim the character of magnificence.</s> <s id="s207">Here almost every object confesses cultivation; but the islands, though numerous and woody, are small, and in general bear a resemblance to the artificial circles raised in gentlemen's canals, for aquatic fowls to breed in.</s> <s id="s208">The great island is little better than a bank of sand, and is now under the despoiling hand of a deformer.</s> <s id="s209">The hills in general are humble, except above <enamex sw="w38669" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex>; and the margin of the water is irregularly indented, forming numerous bays and promontories; the latter, composed of fine meadow-ground and ranges of trees, are of exquisite beauty; while on every side a vast expense of woodlands is stretched upon the view.</s></p>
<p><s id="s210"><enamex sw="w38938" long="-2.93438" lat="54.37296" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_SD402977" name="Winderemere (Lake)" conf="99991">Windermere Lake</enamex> is twelve computed miles long, and not above one in the widest part.</s> <s id="s211">The greatest depth is supposed to be about forty fathoms.</s> <s id="s212">It abounds in pike, trout, char, eels, and perch.</s></p>
<p><s id="s213">Quitting the banks of the lake a little beyond <enamex sw="w39178" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>, we found a very good road, though a little hilly, to <enamex sw="w39240" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex>, and a delightful ride.</s> <s id="s214">Passed by <enamex sw="w39281" long="-2.855297253126893" lat="54.38106807840329" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33120" name="Ings" conf="2.6">Ings</enamex> church, a neat, modern building, which is said to owe its foundation to the following event:</s></p>
<p><s id="s215">A British merchant, of the name of <enamex sw="w39414" long="-2.855297253126893" lat="54.38106807840329" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:33120" name="Ings" conf="2.6">Ings</enamex>, or <enamex sw="w39423" long="-3.244792662301895" lat="57.67469792895464" type="water" gazref="unlock:8787873" name="Innes Canal" conf="0.9003722973">Innes</enamex>, a native of this part of the country, having acquired a very considerable fortune at <enamex sw="w39515" long="-9.1333333" lat="38.7166667" type="pplc" gazref="geonames:2267057" name="Lisbon" conf="1.742959016">Lisbon</enamex>, where he had resided many years; and from whence he had, from time to time, conveyed great part of his property to his relations in <enamex  sw="w39655" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>; at length, resolved to return to this native country, and having converted the remainder of this effects into <enamex  sw="w39774" name="Large admin unit">Portugal</enamex> gold, embarked with it privately, on board a vessel, bound for <enamex  sw="w39846" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>; which was scarcely got out of the harbour, when his escape was discovered, and a great outcry made from the shore to bring her back: the captain, sensible of his own danger, would have tacked about, and landed him, when his whole property would have been confiscated, and his person imprisoned; it being contrary to the laws of <enamex  sw="w40183" name="Large admin unit">Portugal</enamex> to carry the gold coin out of the kingdom; but, providentially, the wind blowing directly contrary, obliged the captain to continue his course, and he arrived safe in <enamex  sw="w40359" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>; and built this church in grateful remembrance of his wonderful preservation.</s></p>
<p><s id="s216"><enamex sw="w40445" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex></s>
</p><p><s id="s217">I had only just time to examine this ancient town on our arrival, as we were engaged to dine with Mr. <enamex sw="w40554" long="-2.67414" lat="54.56738" type="other" gazref="unlock:4568635" name="Little Strickland" conf="1.844785743">Strickland</enamex>, at <enamex sw="w40569" long="-2.7715" lat="54.284" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_6287029" name="Sizer Castle" conf="99992">Sizergh Hall</enamex>, about three miles out of <enamex sw="w40608" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex>, on the road to <enamex sw="w40631" long="-2.7746" lat="54.2267" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD496815" name="Milnthorpe" conf="99992">Milthrop</enamex>:</s></p>
<p><s id="s218"><enamex sw="w40641" long="-2.775715663908865" lat="54.28048529968509" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11284405" name="Sizergh Castle" conf="2.2">Sizergh</enamex>, or, as it is commonly called, <enamex sw="w40680" long="-2.7715" lat="54.284" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_6287029" name="Sizer Castle" conf="99992">Siser Hall</enamex>, is a venerable old mansion, said to have been built in the reign of Henry Ii.</s> <s id="s219">consequently it is one of the most ancient family seats in <enamex  sw="w40829" name="Large admin unit">Britain</enamex>, as its large antique tower alone sufficiently testifies; and in <enamex sw="w40902" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex> church there is, I understand, a chapel belonging to the <enamex sw="w40966" long="-2.67414" lat="54.56738" type="other" gazref="unlock:4568635" name="Little Strickland" conf="1.844785743">Strickland</enamex> family, which shows their early settlement in this country.</s></p>
<p><s id="s220">Considerable additions and improvements have been made by the present worthy owner; and the whole building, being white, has a very advantageous appearance, having a back ground of old oaks and forest trees; a pretty opening into a small park, and the <enamex sw="w41289" long="-2.806404741590844" lat="54.33404878379706" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772001" name="River Kent" conf="2.4">River Kent</enamex> in front, on which there is a considerable iron-forge, and two water-falls, of no great height.</s> <s id="s221">The principal rooms are lofty spacious, lined with oak, and carved with the same ancient and exquisite taste as the admired great room in <enamex sw="w41534" long="-0.595574683966458" lat="51.48754951104155" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11323845" name="Windsor Castle" conf="0.892805015">Windsor Castle</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s222">After passing the day in the most agreeable manner, at this delightful retreat, our party returned in the evening to the inn, at <enamex sw="w41679" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex>; dressed and went to a ball, in the house: the room was rather small, but the company very genteel; the ladies in general handsome; though the music, after that I had heard in <enamex  sw="w41862" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex>, appeared to me very indifferent.</s></p>
<p><s id="s223">Morning pleasant and promising a fine day.</s></p>
<p><s id="s224">Having taken leave of the ladies at breakfast, Sir Michael, who is universally known and respected here, did me the honour to accompany me in taking a general view of the town.</s> <s id="s225">It consists of two principal streets, one about a mile and a quarter long, the other about half a mile; the houses which are ill built, stand irregularly, and for the most part have a mean appearance, though there are many of a <enamex sw="w42353" long="-4.99258216412324" lat="54.99219438715534" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788263" name="Lake Superior" conf="0.9717482139">superior</enamex> kind, the residence of the more opulent inhabitants.</s> <s id="s226">The only public building worth the notice of travellers, the castle being in ruins, is the parish church, one of the largest perhaps in <enamex  sw="w42551" name="Large admin unit">Britain</enamex>: it is a fine old Gothic edifice with a square tower, very plain within, being destitute of all ornament, but kept remarkably clean and neat.</s></p>
<p><s id="s227">The inhabitants of <enamex sw="w42720" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex> are very industrious, and, from time immemorial, have carried on an extensive trade in fish hooks, for the fabrication of which they are famous; they have also established a cotton manufactory, and expect great advantages from it.</s> <s id="s228">Indeed, if we may judge from the extensive tenter-grounds surrounding the town, it is already in a flourishing condition.</s> <s id="s229">The <enamex sw="w43084" long="-2.806404741590844" lat="54.33404878379706" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772001" name="River Kent" conf="2.4">River Kent</enamex>, over which there are three stone bridges, meanders through the town; and running into a pretty valley, renders the situation very convenient for bleaching their cottons and linens.</s> <s id="s230">The white appearance of the cloth on the tenters, it seems, has deceived strangers on their approach to the town in the dusk of the evening, who have mistaken them for small buildings, most of the houses being of stone, covered with a white, rough cast; and this deception made them conceive the town to be much larger than it is in reality.</s></p>
<p><s id="s231">At the Hee, near <enamex sw="w43636" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex>, the property of Mr. Robinson, a few years since a branch was blown off a beech tree, which measured two hundred cubic feet; the parent tree, when cut down, measured eight hundred feet.</s></p>
<p><s id="s232">With proper acknowledgments for his polite attention and repeated civilities, I bid adieu to my worthy friend, and got on horseback precisely at twelve o'clock, intending, if possible to be at <enamex  sw="w44022" name="Not a placename">Marshfield</enamex> by three.</s></p>
<p><s id="s233">The country, on quitting the suburbs of <enamex sw="w44083" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex>, becomes very barren, being almost destitute of leaf or grass; the russet predominates, and the road is hilly and stony, which made it unpleasant riding; but soon coming in sight of <enamex sw="w44272" long="-2.59817" lat="54.20509" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825825" name="Kirby Lonsdale Cockpit Hill" conf="1.967838395">Kirby Lonsdale</enamex>, my eye was instantly relieved, and my ideas enlivened; for here the beautiful <enamex sw="w44366" long="-2.672622913542797" lat="54.21368667875034" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788892" name="River Lune" conf="2.4">River Lune</enamex> refreshes the vale; some hanging woods, corn fields, and good pastures, together with the pleasing appearance of the neat town of <enamex sw="w44507" long="-2.59817" lat="54.20509" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825825" name="Kirby Lonsdale Cockpit Hill" conf="1.967838395">Kirby Lonsdale</enamex> rendered the scene quite delightful.</s></p>
</text>
</document>