<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1860_a"><p><s id="s1">From Silversdale to <enamex sw="w32" long="-2.8066" lat="54.2157" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD475803" name="Kent's Mouth" conf="99992">Kent sand</enamex> side, Whose soil is sown with cockle shells; From <enamex sw="w92" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> eke, and <enamex sw="w109" long="-3.0667" lat="54.3667" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2652457" name="Coniston" conf="99992">Connyside</enamex>, With fellows fierce from <enamex sw="w145" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> fells.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s2">Lancashire Ballad of <enamex sw="w182" long="-2.166786694325647" lat="55.63095967985625" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11145646" name="Flodden Field" conf="0.9061752782">Flodden Field</enamex></s></p>
<p><s id="s3"><enamex sw="w196" long="-2.971573845828191" lat="54.11726758179064" type="water" gazref="unlock:11222778" name="Morecambe Bay" conf="2.4">Morecambe Bay</enamex>, or, the great crooked bay, which divides the districts of <enamex sw="w269" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> and <enamex sw="w281" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> from the rest of <enamex  sw="w306" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>, and which receives the waters of the <enamex sw="w354" long="-2.816670591684018" lat="53.86550796357606" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36276" name="St Michael'S On Wyre" conf="1.6">Wyre</enamex>, the <enamex sw="w364" long="-2.672622913542797" lat="54.21368667875034" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788892" name="River Lune" conf="2.4">Lune</enamex>, the <enamex sw="w374" long="-2.726783337585184" lat="54.1508413117057" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771998" name="River Keer" conf="2.4">Keer</enamex>, the <enamex sw="w384" long="-2.896315912832438" lat="54.33423674322094" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36927" name="Winster" conf="2.6">Winster</enamex>, the <enamex  sw="w397" name="Large admin unit">Kent</enamex>, the <enamex sw="w407" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex>, and other rivers of less note, is a grand object, lying among scenes of singular interest and beauty.</s> <s id="s4">Its picturesquely-irregular shores are full of varied charms-soft secluded vales, and green nooks of nestling-old towns and villages, rich parks, and wildwoods sloping to the water-which are all the more charming that they cling like a garland about this playground of the capricious sea, with the outlines of the mountains crowding round in the rearward, tier over tier, in stormy majesty.</s> <s id="s5">Within the fine sweep of scenery overlooking this bay, there is many a venerable home of ancient religion, many a towered steep and storied glen, that wakes the memories of a thousand years gone by.</s> <s id="s6"><enamex sw="w1106" long="-2.878643961524713" lat="54.06404841396252" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11222777" name="Morecambe" conf="3.142603975">Morecambe</enamex> is, also, the outfall of <enamex sw="w1141" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> and <enamex sw="w1156" long="-3.0635" lat="54.3683" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD310975" name="Coniston Water Head" conf="99992">Coniston waters</enamex>, and is the most impressive gateway to the Lake Country.</s> <s id="s7">From its shores at <enamex sw="w1248" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, the River <enamex sw="w1270" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex> will lead the traveller by windings full of changeful beauty, nine miles, to that pleasant resting-place called" <enamex sw="w1389" long="-2.959809373549684" lat="54.2701718942731" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11229861" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>," at the foot of <enamex sw="w1419" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>.</s> <s id="s8"><enamex sw="w1431" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> and <enamex sw="w1443" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> have been compartively unknown, on account of difficulty of access in days gone by; but now that the line from <enamex sw="w1562" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> to <enamex sw="w1575" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> skirts these sequestered regions, their attractions cannot fail to arrest the attention of all lovers of the picturesque in nature.</s> <s id="s9">In addition to its natural beauty, <enamex sw="w1753" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> is indeed" a land whose stones are iron, and out of whose hills thou mayest dig brass;" but the wild fells and green valleys of <enamex sw="w1889" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> knowlittle of the bustling world, save what belongs to their purely agricultural and pastoral character; and the primitive race of mountain folk dwelling therein clings tothe manners, language, and traditions of its" fore-elders" with an affection little disturbed by communion with the great changes of modern life.</s> <s id="s10">To the scholar andstudent of manners, to the lover of nature, and the man of science, these secluded hills and glens teem with rich and rare interest.</s></p>
<p><s id="s11">Before the railway was made the old way of crossing the sands from <enamex sw="w2432" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> to <enamex sw="w2445" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> must have been very striking, both from the character of the scenery aroundand a sense of danger, which cannot but have given something of the piquancy of adventure to the journey.</s> <s id="s12">The channels are constantly shifting, particularly after heavyrains, when they are perilously uncertain.</s> <s id="s13">For many centuries past, two guides have conducted travellers over them.</s> <s id="s14">Their duty is to observe the changes, and find fordable points.</s> <s id="s15">In all seasons and states of the weather this was their duty, and in times of storm and fog it must have been fraught with danger.</s> <s id="s16">These guides wereanciently appointed by the Prior of <enamex sw="w3063" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>, and received synodal and Peter Pence for their maintance.</s> <s id="s17">They are now paid from the revenues of the duchy.</s> <s id="s18">This office ofguide has been so long held by a family of the name of Carter, that the country people have given that name to the office itself.</s> <s id="s19">A gentleman, crossing from <enamex sw="w3351" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex>, once asked the guide if" Carters" were never lost on the sands.</s> <s id="s20">" I never knew any lost," said the guide;" there's one or two drowned now and then, but theyere generally foundsomewhere i' th bed when the tide goes out."</s> <s id="s21">A certain ancient mariner, called <enamex sw="w3613" long="-2.310068065097231" lat="53.63538681173947" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11234240" name="Nuttall" conf="1.542141542">Nuttall</enamex>, who lives at Grange, on the <enamex sw="w3650" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> shore, told me that" people who get their livingby' following the sands,' hardly ever die in their beds.</s> <s id="s22">They end their days on the sands; and even their horses and carts are generally lost there.</s> <s id="s23">I have helped," said he," to pull horses and coaches, ay, and guides too, out of the sands.</s> <s id="s24">The channel," he continued," is seldom two days together in one place.</s> <s id="s25">You may make a chart one day, and, before the ink is dry, it will have shifted."</s> <s id="s26">I found, indeed, byinquiry, that those who have travelled the sands longest, are always most afraid of them; and that these silent currents, which shimmer so beautifully in the sunshine, have been" the ribs of death" to thousands.</s> <s id="s27">The old" <enamex sw="w4338" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.4">Over</enamex> Sands" route began at <enamex sw="w4365" long="-2.800813564608896" lat="54.09802913000562" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:20867" name="Hest Bank" conf="2.6">Hest Bank</enamex>, a cliff on the shore, about three miles from <enamex sw="w4421" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex>.</s> <s id="s28">The coach, and whatevertravellers might be going, used to meet the guide on the banks of the River <enamex sw="w4531" long="-2.726783337585184" lat="54.1508413117057" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771998" name="River Keer" conf="2.4">Keer</enamex>, which runs over the sands, about three miles from <enamex sw="w4587" long="-2.800813564608896" lat="54.09802913000562" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:20867" name="Hest Bank" conf="2.6">Hest Bank</enamex>.</s> <s id="s29">Here the guide carefullytried the bed of the stream before travellers were allowed to cross - for what was fordable yesterday to-day might be a quicksand.</s> <s id="s30">The safe tracks are indicated by branches of furze, called" brogs," stuck in the sand.</s> <s id="s31">The old word" brog," means a broken branch; and it is very likely that the word" brob," applied by the people ofFurness and <enamex sw="w4964" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> to these furze branches, is merely a corruption of the former word.</s> <s id="s32">On reaching Kent's Bank, the coach went about three miles through the villages onthe <enamex sw="w5125" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> shore, and then forward across the <enamex sw="w5168" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex> estuary, to Ulverstone town.</s> <s id="s33">These sands, though not one - third the distance of the sands between <enamex sw="w5271" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w5285" name="Large admin unit">Kent</enamex>' sBank, are considered much more dangerous.</s> <s id="s34">Probably the difference may arise from the greater number of persons crossing from <enamex sw="w5416" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> to <enamex sw="w5427" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s35">In every village, andin almost every house I entered, upon the shores of this bay, I met with tales of danger and disaster which have occurred upon these sands; and, even now, there is a kindof daily excitement there, arising from the dangerous possibilities of travelling over them.</s> <s id="s36">Such was the old" <enamex sw="w5741" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.4">Over</enamex> Sands" route from <enamex sw="w5764" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex>.</s> <s id="s37">In Mrs. Hemans' letters, she thus alludes to the journey: -" I must not omit to tell you that Mr. Wordsworth not only admired our exploit in crossing the <enamex sw="w5927" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> sandds as a deed of' derringdo,' but as a decided proof of taste.</s> <s id="s38">The lake scenery, he says, is never seen to such advantage as after the passage of what he calls its majestic barrier."</s></p>
<p><s id="s39">This impressive scene may now be traversed by all who prefer speed and ease to danger and delay free from the uncertainties of the old route.</s> <s id="s40">Along the picturesquenorthern shores of this" majestic barrier," the new line of railway from <enamex sw="w6360" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> to <enamex sw="w6373" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> winds by <enamex sw="w6393" long="-2.820874446921715" lat="54.16814672786025" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:18374" name="Silverdale" conf="2.6">Silverdale</enamex>, with the gran features of land and sea full insight; and the traveller lake-wards may, at comparatively little cost of time and money, look upone a scene so strikingly different to what he will find in the countryhe is going to, that the variety itself cannot but add to the interest of his journey.</s> <s id="s41">The length of the line from <enamex sw="w6733" long="-2.772858747652117" lat="54.12769635103146" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11099650" name="Carnforth" conf="2.6">Carnforth</enamex>, six miles beyond <enamex sw="w6761" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex>, to <enamex sw="w6775" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> is about twenty miles, and, though it passes through one or two rural villages which hide the sea for a few minutes, two - thirds of its length commands a continually changing view of <enamex sw="w6968" long="-2.971573845828191" lat="54.11726758179064" type="water" gazref="unlock:11222778" name="Morecambe Bay" conf="2.4">Morecambe Bay</enamex>.</s> <s id="s42">It often runs over large tracts ofthe sands, wheere the waves sometimes come lashing the firm embankment, like occan skirmishers sent out from the main body to remonstrate with this bold invader of theirold domain.</s> <s id="s43">On the land-ward side, every mile brings a new picture; the land is full of changeful picturesqueness of indentation; and the shelving shores of light-huedlime-stone rock, which we pass now and then, are rich in exquisite variety of form and colour.</s> <s id="s44">The woods are peculiarly beautiful to look upon, their lighter shades of green being charmingly relieved by numbers of the dark historic yew tree, full of brave remembrances of <enamex  sw="w7625" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> and its forest life in the olden time.</s> <s id="s45">Here, where therugged selvedge of our mountain district softens into slopes of fertile beauty by the fitful sea, - and where the mountain streams, at last, wind silently homewards overthe sands, we flit by many a sylvan nook, and many a country nest, where we should be glad to linger; - and by the outlet of many a little paradisal glen, nestling in theverdant creases of <enamex sw="w8041" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>'s fells, which once seen, will nevermore be willingly forgotten, but remain a bower of beautiful rememberance, where the mind may find aresting-place even in the city's busy throng.</s></p>
<p><s id="s46">Early in the month of May I found myself, one fine evening, walking about the platform of <enamex sw="w8321" long="-2.77147" lat="54.12961" type="other" gazref="unlock:9773244" name="Carnforth Railway Station" conf="2">Carnforth Station</enamex>, waiting for the train to <enamex sw="w8365" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s47">It was that delightfultime of the day when the birds were beginning to get stiller, and might be heard more distinctly than before, singing their little nestward solos with drowsy delight, hereand there among the trees.</s> <s id="s48">The train started, and for the first time I was rolling towards <enamex sw="w8661" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, by the way of the <enamex sw="w8691" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> shore.</s> <s id="s49">We were soon over the River <enamex sw="w8734" long="-2.726783337585184" lat="54.1508413117057" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771998" name="River Keer" conf="2.4">Keer</enamex>, which, having left the hills, comes gliding through a green plain on the right, and then on across the <enamex sw="w8842" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> sands, where its shifty channel have been the death-bedof many a gallant man.</s> <s id="s50">Now we came to <enamex sw="w8945" long="-2.80378" lat="54.16944" type="other" gazref="unlock:9773282" name="Silverdale Railway Station" conf="2">Silverdale Station</enamex>, where brown-faced, stalwart men were unloading timber, or lounging about the whole-some looking, work-a-dayvillage.</s> <s id="s51">In a few minutes we are off again.</s> <s id="s52">Gardens, and comfortable stone-built farm-houses, and little orchards all white with apple-blossom are fitting past, and the raggedsummits of <enamex sw="w9258" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> Fells draw nearer to the eye.</s></p>
<p><s id="s53">Just before reaching the temporary station at <enamex sw="w9342" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex> we catch a glimpse of <enamex sw="w9372" long="-2.835153265248907" lat="54.18121297070689" type="other" gazref="unlock:11063900" name="Arnside Tower" conf="2">Arnside Tower</enamex>, a massive old peel, on an eminence at the head of a solitary vale to seaward. In the northward distance there is a fine view of the <enamex  sw="w9518" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland hills</enamex> at this point.</s> <s id="s54">Delightful <enamex sw="w9561" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex>! If any man loves the beautiful in nature-if he be a geologist, or a botanist, or an invalid in search of peaceful restoration-let him wander about <enamex sw="w9717" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex>, and pleasant <enamex sw="w9739" long="-2.820874446921715" lat="54.16814672786025" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:18374" name="Silverdale" conf="2.6">Silverdale</enamex> Which is close by.</s> <s id="s55">Shortly after this evening ride I returned for a ramble about <enamex sw="w9831" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex>, one sunny day, in company with Mr. W. Salmon, president of the Horticultural Society of <enamex sw="w9928" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, and Mr. <enamex sw="w9948" long="-2.430426782171715" lat="53.57208890145878" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11082597" name="Bolton" conf="2.174714103">Bolton</enamex>, of Swartmoor, a notable geologist, and a personal" friend and fellow-labourarer" of Professor SedgwickThe day was so fine, and the scene so beautiful, that we were as blithe as threc lads going a-nutting to the woods on a holiday morning in summer time.</s> <s id="s56">The old station-masterat <enamex sw="w10235" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex> kenw the names of the hills around, and every remarkable point of the glorious landscape.</s> <s id="s57">We chatted with him a few minutes, watching the beautiful effect of a cloud-shadow gliding over the grand limestone crags of" <enamex sw="w10459" long="-2.922192051215889" lat="54.6479783587203" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11320168" name="Whitbarrow Village" conf="2.530219053">Whitbarrow</enamex>" in the sunlight; and, after beggin a few matches, we lit our cigars, and took up a shady lane towards thepicturesque hill called" <enamex sw="w10601" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex> <enamex  sw="w10609" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>."</s> <s id="s58">Having wound up this pleasant lane, between tall bushy hedgerows, about half a mile, we met the gamekeeper, who gave me directions forthe ascent of the" <enamex  sw="w10769" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>," warning us to carefully against the use of fire, by which considerable damage had been done in the woods above.</s> <s id="s59">Skirting the eastern slope of the hill, a good road brought us into the vale at the head of which" <enamex sw="w10986" long="-2.835153265248907" lat="54.18121297070689" type="other" gazref="unlock:11063900" name="Arnside Tower" conf="2">Arnside Tower</enamex>," a massive old quadrangular building, of limestone, stands, a lonesome, gloomy-looking ruin.</s> <s id="s60">It isfinely situated on an isthmus which connects the two peninsulas of <enamex sw="w11166" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex> and <enamex sw="w11178" long="-2.820874446921715" lat="54.16814672786025" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:18374" name="Silverdale" conf="2.6">Silverdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s61">Seawad, it commands a view of <enamex sw="w11220" long="-2.757884211601201" lat="54.14576906519672" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11313874" name="Warton" conf="2.6">Warton</enamex> Sands, and looks right over the bay, out to <enamex sw="w11271" long="-4.692535773887674" lat="54.22593372544603" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11241717" name="Peel Castle" conf="0.8191860256">Peel Castle</enamex>, off the far western point of Low <enamex sw="w11317" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>.</s> <s id="s62"><enamex sw="w11326" long="-2.749737254586139" lat="54.54131161530717" type="other" gazref="unlock:11137532" name="Eastward" conf="1.905901419">Eastward</enamex>, it overlooks the lone green vale of <enamex sw="w11372" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex>, with its little tarn shining in the hollow, and beyond there is a viewof <enamex sw="w11454" long="-2.71334707329606" lat="54.22693903105996" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11142147" name="Farleton" conf="2.6">Farleton</enamex> <enamex  sw="w11463" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>, and of the sands formed by the River Kier.</s> <s id="s63">The walls of this ancient border stronghold are of great thickness, and the small rude windows, doorways, shot-holes, and quaint fireplaces are still visible.</s> <s id="s64">There are no evidences of any other ancient outbuildings or defences connected with it, and, probably, as Dr. Whittaker says," It has beenmerely a place of temporary retreat, in case of sudden alarm from the north, for the neighbouring inhabitants."</s> <s id="s65">With the exception of an old farmhouse, a little below the tower, there is no other building in all the vale of <enamex sw="w12031" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex>.</s> <s id="s66">The old name of the township was" Earnseat," from the" earn," for which it was a favourite retreat in ancient times.</s> <s id="s67">Thedistrict, especially about the" <enamex  sw="w12192" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>," is famous for rare ferns, and the northern shore of that rocky beight is a favourite wandering ground of the geologist.</s> <s id="s68">Leaving the road onthe slope of" <enamex sw="w12352" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex> <enamex  sw="w12360" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>," we walked through the old farm-yard below, and thence up to the tower.</s> <s id="s69">Within, all was ruined, and wild, and roofless, but we found the ancient windinglimestone staircase sufficiently good for us to get to the top without difficulty.</s> <s id="s70">Here we sat down on the broad, grass-grown, ruined wall, to look about us.</s> <s id="s71">In spite of thebeauty of the woods on" <enamex sw="w12715" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex> <enamex  sw="w12723" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>," the greenness of the vale, and the fine views east and west, there was a touch of desolation in the scene, to which the mouldering tower wesat upon contributed a solemn share.</s> <s id="s72">In the east a train, laden with <enamex sw="w12938" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> ore, darted by the end of the vale, and broke the dreamy stillness with remembrances of the activeworld.</s> <s id="s73">It passed, and all was still again, except where a number of swallows skimmed the air in graceful flights between our ruined resting-place and the ground.</s> <s id="s74">I chanced to fling some shreds of paper fromthe tower, which, as they were borne away in quivering gyrations by the wind, were instantly pursued by the birds, and rarely reached the ground before they were caught by one orother of these dainty ariels, and carried off to nooks in the caves of the old farmhouse below.</s> <s id="s75">One of my friends said it reminded him of the pursuit of knowledge under dfficulties, and was another evidence of the growing taste for reading in these times.</s> <s id="s76">Another suggested thhat perhaps these <enamex sw="w13721" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex> swallows might inherit the souls of departed politicians, andwere anxious to know something of the political movements of the day; and, pointing to a day bird which dropped the shred he had caught in his bill, he said that one evidently did n't agree with the leading article, and therefore declined to take the paper in any further.</s> <s id="s77">Another thought they might have heard of the dispute about the duty, or might be in some wayinterested in the consumption of the article.</s> <s id="s78">But rumblings of distant thunder warned us that we had far to go, so we came down the stairs of the ruined tower, and began the ascent of" <enamex sw="w14337" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex> <enamex  sw="w14345" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>."</s> <s id="s79">A good footpath leads aslant the hill, through groves of larch, spruce, and fir, whose different hues of green look very beautiful in the sunshine.</s> <s id="s80"><enamex sw="w14500" long="-68.95726790000001" lat="45.8944903" type="other" gazref="unlock:7697380" name="Abot Trail" conf="0.4206400729">Abot</enamex> half the way we left the footpath, and struck up the shingly bill-side to save time.</s> <s id="s81">The slope was steeper than any ordinary proof, and the shingles gave way at every step; but we toiled up, oftenusing our hands, till we reached a green spot at the edge of the wood upon the summit.</s> <s id="s82">Here, among gorse bushes and tufts of ling, we found it very pleasant to rest.</s> <s id="s83">The view was finefrom this point.</s> <s id="s84">At the foot of the hill lay the lone vale of <enamex sw="w14946" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex>, with its hoary tower standing solitarily at the head, like a worn out soldier dreaming of departed wars-and its silvery pool shining in the green hollow, the little bright eye of the silent dell.</s> <s id="s85"><enamex sw="w15151" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.4">Over</enamex> the fir-clad ridge beyond we had a charming glimpse of <enamex sw="w15211" long="-2.820874446921715" lat="54.16814672786025" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:18374" name="Silverdale" conf="2.6">Silverdale</enamex>, and its pretty sequesteredvillage near the sea.</s> <s id="s86">I understand that the sands on <enamex sw="w15302" long="-2.820874446921715" lat="54.16814672786025" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:18374" name="Silverdale" conf="2.6">Silverdale</enamex> shore are very fine for bathing.</s> <s id="s87">In this delightful dale there is a small lake called" <enamex sw="w15400" long="-2.8025" lat="54.5218" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2647299" name="Haweswater" conf="99992">Hawes Tarn</enamex>," crowded with pike, and remarkable for its thick bed of snow-white, tiny, univalve sea shells, of fragile beauty.</s> <s id="s88">The waters of this tarn are said to be affected by the rise and fall of the tide.</s> <s id="s89">The sunwas shining all around, and we had a full view of" <enamex sw="w15665" long="-2.71334707329606" lat="54.22693903105996" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11142147" name="Farleton" conf="2.6">Farleton</enamex> <enamex  sw="w15674" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>," and the picturesque limestone bridges running eastward.</s> <s id="s90">In a far corner of the milnthorpe Sands, the white tower of <enamex sw="w15797" long="-2.775041054829904" lat="54.24453531756829" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11170961" name="Heversham" conf="2.6">Heversham</enamex> church peeped out prettily from the green woods down by the shore; whilst in the east all the great <enamex  sw="w15907" name="Large admin unit">Yorkshire hills</enamex> were robed in gloom, and solemn rollings of distant thundertold that a storm was raging among them.</s> <s id="s91">It was a glorious sight; but cool gusts came now and then through the sunshine, and the trees on" <enamex sw="w16121" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex> <enamex  sw="w16129" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>" began to talk of the comingtempest.</s> <s id="s92">Our old friend said that rain would certainly overtake us before the day had run by, and as a fir tree was but a riddly shelter in heavy showers, we had better go nearer the haunts of man.</s> <s id="s93">He pocketed hisgeological hammer, slung his strong wallet over his shoulder, and led on through scratchy brushwood, under the green shades that cover all the hill top, emerging on the open northernslope, from whence the view of" <enamex sw="w16589" long="-2.922192051215889" lat="54.6479783587203" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11320168" name="Whitbarrow Village" conf="2.530219053">Whitbarrow</enamex>," the shores and sands channel of the <enamex  sw="w16638" name="Large admin unit">Kent</enamex>, and the distant mountains of <enamex  sw="w16673" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, is wonderfully fine.</s> <s id="s94">Descending to the water side, ourold friend donned his spectacles, and took out his hammer again; and the two geologists wandered about the rocky shore in a trance of scientific delight, picking up many specimensinteresting to them.</s> <s id="s95">One of these specimens-I was requested to show to an eminent geologist in <enamex sw="w17014" long="-2.250909844579199" lat="53.51088669792344" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:9710" name="Manchester" conf="2.177003304">Manchester</enamex>, whose name was familiar to them.</s> <s id="s96">We found some simple, substantial cheer at a little country inn, called the" Fighting Cocks," near the river side.</s> <s id="s97">From this place we wend westward a mile or so, then up the valley of the <enamex sw="w17247" long="-2.896315912832438" lat="54.33423674322094" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36927" name="Winster" conf="2.6">Winster</enamex> to" <enamex sw="w17259" long="-2.925256525348697" lat="54.78277548656492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11171827" name="High Head Castle" conf="2.169573108">Castle Head</enamex>," where we spent two pleasant hours in the house and grounds.</s> <s id="s98">From this place we went westward a mile or so, then up the valley of the <enamex sw="w17406" long="-2.896315912832438" lat="54.33423674322094" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36927" name="Winster" conf="2.6">Winster</enamex> to" <enamex sw="w17418" long="-2.925256525348697" lat="54.78277548656492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11171827" name="High Head Castle" conf="2.169573108">Castle Head</enamex>," where we spent two pleasant hours in thehouse and grounds.</s> <s id="s99">From thence we crossed over" Aggerslack," down into" <enamex sw="w17544" name="Lindal Lane">Lindal Lane</enamex>," then up the opposite steep again, by the way of" <enamex sw="w17607" name="Slack Farm">Slack Farm</enamex>," right over the rocky summit of" <enamex sw="w17651" long="-2.922900359" lat="54.20590361" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00209" name="Hampsfell" conf="99992">Hampsfield Fell</enamex>," descending into the old town of <enamex sw="w17701" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>, where we took tea at the Cavendish Arms," the principal inn, which stands on the site of the ancient priory buildings nearthe church.</s> <s id="s100">A seven mile walk in the gloaming through <enamex sw="w17886" long="-2.95" lat="54.2" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_2653631" name="Cartmel" conf="99992">Cartmel park</enamex>, by the woods of <enamex sw="w17916" long="-2.973259116317761" lat="54.1891650792199" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11176859" name="Holker" conf="2.6">Holker</enamex>, and partly over the <enamex sw="w17944" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex> Sands, brought us to <enamex sw="w17971" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> about ten at night, after twentymiles walk, just in time to get well wet by the storm which we had watched in the forenoon from the eastern edge of" <enamex sw="w18131" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex> <enamex  sw="w18139" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>."</s> <s id="s101">In spite of this, I hardly ever had a more delightfulramble through a more finely-varied country than the one I had that day.</s> <s id="s102">After this passing notice of my excursion to <enamex sw="w18317" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex>, I will now return to my first ride to <enamex sw="w18364" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> by rail.</s></p>
<p><s id="s103">Soon after the train leaves <enamex sw="w18412" long="-2.82804" lat="54.20257" type="other" gazref="unlock:9773232" name="Arnside Railway Station" conf="2">Arnside Station</enamex>, the great bay begins to show itself as we rumble over the fine viaduct that crosses the <enamex sw="w18517" long="-2.806404741590844" lat="54.33404878379706" type="water" gazref="unlock:8772001" name="River Kent" conf="2.4">River Kent</enamex>, and the yellow sads of its estuaryspread out on each land.</s> <s id="s104">One of my fellow-travellers pointed to a lonely stork standing quietly in the midst of the sandy waste, like some weird genius of the solitude.</s> <s id="s105">On the other side, near the embankment, the" Old John," the oldest trading vessel of <enamex sw="w18816" long="-2.971573845828191" lat="54.11726758179064" type="water" gazref="unlock:11222778" name="Morecambe Bay" conf="2.4">Morecambe Bay</enamex>, was ashore.</s> <s id="s106">The low slopes near the line are richly wooded with light-hued larch, and spruce, and fir, mingling beautifully with dark green yew trees.</s> <s id="s107">The line now clips the rocky shore for about a mile, and we are rolling over the little River <enamex sw="w19075" long="-2.896315912832438" lat="54.33423674322094" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36927" name="Winster" conf="2.6">Winster</enamex>, one of the boundary lines of <enamex  sw="w19113" name="Large admin unit">Lancashireand</enamex> West <enamex  sw="w19132" name="Large admin unit">Moreland</enamex>; but, like the rest of these waters in <enamex sw="w19180" long="-2.971573845828191" lat="54.11726758179064" type="water" gazref="unlock:11222778" name="Morecambe Bay" conf="2.4">Morecambe Bay</enamex>, so changeful in its course over the sands, that you pretty island, a little way from the shore, which looks" as quietas a spot of sky among the evening clouds," has been known to be first in <enamex  sw="w19386" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>, then in <enamex  sw="w19406" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>, and back again in <enamex  sw="w19438" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>, all in a month's time, through the caprice of this little <enamex sw="w19508" long="-2.896315912832438" lat="54.33423674322094" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36927" name="Winster" conf="2.6">Winster</enamex>, which, when the fit is on it, thus plays at hide-and-seek with the two counties.</s> <s id="s108">The scenery richensas we roll along.</s> <s id="s109">The grand bay on one side, on the other picturesque rocks and snatches of woodland, sloping to the shore, with the wild feels behind, all going by in a panoramic flight. It was about low water: the sun was settling, and all that great marine wilderness, beyond which the retired sea was out of sight, - if a long line of golden light, far off, had not told itswhereabouts-that sandy expanse was so still that, but for here and there a stranded boat, and a smack let aslaut on the shore in the distance, it might have been a sea-beach belonging to someworld un-known to man.</s> <s id="s110">This threshold of the mighty sea, where its children come to play, and on which so many suns have looked the grand farewell of day, was once more lighted with a glorywhich made the pomp of man seem poor.</s></p>
<p><s id="s111">This valley, on the right hand, through which the <enamex sw="w20461" long="-2.896315912832438" lat="54.33423674322094" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36927" name="Winster" conf="2.6">Winster</enamex> flows, is a beautiful scene.</s> <s id="s112">The level plain, enclosed by an irregular semicircle of hills, is all land reclaimed from the sea atdifferent times.</s> <s id="s113">More than four hundred acres have been added to this reclamation by the new railway line.</s> <s id="s114">A remarkable conical hill, thickly clothed with wood, rises from the plain, in an isolated way.</s> <s id="s115">This singular height is called" <enamex sw="w20834" long="-2.925256525348697" lat="54.78277548656492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11171827" name="High Head Castle" conf="2.169573108">Castle Head</enamex>," anciently," <enamex sw="w20860" long="-3.132864841" lat="54.59417441" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00072" name="Castle Head" conf="99992">Atterpile</enamex> Castle."</s> <s id="s116">There is a quiet mansion in a secluded part of the grounds, and" if ever there was a house with a story, that looks like one."</s> <s id="s117">The sea formerly washed round the hill, and, as the old mariner at Grange told me," it must have been a capital place for smuggling in those days."</s> <s id="s118">" <enamex sw="w21154" long="-2.925256525348697" lat="54.78277548656492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11171827" name="High Head Castle" conf="2.169573108">Castle Head</enamex>" is supposedto have been a Roman settlement, or outpost of some kind, from the discovery of coins, ornaments, and other articles of Roman workmanship.</s> <s id="s119">About sixty years ago may curious articles were foundthere, among which were parts of human skull, vertebre,&amp; c., teeth of buffaloes, tusks of boar, pieces of limestone, resembling ben's eggs; rings of blue rag-stone, lead, clay, and glass; ninety - fivesticas of Northumbrian kings, seventy - five Roman coins, a stone, supposed to have been a mould for casting silver rings; iron ore, petrified bone, pebbles, impressions of clay, pottery, or bone, and other ancient relics.</s> <s id="s120">This looks as if" <enamex sw="w21807" long="-2.925256525348697" lat="54.78277548656492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11171827" name="High Head Castle" conf="2.169573108">Castle Head</enamex>" was a place of many strange stories, which have drifted into the misty past to return no more.</s> <s id="s121">The tenantless hall of" <enamex sw="w21939" long="-3.132864841" lat="54.59417441" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00072" name="Castle Head" conf="99992">Castel Head</enamex>" standsamongst woods and gardens at the rearward base of this lonely-looking height.</s> <s id="s122">The sole inahabitants of the place, at present, consist of a Scotch gardener and his family.</s> <s id="s123">When I visited the spot, with my two scientific friends, we wandered sometime before we met with" <enamex sw="w22226" long="-0.2977978055229835" lat="52.13109864643094" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11277914" name="Sandy" conf="1.406703853">Sandy</enamex>," till, at last, by dint of shouting-which seemed to hush into wistful stillness the lonely woods around-we roused himfrom the hothouses.</s> <s id="s124">He led us through the echoing rooms of the empty mansion, up to the roof, from which we had a good view of the gardens and grounds.</s> <s id="s125">After this we ascended, by circuitous paths, androcky bemossed steps, terrace after terrace, to the shady plateau upon the summit of this singular hill, which certainly is suggestive of a deserted encampment.</s> <s id="s126">I could imagine any of the races which have had mastery in <enamex  sw="w22770" name="Large admin unit">Britain</enamex> occupying that commanding eminence. The view over the bay, from embowered seats and recesses on the southern edge, are very beautiful.</s> <s id="s127">Obliging," <enamex sw="w22923" long="-0.2977978055229835" lat="52.13109864643094" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11277914" name="Sandy" conf="1.406703853">Sandy</enamex>" was full of simple earnestness about ferns and flowers.</s> <s id="s128">He seemed to have littleenthusiasm about anything but horticulture, except autographs, of which he showed us a curious store, collected during many years.</s> <s id="s129">He was quite at home in this picturesque solitude, although the placeis said to be haunted, and" Thir folk i' the village o' <enamex sw="w23266" long="-3.147763507072249" lat="54.17284167617383" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:23530" name="Lindal In Furness" conf="2.6">Lindal</enamex>, wha wadna walk ower' t after dark for the hail estate."</s> <s id="s130">In the lower escarpment of rock, on the southern side, our old geological friend pointedout a place where the union of the two stratifications of slate and limestone shows distinctly.</s> <s id="s131">This is the only place in the district where this union is so clearly visible.</s></p>
<p><s id="s132">Nearly opposite the green recess in which" <enamex sw="w23635" long="-2.925256525348697" lat="54.78277548656492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11171827" name="High Head Castle" conf="2.169573108">Castle Head</enamex>" is such a singular feature of the scene," <enamex sw="w23690" long="-2.881501513445659" lat="54.19886022591795" type="other" gazref="unlock:11177622" name="Holme Island" conf="2">Holme Island</enamex>" stands in the bay, about two hundred yards from the railway line, and, as Spenser says, it</s></p>
<p><s id="s133">" Seems so sweet and pleasant to the eye," That it would tempt a man to touchen there."</s></p>
<p><s id="s134">Less than half a century since, this island was little more than a bare rock-a lone domain of wind and wave, and birds that love the sea.</s> <s id="s135">Within that time, however, it has, at immense expense, beenconverted into a perfect marine paradise.</s> <s id="s136">Though not much more than then acres in extent, the gardens and grounds are so tastefully varied that a man may ramble an hour or two about it and still find himselfin a new scene-still meet with" some-thing rich and strange" - and, in some parts, the little landscape is so artfully natural in appearance that he might forget it was the result of man's taste and enterprise.</s> <s id="s137">Onthe western side of the island, a white limestone building, perfectly modelled after the temple of Vesta, looks out westward over the bay; an, in sheltered nooks, rock-hewn stairs lead down to sand-banks sosmooth, so gently-swelling and secluded, that fair Sabrina might sit there</s></p>
<p><s id="s138">" Under the cool translucent wave Her brigth hair knitting."</s></p>
<p><s id="s139">free from fear of intrusion.</s> <s id="s140">The grounds and gardens are rich in plants and flowers of the rarest description, from all parts of the world.</s> <s id="s141">The house is shadily situated, about the middle of the island, amongfine trees and tasteful grounds.</s></p>
<p><s id="s142">From the highest points and opensings in the shades of" <enamex sw="w25135" long="-2.881501513445659" lat="54.19886022591795" type="other" gazref="unlock:11177622" name="Holme Island" conf="2">Holme Island</enamex>" - that sylvan gem of the waters-the views are wildly beautiful or solemnly grand, whichever way we turn.</s> <s id="s143">Far ont, off the extreme north-westernshore of the bay, the massive ruins of <enamex sw="w25329" long="-4.692535773887674" lat="54.22593372544603" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11241717" name="Peel Castle" conf="0.8191860256">Peel Castle</enamex> That ancient stronghold of the abbots of <enamex sw="w25382" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> Stand mouldering in wild isolation among the waves.</s> <s id="s144">They have done with the maraunding Scot, the pomp of prelates, and the din of war; and now, all silent and unsentinelled, they glide majestically into the wastes of time.</s> <s id="s145">Left to the washing waves and whistling winds-acrumbling shelter of the seabird -</s></p>
<p><s id="s146">" The empty ruins lapsed again Into nature's wide domain, Sow themselves with seed and grain, As day and night and day go by."</s></p>
<p><s id="s147">Leaving this ruined fortress, the eye travels along the low fertile shores on which <enamex sw="w25904" long="-3.0986" lat="54.1301" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2657532" name="Aldingham" conf="99992">Aldingham Castle</enamex> and village, now washed away, once stood near the sea.</s> <s id="s148">The bold peaks of Higher <enamex sw="w26001" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> in the rearward of thescene.</s> <s id="s149">The village of <enamex sw="w26053" long="-3.07058438082128" lat="54.16288715481818" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:44173" name="Bardsea" conf="2.6">Bardsea</enamex>, <enamex sw="w26062" long="-3.064741936428078" lat="54.17041334190125" type="other" gazref="unlock:11115195" name="Conishead Priory" conf="2">Conishead Priory</enamex>, the town of <enamex sw="w26092" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, and the beautiful estuary of the <enamex sw="w26137" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex>, are all hidden from" <enamex sw="w26165" long="-2.881501513445659" lat="54.19886022591795" type="other" gazref="unlock:11177622" name="Holme Island" conf="2">Holme Island</enamex>" by the promontory of <enamex sw="w26200" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>; but on the north, it commands a fine viewof the most picturesque part of the <enamex sw="w26286" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> shore, with the tops of its woody fells standing against the sky, like the wild outlines of a petrified tempest.</s> <s id="s150">Looking east, the fells between <enamex sw="w26439" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> and <enamex sw="w26453" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex>, and, beyondthese, <enamex sw="w26479" long="-2.39060829456302" lat="54.16549773629642" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11182520" name="Ingleborough (Fort)" conf="2.07328217">Ingleborough</enamex>, and other <enamex  sw="w26503" name="Large admin unit">Yorkshire hills</enamex>, may be seen.</s> <s id="s151">Southward, and immediately opposite the island, is" <enamex sw="w26585" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex> <enamex  sw="w26593" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Knot</enamex>," with its fir-grove crown.</s> <s id="s152">Farther south, <enamex sw="w26641" long="-2.7734" lat="54.1547" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11313878" name="Warton Crag" conf="99992">Warton Crags</enamex> rise up, and villas and white meansionsgleam among the thickly-wooded lower slopes, till <enamex sw="w26743" name="Silverdale Point">Silverdale Point</enamex> seems to shoot into the bay, like a great dark needle.</s> <s id="s153">Beyond this, the green ridges of <enamex sw="w26848" long="-2.430426782171715" lat="53.57208890145878" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11082597" name="Bolton" conf="2.174714103">Bolton</enamex> Le-Sands, <enamex sw="w26865" long="-2.772858747652117" lat="54.12769635103146" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11099650" name="Carnforth" conf="2.6">Carnforth</enamex>, <enamex sw="w26876" long="-2.800813564608896" lat="54.09802913000562" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:20867" name="Hest Bank" conf="2.6">Hest Bank</enamex>, <enamex sw="w26887" long="-2.893344096261091" lat="54.03697321331941" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11172942" name="Higher Heysham" conf="2.6">Heysham</enamex>, Poulton Le-Sands, andthe" <enamex sw="w26922" long="-1.42449826002121" lat="54.90359306335449" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14124820" name="Sunderland" conf="2.186332116">Sunderland</enamex> Shoulder," hide the estuary of the <enamex sw="w26968" long="-2.672622913542797" lat="54.21368667875034" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788892" name="River Lune" conf="2.4">Lune</enamex>," that to old <enamex sw="w26987" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> his name doth lend," of which River Michael Drayton says so cheerily: -</s></p>
<p><s id="s154">" For salmon me excels; and for this name of <enamex sw="w27112" long="-2.83333" lat="54.05" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2643381" name="River Lune" conf="99991">Lun</enamex>, That I am christened by, the Britons it begun, Which fulness doth import of waters still increase To <enamex  sw="w27218" name="Not a placename">Neptune</enamex> lowting low, when christal <enamex sw="w27253" long="-2.672622913542797" lat="54.21368667875034" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788892" name="River Lune" conf="2.4">Lune</enamex> doth cease; And Conder coming in conducts her by the hand, Till lastly she salutes the Point of <enamex sw="w27354" long="-1.42449826002121" lat="54.90359306335449" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14124820" name="Sunderland" conf="2.186332116">Sunderland</enamex>, And leaves our dainty <enamex sw="w27388" long="-2.672622913542797" lat="54.21368667875034" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788892" name="River Lune" conf="2.4">Lune</enamex> to amphitrite's care.</s> <s id="s155">So blyth and bonny now the lads and lasses are, That ever and anon the bagpipe up doth blow; Cast in a gallant round about the hearth they go, And every village smokes at wakes with lusty cheer, Then hey, they cry, for <enamex sw="w27634" long="-2.83333" lat="54.05" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2643381" name="River Lune" conf="99991">Lun</enamex>, and hey for <enamex  sw="w27651" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>.</s> <s id="s156">That one high hill was heard to tell it to his brother."</s></p>
<p><s id="s157">All this, however, gives but a very imperfect idea of the great extent and variety of view from" <enamex sw="w27817" long="-2.881501513445659" lat="54.19886022591795" type="other" gazref="unlock:11177622" name="Holme Island" conf="2">Holme Island</enamex>."</s> <s id="s158">The shoreward scenes opposite are very beautiful.</s></p>
<p><s id="s159">It is the shout of the coming foe, Ride, ride for thy life, Sir John; But still the waters deeper grew, The wild sea foam rushed on.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s160">Old Ballad</s></p>
<p><s id="s161">A Little beyond" <enamex sw="w28044" long="-2.881501513445659" lat="54.19886022591795" type="other" gazref="unlock:11177622" name="Holme Island" conf="2">Holme Island</enamex>," and about half - way between <enamex sw="w28086" long="-2.772858747652117" lat="54.12769635103146" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11099650" name="Carnforth" conf="2.6">Carnforth</enamex> and <enamex sw="w28100" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, the train stops at the the pretty seaside village of Grange.</s> <s id="s162">It looks veryinviting from the railway, but not till one is is it can they fairly see how pretty it is, and how fine the views are from its higher parts.</s> <s id="s163">From the rail it looks acluster of gardens and white limestone houses scattered about the undulent lower slopes of" <enamex sw="w28443" long="-3.272975138161649" lat="54.46502747709917" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11328681" name="Yewbarrow" conf="2.4">Yewbarrow</enamex>," a craggy wooded height which fills the immediate background.</s> <s id="s164">Itmatters very little where you build a house in Grange, it is sure to have a pleasant outlook, and is never in the way of its neighbour; for the land over which the dwellings are so picturesquely dribbled about is all fertile dingles, and knolls, and nest-like nooks, mixed with bloomy orchards, flower gardens, and scattered tufts ofwood; and there are several mansions thereabout, whose green shades and ornamental grounds give a park-like tone to the skirts of the village.</s> <s id="s165">The church, with its tiny" heaven pointing" spire, stands on a green eminence at the head of the village.</s> <s id="s166">Near the church, as usual, there is a comfortable old inn.</s> <s id="s167">The open space in front of" The Crown," commands a good view of the eastern part of the bay, with the <enamex  sw="w29259" name="Large admin unit">Yorkshire hills</enamex> behind, and all the picturesque fells and wooded shores on the <enamex sw="w29338" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> side. Grange, though not unknown to fame among lovers of nature and wanderers to the sea, has, like the rest of <enamex sw="w29459" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>, been peculiarly secluded by its position.</s> <s id="s168">The Lancasterand <enamex sw="w29527" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> line now runs by the foot of the village, bringing it into direct communication with the main lines from the south.</s> <s id="s169">Before the railway was made, the tidewashed the garden walls of the village.</s></p>
<p><s id="s170">As I walked about the open elevated ground in front of the" Crown," looking at the bay and the hills, I asked several questions of two or three villagers who werelounging about.</s> <s id="s171">They eyed me from head to foot, wondering where I came from, and what I had to do with their hills and dales; at last, settling in their own minds that Imust be a strange land-surveyor, preparing for fresh changes in that part of the country, a stalwart young man, who stood down in the village-street with a bundle ofpapers in his hand, he said." That's the man for ye.</s> <s id="s172">He's read a deeal o' books.</s> <s id="s173">He knaas summat abaat ivvery thing, nearly; an' he knaas mair abaat Grange, I sud think, than onybody at's in it."</s> <s id="s174">I found him an enthusiastic entomologist and ornithologist, and a very unassuming, intelligent man, of mainly manners.</s> <s id="s175">We sat down in the" Crown" chatting, and listening whilst" Aad Billy," a blind fiddler, who lives by scattering mustic among the kind-hearted folk of <enamex sw="w30689" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> Fells, played" Scots wha hae we' Wallacebled," and" Bannocks o' bear meal, bannocks o' barley."</s> <s id="s176">The old man beat time with his foot, and accompanied his instrument with a curious croon, which made up in quaintnessfor what it lacked in harmony.</s> <s id="s177">I could not help thinking, as he sat there, that a country village without a blind fiddler is wanting in a valuable feature of human interest.</s> <s id="s178">Leaving" Aad Billy" at the end of" <enamex sw="w31119" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.4">Over</enamex> Bogie," my friend proposed that we should go to the top of" <enamex sw="w31184" long="-3.272975138161649" lat="54.46502747709917" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11328681" name="Yewbarrow" conf="2.4">Yewbarrow</enamex>," the hill at the rear of the village, from the summit of which he said the views were magnificent.</s> <s id="s179">As we went out at the head of the village by a shady road, he opened the gate of a small enclosed knoll, on the right hand, saying," Stop, my workshop is in here.</s> <s id="s180">We'll peep at it, if you like, before we go up."</s> <s id="s181">In the centre of this enclosure there was a rude, round hut, built of limestone, something like a large summer-house.</s> <s id="s182">On entering, I found myself in a little museum, filled with strange birds, and carefully arranged glass cases of rear shells andinsects.</s> <s id="s183">Against the wall hung a broken skeleton head and horns of the Irish elk, which had been found in the neighbouring sands, a few years ago.</s> <s id="s184">In one corner was reareda large slab of red standstone, from Storton, in <enamex  sw="w31970" name="Large admin unit">Cheshire</enamex>, on which were plainly imprinted the footsteps of some antediluvian creature; he thought it was the plesiasaurus.</s> <s id="s185">The place was full of curiosities; and I noticed a live wood owl, in a cage outside, with its large, lustrous eyes, blinking in the sunshine.</s> <s id="s186">Leaving this little sanctum ofscience, we went through the shady grounds of" <enamex sw="w32312" long="-3.075861455" lat="54.36901996" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00095" name="Yewdale Lodge" conf="99992">Yewbarrow Lodge</enamex>," and thence, by rocky, sinuous paths to the summit of" <enamex sw="w32384" long="-3.272975138161649" lat="54.46502747709917" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11328681" name="Yewbarrow" conf="2.4">Yewbarrow</enamex>."</s> <s id="s187">This hill takes its name from the yewtree, for the growth of which it is remarkable, and from" barrow," a cairn or burial place.</s> <s id="s188">Here I was glad to sit down and look round, for I was out of wind, and the view hadgrown grander as we rose.</s> <s id="s189"><enamex sw="w32634" long="-2.878643961524713" lat="54.06404841396252" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11222777" name="Morecambe" conf="3.142603975">Morecambe</enamex> and a great extent of its shores were full in sight, the slopes and lowlands all beauty and fertility, all above and in the distance wild and majestic.</s> <s id="s190">My friend told me that, on a favourable day, the town of <enamex sw="w32853" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> was almost as distinctly in sight as the houses at the foot of the hill; but he surprisedme more by saying that the great, ivy clad, lime-stone rocks upon the summit of" <enamex sw="w33033" long="-3.272975138161649" lat="54.46502747709917" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11328681" name="Yewbarrow" conf="2.4">Yewbarrow</enamex>," were unmistakably waterworn, that is, worn by the action of the sea.</s> <s id="s191">The villagelay under the eye, as clearly as a map or model on a table.</s> <s id="s192">We could see all its houses, perching or nestling in picturesque confusion, among straggling gardens and bloomynooks.</s> <s id="s193">We could see all its mansions, with their rich grounds, and woods now spreading out the bright green of spring in the sunshine; its white roads and bye lanes, windingthrough orchards, and under over-lapping trees, about the green knolls and dingles, and lacing the land with lines of ever-varying loveliness.</s> <s id="s194">Grange is no less pleasantin its own quiet beauty, and in the scenery about it, than in the salubrity of its climate, which is said to rival that of the southern coast of <enamex  sw="w33783" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s> <s id="s195">It spring, itsaverage tempeature is higher than that of any other place in the north of <enamex  sw="w33880" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s> <s id="s196">In summer, the heat is tempered by the saline breeze.</s> <s id="s197">Beautifully seated on this lower slopeof" <enamex sw="w33985" long="-3.272975138161649" lat="54.46502747709917" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11328681" name="Yewbarrow" conf="2.4">Yewbarrow</enamex>," it is sheltered on the north and west by the green hills, and its natural charms are heightened by the never-palling witcheries of the changeful sea.</s> <s id="s198">Artists, and other curious children of nature, who love to go about in the world" spying fancies," as coutnry folk quaintly call it, would find its neighborhood full of interest.</s></p>
<p><s id="s199">It was a beautiful sight; and, as I descended the hill, by another route, to meet the train, I resolved that, if possible, it should not be lond before I looked uponthat peaceful nest again.</s></p>
<p><s id="s200">The grandest height near Grange is" Hampsfell," at the read of" <enamex sw="w34580" long="-2.99073383468145" lat="54.27891049248326" type="other" gazref="unlock:11328622" name="Yew Barrow" conf="2">Yew Barrow</enamex>."</s> <s id="s201">Whosoever desires to see that country well, ought to ascend" Hampsfell," at sunrise of sunset, on a fine day, and he may look upon a scene of such magnificence as is rarely met with in any land.</s> <s id="s202">For those who are not strong, a carriage road leads up the southside of Eggerslack wood, nearly to the summit of the fell; but the sturdy pedestrian should go out at the lower end of Grange, and up the narrow, romantic glen, called" <enamex sw="w35021" name="Lindal Lane">Lindal Lane</enamex>," till he comes to a farmhouse called" <enamex sw="w35072" long="-2.597286415065166" lat="53.70771401035448" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771590" name="Slack Brook" conf="1.357175855">Slack</enamex>," on the left hand side of the road.</s> <s id="s203">This shady gorge is a little fairy-land of woodland beauty in summer time. After crossing the yard of <enamex sw="w35216" name="Slack farm">Slack farm</enamex>, a rough footpath leads up through plantations of larch and spruce; and coppice woods of oak and hazel, sprinkled, now and then, with theglittering birch-that silver-robed lady of the woods-the beech, the ash" for nothing ill," the alder and the dark green yew," obedient to the bender's will."</s> <s id="s204">These woods, which are carefully cultivated for" bobbin wood," hoops, wicker-work, and other purposes, are great sources of employment to the people around.</s> <s id="s205">As the traveller winds throughthe sylvan scene, by changeful pleasure upward led, he meets with glimpses of the sea, gleaming through the southward trees; and there is many a nook of the mountain path where he may sit in cool shadow, listening to the wild birds which fill all the woods with their tune-ful rejoicings.</s> <s id="s206">Emerging from this leafy screen, he finds rocky, unshaded moorlands, stretching upward still, in silent desolation.</s> <s id="s207">Great picturesque masses of limestone crop out from the heatherywaste, their ragged crevices beautiful with plumy ferns.</s> <s id="s208">There is still a rude pathway to the summit, but, for a good walker," The <enamex sw="w36308" name="Crow Gate">Crow Gate</enamex>" across the moor will bemore interesting.</s> <s id="s209">At last, the top of a square, squat limestone tower appears on the distant height.</s> <s id="s210">This is" Hampsfell Hospice," a modern erection, built by a former pastor of the <enamex sw="w36523" long="-2.894482243304862" lat="54.28519073410449" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:22647" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel parish</enamex>, for the shelter and entertainment of wan-derers over the fell.</s> <s id="s211">As he draws nearer this little benevolent coronet of lonely" Hampsfell," mountain and vale, and land and sea, expand so glo-riously, that he cannot but halt now and then to gaze around with wonder and delight.</s> <s id="s212">Inside the tower there are stoneseats, and a good fire-place, for which the heather around affords ready and abundant kindling.</s> <s id="s213">Upon the walls are wooden tablets, inscribed with verses allusive to the scenery and the purpose of the building.</s> <s id="s214">From these I copied the following: -</s></p>
<p><s id="s215">" This hospice has an open door, Welcome alike to rich and poor; A roomy seat for young and old.</s> <s id="s216">Where they may screen them from the cold; Three windows that command a view, To north, to west, and southward too; A flight of steps requiring care; A roof that shews a prospect rare; Mountain and vale you thence survey, - The winding strearas and noble hay.</s> <s id="s217">The sun at noon the shadow hides Along the east and westward sides.</s> <s id="s218">A lengthened chain holds guard around, To keep the cattle from the ground.</s> <s id="s219">Kind reader, freely take your pleasure.</s> <s id="s220">But do not mischief to my treasure!"</s></p>
<p><s id="s221">From the roof of this" Hospice" the views are indeed glorious, both in variety of character and extent of range.</s> <s id="s222">Fertile, peace-breathing valleys; old castle, and churches, and quaint hamlets and towns, - eloquent relics of past history; lonely glens, rich parks, and forest steeps; picturesque homse-steads, in pleasant nooks of shelter; beautiful estuaries; the fresh blue bay bleak brown moorlands; wild craggy fells; and storm-worn mountains, each different in height and form, - the grand old guardians of themagnifi-cent scene.</s> <s id="s223">Beginning with <enamex sw="w38208" long="-4.692535773887674" lat="54.22593372544603" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11241717" name="Peel Castle" conf="0.8191860256">Peel Castle</enamex>, in the sea-washed west, the eye wanders over solemn Black Coombe, and Druid Swinstead, Fletcher Fell, Stoneshead, and allthe <enamex sw="w38346" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> range, in which the bold round peak of the" <enamex sw="w38399" long="-3.12208" lat="54.37042" type="other" gazref="unlock:4565407" name="Old Man of Coniston" conf="2">Old Man</enamex>" is the most familiar mark.</s> <s id="s224">Then come <enamex sw="w38445" long="-3.118464887566315" lat="54.45756762847756" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11191353" name="Langdale Pikes" conf="2.4">Langdale Pikes</enamex>, <enamex sw="w38461" long="-3.21333" lat="54.45583" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00026" name="Scafell" conf="99991">Scaw Fell</enamex>, <enamex sw="w38472" long="-3.195844359582791" lat="54.46581531356443" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11158711" name="Great End" conf="2.4">Great End</enamex>, <enamex sw="w38483" long="-3.164480720837862" lat="54.44814432815852" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11084014" name="Bow Fell" conf="2.4">Bow Fell</enamex>, part of <enamex sw="w38501" long="-3.139386682889271" lat="54.65511833106305" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11284754" name="Skiddaw" conf="2.388804828">Skiddaw</enamex>, shewing itself beyond the gap of Dunmail; then" the dark brow of the mighty <enamex sw="w38585" long="-3.043402327204126" lat="54.53913510713601" type="water" gazref="unlock:11169754" name="Helvellyn Gill" conf="2.370620619">Helvellyn</enamex>," monarch of all that wonderful land of beautiful waters, rises up majestically above thegreen vally of <enamex sw="w38699" long="-1.361732484769859" lat="51.99535612997623" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:22330" name="Barford St John" conf="1.46469423">St. John</enamex>.</s> <s id="s225">Looking eastward, we see the pleasant vale of the <enamex  sw="w38759" name="Large admin unit">Kent</enamex>, with its fine estuary; the woodland shores of Miluthorpe; the grand crags of Whitbarrowand <enamex sw="w38856" long="-2.71334707329606" lat="54.22693903105996" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11142147" name="Farleton" conf="2.6">Farleton</enamex>, with kindred limestone ridges stretching out beyond.</s> <s id="s226">Farther eastward the hills of Yorkshire rise in the blue sky.</s> <s id="s227">In the south, over <enamex sw="w39000" long="-2.835515685876524" lat="54.19918791340264" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11063895" name="Arnside" conf="2.6">Arnside</enamex>, <enamex sw="w39009" long="-2.820874446921715" lat="54.16814672786025" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:18374" name="Silverdale" conf="2.6">Silverdale</enamex>, andWarton, we have the fells and green lowlangs of the <enamex sw="w39076" long="-2.83333" lat="54.06667" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00068" name="Lancaster" conf="99992">Lancaster side</enamex>; ridge after ridge the <enamex sw="w39114" long="-2.672622913542797" lat="54.21368667875034" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788892" name="River Lune" conf="2.4">Lune</enamex> and the <enamex sw="w39127" long="-2.816670591684018" lat="53.86550796357606" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36276" name="St Michael'S On Wyre" conf="1.6">Wyre</enamex>, till the masts and lighthouse of <enamex sw="w39166" long="-2.766793558648539" lat="54.00443279751632" type="civil" gazref="unlock:22554060" name="Lancaster and Fleetwood Co Const" conf="2.886520109">Fleetwood</enamex> shew themselves far out to Seaward.</s> <s id="s228">If the day be fine, the mountains of <enamex  sw="w39249" name="Large admin unit">Wales</enamex>, <enamex sw="w39256" long="-1.500309168183582" lat="54.64543028105785" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13372576" name="Bradbury and the Isle CP" conf="1.295887309">the Isle</enamex> of Man, and even the coast of <enamex  sw="w39295" name="Large admin unit">Ireland</enamex> may sometimes be seen.</s> <s id="s229">It is a glorious combination of landand sea; but, perhaps, the most charming bit of all the landscape is in the valley of <enamex sw="w39448" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>, just at the western foot of Hamsfell.</s> <s id="s230">The little town, nestling round its venerable church, looks so near that one might almost, expect to hear some sounds of life arise therefrom; but it is as still down there in the middle of the sunlit valeas if it was only the quaint centre-pice in the pattern of a green carpet.</s></p>
<p><s id="s231">I feel that what is here written gives but an imperfect idea of the wonderful prospects commanded by <enamex sw="w39876" long="-2.927687714972389" lat="54.20750221833886" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11165069" name="Hampsfell" conf="2.4">Hampsfell</enamex>; and I can only add that no traveller, who has opportunity, and cares for the glories of nature, ought to go b that mountain unclimbed.</s> <s id="s232">I have noticed, after ascending some of the highest points of that district, that although the same objects may chance to be seen from several heights, yet the points of view are so different that in each case we get a new picture.</s></p>
<p><s id="s233">In the neighbourhood of Grange there are several mansions and houses of considerable interest, such as" <enamex sw="w40357" long="-2.926883111983222" lat="54.17155321711211" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11055221" name="Abbot Hall" conf="2.2">Abbot Hall</enamex>,"" <enamex sw="w40371" long="-2.927889140988545" lat="54.2164894337604" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11165071" name="Hampsfield Hall" conf="2.2">Hampsfield Hall</enamex>,"" <enamex sw="w40390" long="-2.867679985285398" lat="54.27087005140925" type="other" gazref="unlock:11324605" name="Witherslack Hall (Sch)" conf="2">Witherslack Hall</enamex>" - a fine old house, formerly belonging to the Earls of <enamex sw="w40460" long="-1.481055713285496" lat="52.91280453819406" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:9750" name="Derby" conf="2.044970005">Derby</enamex>;" <enamex sw="w40468" long="-2.958974995175348" lat="54.23422359985522" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11098391" name="Cark Hall Allotment" conf="2.2">Cark Hall</enamex>,"" <enamex sw="w40481" long="-2.989872299218943" lat="54.24296258057584" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11076850" name="Bigland Hall" conf="2.2">Bigland Hall</enamex>,"" Merlewood," and" <enamex sw="w40514" long="-2.98858352875109" lat="54.18904029214188" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11176860" name="Holker Hall" conf="2.2">Holker Hall</enamex>," the favourite seat of the Duke of Devonshire, with its noble parksloping down to pictureseque cliffs of mountain limestone and old red sandstone.</s> <s id="s234"><enamex sw="w40674" long="-2.98858352875109" lat="54.18904029214188" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11176861" name="Holker Park" conf="2.2">Holker park</enamex> contains many remarkable trees, of much greater size than is common so nearthe sea.</s></p>
<p><s id="s235">The distance from Grange to <enamex sw="w40798" long="-2.959809373549684" lat="54.2701718942731" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11229861" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, at the foot of <enamex sw="w40827" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>, in six miles.</s> <s id="s236">The road thither winds out at the lower end of Grange, between the woody heightsof Aggerslack and <enamex sw="w40951" long="-3.098473619501757" lat="54.28696599116789" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11080897" name="Blawith" conf="2.6">Blawith</enamex>, and up the beautiful glen called" <enamex sw="w40994" name="Lindal Lane">Lindal Lane</enamex>."</s> <s id="s237">An omnibus runs twice a day in summer between these points, through the villages of <enamex sw="w41092" long="-3.147763507072249" lat="54.17284167617383" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:23530" name="Lindal In Furness" conf="2.6">Lindal</enamex> andNewton.</s> <s id="s238">The village of <enamex sw="w41125" long="-3.147763507072249" lat="54.17284167617383" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:23530" name="Lindal In Furness" conf="2.6">Lindal</enamex> about two miles from Grange, is worth going a long way to look at.</s> <s id="s239">It is not only picturesque in itself, but is picturesquely situated amongscenes of singular beauty, and commands an enchanting peep of the bay, with a view of the rich vale in which" <enamex sw="w41382" long="-2.925256525348697" lat="54.78277548656492" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11171827" name="High Head Castle" conf="2.169573108">Castle Head</enamex>" is such a singular feature.</s> <s id="s240">The whole six milesrde to <enamex sw="w41449" long="-2.959809373549684" lat="54.2701718942731" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11229861" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex> through <enamex sw="w41470" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> Fells is full of interest to anyone who can enjoy the contrast of peaceful fertility overlooked by craggy wildness, which he will passthrough on the way.</s></p>
<p><s id="s241">Quiaiut <enamex sw="w41640" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>, the market town of the sequested district which bears its name, is little more than two miles north of Grange-a pleasant walk over the hills on a fineday.</s> <s id="s242">Its noble old priory is the only conventual church in <enamex  sw="w41858" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex> which escaped mutilation after the dissolution of the monasteries.</s> <s id="s243">This escape arose from its beingpartly the parish church, as as well as the church of the priory.</s> <s id="s244">About theree miles from this town, and about the same from Grange, it the famous" <enamex sw="w42116" long="-2.941792945442159" lat="54.15345984931304" type="water" gazref="unlock:11178031" name="Holy Well" conf="2.4">Holy Well</enamex> of <enamex sw="w42129" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>" - a fine medicianl spring, which is a great attraction in the summer months.</s> <s id="s245">Its waters are celebrated for the cure of gout, stone, and cutaneous diseases.</s> <s id="s246">For many years past the miners employed in the <enamex sw="w42339" long="-2.428735222392866" lat="54.77578890164898" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13299118" name="Alston Moor Ward" conf="2.24623424">Alston Moor</enamex> Lead Mines, being liable to certain diseases arising from the nature of their labours, have made annual pilgrimage to the villageof Kent's Bank, near here, in order to have the benefit of <enamex sw="w42539" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>'" <enamex sw="w42549" long="-2.941792945442159" lat="54.15345984931304" type="water" gazref="unlock:11178031" name="Holy Well" conf="2.4">Holy Well</enamex>."</s> <s id="s247"><enamex sw="w42561" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> is a settlement of great antiquity.</s> <s id="s248">Camden says of the district, that" in 667, Egfrid, Kind of <enamex sw="w42663" long="-2.5" lat="55" type="other" gazref="unlock:4565632" name="Northumbria" conf="0.803857868">Northumbria</enamex>, gave <enamex sw="w42681" long="-3.392880350420522" lat="54.81426162231475" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11177650" name="Holme St Cuthbert" conf="2.488132394">St. Cuthbert</enamex> the land, and all the Britons in it."</s> <s id="s249">" In 1188," according to Baines," the foundation of a priory for canons regular of St. Augustine was laid by William Mareschal, the elder, Earl of Pembroke."</s> <s id="s250">His charter concludes with these words: -" This house I have founded for the increase of our holyreligion, giving and granting to it every kind of liberty that heart can conceive, or the mouth utter; and whoever shall in any way infringe upon these immunities, or injure the said priory, may he incur the curse of God, of the blessed Virgin Mary, and all other saints, as well as my particular malediction."</s> <s id="s251">This priory was enrichedby many grants and donations of pontiffs and princes, and many" offerings of the faithful."</s> <s id="s252">The town is situated in a vale watered by two streams stands the fine oldconventual church, with its curious belfry rising from the central tower, a square inscribed within a square diagonal to its base.</s> <s id="s253">Of course, there is a tradition connectedwith the foundation of <enamex sw="w43678" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> Priory.</s> <s id="s254">It seems that a nearly seven hundred years ago, a number of foreign monks, wandering about the country in search of a settlement, somehow found their way into this, then, dense forest wild.</s> <s id="s255">They were preparing to build their church upon a hill-top in the neighbourhood, when a voice spoke to them outof the air, saying:" Not there; but in a valley between two rivers, where the one runs north and the other south."</s> <s id="s256">It seems unfortunate that the voice should neglect tothem where that valley was, as they happened to be so near at the time.</s> <s id="s257">But it was so; for these homeless fathers wandered, after that, all over the north of <enamex  sw="w44319" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>, infruitless search, until they found the place, at last, near the very hill where they first heard" the voice in the air."</s> <s id="s258">Here, on an island of hard ground between thesesingular streams, they build the Priory of <enamex sw="w44541" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>, and dedicated it to St. Mary.</s> <s id="s259">They also built a small chapel on the hill, where they heard the voice, and they dedicatedit to St. Bernard.</s> <s id="s260">The chapel is now gone, but the hill is called" St. Bernard's Mount" to this day.</s></p>
<p><s id="s261">Going from a place like <enamex sw="w44795" long="-2.250909844579199" lat="53.51088669792344" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:9710" name="Manchester" conf="2.177003304">Manchester</enamex> into this little monastic town is almost like going to bed, or sinking into an antiquarian dream, all in so quaint and quiet.</s> <s id="s262">Themarket Place in a square of old-fashioned houses, with the fish stones near the middle.</s> <s id="s263">This old market-place looked so drowsy when I saw it that it seemed astonished ifanybody walked across it.</s> <s id="s264">On one side, an ancient gateway leads into a coistral old street, in which the principal inn is situated.</s> <s id="s265">This gateway is a relic of the original buildings connected with the priory.</s> <s id="s266">There are inns of more imposing appearance, but I met with kind attention and good cheer at the King's Arms, near the bridge, whereI spent a pleasant hour among some hungry wood-cutters, who had been at work all day in the fells.</s> <s id="s267">Following the advice of a former traveller in <enamex sw="w45589" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>, I had inquiredof a man with a red nose, who happened to be leaning on the bridge, where I could get a good glass of ale, and he directed me to this house.</s> <s id="s268">I found the place filled witha cheerful aroma; and, in a few minutes, I got so thick with hungry woodcutters, who were waiting for their evening meal, that I was invited to join them at an immensedish of savoury" lobscouse," prepared by the handsoom, good-tempered landlady.</s> <s id="s269">Judging by the alacrity with which the dish was emptied, I should say that every stomachthere was in good order; and I only hope these jolly woodman had not miscalculated my capacity when they invited me to the feast, - for, simple as the fare was, the feastwas fine.</s> <s id="s270">We finished off with oatcake, and butter and cheese, and a glorious dish of crisp water-cresses-the whole seasoned with a good deal of hearty fun, which is notthe worst part of the best meal a man can eat.</s> <s id="s271">From this house the landlord directed me to an old building, occupied as a saddler's shop, in the opposite corner of the square.</s> <s id="s272">Here i found the parish clerk, William <enamex sw="w46668" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex>, who kindly took me through the church and up to the top of the central tower.</s></p>
<p><s id="s273">The walls of the choir and transept of this old church belong to the first erection; the windows are of a later date.</s> <s id="s274">There is a noble east window, 48 feet high, containingsome fine stained glass.</s> <s id="s275">On the north side of the proper choir is a narrow chapel, anciently called the" Piper's Choir;" and on the south side what is called the" <enamex sw="w47092" long="-0.1322934205611927" lat="51.54404014997548" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11097202" name="Camden Town" conf="1.548911423">Town</enamex> Choir," which has two stone seats for the officiating priests.</s> <s id="s276">This is supposed to have been anciently the parish church.</s> <s id="s277">There are 26 ancient stalls in the choir, with theirgrotesquely-carved misesereres, all in perfect condition.</s> <s id="s278">There are many ancient monumental decorations in this church: bit the most remarkable is a magnificientmonument of the <enamex sw="w47448" long="-3.56163" lat="54.61363" type="other" gazref="unlock:4571823" name="Harrington" conf="1.908677464">Harrington</enamex> family, under an arched canopy.</s> <s id="s279">In the old library I was shown some rare and curious books, among which were the following: -" The Second Part of the <enamex  sw="w47607" name="Not a placename">Faerie Queene</enamex>, containing the Fourth, Fifth, and Sixth Bookes.</s> <s id="s280">By Ed.</s> <s id="s281">Spencer.</s> <s id="s282">Printed at <enamex sw="w47697" long="-0.08573711413610305" lat="51.48768230024373" type="civila" gazref="unlock:13326794" name="Greater London Authority" conf="2.692469216">London</enamex>, for William <enamex sw="w47717" long="-3.457115296600183" lat="54.43598051808319" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11247683" name="Ponsonby" conf="2.54769419">Ponsonby</enamex>, 15596." a folio copy of" Fox's Book of Martyrs," in black letter, 1610.</s> <s id="s283">A black-letter Bible, in six vols, printed at <enamex sw="w47844" long="7.57327" lat="47.5584" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00111" name="Basle" conf="99992">Basle</enamex>, in 1502.</s> <s id="s284">A quarto copy of the works of Thomas Aquinas, in black letter, printed at <enamex sw="w47934" long="12.3266667" lat="45.4386111" type="ppla" gazref="geonames:3164603" name="Venice" conf="1.694223564">Venice</enamex>, in 1506.</s> <s id="s285">A quaint little volume entitled" Apophthegemes New and Old, collected by the right Honourable Francis Lo.</s> <s id="s286"><enamex sw="w48057" long="-0.3560329726548828" lat="51.74602912097793" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13239419" name="Verulam Ward" conf="1.288041005">Verulam</enamex>, Viscount St. Alban, 1625."</s> <s id="s287">The Ancient Parish Register of <enamex sw="w48124" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> for the last 300 years.</s> <s id="s288">As we came out the clerk pointed to the Duke of Devonshire's pew; and I found, everywhere, that his grace, and the family altogether, have the right good-will of the people of <enamex sw="w48332" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>.</s> <s id="s289">After a parting stroll by twilight round the noble old church, and its calm, quaint, pastoral town, just as the stars began to struggle with declining day, I took the lonely road to Grange, through <enamex sw="w48539" long="-2.942405528931496" lat="54.18042158778795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11058525" name="Allithwaite" conf="2.6">Allithwaite</enamex>, a rude village, whose inhabitants, like those of <enamex sw="w48601" long="-2.943633715673867" lat="54.2343446874937" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11171401" name="High Cark" conf="2.6">Cark</enamex> and <enamex sw="w48610" long="-2.9721" lat="54.1741" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2649281" name="Flockborough" conf="99991">Flook Borough</enamex>, live mainly by fishing and cockling upon the sands.</s></p>
<p><s id="s290">These villages consist principally, in each case, of one straggling street of humble cottages; and, though there is not much attraction in their outward appearance, considerableinterest attaches to the peculiar way of human life therein.</s> <s id="s291">Some idea of the fishery on this shore may be had from the fact that, in addition to flook, plaice, salmon, andother fish, thee is sometimes as much as one thousand tones of cockles sent from <enamex sw="w49107" long="-2.943633715673867" lat="54.2343446874937" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11171401" name="High Cark" conf="2.6">Cark</enamex>, in one season, principally to the manufacturing towns of <enamex  sw="w49170" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>.</s> <s id="s292">Cockles are foundin large beds, called" skeers."</s> <s id="s293">The fish is buried about an inch below the surface, and its place is known by two little holes in the sand, called" eyes;" from thence thecockler whips out the fish with a kind of three - pronged bent fork, called a" craam."</s> <s id="s294">Although these cocklers generally belong to the poorest class of people, no quarrels take place among them on the sands.</s> <s id="s295">This arises from a firm belief that if ever they quarrel upon the sands, the cockles would leave that place with the next tide.</s></p>
<p><s id="s296">It is in these three fishing villages that the lead-miners of <enamex  sw="w49765" name="Large admin unit">Northumberland</enamex> and other visitors to the" <enamex sw="w49807" long="-2.941792945442159" lat="54.15345984931304" type="water" gazref="unlock:11178031" name="Holy Well" conf="2.4">Holy Well</enamex>" take up their quarters, but chiefly, I believe, atFlookborough, where there is comfortable accommodation to be had.</s> <s id="s297"><enamex sw="w49934" long="-2.97214" lat="54.17415" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00151" name="Flookburgh" conf="99992">Flookborough</enamex>, as its name indicates, was formerly a market town, holding a charter granted to the Priorof <enamex sw="w50040" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>, by Edward the First.</s> <s id="s298">After the dissolution, this charter was removed to <enamex sw="w50121" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>.</s> <s id="s299">The first part of the name may or may not come from the fish so common on theseshores, - but I heard that a certain dignitary of the church, once visiting there, inquired of a villager how many souls( soles) there were in the place, and the man replied," Well, I dinnet justly knaa; but here's a terrible deeal o' flooks abaat."</s></p>
<p><s id="s300">The country between Grange and the <enamex sw="w50491" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex> sands, about five miles, is very interesting.</s> <s id="s301">Soon after the train leaves Grange, we run through a rocky cutting, which bringsus to <enamex sw="w50629" long="-2.9747" lat="54.17825" type="other" gazref="unlock:9773243" name="Cark And Cartmel Railway Station" conf="2">Cark station</enamex>, two miles from Cart Mel, to which town an omnibus runs daily in summer time.</s> <s id="s302">The line then passes Kent's Bank, with its pleasantly-situated villas, near which" <enamex sw="w50802" long="-2.926883111983222" lat="54.17155321711211" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11055221" name="Abbot Hall" conf="2.2">Abbot Hall</enamex>," a modest, modern mansion, stands in that green corner of the shore, on the site of an old house, said to have belonged to a slyly-jovial prelateof the olden time.</s> <s id="s303">Leaving this place, we rund about two miles by the promontory of <enamex sw="w51043" long="-2.926481469994323" lat="54.15357863275982" type="other" gazref="unlock:11181017" name="Humphrey Head Point" conf="2">Humphrey Head</enamex>, and then begin to cross <enamex sw="w51082" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> sands.</s> <s id="s304">The scenery about <enamex sw="w51118" long="-2.926481469994323" lat="54.15357863275982" type="other" gazref="unlock:11181017" name="Humphrey Head Point" conf="2">Humphrey Head</enamex> is a fine mixture of the hold and the beautiful; andthe country around is full of picturesque rambles.</s> <s id="s305">Up in its grand yew-crowned cliffs there is a remarkable cave, believed by the natives to be an abode of fairies.</s> <s id="s306">Thefamous" <enamex sw="w51360" long="-2.941792945442159" lat="54.15345984931304" type="water" gazref="unlock:11178031" name="Holy Well" conf="2.4">Holy Well</enamex>" is on the western shore of this fine promontory.</s></p>
<p><s id="s307">Upon a low fertile level, between Grange and <enamex sw="w51465" long="-2.926481469994323" lat="54.15357863275982" type="other" gazref="unlock:11181017" name="Humphrey Head Point" conf="2">Humphrey Head</enamex>, a little grey ruin stands near the line.</s> <s id="s308">This is <enamex sw="w51529" long="-2.942201222784968" lat="54.17143435560404" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11327553" name="Wraysholme Tower" conf="2.2">Wraysholme Tower</enamex>, formerly a fortified honse, belongingto the knightly family of <enamex sw="w51610" long="-3.56163" lat="54.61363" type="other" gazref="unlock:4571823" name="Harrington" conf="1.908677464">Harrington</enamex>, of <enamex sw="w51625" long="-3.0986" lat="54.1301" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2657532" name="Aldingham" conf="99992">Aldingham Castle</enamex>, in Low <enamex sw="w51650" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>.</s> <s id="s309">The Saxon town of <enamex sw="w51677" long="-3.094427164995567" lat="54.13419124413438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11058115" name="Aldingham" conf="2.6">Aldingham</enamex> belonged to this family in 1346.</s> <s id="s310">Both town and castle have longsince been swept away by the sea.</s></p>
<p><s id="s311">There is more than one legend connected with this ancient tower.</s> <s id="s312">The following, called" The Last Wolf," is given in the" Remains of John <enamex sw="w51921" long="-71.4928371" lat="41.6078788" type="other" gazref="unlock:7961356" name="Briggs Corner" conf="0.7658482524">Briggs</enamex>," editor of the old Lonsdale Magazine.</s> <s id="s313">It appear from the tradition, which has been put into spirit-stirring verse a few years ago, by an anony-mous writer, that in the proud old days of Wraysholme, Sir Edgar <enamex sw="w52137" long="-3.56163" lat="54.61363" type="other" gazref="unlock:4571823" name="Harrington" conf="1.908677464">Harrington</enamex> had sworn to hunt down the last wolf" in <enamex  sw="w52189" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>'s spacious realm," whose haunt was the woody height of <enamex sw="w52252" long="-2.926481469994323" lat="54.15357863275982" type="other" gazref="unlock:11181017" name="Humphrey Head Point" conf="2">Humphrey Head</enamex>, and whose prey theflocks and herds of Wraysholme.</s> <s id="s314">On the eve of the chase Sir Edgar held a mighty carousal at the tower, among his retainers and noble guests.</s> <s id="s315">During the feast he swore thatthe last wolf should" grace the conqueror's helm," and, also, that -</s></p>
<p><s id="s316">" Whoever that wolf shoud quell, Should have his fair niece for a bridge, And half his lands as well."</s></p>
<p><s id="s317">The orphan lady Adela, old Sir Edgar's ward, with jet black hair of glossy sheen, and bright hazel eyes, was beloved of all the country round; but her heart and trothwere with a gallant young knight of the name of <enamex sw="w52840" long="-3.56163" lat="54.61363" type="other" gazref="unlock:4571823" name="Harrington" conf="1.908677464">Harrington</enamex>, Sir Edgar's son, who having fled to shun his father's wrath, was supposed to be dead in foreign lands.</s> <s id="s318">He seems, however, to have turned up at this great hunting feast just in time, after winning honour against the swarthy Saracen, disguised under the title of Sir John Delisle, inwhom, nevertheless, the old retainers of Wraysholme see that -</s></p>
<p><s id="s319">" A long lost wanderer meets their sight, Whatever his name be now."</s></p>
<p><s id="s320">But, as usual, there are cross purposes in this old tale of love and chivalry, for Layburne, another brave knight, and the friend of Sir Edgar, site by the board, closesnitor for the fair lady, though" from her soul abhorred."</s> <s id="s321">The night drives on in song and jest, and brimming goblets,</s></p>
<p><s id="s322">" Till late, with plenteous cheer oppressed, And foaming tankards drowned, The revellers retire to rest, and silence sinks around."</s></p>
<p><s id="s323">At break of day old Hubert's horn wakes the sleepers to a mighty hunting.</s></p>
<p><s id="s324">" Full threescore riders mount with speed, - Amidst them Layburne strides A gallant steed of Flemish breed, That well his weight abides.</s></p>
<p><s id="s325">" Whilst mounted on an Arab white, Of figure light and free, Rides young <enamex sw="w53961" long="-73.781979252" lat="46.146775948" type="other" gazref="unlock:5248165" name="Lac Delisle" conf="0.5227341682">Delisle</enamex>, the strange knight, All wrapt in mystery."</s></p><p><s id="s326">The huntsman leads the gallant company up to the wolf's covert on <enamex sw="w54078" long="-2.926481469994323" lat="54.15357863275982" type="other" gazref="unlock:11181017" name="Humphrey Head Point" conf="2">Humphrey Head</enamex>.</s> <s id="s327">The dogs get the track of their grisly prey, and a brave chase begins, over Kirkheadand <enamex sw="w54181" long="-2.973259116317761" lat="54.1891650792199" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11176859" name="Holker" conf="2.6">Holker</enamex> to <enamex sw="w54191" long="-2.959809373549684" lat="54.2701718942731" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11229861" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, where they swim the" <enamex sw="w54226" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex>'s brawling flood."</s> <s id="s328">On, through woodland glen, and over wild hill they go, in clamorous dash, till the" grey beastfinds brief shelter in the recesses of <enamex sw="w54384" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> <enamex sw="w54393" long="-3.12208" lat="54.37042" type="other" gazref="unlock:4565407" name="Old Man of Coniston" conf="2">Old Man</enamex>.</s> <s id="s329">Here the hunters breath; but their hounds are staunch, and their horses good as ever broke cover or dashed througha wood; the dogs are on the track again like grim death; away by <enamex sw="w54581" long="-2.977291334332336" lat="54.3599180438576" type="water" gazref="unlock:11140740" name="Esthwaite Water" conf="2.4">Esthwaite</enamex>, and on to the green shores of <enamex sw="w54622" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>, where the painting savage takes the water at one boldplunge," and leaves his foes behind."</s> <s id="s330">The rival knights, Layburne and Delisle, follow," foremost of the dripping train," and win the eastern side of the lake.</s> <s id="s331">Two tirelessbloodhounds keep the scent, and the chase continues along the shore to" craggy Gummershaw,"</s></p>
<p><s id="s332">" Then turns aside to <enamex sw="w54971" long="-2.870270619568472" lat="54.24800657671408" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:42588" name="Witherslack" conf="2.6">Witherslack</enamex>" Where <enamex sw="w54990" long="-2.896315912832438" lat="54.33423674322094" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:36927" name="Winster" conf="2.6">Winster</enamex>'s waters range, And thence to shingly Aggerslack, And sand-surveying Grange.</s></p>
<p><s id="s333">The doomed brute now makes with the instinct of despair for his old shelter on <enamex sw="w55154" long="-2.926481469994323" lat="54.15357863275982" type="other" gazref="unlock:11181017" name="Humphrey Head Point" conf="2">Humphrey Head</enamex>, but as mild evening sinks upon the scene, the fatal hounds are on histrack-and he is driven madly towards a wild chasm,</s></p>
<p><s id="s334">" Begirt by rock on every side, That slopes in shade away."</s></p>
<p><s id="s335">Wolf and dogs rush over the steep.</s> <s id="s336">Layburne's horse starts back from the awful chasm; but impetuous Delisle spurs on, and his fiery steed sweeps to destruction down the shrouded crag like a flash of lightning -</s></p>
<p><s id="s337">" The shingles in its headlong course With rattling din give way, The hazels snap beneath its force, The mountain savins away."</s></p>
<p><s id="s338">After this terrible crisis the fair Adela chances to be pacing the hollow glen on her light palfrey, when the wolf appears in sight, and" bares his glistening teeth."</s></p>
<p><s id="s339">" Her eyes are closed in mortal dread, And ever a look they steal, The wolf and Arab both lie dead, And scathless stands Delisle.</s></p>
<p><s id="s340">" Full promptly from the slaughtered prey, He plucks the recking spear, And cries' Oh, beauteous <enamex sw="w56077" long="-120.8632663" lat="37.7885387" type="other" gazref="unlock:8062621" name="Adela" conf="0.5397315055">Adela</enamex>, Behold thy true love here!'"</s></p><p><s id="s341">Sir Edgar now appears, and discovering in Delisle his lost son, welcomes him affectionately, and gives him the bride of his heart.</s> <s id="s342">By blessed hep the Prior of Cartmelis on his way" to drink at the <enamex sw="w56311" long="-2.941792945442159" lat="54.15345984931304" type="water" gazref="unlock:11178031" name="Holy Well" conf="2.4">Holy Well</enamex>," and he consents to perform the marriage ceremony at once in the neighbouring cavern.</s></p>
<p><s id="s343">" And hence that cave on <enamex sw="w56432" long="-72.3039763" lat="43.2367425" type="other" gazref="unlock:7828181" name="Humphrey Hill" conf="0.759733813">Humphrey Hill</enamex>, Where these fair deeds befell, Is called Sir Edgar's chapel still, As hunters wot full well,</s></p>
<p><s id="s344">" And still that holy fount is there, To which the Prior came; And still it boasts its virtues rare.</s> <s id="s345">And bears its ancient name.</s></p>
<p><s id="s346">" And long on Wraysholme's lattice light A wolf's head might be traced, In honour of the redeross knight, Who bore it for his crest,</s></p>
<p><s id="s347">" In <enamex sw="w56804" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> church his grave is shown, And over it, side by side All graved in stone, lies brave Sir John, And Adela his bridge."</s></p><p><s id="s348">Such is the legend of" The Last Wolf," connected with this ruined tower of Wraysholme, the ancient abode of the Harringtons of <enamex sw="w57056" long="-3.094427164995567" lat="54.13419124413438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11058115" name="Aldingham" conf="2.6">Aldingham</enamex>, in Low <enamex sw="w57074" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>.</s> <s id="s349">I find that, forty years ago, the place was sheltered by clumps of old trees.</s> <s id="s350">These are now gone, and the tower is a mere outhouse to the neighbouring farmstead.</s></p>
<p><s id="s351"><enamex sw="w57244" long="-2.943633715673867" lat="54.2343446874937" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11171401" name="High Cark" conf="2.6">Cark</enamex> is the nearest station to <enamex sw="w57275" long="-2.973259116317761" lat="54.1891650792199" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11176859" name="Holker" conf="2.6">Holker</enamex>, the Duke of Devonshire's <enamex sw="w57308" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> seat.</s> <s id="s352"><enamex sw="w57322" long="-2.98858352875109" lat="54.18904029214188" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11176860" name="Holker Hall" conf="2.2">Holker Hall</enamex> belongs to the middle of the sixteenth century, when it was the residence of a branch of the ancient family of <enamex sw="w57445" long="-2.705402502615134" lat="53.75956131118807" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11249845" name="Preston" conf="2.256064217">Preston</enamex>, of <enamex sw="w57457" long="-2.682114215629325" lat="54.24982874588346" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13402940" name="Preston Patrick CP" conf="2.4">Preston Patrick</enamex>, in <enamex  sw="w57477" name="Large admin unit">Westmoreland</enamex>.</s> <s id="s353">About a century ago this beautiful estate came into possession of the Cavendish family.</s> <s id="s354">The park is full of rich sylvan landscapes, and it contains many noble trees, and trees of very rare kids.</s> <s id="s355">There are delightful walks on the woodland heights behind thepark, which command good views of <enamex sw="w57781" long="-3.11164649" lat="54.38316573" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00176" name="Levers Water" conf="99992">Leven water</enamex>, <enamex sw="w57794" name="Thurston Vale">Thurston Vale</enamex>, the mountains at the head of <enamex sw="w57838" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>, and the <enamex sw="w57858" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> range.</s></p>
<p><s id="s356">When the train clears <enamex sw="w57896" long="-2.926481469994323" lat="54.15357863275982" type="other" gazref="unlock:11181017" name="Humphrey Head Point" conf="2">Humphrey Head</enamex>, the banks of the <enamex sw="w57928" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex> estuary open beautifully in sight.</s> <s id="s357">Wild, rich-hued limestone crags straggle up the north-east side, underoverhanging wodds, and the low shore is all fertile undulations.</s> <s id="s358">The bold railway mole now crosses <enamex sw="w58138" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> Sands, and we rumble over a lofty viaduct, where the broad <enamex sw="w58208" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex> rolls wild and turbid underneath, as if glad to escape from this daring evidence of man's enterprise, to the uncontrollable ocean beyond.</s> <s id="s359">The views from the linesas we cross these sands are peculiarly fine, for this estuary is perhaps the most picturesque of any in <enamex sw="w58480" long="-2.971573845828191" lat="54.11726758179064" type="water" gazref="unlock:11222778" name="Morecambe Bay" conf="2.4">Morecambe Bay</enamex>.</s> <s id="s360"><enamex sw="w58495" long="-3.127623803707886" lat="54.79005157559101" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11319157" name="Westward" conf="2.55793943">Westward</enamex>, <enamex sw="w58505" long="-2.698918803705313" lat="54.28095482898485" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11077772" name="Birkrigg Park" conf="2.2">Birkrigg</enamex> rises above the rich woods and glades of <enamex sw="w58555" long="-3.064741936428078" lat="54.17041334190125" type="other" gazref="unlock:11115195" name="Conishead Priory" conf="2">Conishead Priory</enamex>.</s> <s id="s361">A little westward we see the white village of <enamex sw="w58619" long="-2.789871818718112" lat="54.21747314183408" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11277868" name="Sandside" conf="2.6">Sandside</enamex>, opposite to which, about a mile from the shore, is that interesting little isle of prayeer, called" <enamex sw="w58728" long="-3.034107478873875" lat="54.17068028180302" type="other" gazref="unlock:11103595" name="Chapel Island" conf="2">Chapel Island</enamex>," with its old ruined chantry hidden in the trees.</s> <s id="s362">BehindSandside, the grey smoke of <enamex sw="w58827" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> hovers above the valley at the foot of" <enamex sw="w58878" long="1.167322741392827" lat="51.14730840595256" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11175984" name="Hoad Fm" conf="0.8571240799">Hoad</enamex> Hill."</s> <s id="s363">The traveller may know this hill by the lighthouse-shaped monument on the top.</s> <s id="s364">Further along the shore there is a little cluster of shipping at the port of <enamex sw="w59046" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s365">The low grounds beyond are, first great tracts of yellow sand, then pleasant holmsand valleys; behind these, woody uplands and lofty moors filling the rear of the landscape.</s> <s id="s366">The extreme northward view of the estuary is bounded by a great cluster of Carmelfells, rising peak after peak.</s> <s id="s367">Looking eastward, the shore is a beautiful combination of rock and wildwood, with the great ridge of <enamex sw="w59445" long="-2.927687714972389" lat="54.20750221833886" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11165069" name="Hampsfell" conf="2.4">Hampsfell</enamex> peeping over the promontoryof Humphreay Head.</s></p>
<p><s id="s368">The <enamex sw="w59505" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> sands are considered more dangerous than those on the <enamex sw="w59570" long="-2.83333" lat="54.06667" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00068" name="Lancaster" conf="99992">Lancaster side</enamex>.</s> <s id="s369">Mr. <enamex sw="w59590" long="-75.4496395" lat="39.712058" type="other" gazref="unlock:7253245" name="Raines Corner" conf="0.7352500639">Raines</enamex>, speaking of the old route over this estuary says: -" The track is from <enamex sw="w59667" long="-2.98858352875109" lat="54.18904029214188" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11176860" name="Holker Hall" conf="2.2">Holker Hall</enamex> to <enamex sw="w59682" long="-3.050107782953964" lat="54.19750856602495" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11246934" name="Plumpton Hall" conf="2.2">Plumpton Hall</enamex>, keeping <enamex sw="w59705" long="-3.034107478873875" lat="54.17068028180302" type="other" gazref="unlock:11103595" name="Chapel Island" conf="2">Chapel Island</enamex> a little to the left; and the mind of a visitor is filled with a mixture of awe and gratitude, when, in a short timeafter he has traversed the estuary, almost dry-shod, he beholds the waters advancing into the bay, and bearing stately vessels towards the harbour of <enamex sw="w59985" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, over thevery path which he has so recently trodden."</s> <s id="s370">The Priory of <enamex sw="w60064" long="-3.064741936428078" lat="54.17041334190125" type="other" gazref="unlock:11115195" name="Conishead Priory" conf="2">Conishead</enamex> was anciently charged with the costs of guides across this estuary.</s> <s id="s371">So dangerous were these sands considered, that on" <enamex sw="w60193" long="-3.034107478873875" lat="54.17068028180302" type="other" gazref="unlock:11103595" name="Chapel Island" conf="2">Chapel Island</enamex>," about a mile west of the line, the old monks of <enamex sw="w60257" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> built the small chapel, where prayers were daily offered" for the safety ofthe souls of such as crossed the sands with the morning tide."</s> <s id="s372">There are still some remains of this ancient chapel, which gave its name to the island; and, though" longyears have darkened into time" since the prayers of the church were regularly heard there, no man walks about the shades of this little seaworn solitude without feeling thatsomething of the solemn interest of its ancient associations lingers who is still.</s> <s id="s373">The island is now a favourite resort of pleasure seekers, who cross at low water from the village of <enamex sw="w60865" long="-2.789871818718112" lat="54.21747314183408" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11277868" name="Sandside" conf="2.6">Sandside</enamex>, about a mile distant-and, even in that short distance, sometimes meet with disaster.</s> <s id="s374">The three miles over <enamex sw="w60981" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex> sands must have been destructivelydangerous, for," according to a petition from the Abbot of <enamex sw="w61080" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>, in 19 Ed.</s> <s id="s375">2, the number of sixteen at one time, and six more at another, were sacrificed in this way; and in order to eschew the great mortality of the people of <enamex sw="w61250" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> on passing the sands at ebb of tide, he prayed that he should have a view of frankpledge and a coronerof his own; for everywhere," he says," it would be the salvation of one soul at least."</s></p>
<p><s id="s376">The train is now quitting the sands, and we draw near to Ulverstone town.</s> <s id="s377">Long strings of carriages go by heavily laden the rich iron ore of <enamex sw="w61589" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>.</s> <s id="s378">I was told that the mines of this district now produce between seven and eight hundred thousand tons of the finest ore in <enamex  sw="w61720" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> every year.</s> <s id="s379">Thirty years ago, old Captain Barrow, of <enamex sw="w61780" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, carried all the iron ore got in <enamex sw="w61824" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> in one small vessel.</s> <s id="s380">This Captain Barrow was cousin to Sir John Barrow, late secretary to theAdmiralty, whose monument stands on the top of the" Head," the great round hill, at the right hand side of the line as we run over the railway bridge towards Ulverstone. Sir John was born of very humble parentage, in a little cottage at <enamex sw="w62161" long="-3.080527476617013" lat="54.18825064013102" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11131554" name="Dragley Beck" conf="2.6">Dragley Beck</enamex>, near this town.</s></p>
<p><s id="s381">" About me round I saw Hill, dale, and shady woods, and sunny plains, And liquid lapse of murmuring streams; by these Creatures that lived, and moved, and walked, or flew, Birds on the branches warbling; all things smiled: With fragrance and with joy my heart overflowed."</s> </p>
<p> <s id="s382"><enamex  sw="w62465" name="Not a placename">Milton</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s383">The view of <enamex sw="w62485" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> and the country about it, as seen from the high road near the station, is very picturesque.</s> <s id="s384">The town is pleasantly situated in a vale, on theshores of the <enamex sw="w62651" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex> estuary, among the hills of Low <enamex sw="w62689" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>; and it stands at convenient distances from so many points of interest that I took up head quarters at thewell-known Sun Hote, in the market place.</s> <s id="s385">From hence I made daily excursions into the neighbourhood; and one of my first rambles was to <enamex sw="w62939" long="-3.111174453081801" lat="54.18797183142002" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11296311" name="Swarthmoor" conf="2.6">Swarthmoor</enamex>, about a mile from thetown.</s> <s id="s386"><enamex sw="w62978" long="-3.102066835" lat="54.18633195" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00090" name="Swarthmoor Hall" conf="99992">Swarthmoor Hall</enamex> was, for many years, the residence of George Fox, founder of the Society of Friends.</s> <s id="s387">Leaving <enamex sw="w63087" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> by the south road, about two hundred yardspast the railway station, a bye-path leads over the fields on the right hand a little way, then down into a shady dell, through which a clear rivulet plays its moodymusic, running out of sight again at the south end, under thick, low-lapping branches, which gaze into it and daily with its silvery ripples, as if in love with this limpidministrel, whose song softens into silence in the woods beyond.</s> <s id="s388">This quiet dell is a fairy chapel of sylvan beauty, where the ceaseless hymn of nature is seldom disturbedby other sounds.</s> <s id="s389">In the deepest part of the hollow, and old stone bridge, shaded by tall trees, crosses the stream; from thence a rugged footpath climbs the opposite fields, and in about a quarter of a mile leads close by the rear of a boary pile of stone outhouses of rude appearance.</s> <s id="s390">The road may be miry, but whoever he be that goes that way, in rain or fair weather, let him linger there a breathing while, for the old house in front of these buildings in <enamex sw="w64106" long="-3.102066835" lat="54.18633195" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00090" name="Swarthmoor Hall" conf="99992">Swarthmoor Hall</enamex>, the residence of George Fox.</s> <s id="s391">On my firstvisit, I wandered about some time before I could find any human creature astir.</s> <s id="s392">A contemplative charm seemed to lie upon all around.</s> <s id="s393">The house is a large, irregular, Elizabethian building, with nothing grand about it, save the impressive memories of the great reformer who dwelt in it two centuries ago.</s> <s id="s394">The doorways are small; some ofthe windows are built up; and it has altogether a bald appearance, considering its size and former importance.</s> <s id="s395">But the home of the persecuted puritan still looks over thosequiet fields with a kind of ascetic solemnity, as if it was mingling dreams of the past with a patient waiting for the result of slow decay.</s> <s id="s396">I wandered about the rough, cattle-trodden yard, among mire, and straw, and farming-gear, yet all was still, except a few ducks dabbling in a muddy pool, and a peaceful dog that roamedabout the outhouses, regardless of my presence.</s> <s id="s397">There was no sign of life even about the windows.</s> <s id="s398">At last, I came to a kind of kitchen at the rear of the hall, where Ifound the mistress of the house and her servants, throng at their washing.</s> <s id="s399">When I had explained the purpose of my visit, the mistress pointed to a rude gate at the end, which opened to the front of the hall.</s> <s id="s400">I went through and found myself in a little green paddock, where there was not even one rose left" to mark where a garden had been." There were the principal windows, - one little window looking out from George Fox's study; the other two were old-fashioned bay windows, much larger.</s> <s id="s401">Between there was thesmall old doorway, to which two rude stone steps led up.</s> <s id="s402">All else was plain and unpretending; and all other windows in the lower part of the frontage were built up.</s> <s id="s403">Inside, I was shown the" hall," a quaint, flagged apartment, on the ground floor, with a great old-fashioned fire-place, and a kind of stone dais in the recess of the mullionedwindow.</s> <s id="s404">Here, I was told, the earliest meetings of the" Friends" were held.</s> <s id="s405">From this room, two steps led up to the little solemn sanctuary which was Fox's study; and Ifelt as if every footfall there was an intrusion; for that dim-lighted room, with its tiny lattice and quaint furniture, was the cell of a saint," of whom the world was not worthy."</s> <s id="s406">His bed has been removed from its ancient apartmentinto a room where the farm servants sleep; and I was told that the Bible is now in the possession of a lady belonging to the Society of Friends, in <enamex sw="w66559" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s407">Before Foxmarried the pious widow of Judge Fell, he was once dragged from this house and imprisoned all night in <enamex sw="w66684" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, under a guard of fifteen men, some of whom were perchedin the fireplace, for fear that he should fly up the chimney, and so escape.</s> <s id="s408">From thence he was removed to <enamex sw="w66858" long="-2.80569" lat="54.04996" type="other" gazref="unlock:5825252" name="Lancaster Castle" conf="2">Lancaster Castle</enamex>, where he suffered a long imprisonment.</s> <s id="s409">GeorgeFox seems to have turned <enamex sw="w66946" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> and the country about it upside down in those days, preaching in all sorts of pulpits and private houses, and sometimes in the openmarket-place.</s> <s id="s410">He was once shamefully maltreated in the churchyard of St Mary's, at <enamex sw="w67171" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, after preaching to the congregation there.</s> <s id="s411">About a quarter of a mile west of the hall there is a plain substantial chapel, - the first chapel of the disciples of George Fox, - built at his own cost, in 1688.</s> <s id="s412">It stands in a little flagged enclosure, surrounded by a stone wall about nine feet high.</s> <s id="s413">The white door of the yard was open when I saw it, and the" Friends" were met within, - yet there was no sound, but the sea breeze whistling across the fields of <enamex sw="w67636" long="-3.111174453081801" lat="54.18797183142002" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11296311" name="Swarthmoor" conf="2.6">Swarthmoor</enamex>.</s> <s id="s414">Above the entrance was this inscription, plainly graven," Ex dono, G.F., 1688."</s> <s id="s415">At the western end of the chapelthere is a croft, which was presented with the chapel, for the accomodation of the horses of such Friends as came from a distance.</s></p>
<p><s id="s416">About a mile west of Fox's Chapel, a byeway leads into the old Roman road, at a place where a tesselated pavement was found a few years ago.</s> <s id="s417">A mile further in the samedirection brings us to the bleak summit of" <enamex sw="w68102" long="-2.698918803705313" lat="54.28095482898485" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11077772" name="Birkrigg Park" conf="2.2">Birkrigg</enamex>," which commands a new and extensive prospect of the bay, and it is north and eastern shores.</s> <s id="s418">The pretty village of <enamex sw="w68227" long="-3.07058438082128" lat="54.16288715481818" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:44173" name="Bardsea" conf="2.6">Bardsea</enamex> is full in sight, at the foot of the hill.</s> <s id="s419">On the southern slope of this rocky moorland there is a small Druidical temple, - a circle of nine hoary stones, which, with one exception, are still more or less upright.</s> <s id="s420">A quarter of a mile west of this relic of Britishhistory, and near an antique farmhouse, called" Sunbreak," there is a lonely burial ground, looking out towards the sea.</s> <s id="s421">This is the oldest graveyard of the Society ofFriends.</s> <s id="s422">It is surrounded by a high stone wall, and carelly kept in order.</s> <s id="s423">The door is generally locked, but I found it simply fastened with a staple and chain, and awooden peg.</s> <s id="s424">The interior contains no visible commemoration of the dead; but a thick swathe of the greenest grass covers the whole area, save on the higher side, wherepicturesque fragments of limestone rock, rising above the rich herbage, are so beautifully hemossed here and there, that is seems as if nature, in her quiet, lovelyway, had taken in hand to keep the memories of these nameless tenants of the dust for ever green.</s> <s id="s425">There was something more touchingly beautiful, more suggestive of repose, in the recordless silence of this lone graveyard of the persecuted puritan, than in any cemeteries adorned with grand efforts of monumental art-which so oft intrude upon the solemnity of death things sulled by the vanities of the living.</s> <s id="s426">The sacred simplicity of the spot made one feel more deeply how sound they slept below, in that unassailableshelter from the hurtful world.</s> <s id="s427">The very seabreeze seemed to pause there, and pass over this placce of unawaking dreamers in a kind of requiem-hush.</s></p>
<p><s id="s428"><enamex sw="w69828" long="-3.125034079844071" lat="54.13390909437263" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11153846" name="Gleaston Castle" conf="2.2">Gleaston Castle</enamex> is about six miles from <enamex sw="w69868" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s429">The direct road to it lies through the old village of <enamex sw="w69934" long="-3.126558226707489" lat="54.15367062649398" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:19793" name="Urswick" conf="2.6">Urswick</enamex>.</s> <s id="s430">At the end of this village there is a fine tarn close by the highway.</s> <s id="s431">The people of <enamex sw="w70027" long="-3.126558226707489" lat="54.15367062649398" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:19793" name="Urswick" conf="2.6">Urswick</enamex> Vale have a legend that ruins of an ancient town lie beneath the waters of this tarn.</s> <s id="s432">Near <enamex sw="w70126" long="-3.126558226707489" lat="54.15367062649398" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:19793" name="Urswick" conf="2.6">Urswick</enamex> there is the small monastic ruinof <enamex sw="w70169" long="-1.89169" lat="53.98146" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geonames_ID_6940902" name="Bolton Abbey" conf="99991">Bolton Chapel</enamex>, standing in a farm-yard, by the road, and now used as a cowhouse.</s> <s id="s433">Leaving this village, we pass Redmond Hall, the seat of a family once known in Englishhistory.</s> <s id="s434">About a mile from <enamex sw="w70363" long="-3.125034079844071" lat="54.13390909437263" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11153846" name="Gleaston Castle" conf="2.2">Gleaston Castle</enamex>, in a hollow of the fields, on the left hand side of the road, there is a pretty little sheet of water, called <enamex sw="w70490" long="-3.125034079844071" lat="54.13390909437263" type="water" gazref="unlock:11217281" name="Mere Tarn" conf="2.4">Mere Tarn</enamex>, swarmingwith pike.</s> <s id="s435">he ruins of <enamex sw="w70532" long="-3.125034079844071" lat="54.13390909437263" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11153846" name="Gleaston Castle" conf="2.2">Gleaston Castle</enamex> are of con - siderable extent.</s> <s id="s436">The castle originally consisted of four square towers, connected by strong curtain walls, defending an enclosure, the length of which seemed to me aboutone hundred years.</s> <s id="s437">One of these towers has disappeared, and the other three are more or less ruinous; but the summits of two may yet be easily ascended by the stone steps which wind up in the thickness of the massivewalls.</s> <s id="s438">In its palmy days, this castle must have looked imposing in the heart of the little vale, where it seems to have been placed more for shelter and seclusion thanfor anything commanding in position.</s> <s id="s439">it was built by the <enamex  sw="w71170" name="Not a placename">Flemings</enamex>, lords of the ancient manor of Much Land.</s> <s id="s440">The possessions of Michael le <enamex  sw="w71251" name="Not a placename">Fleming</enamex> were the only lands in all <enamex sw="w71286" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> exempted from the grant made by Stephen, Earl of <enamex sw="w71343" long="11.33875" lat="44.49381" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00048" name="Bologna" conf="99991">Bologne</enamex> and moreton, to <enamex sw="w71367" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.2">Furness Abbey</enamex>.</s> <s id="s441">The name of this Michael, which the natives pronounce" <enamex sw="w71437" long="-2.3" lat="54.6" type="other" gazref="unlock:4567040" name="Mickle Fell" conf="1.840300676">Mickle</enamex>," stillclings to old associations in this neighbourhood, as n the case of" <enamex sw="w71519" name="Mickle Well">Mickle Well</enamex>," not meaning great well, but" Michael's Well."</s> <s id="s442">I remember how, on that breezy day, when, with two friends, I visited the ruins of this castle, as we were casting in a mossy corner at the entrance of the village.</s> <s id="s443">The stones about it were worn by the footing of many generations, and the water was so clear that I could have seen a single thread of a lady's hair at the bottom of it.</s> <s id="s444">I remember, too, that when we were beginningto despair of finding any-thing like substantial refreshment, we met with it at the very last house on the western edge of the village, a clean little hostelry, where wegot an excellent dinner of eggs and bacon, cheese, ale, pickles, salad fresh from the garden behind the house, and three quarts of buttermilk; in addition to which, I hadmy shoe mended; and we were treated with more than common civilty, all for the low charge of three and sixpence, - which was received with satisfaction.</s> <s id="s445">The way of the shoebusiness was this, - I had burst the seam of it, and it was getting squashy with wet, for we had had a delightfully rough tramp over moss and fell, and through miry bye-roads, that day.</s> <s id="s446">The good wife at the alehouse offered to get it mended for me whilst dinner was cooking.</s> <s id="s447">The oldman lent me a shoe of his own to put on meanwhile.</s> <s id="s448">It was as hardas an iron pot; in fact, it had a consider-able weight of iron work about it, and for any rough work, I felt that that one shoe was worth at least four pair such as mine. With one foot handi-capped in this clog of iron and leather, I amused myself with walking about the clean floor of slate stone, listening to the difference of sound in myfoot-steps, which went" fuzz, clang-fuzz, clang," reminding me of the three bells of a little country church that I have heard of, one of which was sound, the next cracked, and the third mended with leather, - their united music amounting to a kind of" ding, dang, puff."</s> <s id="s449">The shoe came back mended before dinner was over, and a thrill of returningcomfort went through my frame when I got it on, for I had felt as if walking with a wet dish-cloth round my foot a while before.</s> <s id="s450">As we returned through the village, oneof my friends proposed that we should just look in upon a relation of his, an old shoemaker, and a quaint man, well versed in the folk lore of the dis - trict.</s> <s id="s451">He then led us up to one of the most comfortable-looking cottages I ever saw.</s> <s id="s452">The floor was as clean as a plate just laid down for dinner, the place smelt as sweetas an herb-stall, and all the polishable metal things shone like pools of water in moonlight.</s> <s id="s453">The cheerful old wife, whose ruddy face was bedded in a snowy old-fashionedcap, and whose eyes, in spite of age and spectacles looked as bright as the stars on a frosty night, rose from her arm-chair, and hobbled about with her crutch, smilingand talking, and talking and smiling, as if she did n't know exactl what to do to show that she was very fain.</s> <s id="s454">At last, opening the door of an inner room, where the heartyold fellow and his son sat at work, she said," What, dinnet ye see wha's here?"</s> <s id="s455">Dropping his hammer, and brushing the dirt from his leather apron, the old man rose abovesix feet into the air, pushed up his spectacles, and shouted," Why, it never is, sewer! It cannot be reightly, can it! It's nowt i' th warld else, aw declare! Well, thisis a capper, hooivvir! What yeere reight good stuff for sore even, mon! Whatever quarter's the wind in, at yeere blawn this gate on?</s> <s id="s456">Well, cum, cum; sit ye daan, an' let's mak use on ye while ye are here."</s> <s id="s457">" Ye hevn't hed yeere teea, aw warnd," said the good wife.</s> <s id="s458">But we were already primely filled with good things; and no other feast couldhave been so delightful as the genial welcome which the old couple gave us.</s> <s id="s459">The day, too, was waning, with an uncertain sky, and we had several miles to go.</s> <s id="s460">As we sat talking with the old man, a fine pair of new double-soled shooting boots stood at my elbow.</s> <s id="s461">I took them up, and asked what such a pair would cost.</s> <s id="s462">he said they could n't be done like them under a pound.</s> <s id="s463">" But," said he," ye sud ha sin a shoe that I stitched abaat an haar sin, for some poor tramp.</s> <s id="s464">I nivver see a warse made shoe i' my life, Ithink.</s> <s id="s465">An' he could n't hev hed' em lang, nawther, - t' leather wur so fresh."</s> <s id="s466">As he went on talking, I slowly lifted my foot till it came fairly into his sight.</s> <s id="s467">" Hello!" saidhe, with a confused gaze," What, wor it yaar shoe?"</s> <s id="s468">It was.</s> <s id="s469">" Well then," replied he," All at I can say is, at yer wit's deeal better nor yer understanding!" We had a gooddeal of gleeful talk with the old folk; after which six miles' walk in a high wind through the vale of <enamex sw="w76120" long="-3.126558226707489" lat="54.15367062649398" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:19793" name="Urswick" conf="2.6">Urswick</enamex> brought us to <enamex sw="w76142" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> at the edge of dark, well pleased with our day's ramble.</s></p>
<p><s id="s470"><enamex sw="w76210" long="-3.064741936428078" lat="54.17041334190125" type="other" gazref="unlock:11115195" name="Conishead Priory" conf="2">Conishead Priory</enamex> is rather more than a mile south of <enamex sw="w76263" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s471">There is a good road through the finest part of <enamex sw="w76323" long="-3.064741936428078" lat="54.17041334190125" type="other" gazref="unlock:11115195" name="Conishead Priory" conf="2">Conishead</enamex> Park to the pretty village of <enamex sw="w76363" long="-3.07058438082128" lat="54.16288715481818" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:44173" name="Bardsea" conf="2.6">Bardsea</enamex>, whichvillage is about three miles from <enamex sw="w76411" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s472">The road goes near the princely mansion, the seat of the Braddylls, which stands upon the site of the ancient priory.</s> <s id="s473">The entrance hall retains some relics of the old monastic buildings.</s> <s id="s474">About a mile beyond the priory, <enamex sw="w76642" long="-3.072" lat="54.1619" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD30107454" name="Bardsey" conf="99992">Bardsea Hall</enamex> stands at the right hand side of the road, in a shelteredspot under the woods, and almost hidden from the traveller by a high wall.</s> <s id="s475">This quaint building was erected by the Molyneux family, as a hunting seat, and it is supposedto occupy the site of the ancient hospital of <enamex sw="w76927" long="-3.07058438082128" lat="54.16288715481818" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:44173" name="Bardsea" conf="2.6">Bardsea</enamex>, the oldest ecclesiastical establishment in <enamex sw="w76979" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>.</s> <s id="s476">This religious house was in existence in the latter part of the eleventh century, and had disappeared before the foundation of <enamex sw="w77115" long="-3.064741936428078" lat="54.17041334190125" type="other" gazref="unlock:11115195" name="Conishead Priory" conf="2">Conishead</enamex> Priory. The best view of the Priory, and its beautiful park scenery, is from the summit of the woods behind <enamex sw="w77232" long="-3.072" lat="54.1619" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD30107454" name="Bardsey" conf="99992">Bardsea Hall</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s477"><enamex sw="w77246" long="-3.07058438082128" lat="54.16288715481818" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:44173" name="Bardsea" conf="2.6">Bardsea</enamex> takes its name from the British word," Bertesg," a place of thickets, as it appears in Doomsday Book.</s> <s id="s478">The village is pleasantly situated on a green eminencesloping gently to the sands.</s> <s id="s479">The woods, and dells, and quiet shore of this pretty sea-side nook, are full of pleasant walks.</s> <s id="s480">There is an antique mansion called" The WellHouse," which is an object of interest.</s> <s id="s481">In the village there are two respectable inns, and I found comfortable fare at the Cavendish Arms, where the landlord, Mr. Gilchrist, a gallant, old, retired preventive officer, from <enamex  sw="w77802" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, delighted me with his tales of wild adventure among the smugglers of the Scottish border, in" auld lang syne."</s></p>
<p><s id="s482"><enamex sw="w77925" long="-3.094427164995567" lat="54.13419124413438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11058115" name="Aldingham" conf="2.6">Aldingham</enamex> is about three miles along the sea-side, west of <enamex sw="w77984" long="-3.07058438082128" lat="54.16288715481818" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:44173" name="Bardsea" conf="2.6">Bardsea</enamex>.</s> <s id="s483">The road goes through the extensive plantations of" Seawood," the property of <enamex sw="w78071" long="-2.7725" lat="54.8089" type="other" gazref="unlock:5830453" name="The Crown Wetheral Hotel" conf="1.91925913">the Crown</enamex>; and throughthe old village of Baycliffe.</s> <s id="s484">The sea is either gleaming beautifully through the woods, or is in open sight, most of the way.</s> <s id="s485"><enamex sw="w78219" long="-3.094427164995567" lat="54.13419124413438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11058115" name="Aldingham" conf="2.6">Aldingham</enamex> Church looks lonely standing therein its little grave-yard by the sea, as if musing on the old Saxon town long since devoured by the hungry waters.</s> <s id="s486">This was originally the parish church of the ancientmanor of Much Land, which extended over the present <enamex sw="w78481" long="-3.094427164995567" lat="54.13419124413438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11058115" name="Aldingham" conf="2.6">Aldingham</enamex> and <enamex sw="w78495" long="-3.135938541934887" lat="54.12823331776305" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:40154" name="Gleaston" conf="2.6">Gleaston</enamex>, and over several villages, such as <enamex sw="w78540" long="-3.059638082226684" lat="52.75903384844726" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255079" name="Rhs Common" conf="1.395089808">Rhos</enamex>, Lies, and Crimelton, which have been swallowed by thesea centuries ago.</s> <s id="s487">Nothing now remains of them but the account of their extent and value, is preserved in the ancient records of <enamex sw="w78728" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.2">Furness Abbey</enamex>.</s> <s id="s488">This church is all that is left of the old town of <enamex sw="w78794" long="-3.094427164995567" lat="54.13419124413438" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11058115" name="Aldingham" conf="2.6">Aldingham</enamex>, the knightly residence and property of the Harringtons, one of which family, Lord de <enamex sw="w78890" long="-3.56163" lat="54.61363" type="other" gazref="unlock:4571823" name="Harrington" conf="1.908677464">Harrington</enamex>, died at the head of the <enamex sw="w78926" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> men, fighting for the Red <enamex sw="w78959" long="-74.7223827" lat="40.3673286" type="other" gazref="unlock:7843883" name="Mount Rose" conf="0.7082576066">Rose</enamex>, at the battle of <enamex sw="w78982" long="-1.492770958031659" lat="53.67966047047277" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11312227" name="Wakefield" conf="2.009643649">Wakefield</enamex>.</s> <s id="s489">The church retains some parts of the original building in its round pillars, and in one of the doorways.</s> <s id="s490">The armsof the Harringtons appear in the east window.</s> <s id="s491">The rectory stands close to the church; and the present rector is the Rev. John Macaulay, brother of the famous historianand statesman.</s></p>
<p><s id="s492">Six miles by rail from <enamex sw="w79311" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, the magnificent ruins of <enamex sw="w79348" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.2">Furness Abbey</enamex> stand in the glen called" <enamex sw="w79388" long="-3.1984" lat="54.1352" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD218717" name="Furness Abbey" conf="99992">Bekanks</enamex> Gill," or the Vale of the Deadly Night Shade, a sylvanseclusion, so cloistral in its character, that it might have been intended by nature to receive the grand pile, whose" bare ruined choirs" new land such an impressivecharm to the scene.</s> <s id="s493">This famous abbey was endowed with extraordinary wealth and power; and its prelates were temporal princes, ruling with almost absolute sway over adistrict as large as <enamex sw="w79803" long="-1.500309168183582" lat="54.64543028105785" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13372576" name="Bradbury and the Isle CP" conf="1.295887309">the Isle</enamex> of Man; and yet, those white-robed monks from <enamex sw="w79858" long="4.5667" lat="45.8167" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:4526575" name="Savingy" conf="99991">Savigny</enamex>, and their successors, were the humanising mediators between feudal tyranny and serfdom, in the rough old days.</s> <s id="s494">I am told that the language of the common people of <enamex sw="w80029" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> still retains French words and idioms not found elsewhere in <enamex  sw="w80098" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>, - lingering relics of the secular influence of the foreign ecclesiasticswho ruled this remote corner of <enamex  sw="w80212" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> so long.</s> <s id="s495">It would be easy to give an architectural description of the ruins from care-ful works already written, but I refrain partly from want of room, and partly because the visitor can buy all that information for a trifle on the spot itself.</s> <s id="s496">I may say, however, that in addition to the generaleffect, the high altar with its beautiful sedilia, the chapter-house, and the Abbot's private chapel, were particularly interesting to me.</s> <s id="s497">Though this monastery has lost the grand proportions of its old completeness, it is still robed in beauty, that" sole permanence inbeing's ceaseless flow;" and kind nature is quietly claiming its remains for her own again.</s> <s id="s498">It is a spot to linger in until the solemn beauty of it becomes an enduring trasure of the spirit.</s> <s id="s499">Reading the ancient chapter of its foundation, I was so struck with the beauty of one passage in it, thatI think the reader will excuse me for repeating it here.</s> <s id="s500">The words are as follows, from" West's Antiquities of <enamex sw="w81194" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>": -" In the name of the Blessed Trinity, and in honourof St. Mary of <enamex sw="w81270" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>, I, Stephen, Earl of <enamex sw="w81299" long="11.33875" lat="44.49381" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00048" name="Bologna" conf="99991">Bologne</enamex> and <enamex sw="w81311" long="-1.94975592311266" lat="52.8056253545372" type="water" gazref="unlock:8789423" name="Moreton Brook" conf="1.239908773">Moreton</enamex>, consulting God, and providing for the safety of my own soil, the soul of my wife the Countess Matilda, the sould of my lord and uncle Henry King of <enamex  sw="w81467" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> and Duke of Normandy, and for the souls of all the faithful, living as well as dead; in the year of our Lord 1127 ofthe Roman indiction, and the 5th and 18th of the Epact; considering every day the uncertainty of life, that the roses and flowers of kings, emperors, and dukes, and the crowns and palms of all the great, wither and decay; and that all things, with an uninterrupted course, tend to dissolution and death: I therefore return, give, and grantto God and St. Mary of <enamex sw="w81953" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>, all <enamex sw="w81966" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> and Walney,"&amp; c.</s> <s id="s501">&amp; c.</s></p>
<p><s id="s502"><enamex sw="w81995" long="-3.177980552513582" lat="54.15480048261493" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11514" name="Dalton-In-Furness" conf="2.6">Dalton</enamex>, the ancient capital of <enamex sw="w82026" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>, is about a mile from the abbey, and four from <enamex sw="w82081" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s503">The Roman road from <enamex sw="w82113" long="-3.490450385504208" lat="54.71199350930456" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11130" name="Maryport" conf="2.507684342">Maryport</enamex> to <enamex sw="w82125" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.134718443">Lancaster</enamex> passes through this town, and it was the site of a Roman station( Galacum).</s> <s id="s504">In Saxon times, this town belonged to Earl Tosti.</s> <s id="s505">Later, it was the manor court and market town of the abbots of <enamex sw="w82324" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>, the square tower of whose castle now stands looking with an antique frown upon the market-place.</s> <s id="s506">Here the civil business of their vast possession was transacted.</s> <s id="s507">The courts baron of <enamex sw="w82514" long="-3.177980552513582" lat="54.15480048261493" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11514" name="Dalton-In-Furness" conf="2.6">Dalton</enamex> are still held in this tower.</s> <s id="s508"><enamex sw="w82551" long="-3.177980552513582" lat="54.15480048261493" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11514" name="Dalton-In-Furness" conf="2.6">Dalton</enamex> church stands hard by the castle, near the edge of a steep rock, overlooking the vale of Deadly Nightshade. Romney, the painter, who was a native of this parish, lies burled in this graveyard, under a plain stone, bearing the name, dates, and the words," Pietor celeberrimus."</s> <s id="s509">The parish of <enamex sw="w82848" long="-3.177980552513582" lat="54.15480048261493" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11514" name="Dalton-In-Furness" conf="2.6">Dalton</enamex> was almost depopulated by thegreat plague, two centuries ago.</s> <s id="s510">In the church there is a massive old stone font, carved with the armorial bearings of the ancient feudal lords of the district.</s> <s id="s511">Thisvenerable relic stood for some time in the church-yard, exposed to mutilation and wear of the elements, until, through the good taste of the Rev. Mr. <enamex  sw="w83199" name="Not a placename">Morgan</enamex>, the presentvicar, it was removed to the interior again.</s></p>
<p><s id="s512"><enamex sw="w83263" long="-4.692535773887674" lat="54.22593372544603" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11241717" name="Peel Castle" conf="0.8191860256">Peel Castle</enamex> is about nine miles from <enamex sw="w83300" long="-3.081393270948825" lat="54.19093311473023" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10880" name="Ulverston" conf="2.6">Ulverston</enamex>, by rail, passing <enamex sw="w83328" long="-3.201549006999698" lat="54.13316968437257" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11148990" name="Furness Abbey" conf="2.2">Furness Abbey</enamex>, to <enamex sw="w83346" name="Peel pier">Peel pier</enamex>.</s> <s id="s513">A boat may be had at the pier, to the island, which is immediately opposite, divided from the main land by a narrow channel.</s> <s id="s514">Going by way of Barrow the distance by rail is about twelve miles; but the route is more varied.</s> <s id="s515">No other way of approachingthe ruins of this fortress is so impressive as by boat from Barrow, which is easily obtained, especially if" civil old Joe <enamex sw="w83728" long="-3.476409437504361" lat="54.54361363475041" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11323632" name="Winder" conf="2.570118491">Winder</enamex>" be about.</s> <s id="s516">This route also gives the tourist a good opportunity ofseeing the harbour, in which the British navy might ride safely in the wildest weather.</s> <s id="s517">The isle of Walney, <enamex sw="w83909" long="-3.154391336611825" lat="54.08868557527661" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11252388" name="Rampside" conf="2.6">Rampside</enamex>, and the most characteristic objects of this remotenook of the <enamex sw="w83981" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> shore, are in sight from the water.</s> <s id="s518">Barrow itself is an interesting spot.</s> <s id="s519">It is now the great port of <enamex sw="w84091" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>, and a place of increasing importance. Here, most of the ore of the district is shipped for <enamex sw="w84190" long="-3.789101892298007" lat="56.02246930188136" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100148" name="Carron" conf="1.304387883">Carron</enamex> and <enamex sw="w84201" long="-3.87179958820343" lat="51.59074020385742" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14131232" name="Swansea" conf="2.122719249">Swansea</enamex>, where it is used to enrich the poorer ores of <enamex  sw="w84256" name="Large admin unit">Scotland</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w84269" name="Large admin unit">Wales</enamex>.</s> <s id="s520">Hollinshed says that the Scots, in the reign of Edward the Second, during one of their raids into <enamex  sw="w84373" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>," met with no iron worth their notice until they came to <enamex sw="w84438" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>, in <enamex  sw="w84450" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>, where they seized all the manufactured iron they could find, and carried it off with the greatest joy, though so heavy of carriage and preferred it to allother plunder."</s> <s id="s521"><enamex sw="w84632" name="Om">Om</enamex> Barrow and its neighbourhood, as in many other parts of <enamex sw="w84691" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>, roads, houses, cattle, and men are more or less colouride with oxide of iron.</s> <s id="s522">A Furnessminer, when disguised in his Sunday clothes, is seldom slow to tell you that he has" taen his degreen | i' the Red Lone College."</s> <s id="s523">The view of <enamex sw="w84927" long="-4.692535773887674" lat="54.22593372544603" type="fac" gazref="unlock:11241717" name="Peel Castle" conf="0.8191860256">Peel Castle</enamex>, as the boat nearthe island from Barrow, is very striking.</s> <s id="s524">The castle was built by the <enamex sw="w85026" long="-0.4152977401859335" lat="51.70108732572091" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11055259" name="Abbots Langley" conf="1.487489371">Abbots</enamex> of <enamex sw="w85036" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex>, in the reign of Edward the Third, upon an older foundation, supposed to be theremains of a Danish fortress.</s> <s id="s525">These fierce sea-rovers often ravaged this part of the coast, and the terrors of their name linger yet among its traditions.</s> <s id="s526">The castle hasbeen a place of much greater extent and strength than now appears.</s> <s id="s527">On the eastern side of the island, where high tides wash the base of the ruins, immense blocks of wall, which have been many years among the waters, are yet as firmly held together by their old cement as if they were solid rock.</s> <s id="s528">On the east and southern sides, the sea nowcovers a great extent of the old foundations, which are visible, here and there, under water.</s> <s id="s529">On the north and western sides, the two great ditches, the double lines ofwall, and the strong flanking towers, still give some idea of the strength of the ancient defences.</s> <s id="s530">Near the ruins, there are two cottages, where the only inhabitants ofthe island reside.</s> <s id="s531">The largest of these cottages is a public-house, chiefly frequented by sailors from the harbours.</s> <s id="s532">Here the visitor may get good plain fare.</s></p>
<p><s id="s533"><enamex sw="w86126" long="-3.0765" lat="54.3361" type="manual_update"  gazref="Geoname_ID_2653454" name="Coniston Water" conf="99991">Coniston Lake</enamex> is about an hour's ride, by rail from <enamex sw="w86178" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, on the furness and <enamex sw="w86209" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex> line.</s> <s id="s534">The line goes by <enamex sw="w86243" long="0.2333333" lat="51.3833333" type="other" gazref="unlock:4570935" name="Horton Kirby" conf="0.8652421097">Kirby</enamex>, the village of <enamex sw="w86265" long="-2.73333" lat="53.81667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4578882" name="Broughton" conf="1">Broughton</enamex>, on the Duddonshore, <enamex  sw="w86296" name="Too ambigious to allocate">Woodlands</enamex>, and <enamex sw="w86311" long="-3.104151401188731" lat="54.33836116242543" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29871" name="Torver" conf="2.6">Torver</enamex>; and then along the western bank of the lake, with the" <enamex sw="w86374" long="-3.12208" lat="54.37042" type="other" gazref="unlock:4565407" name="Old Man of Coniston" conf="2">Old Man</enamex>" and other <enamex sw="w86393" long="-3.3297" lat="54.3116" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11116309" name="Coniston Fells" conf="99992">Coniston mountains</enamex> rising up from the left hand side of the line.</s> <s id="s535">The station is at <enamex sw="w86477" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> village, near the head of the lake.</s> <s id="s536">This line runs a considerable distance by <enamex sw="w86564" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> Sands, commanding an extensive view of the estuary.</s></p>
<p><s id="s537"><enamex sw="w86623" long="-2.959809373549684" lat="54.2701718942731" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11229861" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, at the foot of <enamex sw="w86652" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>, is nine miles from <enamex sw="w86683" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>.</s> <s id="s538">A coach starts thither from the latter place every day in summer.</s> <s id="s539">The road is full of interestingvariety, winding by the banks of the River <enamex sw="w86835" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex> almost all the way.</s> <s id="s540">On the right hand the upper part of the estuary stretches out from near the highway, bounded by thefells and beautiful shores of <enamex sw="w86990" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>; on the left, the green hills of Low <enamex sw="w87035" long="-3.209390296765473" lat="54.27579184624464" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:29112" name="Broughton In Furness" conf="2.6">Furness</enamex> throw their shadows, here and there, across the way.</s> <s id="s541">The River <enamex sw="w87106" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex> brings down thewaters of <enamex sw="w87137" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> to the sea.</s> <s id="s542">About four miles on the road, the beautiful valley of the Crake opens up on the western side, and the summits of the <enamex sw="w87277" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> range arein sight.</s> <s id="s543">Through this valley the <enamex sw="w87329" long="-3.074898268462848" lat="54.26633728536065" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788642" name="River Crake" conf="2.4">River Crake</enamex> empties the waters of <enamex sw="w87363" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> into the <enamex sw="w87381" long="-2.989724572366603" lat="54.25573037981277" type="water" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="River Leven" conf="2.4">Leven</enamex>.</s> <s id="s544">If any sojourner at <enamex sw="w87408" long="-3.081393270948825" lat="54.19093311473023" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10880" name="Ulverston" conf="2.6">Ulverston</enamex> designes a fine walk through picturesque scenery, let him go about two miles along this high road from <enamex sw="w87520" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7937392692">Ulverstone</enamex>, then up <enamex sw="w87540" long="-3.2987" lat="54.5273" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY16051545" name="Newlands Vale" conf="99992">Newland Vale</enamex> about a mile, and then northward across the hills a mile and a half, down to the village of <enamex sw="w87645" long="-3.060088511" lat="54.24063568" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00218" name="Penny Bridge" conf="99991">Penny Bridge</enamex>, at which spot he may be safely left to the influence of the scene.</s> <s id="s545">From these high grounds, between <enamex sw="w87759" long="-3.2987" lat="54.5273" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY16051545" name="Newlands Vale" conf="99992">Newland Vale</enamex> and Crank Vale, there are glorious views of the <enamex sw="w87820" long="-3.3297" lat="54.3116" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:11116309" name="Coniston Fells" conf="99992">Coniston mountains</enamex>.</s> <s id="s546">Near the entrance of the Crake valley the road passes in picturesque little village and Fort of <enamex sw="w87936" long="-3.051020212656498" lat="54.23345607578884" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11160582" name="Greenodd" conf="2.6">Greenodd</enamex>, over the hills, there is an interesting old <enamex sw="w87990" long="-86.8224992" lat="36.2192218" type="other" gazref="unlock:7348579" name="Berean Baptist Chapel" conf="0.6439763162">Baptist chapel</enamex>, built in the intolerant days of the" Five Mile Act."</s> <s id="s547">At <enamex sw="w88062" long="-2.987146226865094" lat="54.25408582837268" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25541" name="Backbarrow" conf="2.6">Backbarrow</enamex> - where a stranger may be surprised to find a cotton-mill in such a spot - the River <enamex sw="w88156" long="-2.757154323" lat="54.27221918" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00177" name="Levens Force" conf="99992">Leven falls</enamex> over the rocks beautifully on the right-hand side of the road.</s> <s id="s548">Thence, to <enamex sw="w88242" long="-2.959809373549684" lat="54.2701718942731" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11229861" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>, the road lies through a delightful wood-land scene between the hills, with the river shining and singing all the way over its old bed of mossy rocks, down in the left-hand hollow.</s> <s id="s549">The old mansion-like inn, called the White Swan, is delightful situated by the clear <enamex sw="w88521" long="-2.9897" lat="54.2557" type="manual update" gazref="unlock:8791312" name="Leven" conf="99992">Leven side</enamex>.</s> <s id="s550">In front, a quaint bridge of five arches spans the stream, and a few yards below it the river runs over a little fall, filling the quiet vale with its drowsy song by night and day.</s> <s id="s551">Above the bridge, the water comes down from <enamex sw="w88758" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> through lovely scenery, gradually narrowing from a lake to a river, with the current of water scarcely discernible.</s> <s id="s552">The picturesque old inn, the bridge, the river, the drowsy fall, the choral woods and every object in the hollow of this green nest of the mountains, is full of beauty and repose; and the hills that shut them in from the rest of the world heighten the general charm.</s> <s id="s553">The clear river glides by the front of the in, with only road between.</s> <s id="s554">It is pleasant to sit at the upper windows, or on the green flower-garnished benches below, in a still summer evening, listening to the birds and the waterfall, and watching the fish leaping up from the glittering water, as if giving a last frolicsome defiance to the cooks at the White Swan.</s> <s id="s555">At <enamex sw="w89519" long="-2.959809373549684" lat="54.2701718942731" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11229861" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex> we are on the very doorstep of that beautiful region of <enamex  sw="w89588" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex> The Lake Country, and -</s></p>
<p><s id="s556">" All that creation's varying mass assumes Of grand or lovely, here aspires and blooms; Bold rise the mountains, rich the gardens glow, Bright lakes expand, and conquering rivers flow.</s></p>
<p><s id="s557">Perhaps the finest views to be had in the immediate neighbourhood of <enamex sw="w89872" long="-2.959809373549684" lat="54.2701718942731" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11229861" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex> are from the summit of <enamex sw="w89908" long="-2.975376102499299" lat="54.27903569046947" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11144594" name="Finsthwaite" conf="2.6">Finsthwaite</enamex>, a lofty wooded height which rises steeply fromthe western side of the inn.</s> <s id="s558">On the top there is a square tower of slate stone, commemorative of the naval victories of <enamex  sw="w90087" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s> <s id="s559">The inside walls are written all over withnames and nameless reliques.</s> <s id="s560">The key of the tower may be had at the White Swan.</s> <s id="s561">A footpath loads through the plantations to the summit, which is a singular mixture of craggy wild-ness and pretty woodland walks.</s> <s id="s562"><enamex sw="w90349" long="-2.975376102499299" lat="54.27903569046947" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11144594" name="Finsthwaite" conf="2.6">Finsthwaite</enamex> commands a glorious extent and variety of scenery in this land of lake and mountain.</s> <s id="s563">Southward, the vale of theLeven winds away to Ulverstone Sands; westward, the mountains of <enamex sw="w90537" long="-3.071790052749298" lat="54.36868891187336" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:25643" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex>; eastward, the fells and vales of <enamex sw="w90580" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex>; and northward, from the foot of the hill, the entire length of crystal <enamex sw="w90660" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>, dotted with its emerald isles, is in full view.</s> <s id="s564">Beyond, the most kingly cluster of all our English mountainsbounds the landscape.</s> <s id="s565">Green is" the favourite colour of God," and the green shores of this garden-girt water are of a brightness such as is rarely met with elsewhere in the world.</s> <s id="s566">Looking upon <enamex sw="w90973" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex> from <enamex sw="w90989" long="-2.975376102499299" lat="54.27903569046947" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11144594" name="Finsthwaite" conf="2.6">Finsthwaite</enamex>, on a sunny day, one may say in the words of Tom <enamex sw="w91050" long="-2.64765" lat="53.3541" type="other" gazref="unlock:13896716" name="Moore" conf="0.9264236602">Moore</enamex>, that Nature seems to have lavished her charms upon the scene -</s></p>
<p><s id="s567">" To make a heaven for love to sigh in," For bards to live and saints to die in."</s></p>
<p><s id="s568">The distance from <enamex sw="w91218" long="-2.959809373549684" lat="54.2701718942731" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11229861" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex> to <enamex sw="w91234" long="-2.74151656837981" lat="54.32658914641318" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:10749" name="Kendal" conf="3.093870132">Kendal</enamex>, by way of <enamex sw="w91252" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> Fells, is ten miles; by <enamex sw="w91284" long="-2.775" lat="54.2602" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD49618522" name="Leven's Bridge" conf="99992">Leven Bridge</enamex>, fifteen miles.</s> <s id="s569">An onmibus goes from the inn twice a day in summer through <enamex sw="w91372" long="-2.898781358846106" lat="54.2886195272222" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11100386" name="Cartmel Fell" conf="2.6">Cartmel</enamex> to the village of Grange.</s> <s id="s570">Steamers start daily in summer to <enamex sw="w91440" long="-2.959272920560253" lat="54.43199742280473" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11255" name="Ambleside" conf="2.6">Ambleside</enamex> and back, calling at <enamex sw="w91471" long="-2.915738676011205" lat="54.36040070757029" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11084353" name="Bowness-On-Windermere" conf="2.6">Bowness</enamex>.</s> <s id="s571">There are ample facilities for boating and fishing; and, in addition to this, I believe there is hardly a house of entertainment in the lake country more notable for genuine comfort and the general excellence of its accomodation, that the White Swan at <enamex sw="w91732" long="-2.959809373549684" lat="54.2701718942731" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11229861" name="Newby Bridge" conf="2.6">Newby Bridge</enamex>.</s></p>
</text>
</document>