<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document>

<text id="1820_a"><p><s id="s1">The River <enamex sw="w22" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>, A Series Of Sonnets: Vaudracour And Julia: And Other Poems. To Which Is Annexed, A Topographical Description Of The Country of the Lakes In The North Of <enamex  sw="w186" name="Large admin unit">England</enamex>.</s> </p><p><s id="s2">By William Wordsworth.</s> </p><p><s id="s3"><enamex sw="w219" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.550528319">London</enamex>: Printed For Longman, <enamex sw="w248" long="-1.087943658706903" lat="53.56837944640728" type="water" gazref="unlock:8787294" name="Grumble Hurst" conf="1.078702875">Hurst</enamex>, <enamex sw="w255" long="6.4" lat="51.7666667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4319026" name="Rees" conf="0.810908015">Rees</enamex>, <enamex sw="w261" long="-3.869865417921439" lat="53.33347365335865" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11159103" name="Great Orme" conf="1.030232567">Orme</enamex>, And Brown, <enamex sw="w278" long="-0.0981" lat="51.5147" type="manual_update"  gazref="ZZSH00035" name="Paternoster Row" conf="99991">Paternoster</enamex> Row.</s> <s id="s4">1820.</s> </p><p><s id="s5">The River <enamex sw="w311" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>.</s> <s id="s6">A Series Of Sonnets.</s> </p><p><s id="s7">The River <enamex sw="w352" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> rises on <enamex sw="w368" long="-3.117730429406299" lat="54.43060862223145" type="other" gazref="unlock:11327715" name="Wrynose Fell" conf="2">Wrynose Fell</enamex>, on the confines of <enamex  sw="w401" name="Large admin unit">Westmorland</enamex>, <enamex  sw="w414" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, and <enamex  sw="w430" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex>; and, serving as the boundary to the two latter counties, for the space of about twenty - five miles, enters the Irish sea, between the isle of Walney and the lordship of <enamex sw="w610" long="-3.2726" lat="54.2099" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD171801" name="Millom" conf="99992">Millum</enamex>.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s8">I.</s></p>
<p><s id="s9">Not envying shades which haply yet may throw A grateful coolness round that rocky spring, Bandusia, once responsive to the string Of the Horatian lyre with babbling flow; Careless of flowers that in perennial blow Round the moist marge of Persian fountains cling; Heedless of Alpine torrents thundering Through icy portals radiant as heaven's bow; I seek the birth-place of a native stream.-- All hail ye mountains, hail thou morning light! Better to breathe upon this aery height Than pass in needless sleep from dream to dream; Pure flow the verse, pure, vigorous, free, and bright, For <enamex sw="w1211" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>, long loved <enamex sw="w1230" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>, is my theme!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s10">Ii.</s></p>
<p><s id="s11">Child of the clouds! remote from every taint Of sordid industry thy lot is cast; Thine are the honors of the lofty waste; Not seldom, when with heat the valleys faint, Thy hand-maid Frost with spangled tissue quaint Thy cradle decks;-- to chant thy birth, thou hast No meaner Poet than the whistling Blast, And Desolation is thy Patron Saint! She guards thee, ruthless Power! who would not spare Those mighty forests, once the bison's screen, Where stalked the huge deer to his shaggy lair Through paths and alleys roofed with sombre green; Thousands of years before the silent air Was pierced by whizzing shaft of hunter keen!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s12">The deer alluded to is the <enamex sw="w1911" long="-2.520157073850562" lat="53.49981626409657" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11193764" name="Leigh" conf="1.90063728">Leigh</enamex>, a gigantic species long since extinct.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s13">Iii.</s></p>
<p><s id="s14">How shall I paint thee?-- Be this naked stone My seat while I give way to such intent; Pleased could my verse, a speaking monument, Make to the eyes of men thy features known.</s> <s id="s15">But as of all those tripping lambs not one Outruns his fellows, so hath nature lent To thy beginning nought that doth present Peculiar grounds for hope to build upon.</s> <s id="s16">To dignify the spot that gives thee birth, No sign of hoar Antiquity's esteem Appears, and none of modern Fortune's care; Yet thou thyself hast round thee shed a gleam Of brilliant moss, instinct with freshness rare; Prompt offering to thy Foster Mother, Earth!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s17">Iv.</s></p>
<p><s id="s18">Take, cradled Nursling of the mountain, take This parting glance, no negligent adieu! A Protean change seems wrought while I pursue The curves, a loosely-scattered chain doth make; Or rather thou appear a glistering snake, Silent, and to the gazer's eye untrue, Thridding with sinuous lapse the rushes, through Dwarf willows gliding, and by ferny brake.</s> <s id="s19">Starts from a dizzy steep the undaunted Rill Robed instantly in garb of snow-white foam; And laughing dares the Adventurer, who hath clomb So high, a rival purpose to fulfil; Else let the Dastard backward wend, and roam, Seeking less bold achievement, where he will!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s20">V.</s></p>
<p><s id="s21">Sole listener, <enamex sw="w3212" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>! to the breeze that played With thy clear voice, I caught the fitful sound Wafted over sullen moss and craggy mound, Unfruitful solitudes, that seemed to upbraid The sun in heaven!-- but now, to form a shade For Thee, green alders have together wound Their foliage; ashes flung their arms around; And birch-trees risen in silver colonnade.</s> <s id="s22">And thou hast also tempted here to rise,' Mid sheltering pines, this Cottage rude and grey; Whose ruddy children, by the mother's eyes Carelessly watched, sport through the summer day, Thy pleased associates:-- light as endless May On infant bosoms lonely Nature lies.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s23">Vi.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s24">Flowers.</s></p>
<p><s id="s25">Ere yet our course was graced with social trees It lacked not old remains of hawthorn bowers, Where small birds warbled to their paramours; And, earlier still, was heard the hum of bees; I saw them ply their harmless robberies, And caught the fragrance which the sundry flowers, Fed by the stream with soft perpetual showers, Plenteously yielded to the vagrant breeze.</s> <s id="s26">There bloomed the strawberry of the wilderness; The trembling eye-bright showed her sapphire blue, The thyme her purple like the blush of even; And, if the breath of some to no caress Invited, forth they peeped so fair to view, All kinds alike seemed favourites of Heaven.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s27">Vii.</s></p>
<p><s id="s28">" Change me, some God, into that breathing rose!" The love-sick Stripling fancifully sighs, The envied flower beholding, as it lies On Laura's breast, in exquisite repose; Or he would pass into her Bird, that throws The darts of song from out its wiry cage; Enraptured,-- could he for himself engage The thousandth part of what the Nymph bestows, And what the little careless Innocent Ungraciously receives.</s> <s id="s29">Too daring choice! There are whose calmer mind it would content To be an unculled floweret of the glen, Fearless of plough and scythe; or darkling wren, That tunes on <enamex sw="w5062" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>'s banks her slender voice.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s30">Viii.</s></p>
<p><s id="s31">What aspect bore the Man who roved or fled, First of his tribe, to this dark dell-- who first In this pellucid Current slaked his thirst?</s> <s id="s32">What hopes came with him?</s> <s id="s33">what designs were spread Along his path?</s> <s id="s34">His unprotected bed What dreams encompassed?</s> <s id="s35">Was the Intruder nursed In hideous usages, and rites accursed, That thinned the living and disturbed the dead?</s> <s id="s36">No voice replies;-- the earth, the air is mute; And Thou, blue Streamlet, murmuring yield no more Than a soft record that whatever fruit Of ignorance thou might witness heretofore, Thy function was to heal and to restore, To soothe and cleanse, not madden and pollute!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s37">Ix.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s38">The <enamex sw="w5741" long="-71.26479" lat="42.90761" type="other" gazref="unlock:10826663" name="Stepping Stones School" conf="0.6666008597">Stepping Stones</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s39">The struggling Rill insensibly is grown Into a Brook of loud and stately march, Crossed ever and anon by plank and arch; And, for like use, lo! what might seem a zone Chosen for ornament; stone matched with stone In studied symmetry, with interspace For the clear waters to pursue their race Without restraint.-- How swiftly have they flown! Succeeding-- still succeeding! Here the Child Puts, when the high-swoln Flood runs fierce and wild, His budding courage to the proof;-- and here Declining Manhood learns to note the sly And sure encroachments of infirmity, Thinking how fast time runs, life's end how near!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s40">X.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s41">The Same Subject.</s></p>
<p><s id="s42">Not so that Pair whose youthful spirits dance With prompt emotion, urging them to pass; A sweet confusion checks the Shepherd Lass; Blushing she eyes the dizzy flood askance,-- To stop ashamed-- too timid to advance; She ventures once again-- another pause! His outstretched hand He tauntingly withdraws-- She sues for help with piteous utterance! Chidden she chides again; the thrilling touch Both feel when he renews the wished-for aid: Ah! if their fluttering hearts should stir too much, Should beat too strongly, both may be betrayed.</s> <s id="s43">The frolic Loves who, from yon high rock, see The struggle, clap their wings for victory!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s44">Xi.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s45">The Fa ËR y Chasm.</s></p>
<p><s id="s46">No fiction was it of the antique age: A sky-blue stone, within this sunless cleft, Is of the very foot-marks unbereft Which tiny Elves impressed-- on that smooth stage Dancing with all their brilliant equipage In secret revels-- haply after theft Of some sweet babe, flower stolen, and coarse weed left, For the distracted mother to assuage Her grief with, as she might!-- But, where, oh where Is traceable a vestige of the notes That ruled those dances, wild in character?</s> <s id="s47">-- Deep underground?-- Or in the upper air, On the shrill wind of midnight?</s> <s id="s48">or where floats <enamex sw="w7605" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.4">Over</enamex> twilight fields the autumnal gossamer?</s></p>
<p> <s id="s49">Xii.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s50">Hints For The Fancy.</s></p>
<p><s id="s51">On, loitering Muse!-- The swift Stream chides us-- on! Albeit his deep-worn channel doth immure Objects immense, pourtrayed in miniature, Wild shapes for many a strange comparison! Niagaras, Alpine passes, and anon Abodes of Naïads, calm abysses pure, Bright liquid mansions, fashioned to endure When the broad Oak drops, a leafless skeleton, And the solidities of mortal pride, Palace and Tower, are crumbled into dust!-- The Bard who walks with <enamex sw="w8122" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> for his guide, Shall find such toys of Fancy thickly set:-- Turn from the sight, enamoured Muse-- we must; Leave them-- and, if thou canst, without regret!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s52">Xiii.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s53">Open Proespect.</s></p>
<p><s id="s54">Hail to the fields-- with Dwellings sprinkled over, And one small Hamlet, under a green hill, Clustered with barn and byer, and spouting mill! A glance suffices,-- should we wish for more, Gay June would scorn us;-- but when bleak winds roar Through the stiff lance-like shoots of pollard ash, Dread swell of sound! loud as the gusts that lash The matted forests of Ontario's shore By wasteful steel unsmitten, then would I Turn into port,-- and, reckless of <enamex sw="w8762" long="-3.331238891935261" lat="54.83292999033717" type="other" gazref="unlock:11149426" name="Gale, The" conf="1.733579411">the gale</enamex>, Reckless of angry <enamex sw="w8790" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> sweeping by, While the warm hearth exalts the mantling ale, Laugh with the generous household heartily, At all the merry pranks of Donnerdale!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s55">Xiv.</s></p>
<p><s id="s56">O Mountain Stream! the Shepherd and his <enamex sw="w8986" long="95.38290000000001" lat="5.3099" type="other" gazref="unlock:6030749" name="Cot Batee" conf="0">Cot</enamex> Are privileged Inmates of deep solitude; Nor would the nicest Anchorite exclude A field or two of brighter green, or plot Of tillage-ground, that seemeth like a spot Of stationary sunshine:-- thou hast viewed These only, <enamex sw="w9210" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>! with their paths renewed By fits and starts, yet this contents thee not.</s> <s id="s57">Thee hath some awful Spirit impelled to leave, Utterly to desert, the haunts of men, Though simple thy companions were and few; And through this wilderness a passage cleave Attended but by thy own voice, save when The <enamex sw="w9509" long="-2.411843342259774" lat="54.38262720582438" type="water" gazref="unlock:8771932" name="Clouds Gill" conf="2.249952851">Clouds</enamex> and Fowls of the air thy way pursue!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s58">XV.</s></p>
<p><s id="s59">From this deep chasm-- where quivering sun-beams play Upon its loftiest crags-- mine eyes behold A gloomy Niche, capacious, blank, and cold; A concave free from shrubs and mosses grey; In semblance fresh, as if, with dire affray, Some Statue, placed amid these regions old For tutelary service, thence had rolled, Startling the flight of timid Yesterday! Was it by mortals sculptured?-- weary slaves Of slow endeavour! or abruptly cast Into rude shape by fire, with roaring blast Tempestuously let loose from central caves?</s> <s id="s60">Or fashioned by the turbulence of waves, Then, when over highest hills the Deluge past?</s></p>
<p> <s id="s61">Xvi.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s62">American Tradition.</s></p>
<p><s id="s63">Such fruitless questions may not long beguile Or plague the fancy, mid the sculptured shows Conspicuous yet where Oroonoko flows; There would the Indian answer with a smile Aimed at the White Man's ignorance, the while Of the Great Waters telling, how they rose, Covered the plains, and wandering where they chose, Mounted through every intricate defile, Triumphant.-- Inundation wide and deep, <enamex sw="w10589" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.4">Over</enamex> which his Fathers urged, to ridge and steep Else unapproachable, their buoyant way; And carved, on mural cliff's undreaded side, Sun, moon, and stars, and beast of chase or prey; Whatever they sought, shunned, loved, or deified!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s64">See Humboldt's Personal Narrative.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s65">Xvii.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s66">Return.</s></p>
<p><s id="s67">A Dark plume fetch me from yon blasted Yew Perched on whose top the Danish Raven croaks; Aloft, the imperial Bird of <enamex sw="w10992" long="12.4833333" lat="41.9000000" type="pplc" gazref="geonames:3169070" name="Rome" conf="1.917051257">Rome</enamex> invokes Departed ages, shedding where he flew Loose fragments of wild wailing that bestrew The clouds, and thrill the chambers of the rocks, And into silence hush the timorous flocks, That slept so calmly while the nightly dew Moistened each fleece, beneath the twinkling stars: These couched mid that lone Camp on <enamex sw="w11312" long="-3.1854" lat="54.4028" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY23150146" name="Hardknot" conf="99992">Hardknot</enamex>'s height, Whose Guardians bent the knee to <enamex  sw="w11364" name="Not a placename">Jove</enamex> and Mars: These near that mystic Round of Druid frame, Tardily sinking by its proper weight Deep into patient Earth, from whose smooth breast it came!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s68">Xviii.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s69"><enamex sw="w11529" long="-3.187972142" lat="54.35484638" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00087" name="Seathwaite Chapel" conf="99992">Seathwaite Chapel</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s70">Sacred Religion," mother of form and fear," Dread Arbitress of mutable respect, New rites ordaining when the old are wrecked, Or cease to please the fickle worshipper; If one strong wish may be embosomed here, Mother of Love! for this deep vale, protect Truth's holy lamp, pure source of bright effect, Gifted to purge the vapoury atmosphere That seeks to stifle it;-- as in those days When this low Pile a Gospel Teacher knew, Whose good works formed an endless retinue: Such <enamex sw="w12024" long="-1.798362096885317" lat="54.45897870522764" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790646" name="Priest Gill" conf="1.163706768">Priest</enamex> as Chaucer sang in fervent lays; Such as the heaven-taught skill of Herbert drew; And tender Goldsmith crowned with deathless praise!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s71"><enamex sw="w12166" long="-73.55889999999999" lat="45.5032" type="other" gazref="unlock:5424495" name="Hotel XIX Siecle" conf="0.4044925002">Xix</enamex>.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s72">Tributary Stream.</s></p>
<p><s id="s73">My frame hath often trembled with delight When hope presented some far-distant good, That seemed from heaven descending, like the flood Of yon pure waters, from their aery height, Hurrying with lordly <enamex sw="w12391" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> to unite; Who, mid a world of images imprest On the calm depth of his transparent breast, Appears to cherish most that Torrent white, The fairest, softest, liveliest of them all! And seldom hath ear listened to a tune More lulling than the busy hum of Noon, Swoln by that voice-- whose murmur musical Announces to the thirsty fields a boon Dewy and fresh, till showers again shall fall.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s74"><enamex sw="w12785" long="-73.55889999999999" lat="45.5032" type="other" gazref="unlock:5424495" name="Hotel XIX Siecle" conf="0.4044925002">Xix</enamex>.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s75">The Plain Of Donnerdale.</s></p>
<p><s id="s76">The old inventive Poets, had they seen, Or rather felt, the entrancement that detains Thy waters, <enamex sw="w12914" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>! mid these flowery plains, The still repose, the liquid lapse serene, Transferred to bowers imperishably green, Had beautified Elysium! But these chains Will soon be broken;-- a rough course remains, Rough as the past; where Thou, of placid mien, Innocuous as a firstling of a flock, And countenanced like a soft cerulean sky, Shalt change thy temper; and, with many a shock Given and received in mutual jeopardy, Dance like a Bacchanal from rock to rock, Tossing her frantic thyrsus wide and high!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s77">Xxi.</s></p>
<p><s id="s78">Whence that low voice?-- A whisper from the heart, That told of days long past when here I roved With friends and kindred tenderly beloved; Some who had early mandates to depart, Yet are allowed to steal my path athwart By <enamex sw="w13647" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>'s side; once more do we unite, Once more beneath the kind Earth's tranquil light; And smothered joys into new being start.</s> <s id="s79">From her unworthy seat, the cloudy stall Of Time, breaks forth triumphant Memory; Her glistening tresses bound, yet light and free As golden locks of birch, that rise and fall On gales that breathe too gently to recal Aught of the fading year's inclemency!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s80">Xxii.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s81">Tradition.</s></p>
<p><s id="s82">A Love Lorn Maid, at some far-distant time, Came to this hidden pool, whose depths surpass In crystal clearness Dian's looking-glass; And, gazing, saw that rose, which from the prime Derives its name, reflected as the chime Of echo doth reverberate some sweet sound: The starry treasure from the blue profound She longed to ravish;-- shall she plunge, or climb The humid precipice, and seize the guest Of April, smiling high in upper air?</s> <s id="s83">Desperate alternative! what fiend could dare To prompt the thought?-- Upon the steep rock's breast The lonely Primrose yet renews its bloom, Untouched memento of her hapless doom!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s84">Xxiii.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s85">Sheep Washing.</s></p>
<p><s id="s86">Sad thoughts, avaunt!-- the fervour of the year, Poured on the fleece-encumbered flock, invites To laving currents, for prelusive rites Duly performed before the Dales Men shear Their panting charge.</s> <s id="s87">The distant Mountains hear, Hear and repeat, the turmoil that unites Clamour of boys with innocent despites Of barking dogs, and bleatings from strange fear.</s> <s id="s88">Meanwhile, if <enamex sw="w15065" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>'s spotless breast receive Unwelcome mixtures as the uncouth noise Thickens, the pastoral River will forgive Such wrong; nor need we blame the licensed joys Though false to Nature's quiet equipoise: Frank are the sports, the stains are fugitive.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s89">Xxiv.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s90">The Resting Place.</s></p>
<p><s id="s91">Mid Noon is past;-- upon the sultry mead No zephyr breathes, no cloud its shadow throws: If we advance unstrengthened by repose, Farewell the solace of the vagrant reed.</s> <s id="s92">This Nook, with woodbine hung and straggling weed, Tempting recess as ever pilgrim chose, Half grot, half arbour, proffers to enclose Body and mind, from molestation freed, In narrow compass-- narrow as itself: Or if the Fancy, too industrious Elf, Be loth that we should breathe awhile exempt From new incitements friendly to our task, There wants not stealthy prospect, that may tempt Loose Idless to forego her wily mask.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s93">XXV.</s></p>
<p><s id="s94">Methinks' twere no unprecedented feat Should some benignant Minister of air Lift, and encircle with a cloudy chair, The One for whom my heart shall ever beat With tenderest love;-- or, if a safer seat Atween his downy wings be furnished, there Would lodge her, and the cherished burden bear <enamex sw="w16233" long="-4.359584582968855" lat="55.37465504283097" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11237782" name="Over Hill" conf="1.125314547">Over hill</enamex> and valley to this dim retreat! Rough ways my steps have trod; too rough and long For her companionship; here dwells soft ease: With sweets which she partakes not some distaste Mingles, and lurking consciousness of wrong; Languish the flowers; the waters seem to waste Their vocal charm; their sparklings cease to please.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s95">Xxvi.</s></p>
<p><s id="s96">Return, Content! for fondly I pursued, Even when a child, the Streams-- unheard, unseen; Through tangled woods, impending rocks between; Or, free as air, with flying inquest viewed The sullen reservoirs whence their bold brood, Pure as the morning, fretful, boisterous, keen, Green as the salt-sea billows, white and green, Poured down the hills, a choral multitude! Nor have I tracked their course for scanty gains; They taught me random cares and truant joys, That shield from mischief and preserve from stains Vague minds, while men are growing out of boys; Maturer Fancy owes to their rough noise Impetuous thoughts that brook not servile reins.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s97">Xxvii.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s98">Journey Renewed.</s></p>
<p><s id="s99">I <enamex sw="w17249" long="-74.7223827" lat="40.3673286" type="other" gazref="unlock:7843883" name="Mount Rose" conf="0.6361593602">Rose</enamex> while yet the cattle, heat-opprest, Crowded together under rustling trees, Brushed by the current of the water-breeze; And for their sakes, and love of all that rest, On <enamex sw="w17424" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>'s margin, in the sheltering nest; For all the startled scaly tribes that slink Into his coverts, and each fearless link Of dancing insects forged upon his breast; For these, and hopes and recollections worn Close to the vital seat of human clay; Glad meetings-- tender partings-- that upstay The drooping mind of absence, by vows sworn In his pure presence near the trysting thorn; I thanked the Leader of my onward way.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s100">Xxviii.</s></p>
<p><s id="s101">No record tells of lance opposed to lance, Horse charging horse mid these retired domains; Nor that their turf drank purple from the veins Of heroes fallen, or struggling to advance, Till doubtful combat issued in a trance Of victory, that struck through heart and reins, Even to the inmost seat of mortal pains, And lightened over the pallid countenance.</s> <s id="s102">Yet, to the loyal and the brave, who lie In the blank earth, neglected and forlorn, The passing Winds memorial tribute pay; The Torrents chaunt their praise, inspiring scorn Of power usurped,-- with proclamation high, And glad acknowledgment of lawful sway.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s103">Xxix.</s></p>
<p><s id="s104">Who swerves from innocence, who makes divorce Of that serene companion-- a good name, Recovers not his loss; but walks with shame, With doubt, with fear, and haply with remorse.</s> <s id="s105">And oft-times he, who, yielding to the force Of chance-temptation, ere his journey end, From chosen comrade turns, or faithful friend, In vain shall rue the broken intercourse.</s> <s id="s106">Not so with such as loosely wear the chain That binds them, pleasant River! to thy side:-- Through the rough copse wheel Thou with hasty stride, I choose to saunter over the grassy plain, Sure, when the separation has been tried, That we, who part in love, shall meet again.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s107">XXX.</s></p>
<p><s id="s108">The Kirk of <enamex sw="w19126" long="-3.23131251504889" lat="54.33079824521489" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35362" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex> to the Pilgrim's eye Is welcome as a Star, that doth present Its shining forehead through the peaceful rent Of a black cloud diffused over half the sky; Or as a fruitful palm-tree towering high <enamex sw="w19326" long="-3.29016003692186" lat="54.45940722344784" type="water" gazref="unlock:8790319" name="Over Beck" conf="2.4">Over</enamex> the parched waste beside an Arab's tent; Or the Indian tree whose branches, downward bent, Take root again, a boundless canopy.</s> <s id="s109">How sweet were leisure! could it yield no more Than mid that wave-washed Church Yard to recline, From pastoral graves extracting thoughts divine; Or there to pace, and mark the summits hoar Of distant moon-lit mountains faintly shine, Soothed by the unseen River's gentle roar.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s110">Xxxi.</s></p>
<p><s id="s111">Not hurled precipitous from steep to steep; Lingering no more mid flower-enamelled lands And blooming thickets; nor by rocky bands Held;-- but in radiant progress towerd the Deep Where mightiest rivers into powerless sleep Sink, and forget their nature;-- now expands Majestic <enamex sw="w20020" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>, over smooth flat sands, Gliding in silence with unfettered sweep! Beneath an ampler sky a region wide Is opened round him;-- hamlets, towers, and towns, And blue-topped hills, behold him from afar; In stately mien to sovereign <enamex sw="w20254" long="-0.2985421493649483" lat="51.43580055236816" type="civila" gazref="unlock:14121770" name="Richmond upon Thames" conf="1.57980179">Thames</enamex> allied, Spreading his bosom under <enamex sw="w20295" long="0.6429" lat="51.2677" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_2646748" name="Kentish Downs" conf="99992">Kentish downs</enamex>, With Commerce freighted or triumphant War.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s112">Xxxii.</s></p>
<p><s id="s113">But here no cannon thunders to <enamex sw="w20392" long="-3.331238891935261" lat="54.83292999033717" type="other" gazref="unlock:11149426" name="Gale, The" conf="1.733579411">the gale</enamex>; Upon the wave no haughty pendants cast A crimson splendour; lowly is the mast That rises here, and humbly spread the sail; While less disturbed than in the narrow Vale Through which with strange vicissitudes he passed, The Wanderer seeks that receptacle vast Where all his unambitious functions fail.</s> <s id="s114">And may thy Poet, cloud-born Stream! be free, The sweets of earth contentedly resigned, And each tumultuous working left behind At seemly distance, to advance like Thee, Prepared, in peace of heart, in calm of mind And soul, to mingle with Eternity!</s></p>
<p> <s id="s115">Xxxiii.</s></p>
<p> <s id="s116">Conclusion.</s></p>
<p><s id="s117">I Thought of Thee, my partner and my guide, As being past away.-- Vain sympathies! For, backward <enamex sw="w21071" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>! as I cast my eyes, I see what was, and is, and will abide; Still glides the Stream, and shall for ever glide; The Form remains, the Function never dies; While we, the brave, the mighty, and the wise, We Men, who in our morn of youth defied The elements, must vanish;-- be it so! Enough, if something from our hands have power To live, and act, and serve the future hour; And if, as towerd the silent tomb we go, Through love, through hope, and faith's transcendant dower, We feel that we are greater than we know.</s></p>
<p><s id="s118">Postscript.</s> </p><p><s id="s119">A Poet, whose works are not yet known as they deserve to be, thus enters upon his description of the" Ruins of <enamex sw="w21716" long="12.4833333" lat="41.9000000" type="pplc" gazref="geonames:3169070" name="Rome" conf="1.917051257">Rome</enamex>,"</s></p>
<p><s id="s120">" The rising Sun Flames on the ruins in the purer air Towering aloft;"</s></p>
<p><s id="s121">and ends thus,</s></p>
<p><s id="s122">" The setting Sun displays His visible great round, between yon towers, As through two shady cliffs."</s></p>
<p><s id="s123">Mr. Crowe, in his excellent loco-descriptive Poem," <enamex sw="w21961" long="-2.801999007876161" lat="50.80973084006479" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11194431" name="Lewesdon Hill" conf="1.009662271">Lewesdon Hill</enamex>," is still more expeditious, finishing the whole on a May Morning, before breakfast.</s></p>
<p><s id="s124">" To Morrow for severer thought, but now To breakfast, and keep festival to-day."</s></p>
<p><s id="s125">No one believes, or is desired to believe, that these Poems were actually composed within such limits of time, nor was there any reason why a prose statement should acquaint the Reader with the, plain fact, to the disturbance of poetic credibility.</s> <s id="s126">But, in the present case, I am compelled to mention, that the above series of Sonnets was the growth of many years;-- the one which stands the 14th was the first produced; and others were added upon occasional visits to the Stream, or as recollections of the scenes upon its banks awakened a wish to describe them.</s> <s id="s127">In this manner I had proceeded insensibly, without perceiving that I was trespassing upon ground pre-occupied, at least as far as intention went, by Mr. Coleridge; who, more than twenty years ago, used to speak of writing a rural Poem, to be entitled" The Brook," of which he has given a sketch in a recent publication.</s> <s id="s128">But a particular subject cannot, I think, much interfere with a general one; and I have been further kept from encroaching upon any right Mr. C. may still wish to exercise, by the restriction which the frame of the Sonnet imposed upon me, narrowing unavoidably the range of thought, and precluding, though not without its advantages, many graces to which a freer movement of verse would naturally have led.</s></p>
<p><s id="s129">May I not venture, then, to hope, that instead of being a hinderance, by anticipation of any part of the subject, these Sonnets may remind Mr. Coleridge of his own more comprehensive design, and induce him to fulfil it.-- There is a sympathy in streams," one calleth to another;" and, I would gladly believe, that" The Brook" will, ere long, murmur in concert with" The <enamex sw="w23800" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>."</s> <s id="s130">But, asking pardon for this fancy, I need not scruple to say, that those verses must indeed be ill-fated which can enter upon such pleasant walks of nature, without receiving and giving inspiration.</s> <s id="s131">The power of waters over the minds of Poets has been acknowledged from the earliest ages;-- through the" Flumina amem sylvas que inglorius" of <enamex  sw="w24150" name="Not a placename">Virgil</enamex>, down to the sublime apostrophe to the great rivers of the earth, by <enamex  sw="w24226" name="Not a placename">Armstrong</enamex>, and the simple ejaculation of <enamex  sw="w24267" name="Not a placename">Burns</enamex>,( chosen, if I recollect right, by Mr. Coleridge, as a motto for his embryo" Brook")</s></p>
<p><s id="s132">" The Muse nae Poet ever fand her, Till by himsel' he learned to wander, Adown some trotting burn' s meander, And Na' Think Lang."</s></p>
<p><s id="s133">Notes.</s> </p><p><s id="s134">Sonnet Vi.</s> </p><p><s id="s135">" There bloomed the strawberry of the wilderness, The trembling eye-bright showed her saphire blue."</s></p>
<p><s id="s136">These two lines are in a great measure taken from" The Beauties of Spring, a Juvenile Poem," by the Rev. Joseph Sympson, author of" The Vision of Alfred,"&amp; c.</s> <s id="s137">He was a native of <enamex  sw="w24784" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, and was educated in the vale of <enamex sw="w24828" long="-3.020927713122514" lat="54.46105068867795" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:31171" name="Grasmere" conf="2.6">Grasmere</enamex>, and at <enamex sw="w24845" long="-3.023901654228874" lat="54.37750890240144" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11167814" name="Hawkshead Hill" conf="2.6">Hawkshead</enamex> school: his poems are little known, but they contain passages of splendid description; and the versification of his" Vision of Alfred" is harmonious and animated.</s> <s id="s138">The present severe season, with its amusements, reminds me of some lines which I will transcribe as a favourite specimen.</s> <s id="s139">In describing the motions of the Sylphs, that constitute the strange machinery of his" Vision of Alfred," he uses the following illustrative simile:--</s></p>
<p><s id="s140">" glancing from their plumes A changeful light the azure vault illumes.</s> </p>
<p><s id="s141">Less varying hues beneath the Pole adorn The streamy glories of the Boreal morn, That wavering to and fro their radiance shed On Bothnia's gulph with glassy ice overspread, Where the lone native, as he homeward glides, On polished sandals over the imprisoned tides, And still the balance of his frame preserves, Wheeled on alternate foot in lengthening curves, Sees at a glance, above him and below, Two rival heavens with equal splendour glow.</s> <s id="s142">Sphered in the centre of the world he seems, For all around with soft effulgence gleams; Stars, moons, and meteors ray oppose to ray, And solemn midnight pours the blaze of day."</s></p>
<p><s id="s143">He was a man of ardent feeling, and his faculties of mind, particularly his memory, were extraordinary.</s> <s id="s144">Brief notices of his life ought to find a place in the History of <enamex  sw="w26157" name="Large admin unit">Westmorland</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s145">Sonnet Xvii.</s> </p><p><s id="s146">The Eagle requires a large domain for its support; but several pairs, not many years ago, were constantly resident in this country, building their nests in the steeps of <enamex sw="w26353" long="-3.152840038750234" lat="54.52319628836889" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13403088" name="Borrowdale CP" conf="2.4">Borrowdale</enamex>, Wastdale, <enamex sw="w26375" long="-3.429418179792764" lat="54.52620042627977" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11140131" name="Ennerdale Bridge" conf="2.537722452">Ennerdale</enamex>, and on the eastern side of <enamex sw="w26413" long="-3.043402327204126" lat="54.53913510713601" type="water" gazref="unlock:11169754" name="Helvellyn Gill" conf="2.4">Helvellyn</enamex>.</s> <s id="s147">Often have I heard anglers speak of the grandeur of their appearance, as they hovered over <enamex sw="w26515" long="-3.132896161282918" lat="54.42147870822834" type="water" gazref="unlock:11253836" name="Red Tarn" conf="2.4">Red Tarn</enamex>, in one of the coves of this mountain.</s> <s id="s148">The bird frequently returns, but is always destroyed.</s> <s id="s149">Not long since, one visited <enamex sw="w26645" long="-2.999" lat="54.4472" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7288050" name="Rydal Water" conf="99992">Rydal lake</enamex>, and remained some hours near its banks; the consternation which it occasioned among the different species of fowl, particularly the herons, was expressed by loud screams.</s> <s id="s150">The horse also is naturally afraid of the eagle.-- There were several Roman stations among these mountains; the most considerable seems to have been in a meadow at the head of <enamex sw="w27003" long="-2.9079" lat="54.376" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:10204" name="Windermere" conf="99991">Windermere</enamex>, established, undoubtedly, as a check over the passes of <enamex sw="w27071" long="-2.923380170612523" lat="54.48813982572446" type="water" gazref="unlock:8788152" name="Kirkstone Beck" conf="2.4">Kirkstone</enamex>, <enamex sw="w27082" long="-3.042257566142511" lat="54.49420285694539" type="other" gazref="unlock:11134276" name="Dunmail Raise" conf="2">Dunmail Raise</enamex>, and of <enamex sw="w27104" long="-3.1854" lat="54.4028" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY23150146" name="Hardknot" conf="99992">Hardknot</enamex> and <enamex sw="w27117" long="-3.117241463264904" lat="54.41263588064015" type="other" gazref="unlock:11327716" name="Wrynose Pass" conf="2">Wrynose</enamex>.</s> <s id="s151">On the margin of <enamex sw="w27143" long="-2.999" lat="54.4472" type="manual update" gazref="Geoname_ID_7288050" name="Rydal Water" conf="99992">Rydal lake</enamex>, a coin of <enamex  sw="w27165" name="Not a placename">Trajan</enamex> was discovered very lately.-- The Roman Fort here alluded to, called by the country people" <enamex sw="w27264" long="-3.2062" lat="54.4029" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY218015" name="Hardknot Castle" conf="99992">Hardknot</enamex> Castle," is most impressively situated half - way down the hill on the right of the road that descends from <enamex sw="w27380" long="-3.1854" lat="54.4028" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_NY23150146" name="Hardknot" conf="99992">Hardknot</enamex> into <enamex sw="w27394" long="-3.323474574274605" lat="54.38973821999076" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:39694" name="Eskdale Green" conf="2.6">Eskdale</enamex>.</s> <s id="s152">It has escaped the notice of most antiquarians, and is but slightly mentioned by Lysons.-- The Druidical Circle is about half a mile to the left of the road ascending <enamex sw="w27569" long="-3.313787931533084" lat="54.29380151464577" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11293316" name="Stoneside Hill" conf="2.4">Stoneside</enamex> from the vale of <enamex sw="w27596" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>: the country people call it" Sunken Church."</s></p>
<p><s id="s153">The reader who may have been interested in the foregoing Sonnets,( which together may be considered as a Poem) will not be displeased to find in this place a prose account of the <enamex sw="w27829" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>, extracted from Green's comprehensive Guide to the Lakes, lately published.</s> <s id="s154">" The road leading from <enamex sw="w27936" long="-3.069850309407378" lat="54.36812180953843" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11115199" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> to <enamex sw="w27948" long="-2.73333" lat="53.81667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4578882" name="Broughton" conf="0.8553683714">Broughton</enamex> is over high ground, and commands a view of the River <enamex sw="w28012" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>; which, at high water, is a grand sight, having the beautiful and fertile lands of <enamex  sw="w28102" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire</enamex> and <enamex  sw="w28117" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex> stretching each way from its margin.</s> <s id="s155">In this extensive view, the face of nature is displayed in a wonderful variety of hill and dale; wooded grounds and buildings; amongst the latter, <enamex sw="w28312" long="-2.73333" lat="53.81667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4578882" name="Broughton" conf="0.8553683714">Broughton</enamex> Tower, seated on the crown of a hill, rising elegantly from the valley, is an object of extraordinary interest.</s> <s id="s156">Fertility on each side is gradually diminished, and lost in the superior heights of <enamex sw="w28518" long="-3.3293" lat="54.2578" type="manual_update"  gazref="Norgate_ID_SD135855" name="Black Comb" conf="99991">Blackcomb</enamex>, in <enamex  sw="w28532" name="Large admin unit">Cumberland</enamex>, and the high lands between <enamex sw="w28571" long="-2.616" lat="54.2166" type="manual_update"  gazref="unlock:13402946" name="Kirby Lonsdale" conf="99991">Kirkby</enamex> and <enamex sw="w28582" long="-2.628155075629303" lat="51.60218710410136" type="other" gazref="unlock:11159328" name="Great Ulverstone" conf="0.7097255702">Ulverstone</enamex>."</s></p>
<p><s id="s157">" The road from <enamex sw="w28610" long="-2.73333" lat="53.81667" type="other" gazref="unlock:4578882" name="Broughton" conf="0.8553683714">Broughton</enamex> to <enamex sw="w28623" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex> is on the banks of the <enamex sw="w28657" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>, and on its <enamex  sw="w28676" name="Large admin unit">Lancashire side</enamex> it is of various elevations.</s> <s id="s158">The river is an amusing companion, one while brawling and tumbling over rocky precipices, until the agitated water becomes again calm by arriving at a smoother and less precipitous bed, but its course is soon again ruffled, and the current thrown into every variety of foam which the rocky channel of a river can give to water."</s> <s id="s159">( Vide Green's Guide to the Lakes, vol. i. pp. 98-100.)</s></p>
<p><s id="s160">After all, the traveller would be most gratified who should approach this beautiful Stream, neither at its source, as is done in the Sonnets, nor from its termination; but from <enamex sw="w29282" long="-3.069850309407378" lat="54.36812180953843" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11115199" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex> over Walna <enamex sw="w29302" long="-2.629961755372798" lat="53.7869491367909" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11253825" name="Red Scar" conf="1.432117042">Scar</enamex>; first descending into a little circular valley, a collateral compartment of the long winding vale through which flows the <enamex sw="w29430" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex>.</s> <s id="s161">This recess, towards the close of September, when the after-grass of the meadows is still of a fresh green, with the leaves of many of the trees faded, but perhaps none fallen, is truly enchanting.</s> <s id="s162">At a point elevated enough to show the various objects in the valley, and not so high as to diminish their importance, the stranger will instinctively halt.</s> <s id="s163">On the fore-ground, a little below the most favourable station, a rude foot-bridge is thrown over the bed of the noisy brook foaming by the way-side.</s> <s id="s164">Russet and craggy hills, of bold and varied outline, surround the level valley, which is besprinkled with grey rocks plumed with birch trees.</s> <s id="s165">A few home-steads are interspersed, in some places peeping out from among the rocks like hermitages, whose site has been chosen for the benefit of sun-shine as well as shelter; in other instances, the dwelling-house, barn, and byre, compose together a cruciform structure, which, with its embowering trees, and the ivy clothing part of the walls and roof like a fleece, call to mind the remains of an ancient abbey.</s> <s id="s166">Time, in most cases, and nature everywhere, have given a sanctity to the humble works of man that are scattered over this peaceful retirement.</s> <s id="s167">Hence a harmony of tone and colour, a consummation and perfection of beauty, which would have been marred had aim or purpose interfered with the course of convenience, utility, or necessity.</s> <s id="s168">This unvitiated region stands in no need of the veil of twilight to soften or disguise its features.</s> <s id="s169">As it glistens in the morning sunshine, it would fill the spectator's heart with gladsomeness.</s> <s id="s170">Looking from our chosen station, he would feel an impatience to rove among its pathways, to be greeted by the milk-maid, to wander from house to house, exchanging" good-morrows" as he passed the open doors; but, at evening, when the sun is set, and a pearly light gleams from the western quarter of the sky, with an answering light from the smooth surface of the meadows; when the trees are dusky, but each kind still distinguishable; when the cool air has condensed the blue smoke rising from the cottage-chimneys; when the dark mossy stones seem to sleep in the bed of the foaming Brook; then he would be unwilling to move forward, not less from a reluctance to relinquish what he beholds, than from an apprehension of disturbing, by his approach, the quietness beneath him.</s> <s id="s171">Issuing from the plain of this valley, the Brook descends in a rapid torrent passing by the churchyard of <enamex sw="w31914" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>.</s> <s id="s172">The traveller is thus conducted at once into the midst of the wild and beautiful scenery which gave occasion to the Sonnets from the 14th to the 20th inclusive.</s> <s id="s173">From the point where the <enamex sw="w32112" long="-3.183538061" lat="54.36118136" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00084" name="Seathwaite Bridge" conf="99992">Seathwaite brook</enamex> joins the <enamex sw="w32139" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> is a view upwards into the pass through which the river makes its way into the plain of Donnerdale.</s> <s id="s174">The perpendicular rock on the right bears the ancient British name of <enamex sw="w32316" long="-2.811921514610853" lat="54.55888661396433" type="other" gazref="unlock:11242002" name="Pen, The" conf="1.942713941">The Pen</enamex>; the one opposite is called Walla Barrow Crag, a name that occurs in other places to designate rocks of the same character.</s> <s id="s175">The chaotic aspect of the scene is well marked by the expression of a stranger, who strolled out while dinner was preparing, and, at his return, being asked by his host," What way he had been wandering?" replied," As far as it is finished!"</s></p>
<p><s id="s176">The bed of the <enamex sw="w32705" long="-3.230911816118457" lat="54.2820732335677" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:16538" name="Duddon Bridge" conf="2.6">Duddon</enamex> is here strewn with large fragments of rocks fallen from aloft; which, as Mr. Green truly says," are happily adapted to the many - shaped wate-rfalls"( or rather water-breaks, for none of them are high,)" displayed in the short space of half a mile."</s> <s id="s177">That there is some hazard in frequenting these desolate places, I myself have had proof; for one night an immense mass of rock fell upon the very spot where, with a friend, I had lingered the day before.</s> <s id="s178">" The concussion," says Mr. Green, speaking of the event( for he also, in the practice of his art, on that day sat exposed for a still longer time to the same peril)," was heard, not without alarm, by the neighbouring shepherds."</s> <s id="s179">But to return to <enamex sw="w33411" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex> Churchyard: it contains the following inscription.</s></p>
<p><s id="s180">" In memory of the Reverend Robert Walker, who died the 25th of June, 1802, in the 93d year of his age, and 67th of his curacy at <enamex sw="w33602" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s181">" Also, of Anne his wife, who died the 28th of January, in the 93d year of her age."</s></p>
<p><s id="s182">In the parish-register of <enamex sw="w33724" long="-3.187972142" lat="54.35484638" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00087" name="Seathwaite Chapel" conf="99992">Seathwaite Chapel</enamex> is this notice:</s></p>
<p><s id="s183">" Buried, June 28th, the Rev. Robert Walker.</s> <s id="s184">He was curate of <enamex sw="w33819" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex> sixty - six years.</s> <s id="s185">He was a man singular for his temperance, industry, and integrity."</s></p>
<p><s id="s186">This individual is the Pastor alluded to, in the eighteenth Sonnet, as a worthy compeer of the country parson of Chaucer,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s187">An abstract of his character is given in the author's poem of The Excursion; and some account of his life, for it is worthy of being recorded, will not be out of place here.</s></p>
<p><s id="s188">Memoir Of The Rev. Robert Walker.</s> </p><p><s id="s189">In the year 1709, Robert Walker was born at <enamex sw="w34294" long="-3.115290962420766" lat="54.34074434803631" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11309295" name="Under Crag" conf="2.4">Under Crag</enamex>, in <enamex sw="w34309" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>; he was the youngest of twelve children.</s> <s id="s190">His eldest brother, who inherited the small family estate, died at <enamex sw="w34428" long="-3.115290962420766" lat="54.34074434803631" type="mtn" gazref="unlock:11309295" name="Under Crag" conf="2.4">Under Crag</enamex>, aged ninety - four, being twenty - four years older than the subject of this Memoir, who was born of the same mother.</s> <s id="s191">Robert was a sickly infant; and, through his boyhood and youth continuing to be of delicate frame and tender health, it was deemed best, according to the country phrase, to breed him a scholar; for it was not likely that he would be able to earn a livelihood by bodily labour.</s> <s id="s192">At that period few of these Dales were furnished with schoolhouses; the children being taught to read and write in the chapel; and in the same consecrated building, where he officiated for so many years both as preacher and schoolmaster, he himself received the rudiments of his education.</s> <s id="s193">In his youth he became schoolmaster at <enamex sw="w35161" long="-4.207297918909645" lat="55.40527611767631" type="water" gazref="unlock:8795097" name="Loch O' Th' Lowes" conf="1.164946706">Lowes</enamex> Water; not being called upon, probably, in that situation to teach more than reading, writing, and arithmetic.</s> <s id="s194">But, by the assistance of a" Gentleman" in the neighbourhood, he acquired, at leisure hours, a knowledge of the classics, and became qualified for taking holy orders.</s> <s id="s195">Upon his ordination, he had the offer of two curacies; the one, <enamex sw="w35509" long="-3.099910799354899" lat="54.34088551379002" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11303352" name="Torver" conf="2.6">Torver</enamex>, in the vale of <enamex sw="w35532" long="-3.069850309407378" lat="54.36812180953843" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11115199" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex>,-- the other, <enamex sw="w35554" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>, in his native vale.</s> <s id="s196">The value of each was the same, viz.</s> <s id="s197">five pounds per annum: but the cure of <enamex sw="w35662" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex> having a cottage attached to it, as he wished to marry, he chose it in preference.</s> <s id="s198">The young person on whom his affections were fixed, though in the condition of a domestic servant, had given promise, by her serious and modest deportment, and by her virtuous dispositions, that she was worthy to become the helpmate of a man entering upon a plan of life such as he had marked out for himself.</s> <s id="s199">By her frugality she had stored up a small sum of money, with which they began housekeeping.</s> <s id="s200">In 1735 or 1736, he entered upon his curacy; and, nineteen years afterwards, his situation is thus described, in some letters to be found in the Annual Register for 1760, from which the following is extracted:</s></p>
<p> <s id="s201">Page 326.</s></p>
<p><s id="s202">To Mr.____ <enamex sw="w36392" long="-3.069850309407378" lat="54.36812180953843" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11115199" name="Coniston" conf="2.6">Coniston</enamex>, July 26. 1754.</s> <s id="s203">" Sir,</s> </p><p><s id="s204">" I was the other day upon a party of pleasure, about five or six miles from this place, where I met with a very striking object, and of a nature not very common.</s> <s id="s205">Going into a clergyman's house( of whom I had frequently heard) I found him sitting at the head of a long square table, such as is commonly used in this country by the lower class of people, dressed in a coarse blue frock, trimmed with black horn buttons; a checked shirt, a leathern strap about his neck for a stock, a coarse apron, and a pair of great wooden-soled shoes plated with iron to preserve them,( what we call clogs in these parts), with a child upon his knee eating his breakfast; his wife, and the remainder of his children, were some of them employed in waiting upon each other, the rest in teazing and spinning wool, at which trade he is a great proficient; and moreover, when it is made ready for sale, will lay it, by sixteen or thirty - two pounds weight, upon his back, and on foot, seven or eight miles will carry it to the market, even in the depth of winter.</s> <s id="s206">I was not much surprised at all this, as you may possibly be, having heard a great deal of it related before.</s> <s id="s207">But I must confess myself astonished with the alacrity and the good humour that appeared both in the clergyman and his wife, and more so at the sense and ingenuity of the clergyman himself."***</s></p>
<p><s id="s208">Then follows a letter from another person, dated 1755, from which an extract shall be given.</s></p>
<p><s id="s209">" By his frugality and good management he keeps the wolf from the door, as we say; and if he advances a little in the world, it is owing more to his own care than to anything else he has to rely upon.</s> <s id="s210">I do n't find his inclination is running after further preferment.</s> <s id="s211">He is settled among the people, that are happy among themselves; and lives in the greatest unanimity and friendship with them; and, I believe, the minister and people are exceedingly satisfied with each other; and indeed how should they be dissatisfied when they have a person of so much worth and probity for their pastor?</s> <s id="s212">A man, who, for his candour and meekness, his sober, chaste, and virtuous conversation, his soundness in principle and practice, is an ornament to his profession, and an honour to the country he is in; and bear with me if I say, the plainness of his dress, the sanctity of his manners, the simplicity of his doctrine, and the vehemence of his expression, have a sort of resemblance to the pure practice of primitive Christianity."</s></p>
<p><s id="s213">We will now give his own account of himself, to be found in the same place.</s></p>
<p><s id="s214">From The Rev. Robert Walker.</s> <s id="s215">" Sir,</s> </p><p><s id="s216">" Yours of the 26th instant was communicated to me by Mr. C____, and I shoud have returned an immediate answer, but the hand of Providence, then laying heavy upon an amiable pledge of conjugal endearment, hath since taken from me a promising girl, which the disconsolate mother too pensively laments the loss of; though we have yet eight living, all healthful, hopeful children, whose names and ages are as follows: Zaccheus, aged almost eighteen years; Elizabeth, sixteen years and ten months; Mary, fifteen; Moses, thirteen years and three months; Sarah, ten years and three months; <enamex sw="w39582" long="-118.6818428039551" lat="50.57318687438965" type="water" gazref="unlock:14138566" name="Mabel Lake" conf="0.9256736354">Mabel</enamex>, eight years and three months; William Tyson, three years and eight months; and Anne Esther, one year and three months: besides Anne, who died two years and six months ago, and was then aged between nine and ten; and Eleanor, who died the 23d inst., January, aged six years and ten months.</s> <s id="s217">Zaccheus, the eldest child, is now learning the trade of a tanner, and has two years and a half of his apprenticeship to serve.</s> <s id="s218">The annual income of my chapel at present, as near as I can compute it, may amount to about 17 l. 10 s. of which is paid in cash, viz.</s> <s id="s219">5 l. from the bounty of Queen Anne, and 5 l. from W. P., Esq., of P____, out of the annual rents, he being lord of the manor, and 3 l. from the several inhabitants of L____, settled upon the tenements as a rent-charge; the house and gardens I value at 4 l. yearly, and not worth more; and I believe the surplice fees and voluntary contributions, one year with another, may be worth 3 l.; but as the inhabitants are few in number, and the fees very low, this last-mentioned sum consists merely in free-will offerings.</s></p>
<p><s id="s220">" I am situated greatly to my satisfaction with regard to the conduct and behaviour of my auditory, who not only live in the happy ignorance of the follies and vices of the age, but in mutual peace and goodwill with one another, and are seemingly( I hope really too) sincere Christians, and sound members of the established church, not one dissenter of any denomination being amongst them all.</s> <s id="s221">I got to the value of 40 l. for my wife's fortune, but had no real estate of my own, being the youngest son of twelve children, born of obscure parents; and though my income has been but small, and my family large, yet, by a providential blessing upon my own diligent endeavours, the kindness of friends, and a cheap country to live in, we have always had the necessaries of life.</s> <s id="s222">By what I have written( which is a true and exact account, to the best of my knowledge) I hope you will not think your favour to me out of the late worthy Dr. Stratford's effects quite mis-bestowed, for which I must ever gratefully own myself,</s></p>
<p><s id="s223">Sir," your much obliged and most obedient humble servant," R. W., Curate of <enamex sw="w41760" long="-3.1909" lat="54.3536" type="manual update" gazref="Norgate_ID_SD227960" name="Seathwaite" conf="99992">S</enamex>___.</s> <s id="s224">" To Mr. C., of <enamex sw="w41781" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.129191205">Lancaster</enamex>."</s> </p><p><s id="s225">About the time when this letter was written, the Bishop of Chester recommended the scheme of joining the curacy of <enamex sw="w41908" long="-3.23131251504889" lat="54.33079824521489" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35362" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex> to the contiguous one of <enamex sw="w41939" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>, and the nomination was offered to Mr. Walker; but an unexpected difficulty arising, Mr. W., in a letter to the Bishop( a copy of which, in his own beautiful handwriting, now lies before me), thus expresses himself.</s> <s id="s226">" If he," meaning the person in whom the difficulty originated," had suggested any such objection before, I should utterly have declined any attempt to the curacy of <enamex sw="w42331" long="-3.23131251504889" lat="54.33079824521489" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35362" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>; indeed, I was always apprehensive it might be disagreeable to my auditory at <enamex sw="w42415" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>, as they have been always accustomed to double duty, and the inhabitants of <enamex sw="w42502" long="-3.23131251504889" lat="54.33079824521489" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35362" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex> despair of being able to support a schoolmaster who is not curate there also; which suppressed all thoughts in me of serving them both."</s> <s id="s227">And in a second letter to the Bishop he writes:</s></p>
<p><s id="s228">" My Lord,</s> </p><p><s id="s229">" I have the favour of yours of the 1st inst., and am exceedingly obliged on account of the <enamex sw="w42794" long="-3.23131251504889" lat="54.33079824521489" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35362" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex> affair: if that curacy should lapse into your Lordship's hands, I would beg leave rather to decline than embrace it; for the chapels of <enamex sw="w42936" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex> and <enamex sw="w42951" long="-3.23131251504889" lat="54.33079824521489" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35362" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>, annexed together, would be apt to cause a general discontent among the inhabitants of both places; by either thinking themselves slighted, being only served alternately, or neglected in the duty, or attributing it to covetousness in me; all which occasions of murmuring I would willingly avoid."</s> <s id="s230">And in concluding his former letter, he expresses a similar sentiment upon the same occasion," desiring, if it be possible, however, as much as in me lieth, to live peaceably with all men."</s></p>
<p><s id="s231">The year following, the curacy of <enamex sw="w43478" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex> was again augmented; and, to effect this augmentation, fifty pounds had been advanced by himself; and, in 1760, lands were purchased with eight hundred pounds.</s> <s id="s232">Scanty as was his income, the frequent offer of much better benefices could not tempt Mr. W. to quit a situation where he had been so long happy, with a consciousness of being useful.</s> <s id="s233">Among his papers I find the following copy of a letter, dated 1775, twenty years after his refusal of the curacy of <enamex sw="w43949" long="-3.23131251504889" lat="54.33079824521489" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:35362" name="Ulpha" conf="2.6">Ulpha</enamex>, which will show what exertions had been made for one of his sons.</s></p>
<p><s id="s234">" May It Please Your Grace,</s> </p><p><s id="s235">" Our remote situation here makes it difficult to get the necessary information for transacting business regularly; such is the reason of my giving your Grace the present trouble.</s></p>
<p><s id="s236">" The bearer( my son) is desirous of offering himself candidate for deacon's orders at your Grace's ensuing ordination; the first, on the 25th inst., so that his papers could not be transmitted in due time.</s> <s id="s237">As he is now fully at age, and I have afforded him education to the utmost of my ability, it would give me great satisfaction( if your Grace would take him, and find him qualified) to have him ordained.</s> <s id="s238">His constitution has been tender for some years; he entered the college of <enamex sw="w44712" long="-6.2488889" lat="53.3330556" type="pplc" gazref="geonames:2964574" name="Dublin" conf="2.185857479">Dublin</enamex>, but his health would not permit him to continue there, or I would have supported him much longer.</s> <s id="s239">He has been with me at home above a year, in which time he has gained great strength of body, sufficient, I hope, to enable him for performing the function.</s> <s id="s240">Divine Providence, assisted by liberal benefactors, has blest my endeavours, from a small income, to rear a numerous family; and as my time of life renders me now unfit for much future expectancy from this world, I should be glad to see my son settled in a promising way to acquire an honest livelihood for himself.</s> <s id="s241">His behaviour, so far in life, has been irreproachable; and I hope he will not degenerate, in principles or practice, from the precepts and pattern of an indulgent parent.</s> <s id="s242">Your Grace's favourable reception of this, from a distant corner of the diocese, and an obscure hand, will excite filial gratitude, and a due use shall be made of the obligation vouchsafed thereby to</s></p>
<p><s id="s243">" Your Grace's very dutiful and most obedient" Son and Servant," Robert Walker."</s> </p><p><s id="s244">The same man, who was thus liberal in the education of his numerous family, was even munificent in hospitality as a parish priest.</s> <s id="s245">Every Sunday were served upon the long table, at which he has been described sitting with a child upon his knee, messes of broth for the refreshment of those of his congregation who came from a distance, and usually took their seats as parts of his own household.</s> <s id="s246">It seems scarcely possible that this custom could have commenced before the augmentation of his cure; and what would to many have been a high price of self-denial was paid, by the pastor and his family, for this gratification; as the treat could only be provided by dressing at one time the whole, perhaps, of their weekly allowance of fresh animal food; consequently, for a succession of days, the table was covered with cold victuals only.</s> <s id="s247">His generosity in old age may be still further illustrated by a little circumstance relating to an orphan grandson, then ten years of age, which I find in a copy of a letter to one of his sons; he requests that half a guinea may be left for" little Robert's pocket-money," who was then at school; entrusting it to the care of a lady, who, as he says," may sometimes frustrate his squandering it away foolishly," and promising to send him an equal allowance annually for the same purpose.</s> <s id="s248">The conclusion of the same letter is so characteristic, that I cannot forbear to transcribe it.</s> <s id="s249">" We," meaning his wife and himself," are in our wonted state of health, allowing for the hasty strides of old age knocking daily at our door, and threateningly telling us we are not only mortal, but must expect ere long to take our leave of our ancient cottage, and lie down in our last dormitory.</s> <s id="s250">Pray pardon my neglect to answer yours: let us hear sooner from you, to augment the mirth of the Christmas holidays.</s> <s id="s251">Wishing you all the pleasures of the approaching season, I am, dear Son, with lasting sincerity, yours affectionately,</s></p>
<p><s id="s252">" Robert Walker."</s> </p><p><s id="s253">He loved old customs and old usages, and in some instances stuck to them to his own loss; for, having had a sum of money lodged in the hands of a neighbouring tradesman, when long course of time had raised the rate of interest, and more was offered, he refused to accept it; an act not difficult to one, who, while he was drawing seventeen pounds a-year from his curacy, declined, as we have seen, to add the profits of another small benefice to his own, lest he should be suspected of cupidity.</s> <s id="s254">-- From this vice he was utterly free; he made no charge for teaching school; such as could afford to pay gave him what they pleased.</s> <s id="s255">When very young, having kept a diary of his expenses, however trifling, the large amount, at the end of the year, surprised him; and from that time the rule of his life was to be economical, not avaricious.</s> <s id="s256">At his decease he left behind him no less a sum than £ 2000.</s> <s id="s257">and such a sense of his various excellences was prevalent in the country, that the epithet of Wonderful is to this day attached to his name.</s></p>
<p><s id="s258">There is in the above sketch something so extraordinary as to require further explanatory details.-- And to begin with his industry; eight hours in each day, during five days in the week, and half of Saturday, except when the labours of husbandry were urgent, he was occupied in teaching.</s> <s id="s259">His seat was within the rails of the altar; the communion table was his desk; and, like Shenstone's school-mistress, the master employed himself at the spinning-wheel, while the children were repeating their lessons by his side.</s> <s id="s260">Every evening, after school hours, if not more profitably engaged, he continued the same kind of labour, exchanging, for the benefit of exercise, the small wheel, at which he had sate, for the large one on which wool is spun, the spinner stepping to and fro.-- Thus, was the wheel constantly in readiness to prevent the waste of a moment's time.</s> <s id="s261">Nor was his industry with the pen, when occasion called for it, less eager.</s> <s id="s262">Entrusted with extensive management of public and private affairs, he acted, in his rustic neighbourhood, as scrivener, writing out petitions, deeds of conveyance, wills, covenants,&amp; c., with pecuniary gain to himself, and to the great benefit of his employers.</s> <s id="s263">These labours( at all times considerable) at one period of the year, viz.</s> <s id="s264">between Christmas and Candlemas, when money transactions are settled in this country, were often so intense, that he passed great part of the night, and sometimes whole nights, at his desk.</s> <s id="s265">His garden also was tilled by his own hand; he had a right of pasturage upon the mountains for a few sheep and a couple of cows, which required his attendance; with this pastoral occupation he joined the labours of husbandry upon a small scale, renting two or three acres in addition to his own less than one acre of glebe; and the humblest drudgery which the cultivation of these fields required was performed by himself.</s></p>
<p><s id="s266">He also assisted his neighbours in hay-making and shearing their flocks, and in the performance of this latter service he was eminently dexterous.</s> <s id="s267">They, in their turn, complimented him with the present of a hay-cock, or a fleece; less as a recompence for this particular service than as a general acknowledgment.</s> <s id="s268">The Sabbath was in a strict sense kept holy; the Sunday evenings being devoted to reading the Scripture and family prayer.</s> <s id="s269">The principal festivals appointed by the Church were also duly observed; but through every other day in the week, through every week in the year, he was incessantly occupied in work of hand or mind; not allowing a moment for recreation, except upon a Saturday afternoon, when he indulged himself with a Newspaper, or sometimes with a Magazine.</s> <s id="s270">The frugality and temperance established in his house were as admirable as the industry.</s> <s id="s271">Nothing to which the name of luxury could be given was there known; in the latter part of his life, indeed, when tea had been brought into almost general use, it was provided for visitors, and for such of his own family as returned occasionally to his roof, and had been accustomed to this refreshment elsewhere; but neither he nor his wife ever partook of it.</s> <s id="s272">The raiment worn by his family was comely and decent, but as simple as their diet; the home-spun materials were made up into apparel by their own hands.</s> <s id="s273">At the time of the decease of this thrifty pair, their cottage contained a large store of webs of woollen and linen cloth, woven from thread of their own spinning.</s> <s id="s274">And it is remarkable that the pew in the chapel in which the family used to sit, remains neatly lined with woollen cloth spun by the pastor's own hands.</s> <s id="s275">It is the only pew in the chapel so distinguished; and I know of no other instance of his conformity to the delicate accommodations of modern times.</s> <s id="s276">The fuel of the house, like that of their neighbours, consisted of peat, procured from the mosses by their own labour.</s> <s id="s277">The lights by which, in the winter evenings, their work was performed, were of their own manufacture, such as still continue to be used in these cottages; they are made of the pith of rushes dipped in any unctuous substance that the house affords.</s> <s id="s278">White candles, as tallow candles are here called, were reserved to honour the Christmas festivals, and were perhaps produced upon no other occasions.</s> <s id="s279">Once a month, during the proper season, a sheep was drawn from their small mountain flock, and killed for the use of the family; and a cow, towards the close of the year, was salted and dried for winter provision: the hide was tanned to furnish them with shoes.-- By these various resources, this venerable clergyman reared a numerous family, not only preserving them, as he affectingly says," from wanting the necessaries of life;" but affording them an unstinted education, and the means of raising themselves in society.</s></p>
<p><s id="s280">It might have been concluded that no one could thus, as it were, have converted his body into a machine of industry for the humblest uses, and keep his thoughts so frequently bent upon secular concerns, without grievous injury to the more precious parts of his nature.</s> <s id="s281">How could the powers of intellect thrive, or its graces be displayed, in the midst of circumstances apparently so unfavourable, and where, to the direct cultivation of the mind, so small a portion of time was allotted?</s> <s id="s282">But, in this extraordinary man, things in their nature adverse were reconciled.</s> <s id="s283">His conversation was remarkable, not only for being chaste and pure, but for the degree in which it was fervent and eloquent; his written style was correct, simple, and animated.</s> <s id="s284">Nor did his affections suffer more than his intellect; he was tenderly alive to all the duties of his pastoral office: the poor and needy" he never sent empty away,"-- the stranger was fed and refreshed in passing that unfrequented vale,-- the sick were visited; and the feelings of humanity found further exercise among the distresses and embarrassments in the worldly estate of his neighbours, with which his talents for business made him acquainted; and the disinterestedness, impartiality, and uprightness which he maintained in the management of all affairs confided to him were virtues seldom separated in his own conscience from religious obligation.</s> <s id="s285">Nor could such conduct fail to remind those who witnessed it of a spirit nobler than law or custom: they felt convictions which, but for such intercourse, could not have been afforded, that as in the practice of their pastor there was no guile, so in his faith there was nothing hollow; and we are warranted in believing that upon these occasions selfishness, obstinacy, and discord would often give way before the breathings of his good-will and saintly integrity.</s> <s id="s286">It may be presumed also, while his humble congregation were listening to the moral precepts which he delivered from the pulpit, and to the Christian exhortations that they should love their neighbours as themselves, and do as they would be done unto-- that peculiar efficacy was given to the preacher's labours by recollections in the minds of his congregation that they were called upon to do no more than his own actions were daily setting before their eyes.</s></p>
<p><s id="s287">The afternoon service in the chapel was less numerously attended than that of the morning, but by a more serious auditory; the lesson from the New Testament, on those occasions, was accompanied by Burkitt's Commentaries.</s> <s id="s288">These lessons he read with impassioned emphasis, frequently drawing tears from his hearers, and leaving a lasting impression upon their minds.</s> <s id="s289">His devotional feelings and the powers of his own mind were further exercised, along with those of his family, in perusing the Scriptures; not only on the Sunday evenings, but on every other evening, while the rest of the household were at work, some one of the children, and in her turn the servant, for the sake of practice in reading, or for instruction, read the Bible aloud; and in this manner the whole was repeatedly gone through.</s> <s id="s290">That no common importance was attached to the observance of religious ordinances by his family, appears from the following memorandum by one of his descendants, which I am tempted to insert at length, as it is characteristic and somewhat curious.</s> <s id="s291">" There is a small chapel in the county palatine of <enamex sw="w56957" long="-2.801902525771824" lat="54.04660667916625" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11190914" name="Lancaster" conf="3.129191205">Lancaster</enamex>, where a certain clergyman has regularly officiated above sixty years, and a few months ago administered the sacrament of the Lord's Supper in the same, to a decent number of devout communicants.</s> <s id="s292">After the clergyman had received himself, the first company out of the assembly who approached the altar, and kneeled down to be partakers of the sacred elements, consisted of the parson's wife, to whom he had been married upwards of sixty years; one son and his wife; four daughters, each with her husband; whose ages, all added together, amount to above 714 years.</s> <s id="s293">The several and respective distances from the place of each of their abodes to the chapel where they all communicated, will measure more than 1000 English miles.</s> <s id="s294">Though the narration will appear surprising, it is without doubt a fact that the same persons, exactly four years before, met at the same place, and all joined in performance of the same venerable duty."</s></p>
<p><s id="s295">He was indeed most zealously attached to the doctrine and frame of the Established Church.</s> <s id="s296">We have seen him congratulating himself that he had no dissenters in his cure of any denomination.</s> <s id="s297">Some allowance must be made for the state of opinion when his first religious impressions were received, before the reader will acquit him of bigotry, when I mention that at the time of the augmentation of the cure, he refused to invest part of the money in the purchase of an estate offered to him upon advantageous terms, because the proprietor was a quaker;-- whether from scrupulous apprehension that a blessing would not attend a contract framed for the benefit of the church between persons not in religious sympathy with each other; or, as a seeker of peace, he was afraid of the uncomplying disposition which at one time was too frequently conspicuous in that sect.</s> <s id="s298">Of this an instance had fallen under his own notice; for, while he taught school at <enamex sw="w58843" long="-3.322732159981248" lat="54.5723577144906" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209070" name="Loweswater" conf="2.563586479">Loweswater</enamex>, certain persons of that denomination had refused to pay, or be distrained upon, for the accustomed annual interest due from them, among others, under the title of church stock; a great hardship upon the incumbent, for the curacy of <enamex sw="w59087" long="-3.322732159981248" lat="54.5723577144906" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209070" name="Loweswater" conf="2.563586479">Loweswater</enamex> was then scarcely less poor than that of <enamex sw="w59139" long="-3.181453589957629" lat="54.50191128767066" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11279850" name="Seathwaite" conf="2.6">Seathwaite</enamex>.</s> <s id="s299">To what degree this prejudice of his was blamable need not be determined;-- certain it is, that he was not only desirous, as he himself says, to live in peace, but in love, with all men.</s> <s id="s300">He was placable, and charitable in his judgments; and, however correct in conduct and rigorous to himself, he was ever ready to forgive the trespasses of others, and to soften the censure that was cast upon their frailties.-- It would be unpardonable to omit that, in the maintenance of his virtues, he received due support from the partner of his long life.</s> <s id="s301">She was equally strict, in attending to her share of their joint cares, nor less diligent in her appropriate occupations.</s> <s id="s302">A person who had been some time their servant in the latter part of their lives, concluded the panegyric of her mistress by saying to me," She was no less excellent than her husband; she was good to the poor; she was good to everything!" He survived for a short time this virtuous companion.</s> <s id="s303">When she died, he ordered that her body should be borne to the grave by three of her daughters and one granddaughter; and, when the corpse was lifted from the threshold, he insisted upon lending his aid, and feeling about, for he was then almost blind, took hold of a napkin fixed to the coffin; and, as a bearer of the body, entered the chapel, a few steps from the lowly parsonage.</s></p>
<p><s id="s304">What a contrast does the life of this obscurely-seated, and, in point of worldly wealth, poorly-repaid Churchman, present to that of a Cardinal Wolsey!</s></p>
<p><s id="s305">" O' tis a burthen, <enamex  sw="w60664" name="Not a placename">Cromwell</enamex>,' tis a burthen Too heavy for a man who hopes for heaven!"</s></p>
<p><s id="s306">We have been dwelling upon images of peace in the moral world, that have brought us again to the quiet enclosure of consecrated ground in which this venerable pair lie interred.</s> <s id="s307">The sounding brook, that rolls close by the churchyard, without disturbing feeling or meditation, is now unfortunately laid bare; but not long ago it participated, with the chapel, the shade of some stately ash-trees, which will not spring again.</s> <s id="s308">While the spectator from this spot is looking round upon the girdle of stony mountains that encompasses the vale,-- masses of rock, out of which monuments for all men that ever existed might have been hewn, it would surprise him to be told, as with truth he might be, that the plain blue slab dedicated to the memory of this aged pair is a production of a quarry in <enamex sw="w61522" long="-3.71421926410597" lat="53.14944839812833" type="civil" gazref="unlock:13211761" name="North Wales Assembly ER" conf="1.033994842">North Wales</enamex>.</s> <s id="s309">It was sent as a mark of respect by one of their descendants from the vale of Festiniog, a region almost as beautiful as that in which it now lies!</s></p>
<p><s id="s310">Upon the <enamex sw="w61692" long="-3.183538061" lat="54.36118136" type="manual update" gazref="ZZSH00084" name="Seathwaite Bridge" conf="99992">Seathwaite Brook</enamex>, at a small distance from the parsonage, has been erected a mill for spinning yarn; it is a mean and disagreeable object, though not unimportant to the spectator, as calling to mind the momentous changes wrought by such inventions in the frame of society-- changes which have proved especially unfavourable to these mountain solitudes.</s> <s id="s311">So much had been effected by those new powers, before the subject of the preceding biographical sketch closed his life, that their operation could not escape his notice, and doubtless excited touching reflections upon the comparatively insignificant results of his own manual industry.</s> <s id="s312">But Robert Walker was not a man of times and circumstances; had he lived at a later period, the principle of duty would have produced application as unremitting; the same energy of character would have been displayed, though in many instances with widely-different effects.</s></p>
<p><s id="s313">Having mentioned in this narrative the vale of <enamex sw="w62651" long="-3.322732159981248" lat="54.5723577144906" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209070" name="Loweswater" conf="2.563586479">Loweswater</enamex> as a place where Mr. Walker taught school, I will add a few memoranda from its parish register, respecting a person apparently of desires as moderate, with whom he must have been intimate during his residence there.</s></p>
<p><s id="s314">" Let him that would, ascend the tottering seat Of courtly grandeur, and become as great As are his mounting wishes; but for me, Let sweet repose and rest my portion be.</s> </p>
<p> <s id="s315">Henry Forest Curate.</s></p>
<p><s id="s316">" Honour, the idol which the most adore, Receives no homage from my knee; Content in privacy I value more Than all uneasy dignity.</s></p>
<p><s id="s317">Henry Forest came to <enamex sw="w63221" long="-4.207297918909645" lat="55.40527611767631" type="water" gazref="unlock:8795097" name="Loch O' Th' Lowes" conf="1.164946706">Lowes</enamex> Water, 1708, being 25 years of age."</s></p>
<p><s id="s318">" This curacy was twice augmented by Queen Anne's Bounty.</s> <s id="s319">The first payment, with great difficulty, was paid to Mr. John Curwen of <enamex sw="w63394" long="-0.1193526387214661" lat="51.47267150878906" type="ppla" gazref="unlock:14132302" name="London" conf="2.550528319">London</enamex>, on the 9th of May, 1724, deposited by me, Henry Forest, Curate of <enamex sw="w63468" long="-4.207297918909645" lat="55.40527611767631" type="water" gazref="unlock:8795097" name="Loch O' Th' Lowes" conf="1.164946706">Lowes</enamex> Water.</s> <s id="s320">Ye said 9th of May, ye said Mr. Curwen went to the office, and saw my name registered there,&amp; c.</s> <s id="s321">This, by the Providence of God, came by lot to this poor place.</s></p>
<p><s id="s322">Haec testor H. Forest."</s> </p><p><s id="s323">In another place he records that the sycamore trees were planted in the churchyard in 1710.</s></p>
<p><s id="s324">He died in 1741, having been curate thirty - four years.</s> <s id="s325">It is not improbable that H. Forest was the gentleman who assisted Robert Walker in his classical studies at <enamex sw="w63922" long="-3.322732159981248" lat="54.5723577144906" type="ppl" gazref="unlock:11209070" name="Loweswater" conf="2.563586479">Loweswater</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s326">To this parish register is prefixed a motto, of which the following verses are a part.</s></p>
<p><s id="s327">" Invigilate viri, tacito nam tempora gressu Diffugiunt, nulloque sono convertitur annus; Utendum est etate, cito pede praeterit aetas."</s></p>
<p><s id="s328">Sonnet Xvii.</s>
</p><p><s id="s329">" We feel that we are greater that we know."</s></p>
<p><s id="s330">" And feel that I am happier than I know."-- <enamex  sw="w64257" name="Not a placename">Milton</enamex>.</s></p>
<p><s id="s331">The allusion to the Greek Poet will be obvious to the classical reader.</s></p>
</text>
</document>